The tao that can be told
is not the eternal Tao.
The name that can be named
is not the eternal Name.

The unnamable is the eternally real.
Naming is the origin
of all particular things.

Free from desire, you realize the mystery.
Caught in desire, you see only the manifestations.

Yet mystery and manifestations
arise from the same source.
This source is called darkness.

Darkness within darkness.
The gateway to all understanding.

[notes]

When people see some things as beautiful,
other things become ugly.
When people see some things as good,
other things become bad.
Being and non-being create each other.
Difficult and easy support each other.
Long and short define each other.
High and low depend on each other.
Before and after follow each other.

Therefore the Master
acts without doing anything
and teaches without saying anything.
Things arise and she lets them come;
things disappear and she lets them go.
She has but doesn’t possess,
acts but doesn’t expect.
When her work is done, she forgets it.
That is why it lasts forever.

[notes]

If you overesteem great men,
people become powerless.
If you overvalue possessions,
people begin to steal.

The Master leads
by emptying people’s minds and
filling their cores, by weakening their ambition
and toughening their resolve.
He helps people lose everything
they know, everything they desire,
and creates confusion
in those who think that they know.

Practice not-doing,
and everything will fall into place.

[notes]

The Tao is like a well:
used but never used up.
It is like the eternal void:
filled with infinite possibilities.

It is hidden but always present.
I don’t know who gave birth to it.
It is older than God.

[notes]

The Tao doesn’t take sides;
it gives birth to both good and evil.
The Master doesn’t take sides;
she welcomes both saints and sinners.

The Tao is like a bellows:
it is empty yet infinitely capable.
The more you use it, the more it produces;
the more you talk of it, the less you understand.

Hold on to the center.

[notes]

The Tao is called the Great Mother:
empty yet inexhaustible,
it gives birth to infinite worlds.

It is always present within you.
You can use it any way you want.

[notes]

The Tao is infinite, eternal.
Why is it eternal?
It was never born;
thus it can never die.
Why is it infinite?
It has no desires for itself;
thus it is present for all beings.

The Master stays behind;
that is why she is ahead.
She is detached from all things;
that is why she is one with them.
Because she has let go of herself,
she is perfectly fulfilled.

[notes]

The supreme good is like water,
which nourishes all things without trying to.
It is content with the low places that people disdain.
Thus it is like the Tao.

In dwelling, live close to the ground.
In thinking, keep to the simple.
In conflict, be fair and generous.
In governing, don’t try to control.
In work, do what you enjoy.
In family life, be completely present.

When you are content to be simply yourself
and don’t compare or compete,
everybody will respect you.

[notes]

Fill your bowl to the brim
and it will spill.
Keep sharpening your knife
and it will blunt.
Chase after money and security
and your heart will never unclench.
Care about people’s approval
and you will be their prisoner.

Do your work, then step back.
The only path to serenity.

[notes]

Can you coax your mind from its wandering
and keep to the original oneness?
Can you let your body become
supple as a newborn child’s?
Can you cleanse your inner vision
until you see nothing but the light?
Can you love people and lead them
without imposing your will?
Can you deal with the most vital matters
by letting events take their course?
Can you step back from your own mind
and thus understand all things?

Giving birth and nourishing,
having without possessing,
acting with no expectations,
leading and not trying to control:
this is the supreme virtue.

[notes]

We join spokes together in a wheel,
but it is the center hole
that makes the wagon move.

We shape clay into a pot,
but it is the emptiness inside
that holds whatever we want.

We hammer wood for a house,
but it is the inner space
that makes it livable.

We work with being,
but non-being is what we use.

[notes]

Colors blind the eye.
Sounds deafen the ear.
Flavors numb the taste.
Thoughts weaken the mind.
Desires wither the heart.

The Master observes the world
but trusts his inner vision.
He allows things to come and go.
His heart is open as the sky.

[notes]

Success is as dangerous as failure.
Hope is as hollow as fear.

What does it mean that success is as dangerous as failure?
Whether you go up the ladder or down it,
your position is shaky.
When you stand with your two feet on the ground,
you will always keep your balance.

What does it mean that hope is as hollow as fear?
Hope and fear are both phantoms
that arise from thinking of the self.
When we don’t see the self as self,
what do we have to fear?

See the world as your self.
Have faith in the way things are.
Love the world as your self;
then you can care for all things.

[notes]

Look, and it can’t be seen.
Listen, and it can’t be heard.
Reach, and it can’t be grasped.

Above, it isn’t bright.
Below, it isn’t dark.
Seamless, unnamable,
it returns to the realm of nothing.
Form that includes all forms,
image without an image,
subtle, beyond all conception.

Approach it and there is no beginning;
follow it and there is no end.
You can’t know it, but you can be it,
at ease in your own life.
Just realize where you come from:
this is the essence of wisdom.

[notes]

The ancient Masters were profound and subtle.
Their wisdom was unfathomable.
There is no way to describe it;
all we can describe is their appearance.

They were careful
as someone crossing an iced-over stream.
Alert as a warrior in enemy territory.
Courteous as a guest.
Fluid as melting ice.
Shapable as a block of wood.
Receptive as a valley.
Clear as a glass of water.

Do you have the patience to wait
till your mud settles and the water is clear?
Can you remain unmoving
till the right action arises by itself?

The Master doesn’t seek fulfillment.
Not seeking, not expecting,
she is present, and can welcome all things.

[notes]

Empty your mind of all thoughts.
Let your heart be at peace.
Watch the turmoil of beings,
but contemplate their return.

Each separate being in the universe
returns to the common source.
Returning to the source is serenity.

If you don’t realize the source,
you stumble in confusion and sorrow.
When you realize where you come from,
you naturally become tolerant,
disinterested, amused,
kindhearted as a grandmother,
dignified as a king.
Immersed in the wonder of the Tao,
you can deal with whatever life brings you,
and when death comes, you are ready.

[notes]

When the Master governs, the people
are hardly aware that he exists.
Next best is a leader who is loved.
Next, one who is feared.
The worst is one who is despised.

If you don’t trust the people,
you make them untrustworthy.

The Master doesn’t talk, he acts.
When his work is done,
the people say, “Amazing:
we did it, all by ourselves!”

[notes]

When the great Tao is forgotten,
goodness and piety appear.
When the body’s intelligence declines,
cleverness and knowledge step forth.
When there is no peace in the family,
filial piety begins.
When the country falls into chaos,
patriotism is born.

[notes]

Throw away holiness and wisdom,
and people will be a hundred times happier.
Throw away morality and justice,
and people will do the right thing.
Throw away industry and profit,
and there won’t be any thieves.

If these three aren’t enough,
just stay at the center of the circle
and let all things take their course.

[notes]

Stop thinking, and end your problems.
What difference between yes and no?
What difference between success and failure?
Must you value what others value,
avoid what others avoid?
How ridiculous!

Other people are excited,
as though they were at a parade.
I alone don’t care,
I alone am expressionless,
like an infant before it can smile.

Other people have what they need;
I alone possess nothing.
I alone drift about,
like someone without a home.
I am like an idiot, my mind is so empty.

Other people are bright;
I alone am dark.
Other people are sharp;
I alone am dull.
Other people have a purpose;
I alone don’t know.
I drift like a wave on the ocean,
I blow as aimless as the wind.

I am different from ordinary people.
I drink from the Great Mother’s breasts.

[notes]

The Master keeps her mind
always at one with the Tao;
that is what gives her her radiance.

The Tao is ungraspable.
How can her mind be at one with it?
Because she doesn’t cling to ideas.

The Tao is dark and unfathomable.
How can it make her radiant?
Because she lets it.

Since before time and space were,
the Tao is.
It is beyond is and is not.
How do I know this is true?
I look inside myself and see.

[notes]

If you want to become whole,
let yourself be partial.
If you want to become straight,
let yourself be crooked.
If you want to become full,
let yourself be empty.
If you want to be reborn,
let yourself die.
If you want to be given everything,
give everything up.

The Master, by residing in the Tao,
sets an example for all beings.
Because he doesn’t display himself,
people can see his light.
Because he has nothing to prove,
people can trust his words.
Because he doesn’t know who he is,
people recognize themselves in him.
Because he has no goal in mind,
everything he does succeeds.

When the ancient Masters said,
“If you want to be given everything,
give everything up,”
they weren’t using empty phrases.
Only in being lived by the Tao
can you be truly yourself.

[notes]

Express yourself completely,
then keep quiet.
Be like the forces of nature:
when it blows, there is only wind;
when it rains, there is only rain;
when the clouds pass, the sun shines through.

If you open yourself to the Tao,
you are at one with the Tao
and you can embody it completely.
If you open yourself to insight,
you are at one with insight
and you can use it completely.
If you open yourself to loss,
you are at one with loss
and you can accept it completely.

Open yourself to the Tao,
then trust your natural responses;
and everything will fall into place.

[notes]

He who stands on tiptoe
doesn’t stand firm.
He who rushes ahead
doesn’t go far.
He who tries to shine
dims his own light.
He who defines himself
can’t know who he really is.
He who has power over others
can’t empower himself.
He who clings to his work
will create nothing that endures.

If you want to accord with the Tao,
just do your job, then let go.

[notes]

There was something formless and perfect
before the universe was born.
It is serene. Empty.
Solitary. Unchanging.
Infinite. Eternally present.
It is the mother of the universe.
For lack of a better name,
I call it the Tao.

It flows through all things,
inside and outside, and returns
to the origin of all things.

The Tao is great.
The universe is great.
Earth is great.
Man is great.
These are the four great powers.

Man follows the earth.
Earth follows the universe.
The universe follows the Tao.
The Tao follows only itself.

[notes]

The heavy is the root of the light.
The unmoved is the source of all movement.

Thus the Master travels all day
without leaving home.
However splendid the views,
she stays serenely in herself.

Why should the lord of the country
flit about like a fool?
If you let yourself be blown to and fro,
you lose touch with your root.
If you let restlessness move you,
you lose touch with who you are.

[notes]

A good traveler has no fixed plans
and is not intent upon arriving.
A good artist lets his intuition
lead him wherever it wants.
A good scientist has freed himself of concepts
and keeps his mind open to what is.

Thus the Master is available to all people
and doesn’t reject anyone.
He is ready to use all situations
and doesn’t waste anything.
This is called embodying the light.

What is a good man but a bad man’s teacher?
What is a bad man but a good man’s job?
If you don’t understand this, you will get lost,
however intelligent you are.
It is the great secret.

[notes]

Know the male,
yet keep to the female:
receive the world in your arms.
If you receive the world,
the Tao will never leave you
and you will be like a little child.

Know the white,
yet keep to the black:
be a pattern for the world.
If you are a pattern for the world,
the Tao will be strong inside you
and there will be nothing you can’t do.

Know the personal,
yet keep to the impersonal:
accept the world as it is.
If you accept the world,
the Tao will be luminous inside you
and you will return to your primal self.

The world is formed from the void,
like utensils from a block of wood.
The Master knows the utensils,
yet keeps to the block:
thus she can use all things.

[notes]

Do you want to improve the world?
I don’t think it can be done.

The world is sacred.
It can’t be improved.
If you tamper with it, you’ll ruin it.
If you treat it like an object, you’ll lose it.

There is a time for being ahead,
a time for being behind;
a time for being in motion,
a time for being at rest;
a time for being vigorous,
a time for being exhausted;
a time for being safe,
a time for being in danger.

The Master sees things as they are,
without trying to control them.
She lets them go their own way,
and resides at the center of the circle.

[notes]

Whoever relies on the Tao in governing men
doesn’t try to force issues
or defeat enemies by force of arms.
For every force there is a counterforce.
Violence, even well intentioned,
always rebounds upon oneself.

The Master does his job
and then stops.
He understands that the universe
is forever out of control,
and that trying to dominate events
goes against the current of the Tao.
Because he believes in himself,
he doesn’t try to convince others.
Because he is content with himself,
he doesn’t need others’ approval.
Because he accepts himself,
the whole world accepts him.

[notes]

Weapons are the tools of violence;
all decent men detest them.

Weapons are the tools of fear;
a decent man will avoid them
except in the direst necessity
and, if compelled, will use them
only with the utmost restraint.
Peace is his highest value.
If the peace has been shattered,
how can he be content?
His enemies are not demons,
but human beings like himself.
He doesn’t wish them personal harm.
Nor does he rejoice in victory.
How could he rejoice in victory
and delight in the slaughter of men?

He enters a battle gravely,
with sorrow and with great compassion,
as if he were attending a funeral.

[notes]

The Tao can’t be perceived,
Smaller than an electron,
it contains uncountable galaxies.

If powerful men and women
could remain centered in the Tao,
all things would be in harmony.
The world would become a paradise.
All people would be at peace,
and the law would be written in their hearts.

When you have names and forms,
know that they are provisional.
When you have institutions,
know where their functions should end.
Knowing when to stop,
you can avoid any danger.

All things end in the
Tao as rivers flow into the sea.

[notes]

Knowing others is intelligence;
knowing yourself is true wisdom.
Mastering others is strength;
mastering yourself is true power.

If you realize that you have enough,
you are truly rich.
If you stay in the center
and embrace death with your whole heart,
you will endure forever.

[notes]

The great Tao flows everywhere.
All things are born from it,
yet it doesn’t create them.
It pours itself into its work,
yet it makes no claim.
It nourishes infinite worlds,
yet it doesn’t hold on to them.
Since it is merged with all things
and hidden in their hearts,
it can be called humble.
Since all things vanish into it
and it alone endures,
it can be called great.
It isn’t aware of its greatness;
thus it is truly great.

[notes]

She who is centered in the Tao
can go where she wishes, without danger.
She perceives the universal harmony,
even amid great pain,
because she has found peace in her heart.

Music or the smell of good cooking
may make people stop and enjoy.
But words that point to the Tao
seem monotonous and without flavor.
When you look for it, there is nothing to see.
When you listen for it, there is nothing to hear.
When you use it, it is inexhaustible.

[notes]

If you want to shrink something,
you must first allow it to expand.
If you want to get rid of something,
you must first allow it to flourish.
If you want to take something,
you must first allow it to be given.
This is called the subtle perception
of the way things are.

The soft overcomes the hard.
The slow overcomes the fast.
Let your workings remain a mystery.
Just show people the results.

[notes]

The Tao never does anything,
yet through it all things are done.

If powerful men and women
could center themselves in it,
the whole world would be transformed
by itself, in its natural rhythms.
People would be content
with their simple, everyday lives,
in harmony, and free of desire.

When there is no desire,
all things are at peace.

[notes]

The Master doesn’t try to be powerful;
thus he is truly powerful.
The ordinary man keeps reaching for power;
thus he never has enough.

The Master does nothing,
yet he leaves nothing undone.
The ordinary man is always doing things,
yet many more are left to be done.

The kind man does something,
yet something remains undone.
The just man does something,
and leaves many things to be done.
The moral man does something,
and when no one responds
he rolls up his sleeves and uses force.

When the Tao is lost, there is goodness.
When goodness is lost, there is morality.
When morality is lost, there is ritual.
Ritual is the husk of true faith,
the beginning of chaos.

Therefore the Master concerns himself
with the depths and not the surface,
with the fruit and not the flower.
He has no will of his own.
He dwells in reality,
and lets all illusions go.

[notes]

In harmony with the Tao,
the sky is clear and spacious,
the earth is solid and full,
all creatures flourish together,
content with the way they are,
endlessly repeating themselves,
endlessly renewed.

When man interferes with the Tao,
the sky becomes filthy,
the earth becomes depleted,
the equilibrium crumbles,
creatures become extinct.

The Master views the parts with compassion,
because he understands the whole.
His constant practice is humility.
He doesn’t glitter like a jewel
but lets himself be shaped by the Tao,
as rugged and common as a stone.

[notes]

Return is the movement of the Tao.
Yielding is the way of the Tao.

All things are born of being.
Being is born of non-being.

[notes]

When a superior man hears of the Tao,
he immediately begins to embody it.
When an average man hears of the Tao,
he half believes it, half doubts it.
When a foolish man hears of the Tao,
he laughs out loud.
If he didn’t laugh,
it wouldn’t be the Tao.

Thus it is said:
The path into the light seems dark,
the path forward seems to go back,
the direct path seems long,
true power seems weak,
true purity seems tarnished,
true steadfastness seems changeable,
true clarity seems obscure,
the greatest art seems unsophisticated,
the greatest love seems indifferent,
the greatest wisdom seems childish.

The Tao is nowhere to be found.
Yet it nourishes and completes all things.

[notes]

The Tao gives birth to One.
One gives birth to Two.
Two gives birth to Three.
Three gives birth to all things.

All things have their backs to the female
and stand facing the male.
When male and female combine,
all things achieve harmony.

Ordinary men hate solitude.
But the Master makes use of it,
embracing his aloneness, realizing
he is one with the whole universe.

[notes]

The gentlest thing in the world
overcomes the hardest thing in the world.
That which has no substance
enters where there is no space.
This shows the value of non-action.

Teaching without words,
performing without actions:
that is the Master’s way.

[notes]

Fame or integrity: which is more important?
Money or happiness: which is more valuable?
Success or failure: which is more destructive?

If you look to others for fulfillment,
you will never truly be fulfilled.
If your happiness depends on money,
you will never be happy with yourself.

Be content with what you have;
rejoice in the way things are.
When you realize there is nothing lacking,
the whole world belongs to you.

[notes]

True perfection seems imperfect,
yet it is perfectly itself.
True fullness seems empty,
yet it is fully present.

True straightness seems crooked.
True wisdom seems foolish.
True art seems artless.

The Master allows things to happen.
She shapes events as they come.
She steps out of the way
and lets the Tao speak for itself.

[notes]

When a country is in harmony with the Tao,
the factories make trucks and tractors.
When a country goes counter to the Tao,
warheads are stockpiled outside the cities.

There is no greater illusion than fear,
no greater wrong than preparing to defend yourself,
no greater misfortune than having an enemy.

Whoever can see through all fear
will always be safe.

[notes]

Without opening your door,
you can open your heart to the world.
Without looking out your window,
you can see the essence of the Tao.

The more you know,
the less you understand.

The Master arrives without leaving,
sees the light without looking,
achieves without doing a thing.

[notes]

In the pursuit of knowledge,
every day something is added.
In the practice of the Tao,
every day something is dropped.
Less and less do you need to force things,
until finally you arrive at non-action.
When nothing is done,
nothing is left undone.

True mastery can be gained
by letting things go their own way.
It can’t be gained by interfering.

[notes]

The Master has no mind of her own.
She works with the mind of the people.

She is good to people who are good.
She is also good to people who aren’t good.
This is true goodness.

She trusts people who are trustworthy.
She also trusts people who aren’t trustworthy.
This is true trust.

The Master’s mind is like space.
People don’t understand her.
They look to her and wait.
She treats them like her own children.

[notes]

The Master gives himself up
to whatever the moment brings.
He knows that he is going to die,
and he has nothing left to hold on to:
no illusions in his mind,
no resistances in his body.
He doesn’t think about his actions;
they flow from the core of his being.
He holds nothing back from life;
therefore he is ready for death,
as a man is ready for sleep
after a good day’s work.

[notes]

Every being in the universe
is an expression of the Tao.
It springs into existence,
unconscious, perfect, free,
takes on a physical body,
lets circumstances complete it.
That is why every being
spontaneously honors the Tao.

The Tao gives birth to all beings,
nourishes them, maintains them,
cares for them, comforts them, protects them,
takes them back to itself,
creating without possessing,
acting without expecting,
guiding without interfering.
That is why love of the Tao
is in the very nature of things.

[notes]

In the beginning was the Tao.
All things issue from it;
all things return to it.

To find the origin,
trace back to the manifestations.
When you recognize the children
and find the mother,
you will be free of sorrow.

If you close your mind in judgments
and traffic with desires,
your heart will be troubled.
If you keep your mind from judging
and aren’t led by the senses,
your heart will find peace.

Seeing into darkness is clarity.
Knowing how to yield is strength.
Use your own light
and return to the source of light.
This is called practicing eternity.

[notes]

The great Way is easy,
yet people prefer the side paths.
Be aware when things are out of balance.
Stay centered within the Tao.

When rich speculators prosper
while farmers lose their land;
when government officials spend money
on weapons instead of cures;
when the upper class is extravagant and irresponsible
while the poor have nowhere to turn—
all this is robbery and chaos.
It is not in keeping with the Tao.

[notes]

Whoever is planted in the
Tao will not be rooted up.
Whoever embraces the
Tao will not slip away.
Her name will be held in honor
from generation to generation.

Let the Tao be present in your life
and you will become genuine.
Let it be present in your family
and your family will flourish.
Let it be present in your country
and your country will be an example
to all countries in the world.
Let it be present in the universe
and the universe will sing.

How do I know this is true?
By looking inside myself.

[notes]

He who is in harmony with the Tao
is like a newborn child.
Its bones are soft, its muscles are weak,
but its grip is powerful.
It doesn’t know about the union
of male and female,
yet its penis can stand erect,
so intense is its vital power.
It can scream its head off all day,
yet it never becomes hoarse,
so complete is its harmony.

The Master’s power is like this.
He lets all things come and go
effortlessly, without desire.
He never expects results;
thus he is never disappointed.
He is never disappointed;
thus his spirit never grows old.

[notes]

Those who know don’t talk.
Those who talk don’t know.

Close your mouth,
block off your senses,
blunt your sharpness,
untie your knots,
soften your glare,
settle your dust.
This is the primal identity.

Be like the Tao.
It can’t be approached or withdrawn from,
benefited or harmed,
honored or brought into disgrace.
It gives itself up continually.
That is why it endures.

[notes]

If you want to be a great leader,
you must learn to follow the Tao.
Stop trying to control.
Let go of fixed plans and concepts,
and the world will govern itself.

The more prohibitions you have,
the less virtuous people will be.
The more weapons you have,
the less secure people will be.
The more subsidies you have,
the less self-reliant people will be.

Therefore the Master says:
I let go of the law,
and people become honest.
I let go of economics,
and people become prosperous.
I let go of religion,
and people become serene.
I let go of all desire for the common good,
and the good becomes common as grass.

[notes]

If a country is governed with tolerance,
the people are comfortable and honest.
If a country is governed with repression,
the people are depressed and crafty.

When the will to power is in charge,
the higher the ideals, the lower the results.
Try to make people happy,
and you lay the groundwork for misery.
Try to make people moral,
and you lay the groundwork for vice.

Thus the Master is content
to serve as an example
and not to impose her will.
She is pointed, but doesn’t pierce.
Straightforward, but supple.
Radiant, but easy on the eyes.

[notes]

For governing a country well
there is nothing better than moderation.

The mark of a moderate man
is freedom from his own ideas.
Tolerant like the sky,
all-pervading like sunlight,
firm like a mountain,
supple like a tree in the wind,
he has no destination in view
and makes use of anything
life happens to bring his way.

Nothing is impossible for him.
Because he has let go,
he can care for the people’s welfare
as a mother cares for her child.

[notes]

Governing a large country
is like frying a small fish.
You spoil it with too much poking.

Center your country in the Tao
and evil will have no power.
Not that it isn’t there,
but you’ll be able to step out of its way.

Give evil nothing to oppose
and it will disappear by itself.

[notes]

When a country obtains great power,
it becomes like the sea:
all streams run downward into it.
The more powerful it grows,
the greater the need for humility.
Humility means trusting the Tao,
thus never needing to be defensive.

A great nation is like a great man:
When he makes a mistake, he realizes it.
Having realized it, he admits it.
Having admitted it, he corrects it.
He considers those who point out his faults
as his most benevolent teachers.
He thinks of his enemy
as the shadow that he himself casts.

If a nation is centered in the Tao,
if it nourishes its own people
and doesn’t meddle in the affairs of others,
it will be a light to all nations in the world.

[notes]

The Tao is the center of the universe,
the good man’s treasure,
the bad man’s refuge.

Honors can be bought with fine words,
respect can be won with good deeds;
but the Tao is beyond all value,
and no one can achieve it.

Thus, when a new leader is chosen,
don’t offer to help him
with your wealth or your expertise.
Offer instead
to teach him about the Tao.

Why did the ancient Masters esteem the Tao?
Because, being one with the Tao,
when you seek, you find;
and when you make a mistake, you are forgiven.
That is why everybody loves it.

[notes]

Act without doing;
work without effort.
Think of the small as large
and the few as many.
Confront the difficult
while it is still easy;
accomplish the great task
by a series of small acts.

The Master never reaches for the great;
thus she achieves greatness.
When she runs into a difficulty,
she stops and gives herself to it.
She doesn’t cling to her own comfort;
thus problems are no problem for her.

[notes]

What is rooted is easy to nourish.
What is recent is easy to correct.
What is brittle is easy to break.
What is small is easy to scatter.

Prevent trouble before it arises.
Put things in order before they exist.
The giant pine tree
grows from a tiny sprout.
The journey of a thousand miles
starts from beneath your feet.

Rushing into action, you fail.
Trying to grasp things, you lose them.
Forcing a project to completion,
you ruin what was almost ripe.

Therefore the Master takes action
by letting things take their course.
He remains as calm
at the end as at the beginning.
He has nothing,
thus has nothing to lose.
What he desires is non-desire;
what he learns is to unlearn.
He simply reminds people
of who they have always been.
He cares about nothing but the Tao.
Thus he can care for all things.

[notes]

The ancient Masters
didn’t try to educate the people,
but kindly taught them to not-know.

When they think that they know the answers,
people are difficult to guide.
When they know that they don’t know,
people can find their own way.

If you want to learn how to govern,
avoid being clever or rich.
The simplest pattern is the clearest.
Content with an ordinary life,
you can show all people the way
back to their own true nature.

[notes]

All streams flow to the sea
because it is lower than they are.
Humility gives it its power.

If you want to govern the people,
you must place yourself below them.
If you want to lead the people,
you must learn how to follow them.

The Master is above the people,
and no one feels oppressed.
She goes ahead of the people,
and no one feels manipulated.
The whole world is grateful to her.
Because she competes with no one,
no one can compete with her.

[notes]

Some say that my teaching is nonsense.
Others call it lofty but impractical.
But to those who have looked inside themselves,
this nonsense makes perfect sense.
And to those who put it into practice,
this loftiness has roots that go deep.

I have just three things to teach:
simplicity, patience, compassion.
These three are your greatest treasures.
Simple in actions and in thoughts,
you return to the source of being.
Patient with both friends and enemies,
you accord with the way things are.
Compassionate toward yourself,
you reconcile all beings in the world.

[notes]

The best athlete
wants his opponent at his best.
The best general
enters the mind of his enemy.
The best businessman
serves the communal good.
The best leader
follows the will of the people.

All of them embody
the virtue of non-competition.
Not that they don’t love to compete,
but they do it in the spirit of play.
In this they are like children
and in harmony with the Tao.

[notes]

The generals have a saying:
“Rather than make the first move
it is better to wait and see.
Rather than advance an inch
it is better to retreat a yard.”

This is called
going forward without advancing,
pushing back without using weapons.

There is no greater misfortune
than underestimating your enemy.
Underestimating your enemy
means thinking that he is evil.
Thus you destroy your three treasures
and become an enemy yourself.

When two great forces oppose each other,
the victory will go
to the one that knows how to yield.

[notes]

My teachings are easy to understand
and easy to put into practice.
Yet your intellect will never grasp them,
and if you try to practice them, you’ll fail.

My teachings are older than the world.
How can you grasp their meaning?

If you want to know me,
look inside your heart.

[notes]

Not-knowing is true knowledge.
Presuming to know is a disease.
First realize that you are sick;
then you can move toward health.

The Master is her own physician.
She has healed herself of all knowing.
Thus she is truly whole.

[notes]

When they lose their sense of awe,
people turn to religion.
When they no longer trust themselves,
they begin to depend upon authority.

Therefore the Master steps back
so that people won’s be confused.
He teaches without a teaching,
so that people will have nothing to learn.

[notes]

The Tao is always at ease.
It overcomes without competing,
answers without speaking a word,
arrives without being summoned,
accomplishes without a plan.

Its net covers the whole universe.
And though its meshes are wide,
it doesn’t let a thing slip through.

[notes]

If you realize that all things change,
there is nothing you will try to hold on to.
If you aren’t afraid of dying,
there is nothing you can’t achieve.

Trying to control the future
is like trying to take the master carpenter’s place.
When you handle the master carpenter’s tools,
chances are that you’ll cut yourself.

[notes]

When taxes are too high,
people go hungry.
When the government is too intrusive,
people lose their spirit.

Act for the people’s benefit.
Trust them; leave them alone.

[notes]

Men are born soft and supple;
dead, they are stiff and hard.
Plants are born tender and pliant;
dead, they are brittle and dry.

Thus whoever is stiff and inflexible
is a disciple of death.
Whoever is soft and yielding
is a disciple of life.

The hard and stiff will be broken.
The soft and supple will prevail.

[notes]

As it acts in the world, the Tao
is like the bending of a bow.
The top is bent downward;
the bottom is bent up.
It adjusts excess and deficiency
so that there is perfect balance.
It takes from what is too much
and gives to what isn’t enough.

Those who try to control,
who use force to protect their power,
go against the direction of the Tao.
They take from those who don’t have enough
and give to those who have far too much.

The Master can keep giving
because there is no end to her wealth.
She acts without expectation,
succeeds without taking credit,
and doesn’t think that she is better
than anyone else.

[notes]

Nothing in the world
is as soft and yielding as water.
Yet for dissolving the hard and inflexible,
nothing can surpass it.

The soft overcomes the hard;
the gentle overcomes the rigid.
Everyone knows this is true,
but few can put it into practice.

Therefore the Master remains
serene in the midst of sorrow.
Evil cannot enter his heart.
Because he has given up helping,
he is people’s greatest help.

True words seem paradoxical.

[notes]

Failure is an opportunity.
If you blame someone else,
there is no end to the blame.

Therefore the Master
fulfills her own obligations
and corrects her own mistakes.
She does what she needs to do
and demands nothing of others.

[notes]

If a country is governed wisely,
its inhabitants will be content.
They enjoy the labor of their hands
and don’t waste time inventing
labor-saving machines.
Since they dearly love their homes,
they aren’t interested in travel.
There may be a few wagons and boats,
but these don’t go anywhere.
There may be an arsenal of weapons,
but nobody ever uses them.
People enjoy their food,
take pleasure in being with their families,
spend weekends working in their gardens,
delight in the doings of the neighborhood.
And even though the next country is so close
that people can hear its roosters crowing and its dogs barking,
they are content to die of old age
without ever having gone to see it.

[notes]

True words aren’t eloquent;
eloquent words aren’t true.
Wise men don’t need to prove their point;
men who need to prove their point aren’t wise.

The Master has no possessions.
The more he does for others,
the happier he is.
The more he gives to others,
the wealthier he is.

The Tao nourishes by not forcing.
By not dominating, the Master leads.

[notes]

Notes

01. Describing the indescribable, teaching the unteachable, pointing the way to the Way—what does Lao-tzu think he is doing here? It can’t be done. No way.

Hence Po Chü-i, poet and stand-up comedian, wrote,

“He who talks doesn’t know,
he who knows doesn’t talk”:
that is what Lao-tzu told us,
in a book of five thousand words.
If he was the one who knew,
how could he have been such a blabbermouth?

That’s the problem with spiritual teachers. They have to be blabbermouths. But their words are (in the traditional Buddhist metaphor) fingers pointing at the moon; if you watch the finger, you can’t see the moon. How meticulous the great Masters had to be!

A monk asked Ma-tsu, “Why do you teach, ‘Mind is Buddha’?”
Ma-tsu said, “To stop a baby from crying.”
The monk said, “When the crying has stopped, what then?”
Ma-tsu said, “Then I teach, ‘Not mind, not Buddha.’”
The monk said, “How about someone who isn’t attached to either?”
Ma-tsu said, “I would tell him, ‘Not beings.’”
The monk said, “And what if you met a man unattached to all things: what would you tell him?”
Ma-tsu said, “I would just let him experience the great Tao.”

In fact, the truth is right before our eyes; right under our noses; so simple that every child understands it; and yet, as Bankei said, the farther you enter into it, the deeper it is. Where is the way to the Way? What a question!

Still, for complicated minds, drastic measures are needed. Lao-tzu’s book was written as a response, out of grandmotherly kindness. According to the oldest biography,

Lao-tzu lived for a long time in the country of Chou, but seeing its decline he departed. When he reached the frontier, the guard said, “Since you are going away, Sir, could you write a book to teach me the art of living?” Thereupon Lao-tzu wrote his book about the Tao, and departed.

This is legend, but it is an accurate description of the way in which true teaching happens. He who knows doesn’t talk, but words are no hindrance for him. He uses them as he would use gardening tools. When someone asks, he answers.

The tao that can be told / is not the eternal Tao: The text reads, “The tao that can be tao-ed [one meaning of tao being ‘to express’] / is not the eternal Tao.” Other possible renderings: “The way that can be weighed / is not the eternal Way,” “The force that can be forced / is not the eternal Force.”

you realize the mystery: Infinitely marvelous, yet as ordinary as sunlight. Impossible to know, yet as easy as touching your nose when you wash your face.

This source is called darkness: Because none of our senses can perceive it. It is also called “light,” because the less we obstruct it, the more radiant we are.

The gateway to all understanding: In order to understand, we have to remain in the darkness of not-knowing. [ch.01]

02. acts without doing anything: Her actions are appropriate responses. Thus they are effortless. She embodies compassion, yet she doesn’t try to be compassionate. She doesn’t struggle to make money, yet she enjoys spending it when it comes to her. She goes her own way, yet she accepts help gratefully and has no pride in walking alone. She is not elated by praise, not discouraged by neglect. She doesn’t give even a moment’s thought to right or wrong. She never has to make a decision; decisions arise by themselves. She is like an actress who loves her role. The Tao is writing the script.

teaches without saying anything: The way she buys oranges or ties her shoelaces is a teaching. Her face is more eloquent than any scripture could be.

That is why it lasts forever: Not in time and space, but in quality. [ch.02]

03. emptying people’s minds: He empties them of concepts, judgments, and desires. Thus they can return to a state of childlike simplicity.

filling their cores: He fills them with a sense of their original identity. Thus they can return to a state of joy.

weakening their ambition: When they have no false self to nourish or defend, they find that greed, hatred, and arrogance vanish by themselves.

toughening their resolve: Their innermost intention. They develop enough self-reliance to give up the idea of self. [ch.03]

04. Following Ch’en Ku-ying, I have deleted the second stanza of the Chinese text, which seems to be an interpolation from chapter 56.

It is older than God: There is no God when there is nothing but God. [ch.04]

05. The Tao doesn’t take sides; / it gives birth to both good and evil: Literally, “Heaven and earth are impartial; they treat all things like straw dogs,” as the Master “treats all people like straw dogs,” Straw dogs were ritual objects, venerated before the ceremony but afterward abandoned and trampled underfoot. The point here is not that the Tao is cruel to things, nor that the Master is ruthless with people, but that they are impartial. The Master sees all beings arising from the same source, working out their karma (usually with great suffering), and returning to the source. And since people are in constant flux, she understands that at any moment they are capable of the most astonishing spiritual transformations. Why should she pin them motionless with a judgment of “good” or “bad”? [ch.05]

06. First stanza: Literally, “The spirit of the valley never dies. It is called the mysterious female. The gate of the mysterious female is the root of heaven and earth.” Chu Hsi said, “The female is one who receives something and, with it, creates. This creative principle is the most marvelous thing in the universe.” [ch.06]

07. The Tao is infinite, eternal: Here is everywhere. Anytime is now.

The Master stays behind; that is why she is ahead: She is like a turtle: wherever she is, is home. Actually, she is neither behind nor ahead, but exactly even with all things.

She is detached: Bunan said, “It is easy to keep things at a distance; it is hard to be naturally beyond them.” Detachment results in clarity; clarity expresses itself in love. Her heart is like a mirror, which reflects all faces, without judgment, exactly as they are. [ch.07]

08. The supreme good is like water: I asked my friend and teacher Emilie Conrad-Da’oud, founder of Continuum, to comment on this verse. She said,

Water is the source of all life, life’s matrix and fecundity; it overflows into everything, it moves everywhere. We are fundamentally water: muscled water. And the idea that we ever leave the amniotic fluid is a misconception. The amniotic fluid is the state of total nourishment and unconditional love. It is always present for us and contains everything we could possibly want. In fact, we are that fluid of love.

[ch.08]

09. Do your work, then step back: When you do your work whole-heartedly, you are glad to let it go, just as a parent lets a child go, into its own life. [ch.09]

10. Can you let your body become: Literally, “Can you concentrate your chi [vital energy] until it becomes…”

supple as a newborn child’s: Emilie Conrad-Da’oud’s comment:

There is no self-consciousness in the newborn child. Later on, the mind wanders into self-images, starts to think Should I do this? Is this movement right? and loses the immediacy of the moment. As self-consciousness develops, the muscles become less supple, less like the world. But the young child is pure fluidity. It isn’t aware of any separation, so all its movements are spontaneous and alive and whole and perfect.

If an adult body becomes truly supple, though, there’s a quality to its movement that the child’s doesn’t have, a texture of experience, a fourth dimension of time. When we watch a seventy-year-old hand move, we feel, “Yes, that hand has lived.” All the bodies it has touched, all the weights it has lifted, all the heads it has cradled are present in its movement. It is resonant with experience; the fingers curve with a sense of having been there. Whereas in a child’s hand there’s a sense of just arriving. The child’s movement is pristine and innocent and delightful, but a truly supple adult movement is awesome, because all life is included in it.

until you see nothing but the light: That is, until your heart is at peace. The great modern Indian sage Ramana Maharshi said,

There is no greater mystery than this, that we keep seeking reality though in fact we are reality. We think that there is something hiding our reality and that this must be destroyed before reality is gained. How ridiculous! A day will dawn when you will laugh at all your past efforts. That which will be on the day you laugh is also here and now.

Can you love people and lead them / without imposing your will: Emilie Conrad-Da’oud’s comment:

The more supple your body is, the less dictatorial you’ll be. The military stance is the most invasive stance that you can possibly take. Its opposite—the boneless, wishy-washy posture of someone who doesn’t stand for anything—is just as unhealthy. Suppleness is really fluidity. It transcends strength and weakness. When your body is supple, it feels like there’s no barrier in you, you can flow in any direction, your movement is a complete expression of yourself.

by letting events take their course: Literally, “by becoming the female.” The Ho-shang Kung commentary says, “In arranging one’s life properly, one should be as calm and flexible as a woman.” [ch.10]

11. non-being is what we use: The true teacher realizes that there is nothing to teach; that’s why he can teach anyone who wants to learn. The true lover realizes that there is no one to love; that’s why he is available to anyone who needs him. The Master realizes that there is nowhere to stand; that’s why he can stand anywhere. [ch.11]

12. Colors blind the eye, etc.: We need space in order to see, silence in order to hear, sleep in order to carry on with our wakefulness. If the senses are too cluttered with objects, they lose their acuteness and will eventually decay.

Desires wither the heart: Once it has let go of desires, the heart naturally overflows with love, like David’s cup in Psalm 23.

his inner vision: There is no inside or outside for him. He reflects whatever appears, without judgment, whether it is a flower or a heap of garbage, a criminal or a saint. Whatever happens is all right. He treats his own anger or grief just as he would treat an angry or grieving child: with compassion.

open as the sky: The sky holds sun, moon, stars, clouds, rain, snow, or pure azure. Because it doesn’t care which of these appear, it has room for them all. [ch.12]

13. keep your balance: The trick is to go up or down the ladder with your feet on the ground. Bravo! Bravissimo!!

See the world as your self: The outer mirrors the inner. [ch.13]

14. Look, and it can’t be seen: Another way of saying this: “Look, and it’s right before your eyes.” [ch.14]

15. till your mud settles: “Mud” stands for concepts, judgments, desires, expectations—everything that obscures and narrows reality. The Master’s life is pure and placid: predictable like the seasons, obvious like the moon. When our mind/heart becomes transparent, the light of the Tao shines through.

the water is clear: I asked my old teacher, Zen Master Seung Sahn, to comment on this verse. He said,

Our mind is like a glass of clear water. If we put salt into the water, it becomes salt water; sugar, it becomes sugar water; shit, it becomes shit water. But originally the water is clear. No thinking, no mind. No mind, no problem.

[ch.15]

16. Empty your mind: This doesn’t mean “suppress your thoughts,” but “step back from them.” Insight into the Tao has nothing to do with the intellect and its abstractions. When we step out of self-consciousness, we step into the Tao. Lin Ching-hsi said,

The mind is originally empty, and only when it remains empty, without grasping or rejecting, can it respond to natural things, without prejudice. It should be like a river gorge with a swan flying overhead; the river has no desire to retain the swan, yet the swan’s passage is traced by its shadow, without any omission. Another example: A mirror will reflect all things perfectly, whether they are beautiful or ugly; it never refuses to show a thing, nor does it retain the thing after it is gone. The mind should be as open as this.

Does this sound anti-intellectual? But listen to Einstein:

The scientist’s religious feeling takes the form of a rapturous amazement at the harmony of natural law, which reveals an intelligence of such superiority that, in comparison with it, all the systematic thinking of human beings is an utterly insignificant reflection. This feeling is the guiding principle of his life and work.

[ch.16]

17. One of several chapters that are as relevant to child-rearing as to government.

The Master doesn’t talk, he acts: His words are in perfect harmony with his actions. He is always genuine. [ch.17]

18. the great Tao: Jayata said to Vasubandu, “If you have nothing to ask for in your mind, that state of mind is called the Tao.”

goodness and piety appear: When the Tao is forgotten, people act according to rules, not from the heart. This goodness is as insecure as Job’s and can be as self-satisfied as Little Jack Horner’s. Whereas a good father has no intention of being good; he just acts naturally. [ch.18]

19. Throw away holiness and wisdom: When some folks are called saints, other folks think of themselves as sinners. When one fellow is called wise, others imagine that there is something they need to know. The Master doesn’t have these categories; for her, no one is wise or holy; thus, in her presence everyone feels at home. [ch.19]

20. yes and no:

Chao-chou asked Nan-ch’üan, “What is the Tao?”

Nan-ch’üan said, “Everyday mind is the Tao.”
Chao-chou said, “How can I approach it?”
Nan-ch’üan said, “The more you try to approach it, the farther away you’ll be.”
“But if I don’t get close, how can I understand it?”
The Master said, “It’s not a question of understanding or not understanding. Understanding is delusion; not understanding is indifference. But when you reach the unattainable Tao, it is like pure space, limitless and serene. Where is there room in it for yes or no?”

I alone don’t care: If good happens, good; if bad happens, good.

I am like an idiot: First you erase the blackboard; then you can write something new.

I am different from ordinary people: I am more ordinary. When I am hungry, I eat; when I am tired, I sleep; that’s all. Pai-chang said,

After enlightenment one is still the same as one was before. One is simply free from unreality and delusion. The ordinary person’s mind is the same as the sage’s, because Original Mind is perfect and complete in itself. After you have had this recognition, please don’t lose it.

[ch.20]

21. before time and space: Philo said, “Today means boundless and inexhaustible eternity. Months and years and all periods of time are concepts of men, who gauge everything by number; but the true name of eternity is Today.” [ch.21]

22. If you want to become whole, etc.: Unless you accept yourself, you can’t let go of yourself.

Because he doesn’t know who he is: From the standpoint of personality, he knows very well who he is; that is what allows him to use his personality for people’s benefit, rather than be used by it. But from the standpoint of his true self, there is nowhere to stand and no self to know. He doesn’t know; he just is.

Only in being lived by the Tao: This is what Paul of Tarsus meant by, “Not I, but Christ in me.” Or, in a more light-hearted vein, the little boy who when his mother got annoyed and said “Stop sneezing!” answered, “I’m not sneezing! It’s sneezing me!” [ch.22]

23. trust your natural responses: Trust the intelligence of the body. [ch.23]

24. power over others: The other is the self. When we understand this, we are able to use power wisely. [ch.24]

25. mother of the universe: As chapter 51 says, “The Tao gives birth to all beings, / nourishes them, maintains them, / cares for them, comforts them, protects them, / takes them back to itself.”

These are the four great powers: Ho-hum. [ch.25]

26. without leaving home: She never loses touch with who she really is. In the midst of joy or anger or sorrow, she remains imperturbable. [ch.26]

27. This is one of the most important chapters in the Tao Te Ching.

First stanza: I have been very free here, because the central point—openness to reality, openheartedness—needs to be made as clearly as possible. The original text reads:

A good walker leaves no traces or tracks. A good speaker makes no slips or errors. A good calculator needs no counting-sticks or tallies. A good locksmith uses no bolts or keys, yet no one can open. A good binder uses no ropes or cords, yet no one can loosen.

available to all people: Because he is not attached to his own ideas.

you will get lost: In moral judgments. The Tree of the Knowledge of Good and Evil is the Tree of Death. [ch.27]

28. Know the male, I yet keep to the female: Keeping to the receptive allows the creative to arise. Actually, the creative and the receptive are complementary sides of the same process. [ch.28]

29. Do you want to improve the world: Ramana Maharshi said,

Wanting to reform the world without discovering one’s true self is like trying to cover the world with leather to avoid the pain of walking on stones and thorns. It is much simpler to wear shoes.

It can’t be improved: This is the Sabbath mind, as in the first chapter of Genesis: when God, from a state of perfect repose, looks at the world and says, “Behold, it is very good.” Actually, this “it can’t be improved” is the greatest possible improvement. Compare chapter 35: “She perceives the universal harmony, / even amid great pain, / because she has found peace in her heart.” [ch.29]

30. doesn’t try to force issues: He lets the issues resolve themselves.

out of control: Out of the control of his own, tiny, personal, conscious self. [ch.30]

31. Peace is his highest value: Peace means wholeness. [ch.31]

32. Smaller than an electron: Neither small nor large. Neither here nor there. Neither past nor future nor present. Also (as long as we’re discussing this) all of the above. [ch.32]

33. true wisdom: When I know myself, I know others. When I master myself, I don’t need to master others. [ch.33]

34. it doesn’t create them: It is more like a mother than like an artisan, giving birth rather than making. It acts without any conscious plan or purpose. God doesn’t say, “Let there be light.” The light simply is, and is God. [ch.34]

35. peace in her heart: She is centered in the peace; thus she can give herself fully to the pain.

without flavor: Zen Master Seung Sahn’s comment:

The Great Way has no gate.
Clear water has no taste.
The tongue has no bone.
In complete stillness, a stone girl is dancing.

[ch.35]

36. If you want to shrink something: For example, defects in your character. When suppressed or ignored, they continue; but when allowed to be present in your awareness, they eventually wither away. Or, as Blake said from a slightly different perspective, “The road of excess leads to the palace of wisdom.” [ch.36]

37. If powerful men and women / could center themselves in it: They can! [ch.37]

38. The Master does nothing: He has no goal in mind, doesn’t think that he is doing anything. He’s just along for the ride.

yet he leaves nothing undone: No expectations. No regrets. No residue.

When the Tao is lost: You can never lose the Tao. But you can find it.

Therefore the Master concerns himself / with the depths and not the surface: In the depths, there is no distinction between depths and surface. Fruit in autumn, flowers in spring. He enjoys the flowers, as he enjoys the fruit. [ch.38]

39. lets himself be shaped by the Tao: As a piece of marble lets itself be shaped by the sculptor, so that the statue inside can be revealed. Hammer and chisel are necessary agents. Ouch. [ch.39]

40. Being is born of non-being: “Non-being” means beyond the categories of being and non-being. [ch.40]

41. the greatest love seems indifferent: Because it has no preferences. A good father loves all his children equally, whether they turn out to be thieves or carpenters or messiahs. As Jesus of Nazareth said, “Love your enemies [i.e., treat them with generosity and compassion], so that you may be children of your father in heaven: for he makes his sun rise on the evil and on the good, and sends his rain on the just and on the unjust.” [ch.41]

42. The Tao gives birth to One: When it’s called One, it is no longer the Tao. (When it’s called the Tao, it is no longer the Tao.)

One gives birth to Two: Oy!

Two gives birth to Three: Where will it end?

Three gives birth to all things: I knew it! Now once more from the top, with feeling.

All things have their backs to the female, etc.: Literally, “The ten thousand things carry [at their backs] the yin and embrace [in front] the yang; through the blending of the energy [chi] of these two, they achieve harmony.”

Last stanza: I have improvised here. The text reads:

People hate to be orphans, widowers, starvelings. Yet kings and princes take these names as their titles. Therefore sometimes you gain by losing; sometimes you lose by gaining. What others have taught, I teach also: ‘The violent will not die a natural death.’ I will make this the father of my teaching.

[ch.42]

43. gentlest…/ hardest…: Examples: water and rock, love and hostility. [ch.43]

44. Fame or integrity, etc.: But why be caught in these dichotomies? Once he has surrendered to the Tao, the Master accepts whatever comes to him. If fame comes, he uses it with integrity. If money comes, he uses it as pure energy. Success and failure are equally irrelevant to him, because his heart rests in the Tao. [ch.44]

45. True perfection: A cracked coffee cup. The sound of traffic outside your window.

True fullness: Attention, for example. [ch.45]

46. Whoever can see through all fear: This is the only real defense. President Roosevelt said, “We have nothing to fear but fear itself.” I would say, “Not even that.” [ch.46]

47. The more you know: The more you know without knowing yourself. [ch.47]

48. every day something is dropped: Gratefully.

True mastery can be gained: Actually, it can’t be gained. True mastery is letting things take their course. [ch.48]

49. The Master has no mind of her own: She has a strong will and a strong character, but she is permeable. And her mind is so subtle that, in comparison with the rigid thought-and desire-structures of other people, it seems to be pure space.

She also trusts people who aren’t trustworthy: Like a parent whose child has broken a rule. Of course, if a parent is genuine, the child will be genuine too. [ch.49]

50. There are a number of passages in the Tao Te Ching where a much narrower consciousness is at work than in the rest of the book. These passages may be interpolations (several show a concern with immortality, as the later, magical Taoism did). Or perhaps the old fellow had indigestion on the days he wrote them. But since my job was to re-create the essential mind of Lao-tzu, I could not in good conscience include them in this version. What I have done instead is to make improvisations on the passage’s theme, always taking care to remain within the consciousness and language of the main body of the text. For those who are curious, I have included literal translations in these notes.

The text here reads:

Coming in is life; going out is death. Three in ten are companions of life; three in ten are companions of death. And three in ten are moving from life to the place of death. Why is this? Because they live life too intensely. I have heard that he who knows how to preserve his life meets neither rhinoceros nor tiger when he travels by land, and is untouched by the sword when he enters a battle. The rhinoceros finds no place in him to drive its horn; the tiger finds no place in him to sink its claws; the soldier finds no place in him to thrust his sword. Why is this? Because in him there is no place of death.

he has nothing left: Zen Master Seung Sahn’s comment:

Coming in emptyhanded,
going out emptyhanded.
What is your original face?
The moon is shining everywhere.

[ch.50]

51. spontaneously honors the Tao: Honoring the Tao means respecting the way things are. There is a wonderful Japanese story (adapted here from Zenkei Shibayama Roshi’s A Flower Does Not Talk) which portrays this attitude:

A hundred and fifty years ago there lived a woman named Sono, whose devotion and purity of heart were respected far and wide. One day a fellow Buddhist, having made a long trip to see her, asked, “What can I do to put my heart at rest?” She said, “Every morning and every evening, and whenever anything happens to you, keep on saying, ‘Thanks for everything. I have no complaint whatsoever.’” The man did as he was instructed, for a whole year, but his heart was still not at peace. He returned to Sono, crestfallen. “I’ve said your prayer over and over, and yet nothing in my life has changed; I’m still the same selfish person as before. What should I do now?” Sono immediately said, “‘Thanks for everything. I have no complaint whatsoever.’” On hearing these words, the man was able to open his spiritual eye, and returned home with a great joy.

[ch.51]

52. trace back the manifestations: Where do you come from? [ch.52]

53. The great Way is easy: Zen Master Seng-ts’an said,

The great Way is not difficult
if you don’t cling to good and bad.
Just let go of your preferences:
and everything will be perfectly clear.

[ch.53]

54. genuine: The mark of a genuine person is straightforwardness. He has nothing to hide, nothing to defend. [ch.54]

55. like a newborn child: Chuang-tzu said,

The infant cries all day long without straining its throat. It clenches its fist all day long without cramping its hand. It stares all day long without weakening its eyes. Free from all worries, unaware of itself, it acts without thinking, doesn’t know why things happen, doesn’t need to know.

The Master’s power is like this, etc.: I have improvised here. The text reads:

To know harmony is to know the eternal; to know the eternal is to have insight. To improve upon life is ominous; to control the chi by the mind is aggressiveness. When they are too aggressive, things decay. This is non-Tao. Non-Tao soon ends.

[ch.55]

56. Those who know don’t talk. They don’t talk for the sake of talking, or to prove something, or to display themselves. They talk only if it’s appropriate (and if they feel like talking).

Those who talk don’t know: This is ignorance, not the openness of not-knowing. [ch.56]

57. the world will govern itself: Just as Nature regulates itself, without any need of our bright ideas. [ch.57]

58. Second stanza: I have improvised here. The text reads:

Prosperity rests on disaster; disaster is hidden in prosperity. Who knows the line that separates them? The normal becomes the perverted, the good becomes the monstrous. People have long been confused about this.

[ch.58]

59. I have improvised here. The text reads:

In governing people and serving heaven, nothing is better than moderation. Only he who is moderate can prepare in advance. He who prepares in advance accumulates a reserve of te [virtue or power; the Tao as it informs things and acts in the world]. He who accumulates a reserve of te overcomes all obstacles. He who overcomes all obstacles has no limits. He who has no limits can possess a country. He who possesses the mother of a country can keep it for a long time. This is called having deep roots and a strong stem, long life and enduring vision.

[ch.59]

60. step out of its way: It will be like a sword cutting the air. No harm. [ch.60]

61. I have improvised here. The text reads:

A large country is like the lower part of a river. It is the meeting-point of the universe, the female of the universe. The female, by tranquility, conquers the male. By tranquility she takes the lower position. Therefore a large country by placing itself in a lower position can conquer a small country. A small country by being in a lower position can conquer a large country. Therefore the one conquers by placing itself lower, the other conquers by being naturally lower. A large country wants nothing more than to gather people and nourish them. A small country wants nothing more than to enter and serve the people. Since both get what they want, the large country should take the lower position.

[ch.61]

62. The Tao is the center of the universe: The center is everywhere.

the good man’s treasure: It is like the magic purse: he can spend it freely, and there is always more.

the bad man’s refuge: It doesn’t judge him. Thus he can step outside his idea of himself. There is always another chance.

no one can achieve it: Because there is no “it.”

Offer instead / to teach him about the Tao: Better yet, don’t offer. The Master simply responds to circumstances in the appropriate way. If the president or the pope or a border guard has a question, he will be glad to answer it. Otherwise, he minds his business and leaves everything to the Tao. [ch.62]

63. When she runs into a difficulty: A difficulty is like a letter with her address on it. [ch.63]

64. He cares about nothing but the Tao: Which is not to say that he doesn’t love his wife, children, friends, country, planet. But he sees them in the proper perspective: of eternity. And since he and his wife love the Tao even more than they love each other, their marriage is radiant with love. This is the meaning of the Biblical verse “You shall love the Unnamable your God with all your heart, with all your soul, and with all your strength.” [ch.64]

65. kindly taught them to not-know: The ancient Masters taught them the supreme value of Don’t-know Mind, which is forever fresh, open, and fertile with possibilities. (Another name for it is Beginner’s Mind.) [ch.65]

66. The Master is above the people: Not that she feels superior, but that, looking from a higher vantage point, she can see more.

The whole world is grateful to her: Even those who think they are ungrateful.

no one can compete with her: She sees everyone as her equal. [ch.66]

67. Second stanza: I have improvised here. The text reads:

I have three treasures which I preserve and treasure. The first is compassion, the second is frugality, the third is daring not to be first in the world. Whoever has compassion can be brave. Whoever has frugality can be generous. Whoever dares not to be first in the world can become the leader of the world. But to be brave without compassion, generous without frugality, prominent without humility: this is fatal. Whoever shows compassion in battle will conquer. Whoever shows compassion in defense will stand firm. Heaven helps and protects those with compassion.

[ch.67]

68. I have improvised here. The text reads:

A skillful officer isn’t warlike. A skillful fighter isn’t violent. A skillful conqueror isn’t competitive. A skillful employer places himself below others. This is called the te of not competing. This is called the power to use men’s abilities. This is called complying with heaven. Since ancient times it has been the best way.

[ch.68]

69. Underestimating your enemy: Even thinking of him as an enemy is dangerous. If you need a word, use “opponent.” May the best man (as they say) win. [ch.69]

70. easy to put into practice: Grasses and trees have no trouble with it; animals are perfect disciples.

look inside your heart: And keep looking. Keep listening, too, until the sights and the sounds disappear by themselves. [ch.70]

71. First realize that you are sick: Novalis said, “We are close to waking up when we dream that we are dreaming.” [ch.71]

72. Therefore the Master steps back: He doesn’t act as guru or messiah, because he doesn’t want to keep people dependent on him, and thus spiritually immature. When people start to treat him like a holy man, he nips their adoration in the bud and points them to their inner messiah.

people will have nothing to learn: They just need to unlearn. [ch.72]

73. The Tao is always at ease: At ease with herself, the Master puts everyone else at ease. [ch.73]

74. Trying to control the future: Thinking that you know what is good or bad, what is advantageous or harmful. The Huai Nan Tzu tells a story about this:

A poor farmer’s horse ran off into the country of the barbarians. All his neighbors offered their condolences, but his father said, “How do you know that this isn’t good fortune?” After a few months the horse returned with a barbarian horse of excellent stock. All his neighbors offered their congratulations, but his father said, “How do you know that this isn’t a disaster?” The two horses bred, and the family became rich in fine horses. The farmer’s son spent much of his time riding them; one day he fell off and broke his hipbone. All his neighbors offered the farmer their condolences, but his father said, “How do you know that this isn’t good fortune?” Another year passed, and the barbarians invaded the frontier. All the able-bodied young men were conscripted, and nine-tenths of them died in the war. Thus good fortune can be disaster and vice versa. Who can tell how events will be transformed? [ch.74]

75. leave them alone: Offer them the gift of not being dependent on you. [ch.75]

76. disciple of life: The less rigid, the readier for life or death. [ch.76]

77. and doesn’t think that she is better: She is simply more transparent. [ch.77]

78. he is people’s greatest help: The greatest help is wholeheartedly trusting people to resolve their own problems. A true philanthropist, like a good parent, brings people to the point where they can help themselves.

True words seem paradoxical: Only when the mind is cluttered with untruth. [ch.78]

79. If you blame someone else: Confucius said,

In the archer there is a resemblance to the mature person. When he misses the mark, he turns and seeks the reason for his failure in himself.

[ch.79]

80. without ever having gone to see it: Not that they are lacking in appropriate curiosity. But they have their priorities straight. [ch.80]

81. The Master has no possessions: These no-possessions may include a house, a car, a computer, a roomful of books, and an electric toothbrush.

The more he does for others, / the happier he is: Because he is doing it for himself.

The more he gives to others, / the wealthier he is: The less he holds on to, the more he can give himself to others. When he can give himself completely, his wealth is infinite. [ch.81]

Foreword

Tao Te Ching (pronounced, more or less, Dow Deh Jing) can be translated as The Book of the Immanence of the Way or The Book of the Way and of How It Manifests Itself in the World or, simply, The Book of the Way. Since it is already well known by its Chinese title, I have let that stand.

About Lao-tzu, its author, there is practically nothing to be said. He may have been an older contemporary of Confucius (551-479 B.C.E.) and may have held the position of archive-keeper in one of the petty kingdoms of the time. But all the information that has come down to us is highly suspect. Even the meaning of his name is uncertain (the most likely interpretations: “the Old Master” or, more picturesquely, “the Old Boy”). Like an Iroquois woodsman, he left no traces. All he left us is his book: the classic manual on the art of living, written in style of gemlike lucidity, radiant with humor and grace and largeheartedness and deep wisdom: one of the wonders of the world.

People usually think of Lao-tzu as a hermit, a dropout from society, dwelling serenely in some mountain hut, unvisited except perhaps by the occasional traveler arriving from a ’60s joke to ask, “What is the meaning of life?” But it’s clear from his teachings that he deeply cared about society, if society means the welfare of one’s fellow human beings; his book is, among other things, a treatise on the art of government, whether of a country or of a child. The misperception may arise from his insistence on wei wu wei, literally “doing not-doing,” which has been seen as passivity. Nothing could be further from the truth.

A good athlete can enter a state of body-awareness in which the right stroke or the right movement happens by itself, effortlessly, without any interference of the conscious will. This is a paradigm for non-action: the purest and most effective form of action. The game plays the game; the poem writes the poem; we can’t tell the dancer from the dance.

Less and less do you need to force things,
until finally you arrive at non-action.
When nothing is done,
nothing is left undone.

Nothing is done because the doer has wholeheartedly vanished into the deed; the fuel has been completely transformed into flame. This “nothing” is, in fact, everything. It happens when we trust the intelligence of the universe in the same way that an athlete or a dancer trusts the superior intelligence of the body. Hence Lao-tzu’s emphasis on softness. Softness means the opposite of rigidity, and is synonymous with suppleness, adaptability, endurance. Anyone who has seen a t’ai chi or aikido master doing not-doing will know how powerful this softness is.

Lao-tzu’s central figure is a man or woman whose life is in perfect harmony with the way things are. This is not an idea; it is a reality; I have seen it. The Master has mastered Nature; not in the sense of conquering it, but of becoming it. In surrendering to the Tao, in giving up all concepts, judgments, and desires, her mind has grown naturally compassionate. She finds deep in her own experience the central truths of the art of living, which are paradoxical only on the surface: that the more truly solitary we are, the more compassionate we can be; the more we let go of what we love, the more present our love becomes; the clearer our insight into what is beyond good and evil, the more we can embody the good. Until finally she is able to say, in all humility, “I am the Tao, the Truth, the Life.”

The teaching of the Tao Te Ching is moral in the deepest sense. Unencumbered by any concept of sin, the Master doesn’t see evil as a force to resist, but simply as an opaqueness, a state of self-absorption which is in disharmony with the universal process, so that, as with a dirty window, the light can’t shine through. This freedom from moral categories allows him his great compassion for the wicked and the selfish.

Thus the Master is available to all people
and doesn’t reject anyone.
He is ready to use all situations
and doesn’t waste anything.
This is called embodying the light.

What is a good man but a bad man’s teacher?
What is a bad man but a good man’s job?
If you don’t understand this, you will get lost,
however intelligent you are.
It is the great secret.

The reader will notice that in the many passages where Lao-tzu describes the Master, I have used the pronoun “she” at least as often as “he.” The Chinese language doesn’t make this kind of distinction; in English we have to choose. But since we are all, potentially, the Master (since the Master is, essentially, us), I felt it would be untrue to present a male archetype, as other versions have, ironically, done. Ironically, because of all the great world religions the teaching of Lao-tzu is by far the most female. Of course, you should feel free, throughout the book, to substitute “he” for “she” or vice versa.

As to method: I worked from Paul Carus’s literal version, which provides English equivalents (often very quaint ones) alongside each of the Chinese ideograms. I also consulted dozens of translations into English, German, and French. But the most essential preparation for my work was a fourteen-year-long course of Zen training, which brought me face to face with Lao-tzu and his true disciples and heirs, the early Chinese Zen Masters.

With great poetry, the freest translation is sometimes the most faithful. “We must try its effect as an English poem,” Dr. Johnson said; “that is the way to judge of the merit of a translation.” I have often been fairly literal—or as literal as one can be with such a subtle, kaleidoscopic book as the Tao Te Ching. But I have also paraphrased, expanded, contracted, interpreted, worked with the text, played with it, until it became embodied in a language that felt genuine to me. If I haven’t always translated Lao-tzu’s words, my intention has always been to translate his mind.

The Tao that can be trodden is not the enduring and unchanging Tao. The name that can be named is not the enduring and unchanging name.

(Conceived of as) having no name, it is the Originator of heaven and earth; (conceived of as) having a name, it is the Mother of all things.

Always without desire we must be found,
If its deep mystery we would sound;
But if desire always within us be,
Its outer fringe is all that we shall see.

Under these two aspects, it is really the same; but as development takes place, it receives the different names. Together we call them the Mystery. Where the Mystery is the deepest is the gate of all that is subtle and wonderful.[37]

All in the world know the beauty of the beautiful, and in doing this they have (the idea of) what ugliness is; they all know the skill of the skilful, and in doing this they have (the idea of) what the want of skill is.

So it is that existence and nonexistence give birth the one to (the idea of) the other; that difficulty and ease produce the one (the idea of) the other; that length and shortness fashion out the one the figure of the other; that (the ideas of) height and lowness arise from the contrast of the one with the other; that the musical notes and tones become harmonious through the relation of one with another; and that being before and behind give the idea of one following another.

Therefore the sage manages affairs without doing anything, and conveys his instructions without the use of speech.

All things spring up, and there is not one which declines to show itself; they grow, and there is no claim made for their ownership; they go through their processes, and there is no expectation (of a reward for the results). The work is accomplished, and there is no resting in it (as an achievement).

The work is done, but how no one can see;
’Tis this that makes the power not cease to be.[38]

Not to value and employ men of superior ability is the way to keep the people from rivalry among themselves; not to prize articles which are difficult to procure is the way to keep them from becoming thieves; not to show them what is likely to excite their desires is the way to keep their minds from disorder.

Therefore the sage, in the exercise of his government, empties their minds, fills their bellies, weakens their wills, and strengthens their bones.

He constantly (tries to) keep them without knowledge and without desire, and where there are those who have knowledge, to keep them from presuming to act (on it). When there is this abstinence from action, good order is universal.[39]

The Tao is (like) the emptiness of a vessel; and in our employment of it we must be on our guard against all fullness. How deep and unfathomable it is, as if it were the Honoured Ancestor of all things!

We should blunt our sharp points, and unravel the complications of things; we should attemper our brightness, and bring ourselves into agreement with the obscurity of others. How pure and still the Tao is, as if it would ever so continue!

I do not know whose son it is. It might appear to have been before God.[40]

Heaven and earth do not act from (the impulse of) any wish to be benevolent; they deal with all things as the dogs of grass are dealt with. The sages do not act from (any wish to be) benevolent; they deal with the people as the dogs of grass are dealt with.

May not the space between heaven and earth be compared to a bellows?

’Tis emptied, yet it loses not its power;
’Tis moved again, and sends forth air the more.
Much speech to swift exhaustion lead we see;
Your inner being guard, and keep it free.[41]

The valley spirit dies not, aye the same;
The female mystery thus do we name.
Its gate, from which at first they issued forth,
Is called the root from which grew heaven and earth.
Long and unbroken does its power remain,
Used gently, and without the touch of pain.[42]

Heaven is long-enduring and earth continues long. The reason why heaven and earth are able to endure and continue thus long is because they do not live of, or for, themselves. This is how they are able to continue and endure.

Therefore the sage puts his own person last, and yet it is found in the foremost place; he treats his person as if it were foreign to him, and yet that person is preserved. Is it not because he has no personal and private ends, that therefore such ends are realised?[43]

The highest excellence is like (that of) water. The excellence of water appears in its benefiting all things, and in its occupying, without striving (to the contrary), the low place which all men dislike. Hence (its way) is near to (that of) the Tao.

The excellence of a residence is in (the suitability of) the place; that of the mind is in abysmal stillness; that of associations is in their being with the virtuous; that of government is in its securing good order; that of (the conduct of) affairs is in its ability; and that of (the initiation of) any movement is in its timeliness.

And when (one with the highest excellence) does not wrangle (about his low position), no one finds fault with him.[44]

It is better to leave a vessel unfilled, than to attempt to carry it when it is full. If you keep feeling a point that has been sharpened, the point cannot long preserve its sharpness.

When gold and jade fill the hall, their possessor cannot keep them safe. When wealth and honours lead to arrogancy, this brings its evil on itself. When the work is done, and one’s name is becoming distinguished, to withdraw into obscurity is the way of Heaven.[45]

When the intelligent and animal souls are held together in one embrace, they can be kept from separating. When one gives undivided attention to the (vital) breath, and brings it to the utmost degree of pliancy, he can become as a (tender) babe. When he has cleansed away the most mysterious sights (of his imagination), he can become without a flaw.

In loving the people and ruling the state, cannot he proceed without any (purpose of) action? In the opening and shutting of his gates of heaven, cannot he do so as a female bird? While his intelligence reaches in every direction, cannot he (appear to) be without knowledge?

(The Tao) produces (all things) and nourishes them; it produces them and does not claim them as its own; it does all, and yet does not boast of it; it presides over all, and yet does not control them. This is what is called “The mysterious Quality” (of the Tao).[46]

The thirty spokes unite in the one nave; but it is on the empty space (for the axle), that the use of the wheel depends. Clay is fashioned into vessels; but it is on their empty hollowness, that their use depends. The door and windows are cut out (from the walls) to form an apartment; but it is on the empty space (within), that its use depends. Therefore, what has a (positive) existence serves for profitable adaptation, and what has not that for (actual) usefulness.[47]

Colour’s five hues from th’ eyes their sight will take;
Music’s five notes the ears as deaf can make;
The flavours five deprive the mouth of taste;
The chariot course, and the wild hunting waste
Make mad the mind; and objects rare and strange,
Sought for, men’s conduct will to evil change.

Therefore the sage seeks to satisfy (the craving of) the belly, and not the (insatiable longing of the) eyes. He puts from him the latter, and prefers to seek the former.[48]

Favour and disgrace would seem equally to be feared; honour and great calamity, to be regarded as personal conditions (of the same kind).

What is meant by speaking thus of favour and disgrace? Disgrace is being in a low position (after the enjoyment of favour). The getting that (favour) leads to the apprehension (of losing it), and the losing it leads to the fear of (still greater calamity):—this is what is meant by saying that favour and disgrace would seem equally to be feared.

And what is meant by saying that honour and great calamity are to be (similarly) regarded as personal conditions? What makes me liable to great calamity is my having the body (which I call myself); if I had not the body, what great calamity could come to me?

Therefore he who would administer the kingdom, honouring it as he honours his own person, may be employed to govern it, and he who would administer it with the love which he bears to his own person may be entrusted with it.[49]

We look at it, and we do not see it, and we name it “the Equable.” We listen to it, and we do not hear it, and we name it “the Inaudible.” We try to grasp it, and do not get hold of it, and we name it “the Subtle.” With these three qualities, it cannot be made the subject of description; and hence we blend them together and obtain The One.

Its upper part is not bright, and its lower part is not obscure. Ceaseless in its action, it yet cannot be named, and then it again returns and becomes nothing. This is called the Form of the Formless, and the Semblance of the Invisible; this is called the Fleeting and Indeterminable.

We meet it and do not see its Front; we follow it, and do not see its Back. When we can lay hold of the Tao of old to direct the things of the present day, and are able to know it as it was of old in the beginning, this is called (unwinding) the clue of Tao.[50]

The skilful masters (of the Tao) in old times, with a subtle and exquisite penetration, comprehended its mysteries, and were deep (also) so as to elude men’s knowledge. As they were thus beyond men’s knowledge, I will make an effort to describe of what sort they appeared to be.

Shrinking looked they like those who wade through a stream in winter; irresolute like those who are afraid of all around them; grave like a guest (in awe of his host); evanescent like ice that is melting away; unpretentious like wood that has not been fashioned into anything; vacant like a valley, and dull like muddy water.

Who can (make) the muddy water (clear)? Let it be still, and it will gradually become clear. Who can secure the condition of rest? Let movement go on, and the condition of rest will gradually arise.

They who preserve this method of the Tao do not wish to be full (of themselves). It is through their not being full of themselves that they can afford to seem worn and not appear new and complete.[51]

The (state of) vacancy should be brought to the utmost degree, and that of stillness guarded with unwearying vigour. All things alike go through their processes of activity, and (then) we see them return (to their original state). When things (in the vegetable world) have displayed their luxuriant growth, we see each of them return to its root. This returning to their root is what we call the state of stillness; and that stillness may be called a reporting that they have fulfilled their appointed end.

The report of that fulfilment is the regular, unchanging rule. To know that unchanging rule is to be intelligent; not to know it leads to wild movements and evil issues. The knowledge of that unchanging rule produces a (grand) capacity and forbearance, and that capacity and forbearance lead to a community (of feeling with all things). From this community of feeling comes a kingliness of character; and he who is king-like goes on to be heaven-like. In that likeness to heaven he possesses the Tao. Possessed of the Tao, he endures long; and to the end of his bodily life, is exempt from all danger of decay.[52]

In the highest antiquity, (the people) did not know that there were (their rulers). In the next age they loved them and praised them. In the next they feared them; in the next they despised them. Thus it was that when faith (in the Tao) was deficient (in the rulers) a want of faith in them ensued (in the people).

How irresolute did those (earliest rulers) appear, showing (by their reticence) the importance which they set upon their words! Their work was done and their undertakings were successful, while the people all said, “We are as we are, of ourselves!”[53]

When the Great Tao (Way or Method) ceased to be observed, benevolence and righteousness came into vogue. (Then) appeared wisdom and shrewdness, and there ensued great hypocrisy.

When harmony no longer prevailed throughout the six kinships, filial sons found their manifestation; when the states and clans fell into disorder, loyal ministers appeared.[54]

If we could renounce our sageness and discard our wisdom, it would be better for the people a hundredfold. If we could renounce our benevolence and discard our righteousness, the people would again become filial and kindly. If we could renounce our artful contrivances and discard our (scheming for) gain, there would be no thieves nor robbers.

Those three methods (of government)
Thought olden ways in elegance did fail
And made these names their want of worth to veil;
But simple views, and courses plain and true
Would selfish ends and many lusts eschew.[55]

When we renounce learning we have no troubles.
The (ready) “yes,” and (flattering) “yea;”—
Small is the difference they display.
But mark their issues, good and ill;—
What space the gulf between shall fill?

What all men fear is indeed to be feared; but how wide and without end is the range of questions (asking to be discussed)!

The multitude of men look satisfied and pleased; as if enjoying a full banquet, as if mounted on a tower in spring. I alone seem listless and still, my desires having as yet given no indication of their presence. I am like an infant which has not yet smiled. I look dejected and forlorn, as if I had no home to go to. The multitude of men all have enough and to spare. I alone seem to have lost everything. My mind is that of a stupid man; I am in a state of chaos.

Ordinary men look bright and intelligent, while I alone seem to be benighted. They look full of discrimination, while I alone am dull and confused. I seem to be carried about as on the sea, drifting as if I had nowhere to rest. All men have their spheres of action, while I alone seem dull and incapable, like a rude borderer. (Thus) I alone am different from other men, but I value the nursing-mother (the Tao).[56]

The grandest forms of active force
From Tao come, their only source.
Who can of Tao the nature tell?
Our sight it flies, our touch as well.
Eluding sight, eluding touch,
The forms of things all in it crouch;
Eluding touch, eluding sight,
There are their semblances, all right.
Profound it is, dark and obscure;
Things’ essences all there endure.
Those essences the truth enfold
Of what, when seen, shall then be told.
Now it is so; ’twas so of old.
Its name—what passes not away;
So, in their beautiful array,
Things form and never know decay.

How know I that it is so with all the beauties of existing things? By this (nature of the Tao).[57]

The partial becomes complete; the crooked, straight; the empty, full; the worn out, new. He whose (desires) are few gets them; he whose (desires) are many goes astray.

Therefore the sage holds in his embrace the one thing (of humility), and manifests it to all the world. He is free from self-display, and therefore he shines; from self-assertion, and therefore he is distinguished; from self-boasting, and therefore his merit is acknowledged; from self-complacency, and therefore he acquires superiority. It is because he is thus free from striving that therefore no one in the world is able to strive with him.

That saying of the ancients that “the partial becomes complete” was not vainly spoken:—all real completion is comprehended under it.[58]

Abstaining from speech marks him who is obeying the spontaneity of his nature. A violent wind does not last for a whole morning; a sudden rain does not last for the whole day. To whom is it that these (two) things are owing? To Heaven and Earth. If Heaven and Earth cannot make such (spasmodic) actings last long, how much less can man!

Therefore when one is making the Tao his business, those who are also pursuing it, agree with him in it, and those who are making the manifestation of its course their object agree with him in that; while even those who are failing in both these things agree with him where they fail.

Hence, those with whom he agrees as to the Tao have the happiness of attaining to it; those with whom he agrees as to its manifestation have the happiness of attaining to it; and those with whom he agrees in their failure have also the happiness of attaining (to the Tao). (But) when there is not faith sufficient (on his part), a want of faith (in him) ensues (on the part of the others).[59]

He who stands on his tiptoes does not stand firm; he who stretches his legs does not walk (easily). (So), he who displays himself does not shine; he who asserts his own views is not distinguished; he who vaunts himself does not find his merit acknowledged; he who is self-conceited has no superiority allowed to him. Such conditions, viewed from the standpoint of the Tao, are like remnants of food, or a tumour on the body, which all dislike. Hence those who pursue (the course) of the Tao do not adopt and allow them.[60]

There was something undefined and complete, coming into existence before Heaven and Earth. How still it was and formless, standing alone, and undergoing no change, reaching everywhere and in no danger (of being exhausted)! It may be regarded as the Mother of all things.

I do not know its name, and I give it the designation of the Tao (the Way or Course). Making an effort (further) to give it a name I call it The Great.

Great, it passes on (in constant flow). Passing on, it becomes remote. Having become remote, it returns. Therefore the Tao is great; Heaven is great; Earth is great; and the (sage) king is also great. In the universe there are four that are great, and the (sage) king is one of them.

Man takes his law from the Earth; the Earth takes its law from Heaven; Heaven takes its law from the Tao. The law of the Tao is its being what it is.[61]

Gravity is the root of lightness; stillness, the ruler of movement.

Therefore a wise prince, marching the whole day, does not go far from his baggage wagons. Although he may have brilliant prospects to look at, he quietly remains (in his proper place), indifferent to them. How should the lord of a myriad chariots carry himself lightly before the kingdom? If he do act lightly, he has lost his root (of gravity); if he proceed to active movement, he will lose his throne.[62]

The skilful traveller leaves no traces of his wheels or footsteps; the skilful speaker says nothing that can be found fault with or blamed; the skilful reckoner uses no tallies; the skilful closer needs no bolts or bars, while to open what he has shut will be impossible; the skilful binder uses no strings or knots, while to unloose what he has bound will be impossible. In the same way the sage is always skilful at saving men, and so he does not cast away any man; he is always skilful at saving things, and so he does not cast away anything. This is called “Hiding the light of his procedure.”

Therefore the man of skill is a master (to be looked up to) by him who has not the skill; and he who has not the skill is the helper of (the reputation of) him who has the skill. If the one did not honour his master, and the other did not rejoice in his helper, an (observer), though intelligent, might greatly err about them. This is called “The utmost degree of mystery.”[63]

Who knows his manhood’s strength,
Yet still his female feebleness maintains;
As to one channel flow the many drains,
All come to him, yea, all beneath the sky.
Thus he the constant excellence retains;
The simple child again, free from all stains.

Who knows how white attracts,
Yet always keeps himself within black’s shade,
The pattern of humility displayed,
Displayed in view of all beneath the sky;
He in the unchanging excellence arrayed,
Endless return to man’s first state has made.

Who knows how glory shines,
Yet loves disgrace, nor e’er for it is pale;
Behold his presence in a spacious vale,
To which men come from all beneath the sky.
The unchanging excellence completes its tale;
The simple infant man in him we hail.

The unwrought material, when divided and distributed, forms vessels. The sage, when employed, becomes the Head of all the Officers (of government); and in his greatest regulations he employs no violent measures.[64]

If anyone should wish to get the kingdom for himself, and to effect this by what he does, I see that he will not succeed. The kingdom is a spirit-like thing, and cannot be got by active doing. He who would so win it destroys it; he who would hold it in his grasp loses it.

The course and nature of things is such that
What was in front is now behind;
What warmed anon we freezing find.
Strength is of weakness oft the spoil;
The store in ruins mocks our toil.

Hence the sage puts away excessive effort, extravagance, and easy indulgence.[65]

He who would assist a lord of men in harmony with the Tao will not assert his mastery in the kingdom by force of arms. Such a course is sure to meet with its proper return.

Wherever a host is stationed, briars and thorns spring up. In the sequence of great armies there are sure to be bad years.

A skilful (commander) strikes a decisive blow, and stops. He does not dare (by continuing his operations) to assert and complete his mastery. He will strike the blow, but will be on his guard against being vain or boastful or arrogant in consequence of it. He strikes it as a matter of necessity; he strikes it, but not from a wish for mastery.

When things have attained their strong maturity they become old. This may be said to be not in accordance with the Tao: and what is not in accordance with it soon comes to an end.[66]

Now arms, however beautiful, are instruments of evil omen, hateful, it may be said, to all creatures. Therefore they who have the Tao do not like to employ them.

The superior man ordinarily considers the left hand the most honourable place, but in time of war the right hand. Those sharp weapons are instruments of evil omen, and not the instruments of the superior man;—he uses them only on the compulsion of necessity. Calm and repose are what he prizes; victory (by force of arms) is to him undesirable. To consider this desirable would be to delight in the slaughter of men; and he who delights in the slaughter of men cannot get his will in the kingdom.

On occasions of festivity to be on the left hand is the prized position; on occasions of mourning, the right hand. The second in command of the army has his place on the left; the general commanding in chief has his on the right;—his place, that is, is assigned to him as in the rites of mourning. He who has killed multitudes of men should weep for them with the bitterest grief; and the victor in battle has his place (rightly) according to those rites.[67]

The Tao, considered as unchanging, has no name.

Though in its primordial simplicity it may be small, the whole world dares not deal with (one embodying) it as a minister. If a feudal prince or the king could guard and hold it, all would spontaneously submit themselves to him.

Heaven and Earth (under its guidance) unite together and send down the sweet dew, which, without the directions of men, reaches equally everywhere as of its own accord.

As soon as it proceeds to action, it has a name. When it once has that name, (men) can know to rest in it. When they know to rest in it, they can be free from all risk of failure and error.

The relation of the Tao to all the world is like that of the great rivers and seas to the streams from the valleys.[68]

He who knows other men is discerning; he who knows himself is intelligent. He who overcomes others is strong; he who overcomes himself is mighty. He who is satisfied with his lot is rich; he who goes on acting with energy has a (firm) will.

He who does not fail in the requirements of his position, continues long; he who dies and yet does not perish, has longevity.[69]

All-pervading is the Great Tao! It may be found on the left hand and on the right.

All things depend on it for their production, which it gives to them, not one refusing obedience to it. When its work is accomplished, it does not claim the name of having done it. It clothes all things as with a garment, and makes no assumption of being their lord;—it may be named in the smallest things. All things return (to their root and disappear), and do not know that it is it which presides over their doing so;—it may be named in the greatest things.

Hence the sage is able (in the same way) to accomplish his great achievements. It is through his not making himself great that he can accomplish them.[70]

To him who holds in his hands the Great Image (of the invisible Tao), the whole world repairs. Men resort to him, and receive no hurt, but (find) rest, peace, and the feeling of ease.

Music and dainties will make the passing guest stop (for a time). But though the Tao as it comes from the mouth, seems insipid and has no flavour, though it seems not worth being looked at or listened to, the use of it is inexhaustible.[71]

When one is about to take an inspiration, he is sure to make a (previous) expiration; when he is going to weaken another, he will first strengthen him; when he is going to overthrow another, he will first have raised him up; when he is going to despoil another, he will first have made gifts to him:—this is called “Hiding the light (of his procedure).”

The soft overcomes the hard; and the weak the strong.

Fishes should not be taken from the deep; instruments for the profit of a state should not be shown to the people.[72]

The Tao in its regular course does nothing (for the sake of doing it), and so there is nothing which it does not do.

If princes and kings were able to maintain it, all things would of themselves be transformed by them.

If this transformation became to me an object of desire, I would express the desire by the nameless simplicity.

Simplicity without a name
Is free from all external aim.
With no desire, at rest and still,
All things go right as of their will.[73]

(Those who) possessed in highest degree the attributes (of the Tao) did not (seek) to show them, and therefore they possessed them (in fullest measure). (Those who) possessed in a lower degree those attributes (sought how) not to lose them, and therefore they did not possess them (in fullest measure).

(Those who) possessed in the highest degree those attributes did nothing (with a purpose), and had no need to do anything. (Those who) possessed them in a lower degree were (always) doing, and had need to be so doing.

(Those who) possessed the highest benevolence were (always seeking) to carry it out, and had no need to be doing so. (Those who) possessed the highest righteousness were (always seeking) to carry it out, and had need to be so doing.

(Those who) possessed the highest (sense of) propriety were (always seeking) to show it, and when men did not respond to it, they bared the arm and marched up to them.

Thus it was that when the Tao was lost, its attributes appeared; when its attributes were lost, benevolence appeared; when benevolence was lost, righteousness appeared; and when righteousness was lost, the proprieties appeared.

Now propriety is the attenuated form of leal-heartedness and good faith, and is also the commencement of disorder; swift apprehension is (only) a flower of the Tao, and is the beginning of stupidity.

Thus it is that the Great man abides by what is solid, and eschews what is flimsy; dwells with the fruit and not with the flower. It is thus that he puts away the one and makes choice of the other.[74]

The things which from of old have got the One (the Tao) are—

Heaven which by it is bright and pure;
Earth rendered thereby firm and sure;
Spirits with powers by it supplied;
Valleys kept full throughout their void
All creatures which through it do live
Princes and kings who from it get
The model which to all they give.

All these are the results of the One (Tao).

If heaven were not thus pure, it soon would rend;
If earth were not thus sure, ’twould break and bend;
Without these powers, the spirits soon would fail;
If not so filled, the drought would parch each vale;
Without that life, creatures would pass away;
Princes and kings, without that moral sway,
However grand and high, would all decay.

Thus it is that dignity finds its (firm) root in its (previous) meanness, and what is lofty finds its stability in the lowness (from which it rises). Hence princes and kings call themselves “Orphans,” “Men of small virtue,” and as “Carriages without a nave.” Is not this an acknowledgement that in their considering themselves mean they see the foundation of their dignity? So it is that in the enumeration of the different parts of a carriage we do not come on what makes it answer the ends of a carriage. They do not wish to show themselves elegant-looking as jade, but (prefer) to be coarse-looking as an (ordinary) stone.[75]

The movement of the Tao
By contraries proceeds;
And weakness marks the course
Of Tao’s mighty deeds.

All things under heaven sprang from It as existing (and named); that existence sprang from It as nonexistent (and not named).[76]

Scholars of the highest class, when they hear about the Tao, earnestly carry it into practice. Scholars of the middle class, when they have heard about it, seem now to keep it and now to lose it. Scholars of the lowest class, when they have heard about it, laugh greatly at it. If it were not (thus) laughed at, it would not be fit to be the Tao.

Therefore the sentence-makers have thus expressed themselves:—

“The Tao, when brightest seen, seems light to lack;
Who progress in it makes, seems drawing back;
Its even way is like a rugged track.
Its highest virtue from the vale doth rise;
Its greatest beauty seems to offend the eyes;
And he has most whose lot the least supplies.
Its firmest virtue seems but poor and low;
Its solid truth seems change to undergo;
Its largest square doth yet no corner show
A vessel great, it is the slowest made;
Loud is its sound, but never word it said;
A semblance great, the shadow of a shade.”

The Tao is hidden, and has no name; but it is the Tao which is skilful at imparting (to all things what they need) and making them complete.[77]

The Tao produced One; One produced Two; Two produced Three; Three produced All things. All things leave behind them the Obscurity (out of which they have come), and go forward to embrace the Brightness (into which they have emerged), while they are harmonised by the Breath of Vacancy.

What men dislike is to be orphans, to have little virtue, to be as carriages without naves; and yet these are the designations which kings and princes use for themselves. So it is that some things are increased by being diminished, and others are diminished by being increased.

What other men (thus) teach, I also teach. The violent and strong do not die their natural death. I will make this the basis of my teaching.[78]

The softest thing in the world dashes against and overcomes the hardest; that which has no (substantial) existence enters where there is no crevice. I know hereby what advantage belongs to doing nothing (with a purpose).

There are few in the world who attain to the teaching without words, and the advantage arising from non-action.[79]

Of fame or life,
Which do you hold more dear?
Of life or wealth,
To which would you adhere?
Keep life and lose those other things;
Keep them and lose your life:—which brings
Sorrow and pain more near?

Thus we may see,
Who cleaves to fame
Rejects what is more great;
Who loves large stores
Gives up the richer state.

Who is content
Needs fear no shame.
Who knows to stop
Incurs no blame.
From danger free
Long live shall he.[80]

Who thinks his great achievements poor
Shall find his vigour long endure.
Of greatest fullness, deemed a void,
Exhaustion ne’er shall stem the tide.
Do thou what’s straight still crooked deem;
Thy greatest art still stupid seem,
And eloquence a stammering scream.

Constant action overcomes cold; being still overcomes heat. Purity and stillness give the correct law to all under heaven.[81]

When the Tao prevails in the world, they send back their swift horses to (draw) the dung-carts. When the Tao is disregarded in the world, the warhorses breed in the border lands.

There is no guilt greater than to sanction ambition; no calamity greater than to be discontented with one’s lot; no fault greater than the wish to be getting. Therefore the sufficiency of contentment is an enduring and unchanging sufficiency.[82]

Without going outside his door, one understands (all that takes place) under the sky; without looking out from his window, one sees the Tao of Heaven. The farther that one goes out (from himself), the less he knows.

Therefore the sages got their knowledge without travelling; gave their (right) names to things without seeing them; and accomplished their ends without any purpose of doing so.[83]

He who devotes himself to learning (seeks) from day to day to increase (his knowledge); he who devotes himself to the Tao (seeks) from day to day to diminish (his doing).

He diminishes it and again diminishes it, till he arrives at doing nothing (on purpose). Having arrived at this point of non-action, there is nothing which he does not do.

He who gets as his own all under heaven does so by giving himself no trouble (with that end). If one take trouble (with that end), he is not equal to getting as his own all under heaven.[84]

The sage has no invariable mind of his own; he makes the mind of the people his mind.

To those who are good (to me), I am good; and to those who are not good (to me), I am also good;—and thus (all) get to be good. To those who are sincere (with me), I am sincere; and to those who are not sincere (with me), I am also sincere;—and thus (all) get to be sincere.

The sage has in the world an appearance of indecision, and keeps his mind in a state of indifference to all. The people all keep their eyes and ears directed to him, and he deals with them all as his children.[85]

Men come forth and live; they enter (again) and die.

Of every ten three are ministers of life (to themselves); and three are ministers of death.

There are also three in every ten whose aim is to live, but whose movements tend to the land (or place) of death. And for what reason? Because of their excessive endeavours to perpetuate life.

But I have heard that he who is skilful in managing the life entrusted to him for a time travels on the land without having to shun rhinoceros or tiger, and enters a host without having to avoid buff coat or sharp weapon. The rhinoceros finds no place in him into which to thrust its horn, nor the tiger a place in which to fix its claws, nor the weapon a place to admit its point. And for what reason? Because there is in him no place of death.[86]

All things are produced by the Tao, and nourished by its outflowing operation. They receive their forms according to the nature of each, and are completed according to the circumstances of their condition. Therefore all things without exception honour the Tao, and exalt its outflowing operation.

This honouring of the Tao and exalting of its operation is not the result of any ordination, but always a spontaneous tribute.

Thus it is that the Tao produces (all things), nourishes them, brings them to their full growth, nurses them, completes them, matures them, maintains them, and overspreads them.

It produces them and makes no claim to the possession of them; it carries them through their processes and does not vaunt its ability in doing so; it brings them to maturity and exercises no control over them;—this is called its mysterious operation.[87]

(The Tao) which originated all under the sky is to be considered as the mother of them all.

When the mother is found, we know what her children should be. When one knows that he is his mother’s child, and proceeds to guard (the qualities of) the mother that belong to him, to the end of his life he will be free from all peril.

Let him keep his mouth closed, and shut up the portals (of his nostrils), and all his life he will be exempt from laborious exertion. Let him keep his mouth open, and (spend his breath) in the promotion of his affairs, and all his life there will be no safety for him.

The perception of what is small is (the secret of) clear-sightedness; the guarding of what is soft and tender is (the secret of) strength.

Who uses well his light,
Reverting to its (source so) bright,
Will from his body ward all blight,
And hides the unchanging from men’s sight.[88]

If I were suddenly to become known, and (put into a position to) conduct (a government) according to the Great Tao, what I should be most afraid of would be a boastful display.

The great Tao (or way) is very level and easy; but people love the byways.

Their court(-yards and buildings) shall be well kept, but their fields shall be ill-cultivated, and their granaries very empty. They shall wear elegant and ornamented robes, carry a sharp sword at their girdle, pamper themselves in eating and drinking, and have a superabundance of property and wealth;—such (princes) may be called robbers and boasters. This is contrary to the Tao surely![89]

What (Tao’s) skilful planter plants
Can never be uptorn;
What his skilful arms enfold,
From him can ne’er be borne.
Sons shall bring in lengthening line,
Sacrifices to his shrine.

Tao when nursed within one’s self,
His vigour will make true;
And where the family it rules
What riches will accrue!
The neighbourhood where it prevails
In thriving will abound;
And when ’tis seen throughout the state,
Good fortune will be found.
Employ it the kingdom o’er,
And men thrive all around.

In this way the effect will be seen in the person, by the observation of different cases; in the family; in the neighbourhood; in the state; and in the kingdom.

How do I know that this effect is sure to hold thus all under the sky? By this (method of observation).[90]

He who has in himself abundantly the attributes (of the Tao) is like an infant. Poisonous insects will not sting him; fierce beasts will not seize him; birds of prey will not strike him.

(The infant’s) bones are weak and its sinews soft, but yet its grasp is firm. It knows not yet the union of male and female, and yet its virile member may be excited;—showing the perfection of its physical essence. All day long it will cry without its throat becoming hoarse;—showing the harmony (in its constitution).

To him by whom this harmony is known,
(The secret of) the unchanging (Tao) is shown,
And in the knowledge wisdom finds its throne.
All life-increasing arts to evil turn;
Where the mind makes the vital breath to burn,
(False) is the strength, (and o’er it we should mourn.)

When things have become strong, they (then) become old, which may be said to be contrary to the Tao. Whatever is contrary to the Tao soon ends.[91]

He who knows (the Tao) does not (care to) speak (about it); he who is (ever ready to) speak about it does not know it.

He (who knows it) will keep his mouth shut and close the portals (of his nostrils). He will blunt his sharp points and unravel the complications of things; he will attemper his brightness, and bring himself into agreement with the obscurity (of others). This is called “the Mysterious Agreement.”

(Such an one) cannot be treated familiarly or distantly; he is beyond all consideration of profit or injury; of nobility or meanness:—he is the noblest man under heaven.[92]

A state may be ruled by (measures of) correction; weapons of war may be used with crafty dexterity; (but) the kingdom is made one’s own (only) by freedom from action and purpose.

How do I know that it is so? By these facts:—In the kingdom the multiplication of prohibitive enactments increases the poverty of the people; the more implements to add to their profit that the people have, the greater disorder is there in the state and clan; the more acts of crafty dexterity that men possess, the more do strange contrivances appear; the more display there is of legislation, the more thieves and robbers there are.

Therefore a sage has said, “I will do nothing (of purpose), and the people will be transformed of themselves; I will be fond of keeping still, and the people will of themselves become correct. I will take no trouble about it, and the people will of themselves become rich; I will manifest no ambition, and the people will of themselves attain to the primitive simplicity.”[93]

The government that seems the most unwise,
Oft goodness to the people best supplies;
That which is meddling, touching everything,
Will work but ill, and disappointment bring.

Misery!—happiness is to be found by its side! Happiness!—misery lurks beneath it! Who knows what either will come to in the end?

Shall we then dispense with correction? The (method of) correction shall by a turn become distortion, and the good in it shall by a turn become evil. The delusion of the people (on this point) has indeed subsisted for a long time.

Therefore the sage is (like) a square which cuts no one (with its angles); (like) a corner which injures no one (with its sharpness). He is straightforward, but allows himself no license; he is bright, but does not dazzle.[94]

For regulating the human (in our constitution) and rendering the (proper) service to the heavenly, there is nothing like moderation.

It is only by this moderation that there is effected an early return (to man’s normal state). That early return is what I call the repeated accumulation of the attributes (of the Tao). With that repeated accumulation of those attributes, there comes the subjugation (of every obstacle to such return). Of this subjugation we know not what shall be the limit; and when one knows not what the limit shall be, he may be the ruler of a state.

He who possesses the mother of the state may continue long. His case is like that (of the plant) of which we say that its roots are deep and its flower stalks firm:—this is the way to secure that its enduring life shall long be seen.[95]

Governing a great state is like cooking small fish.

Let the kingdom be governed according to the Tao, and the manes of the departed will not manifest their spiritual energy. It is not that those manes have not that spiritual energy, but it will not be employed to hurt men. It is not that it could not hurt men, but neither does the ruling sage hurt them.

When these two do not injuriously affect each other, their good influences converge in the virtue (of the Tao).[96]

What makes a great state is its being (like) a low-lying, down-flowing (stream);—it becomes the centre to which tend (all the small states) under heaven.

(To illustrate from) the case of all females:—the female always overcomes the male by her stillness. Stillness may be considered (a sort of) abasement.

Thus it is that a great state, by condescending to small states, gains them for itself; and that small states, by abasing themselves to a great state, win it over to them. In the one case the abasement leads to gaining adherents, in the other case to procuring favour.

The great state only wishes to unite men together and nourish them; a small state only wishes to be received by, and to serve, the other. Each gets what it desires, but the great state must learn to abase itself.[97]

Tao has of all things the most honoured place.
No treasures give good men so rich a grace;
Bad men it guards, and doth their ill efface.

(Its) admirable words can purchase honour; (its) admirable deeds can raise their performer above others. Even men who are not good are not abandoned by it.

Therefore when the sovereign occupies his place as the Son of Heaven, and he has appointed his three ducal ministers, though (a prince) were to send in a round symbol-of-rank large enough to fill both the hands, and that as the precursor of the team of horses (in the courtyard), such an offering would not be equal to (a lesson of) this Tao, which one might present on his knees.

Why was it that the ancients prized this Tao so much? Was it not because it could be got by seeking for it, and the guilty could escape (from the stain of their guilt) by it? This is the reason why all under heaven consider it the most valuable thing.[98]

(It is the way of the Tao) to act without (thinking of) acting; to conduct affairs without (feeling the) trouble of them; to taste without discerning any flavour; to consider what is small as great, and a few as many; and to recompense injury with kindness.

(The master of it) anticipates things that are difficult while they are easy, and does things that would become great while they are small. All difficult things in the world are sure to arise from a previous state in which they were easy, and all great things from one in which they were small. Therefore the sage, while he never does what is great, is able on that account to accomplish the greatest things.

He who lightly promises is sure to keep but little faith; he who is continually thinking things easy is sure to find them difficult. Therefore the sage sees difficulty even in what seems easy, and so never has any difficulties.[99]

That which is at rest is easily kept hold of; before a thing has given indications of its presence, it is easy to take measures against it; that which is brittle is easily broken; that which is very small is easily dispersed. Action should be taken before a thing has made its appearance; order should be secured before disorder has begun.

The tree which fills the arms grew from the tiniest sprout; the tower of nine storeys rose from a (small) heap of earth; the journey of a thousand li commenced with a single step.

He who acts (with an ulterior purpose) does harm; he who takes hold of a thing (in the same way) loses his hold. The sage does not act (so), and therefore does no harm; he does not lay hold (so), and therefore does not lose his bold. (But) people in their conduct of affairs are constantly ruining them when they are on the eve of success. If they were careful at the end, as (they should be) at the beginning, they would not so ruin them.

Therefore the sage desires what (other men) do not desire, and does not prize things difficult to get; he learns what (other men) do not learn, and turns back to what the multitude of men have passed by. Thus he helps the natural development of all things, and does not dare to act (with an ulterior purpose of his own).[100]

The ancients who showed their skill in practising the Tao did so, not to enlighten the people, but rather to make them simple and ignorant.

The difficulty in governing the people arises from their having much knowledge. He who (tries to) govern a state by his wisdom is a scourge to it; while he who does not (try to) do so is a blessing.

He who knows these two things finds in them also his model and rule. Ability to know this model and rule constitutes what we call the mysterious excellence (of a governor). Deep and far-reaching is such mysterious excellence, showing indeed its possessor as opposite to others, but leading them to a great conformity to him.[101]

That whereby the rivers and seas are able to receive the homage and tribute of all the valley streams, is their skill in being lower than they;—it is thus that they are the kings of them all. So it is that the sage (ruler), wishing to be above men, puts himself by his words below them, and, wishing to be before them, places his person behind them.

In this way though he has his place above them, men do not feel his weight, nor though he has his place before them, do they feel it an injury to them.

Therefore all in the world delight to exalt him and do not weary of him. Because he does not strive, no one finds it possible to strive with him.[102]

All the world says that, while my Tao is great, it yet appears to be inferior (to other systems of teaching). Now it is just its greatness that makes it seem to be inferior. If it were like any other (system), for long would its smallness have been known!

But I have three precious things which I prize and hold fast. The first is gentleness; the second is economy; and the third is shrinking from taking precedence of others.

With that gentleness I can be bold; with that economy I can be liberal; shrinking from taking precedence of others, I can become a vessel of the highest honour. Nowadays they give up gentleness and are all for being bold; economy, and are all for being liberal; the hindmost place, and seek only to be foremost;—(of all which the end is) death.

Gentleness is sure to be victorious even in battle, and firmly to maintain its ground. Heaven will save its possessor, by his (very) gentleness protecting him.[103]

He who in (Tao’s) wars has skill
Assumes no martial port;
He who fights with most good will
To rage makes no resort.
He who vanquishes yet still
Keeps from his foes apart;
He whose hests men most fulfil
Yet humbly plies his art.

Thus we say, “He ne’er contends,
And therein is his might.”
Thus we say, “Men’s wills he bends,
That they with him unite.”
Thus we say, “Like Heaven’s his ends,
No sage of old more bright.”[104]

A master of the art of war has said, “I do not dare to be the host (to commence the war); I prefer to be the guest (to act on the defensive). I do not dare to advance an inch; I prefer to retire a foot.” This is called marshalling the ranks where there are no ranks; baring the arms (to fight) where there are no arms to bare; grasping the weapon where there is no weapon to grasp; advancing against the enemy where there is no enemy.

There is no calamity greater than lightly engaging in war. To do that is near losing (the gentleness) which is so precious. Thus it is that when opposing weapons are (actually) crossed, he who deplores (the situation) conquers.[105]

My words are very easy to know, and very easy to practise; but there is no one in the world who is able to know and able to practise them.

There is an originating and all-comprehending (principle) in my words, and an authoritative law for the things (which I enforce). It is because they do not know these, that men do not know me.

They who know me are few, and I am on that account (the more) to be prized. It is thus that the sage wears (a poor garb of) hair cloth, while he carries his (signet of) jade in his bosom.[106]

To know and yet (think) we do not know is the highest (attainment); not to know (and yet think) we do know is a disease.

It is simply by being pained at (the thought of) having this disease that we are preserved from it. The sage has not the disease. He knows the pain that would be inseparable from it, and therefore he does not have it.[107]

When the people do not fear what they ought to fear, that which is their great dread will come on them.

Let them not thoughtlessly indulge themselves in their ordinary life; let them not act as if weary of what that life depends on.

It is by avoiding such indulgence that such weariness does not arise.

Therefore the sage knows (these things) of himself, but does not parade (his knowledge); loves, but does not (appear to set a) value on, himself. And thus he puts the latter alternative away and makes choice of the former.[108]

He whose boldness appears in his daring (to do wrong, in defiance of the laws) is put to death; he whose boldness appears in his not daring (to do so) lives on. Of these two cases the one appears to be advantageous, and the other to be injurious. But

When Heaven’s anger smites a man,
Who the cause shall truly scan?

On this account the sage feels a difficulty (as to what to do in the former case).

It is the way of Heaven not to strive, and yet it skilfully overcomes; not to speak, and yet it is skilful in (obtaining a reply; does not call, and yet men come to it of themselves. Its demonstrations are quiet, and yet its plans are skilful and effective. The meshes of the net of Heaven are large; far apart, but letting nothing escape.[109]

The people do not fear death; to what purpose is it to (try to) frighten them with death? If the people were always in awe of death, and I could always seize those who do wrong, and put them to death, who would dare to do wrong?

There is always One who presides over the infliction death. He who would inflict death in the room of him who so presides over it may be described as hewing wood instead of a great carpenter. Seldom is it that he who undertakes the hewing, instead of the great carpenter, does not cut his own hands![110]

The people suffer from famine because of the multitude of taxes consumed by their superiors. It is through this that they suffer famine.

The people are difficult to govern because of the (excessive) agency of their superiors (in governing them). It is through this that they are difficult to govern.

The people make light of dying because of the greatness of their labours in seeking for the means of living. It is this which makes them think light of dying. Thus it is that to leave the subject of living altogether out of view is better than to set a high value on it.[111]

Man at his birth is supple and weak; at his death, firm and strong. (So it is with) all things. Trees and plants, in their early growth, are soft and brittle; at their death, dry and withered.

Thus it is that firmness and strength are the concomitants of death; softness and weakness, the concomitants of life.

Hence he who (relies on) the strength of his forces does not conquer; and a tree which is strong will fill the outstretched arms, (and thereby invites the feller.)

Therefore the place of what is firm and strong is below, and that of what is soft and weak is above.[112]

May not the Way (or Tao) of Heaven be compared to the (method of) bending a bow? The (part of the bow) which was high is brought low, and what was low is raised up. (So Heaven) diminishes where there is superabundance, and supplements where there is deficiency.

It is the Way of Heaven to diminish superabundance, and to supplement deficiency. It is not so with the way of man. He takes away from those who have not enough to add to his own superabundance.

Who can take his own superabundance and therewith serve all under heaven? Only he who is in possession of the Tao!

Therefore the (ruling) sage acts without claiming the results as his; he achieves his merit and does not rest (arrogantly) in it:—he does not wish to display his superiority.[113]

There is nothing in the world more soft and weak than water, and yet for attacking things that are firm and strong there is nothing that can take precedence of it;—for there is nothing (so effectual) for which it can be changed.

Everyone in the world knows that the soft overcomes the hard, and the weak the strong, but no one is able to carry it out in practice.

Therefore a sage has said,
“He who accepts his state’s reproach,
Is hailed therefore its altars’ lord;
To him who bears men’s direful woes
They all the name of King accord.”

Words that are strictly true seem to be paradoxical.[114]

When a reconciliation is effected (between two parties) after a great animosity, there is sure to be a grudge remaining (in the mind of the one who was wrong). And how can this be beneficial (to the other)?

Therefore (to guard against this), the sage keeps the left-hand portion of the record of the engagement, and does not insist on the (speedy) fulfilment of it by the other party. (So), he who has the attributes (of the Tao) regards (only) the conditions of the engagement, while he who has not those attributes regards only the conditions favourable to himself.

In the Way of Heaven, there is no partiality of love; it is always on the side of the good man.[115]

In a little state with a small population, I would so order it, that, though there were individuals with the abilities of ten or a hundred men, there should be no employment of them; I would make the people, while looking on death as a grievous thing, yet not remove elsewhere (to avoid it).

Though they had boats and carriages, they should have no occasion to ride in them; though they had buff coats and sharp weapons, they should have no occasion to don or use them.

I would make the people return to the use of knotted cords (instead of the written characters).

They should think their (coarse) food sweet; their (plain) clothes beautiful; their (poor) dwellings places of rest; and their common (simple) ways sources of enjoyment.

There should be a neighbouring state within sight, and the voices of the fowls and dogs should be heard all the way from it to us, but I would make the people to old age, even to death, not have any intercourse with it.[116]

Sincere words are not fine; fine words are not sincere. Those who are skilled (in the Tao) do not dispute (about it); the disputatious are not skilled in it. Those who know (the Tao) are not extensively learned; the extensively learned do not know it.

The sage does not accumulate (for himself). The more that he expends for others, the more does he possess of his own; the more that he gives to others, the more does he have himself.

With all the sharpness of the Way of Heaven, it injures not; with all the doing in the way of the sage he does not strive.[117]

Endnotes

1

Throughout the book, all renditions of Latinized Chinese words follows the Wade-Giles romanization system. However, because most readers are probably more familiar with the name Laozi and Tao Te Ching, romanization for these two term were retained.

—SE editor

↩︎

2

Much of what is referred in the past two paragraphs that is not directly related to the

Tao Te Ching

is not included in this ebook production, but the paragraphs are retained for context.

—SE editor

↩︎

3

The rest of the “Preface” by Legge solely concerns his translation of

Chuang-tzŭ

and other shorter Taoist works, which was originally included in his work

Sacred Books of the East

, Vol. XXXIX and XL as published. Because these has no relevance to this ebook production of the

Tao Te Ching

, they are omitted.

—SE editor

↩︎

4

The “appendixes” referred here by Legge is not included in this ebook production.

—SE editor

↩︎

5

The sixth chapter of Laozi’s treatise, that about “the Spirit of the Valley,” is referred to in

Lieh-tzŭ

(I 1 b), as being from Huang Ti, from which the commentator Tu Tao-chien (about AD 1300) takes occasion to say: “From which we know that Laozi was accustomed to quote in his treatise passages from earlier records—as when he refers to the remarks of ‘some sage,’ of ‘some ancient,’ of ‘the sentence-makers,’ and of ‘some writer on war.’ In all these cases he is clearly introducing the words of earlier wise men. The case is like that of Confucius when he said, ‘I am a transmitter and not a maker,’ etc.” Found in

Chiao Hung

, in loc. ↩︎

6

See in books IX, X, and XII. ↩︎

7

In the present district of Lingbao, Shanzhou, province of Henan. ↩︎

8

In an ordinary

Student’s Manual

I find a note with reference to this incident to which it may be worth while to give a place here:—The warden, it is said, set before Laozi a dish of tea; and this was the origin of the custom of tea-drinking between host and guest (see the 幼學故事尋源, ch. 7, on “Food and Drink”). ↩︎

9

The earlier old man of the ho-side is styled in Chinese 河上丈人; the other 河上公; but the designation have the same meaning. Some critical objections to the genuineness of the latter’s commentary on the ground of the style are without foundation. ↩︎

10

See Chiao Hung’s

Wings

or

Helps

, ch. v p. 11 a. ↩︎

11

Notes on Chinese Literature

, p. 173. ↩︎

12

A section of this introduction here is omitted as it solely concerned of the book

Chuang-tzŭ

and other writings by the former’s namesake, which are not included in this ebook production.

—SE editor

↩︎

13

Language and Languages

, pp. 184, 185. ↩︎

14

Natur. Quaest.

lib. II cap. xiv. ↩︎

15

Martineau’s

Types of Ethical Theory

, I p. 286, and his whole

Conjectural History of Spinoza’s Thought

. ↩︎

16

道 is equivalent to the Greek ἡ ὁδός, the way. Where this name for the Christian system occurs in our

Revised Version of the New Testament

in the

Acts of the Apostles

, the literal rendering is adhered to, Way being printed with a capital W. See

Acts

ix 2; xix 9; xxii 4; xxiv 14, 22. ↩︎

17

大塗. The

Kʽang-hsi dictionary

defines tʽu by lu, road or way.

Medhurst

gives “road.” Unfortunately, both

Morrison

and

Williams

overlooked this definition of the character. Giles has also a note in loc., showing how this synonym settles the original meaning of Tao in the sense of “road.” ↩︎

18

The

Tao Te Ching

, ch. 25 and

Chuang-tzŭ

, XIII par. 1. ↩︎

19

See

Strange Stories from a Chinese Studio

, vol. i p. 1 note 2. ↩︎

20

Kuang Chêng-tzŭ heads the list of characters in Ko Hung’s

History of Spirit-like Immortals

(神仙傳), written in our fourth century. “He was,” it is said, “an immortal of old, who lives on the hill of Kʽung-tung in a grotto of rocks.” ↩︎

21

For this sentence we find in Mr. Balfour:—“Spirits of the dead, receiving it, become divine; the very gods themselves owe their divinity to its influence; and by it both heaven and earth were produced.” The version of it by Mr. Giles is too condensed:—“Spiritual beings drew their spirituality thereform, while the universe became what we see it now.” ↩︎

22

Compare also bk. XXII parr. 7, 8, and XXIII par. 10. ↩︎

23

Mr. Balfour had given for this sentence:—“In the beginning of all things there was not even nothing. There were no names; these arose afterwards.” In his critique on Mr. Balfour’s version in 1882, Mr. Giles proposed:—“At the beginning of all things there was nothing; but this nothing had no name.” He now in his own version gives it, “At the beginning of the beginning, even nothing did not exist. Then came the period of the nameless;”—an improvement, certainly, on the other; but which can hardly be accepted as the correct version of the text. ↩︎

24

The

Tao Te Ching

, ch. 14; et al. ↩︎

25

Ch. 50. ↩︎

26

That is, between heaven and earth. ↩︎

27

Quoted in the

Amplification of the Sixteen Precepts or Maxims

of the second emperor of the present dynasty by his son. The words are from Dr. Milne’s version of

The Sacred Edict

, p. 137. ↩︎

28

In his index of the

Tripiṭaka

, Mr. Bunyio Nanjio (p. 359) assigns Liu Mi and his work to the Yüen dynasty. In a copy of the work in my possession they are assigned to that of Sung. The author, no doubt, lived under both dynasties—from the Sung to the Yüen. ↩︎

29

See bk. XV par. 1. ↩︎

30

Bk. XI par. 5. ↩︎

31

Bk. XVI par. 2. ↩︎

32

Tao Te Ching

, ch. 19. ↩︎

33

Confucian Analects

, XIV 36. ↩︎

34

Julien translates this by “il erre à l’aventure.” In 1861 I rendered it, “He moves as if his feet were entangled.” To one critic it suggests the idea of a bundle or wisp of brushwood rolled about over the ground by the wind. ↩︎

35

The character may mean “the old boy,” and so understood have given rise to various fabulous legends; that his mother had carried him in her womb for seventy-two years (some say, for eighty-one), and that when born the child had the white hair of an old man. Julien has translated the fabulous legend of Ko Hung of our fourth century about him. By that time the legends of Buddhism about Śākyamuni had become current in China, and were copied and applied to Laozi by his followers. Looking at the meaning of the two names, I am surprised no one has characterized Laozi as the Chinese Seneca. ↩︎

36

Kʽang-sang Tzŭ is evidently the Kêng-sang Chʽu of Chuang’s book XXIII. Wei-lei Hsü is supposed by Ssŭ-ma Chên of the Tʽang dynasty, who called himself the Lesser Ssŭ-ma, to be the name of a book; one, in that case, of the lost books of Chuang. But as we find the “Hill of Wei-lei” mentioned in bk. XXIII as the scene of Kʽang-sang Tzŭ’s Taoistic labours and success, I suppose that Chʽien’s reference is to that. The names are quoted by him from memory, or might be insisted on as instances of different readings. ↩︎

37

體道, “Embodying the Tao.” The author sets forth, as well as the difficulty of his subject would allow him, the nature of the Tao in itself, and its manifestation. To understand the Tao one must be partaker of its nature.

Par. 3 suggests the words of the apostle John, “He that loveth not knoweth not God; for God is love.” Both the Tao, Laozi’s ideal in the absolute, and its Tê, or operation, are comprehended in his chapter, the latter being the Tao with the name, the Mother of all things. See the ↩︎

38

養牲, “The Nourishment of the Person.” But many of Ho-shang Kung’s titles are more appropriate than this.

The chapter starts with instances of the antinomies, which suggest to the mind each of them the existence of its corresponding opposite; and the author finds in them an analogy to the “contraries” which characterize the operation of the Tao, as stated in chapter 40. He then proceeds to describe the action of the sage in par. 3 as in accordance with this law of contraries; and, in par. 4, that of heaven and earth, or what we may call nature, in the process of the vegetable world.

Par. 2 should be rhymed, but I could not succeed to my satisfaction in the endeavour to rhyme it. Every one who can read Chinese will see that the first four members rhyme. The last two rhyme also, the concluding 隨 being pronounced so;—see the

Kʽang-hsi dictionary

in voc. ↩︎

39

安民, “Keeping the People at Rest.” The object of the chapter is to show that government according to the Tao is unfavourable to the spread of knowledge among the people, and would keep them rather in the state of primitive simplicity and ignorance, thereby securing their restfulness and universal good order. Such is the uniform teaching of Laozi and his great follower Chuang-tzŭ, and of all Taoist writers. ↩︎

40

無源, “The Fountainless.” There is nothing before the Tao; it might seem to have been before God. And yet there is no demonstration by it of its presence and operation. It is like the emptiness of a vessel. The second character = 沖 = 盅;—see

Kʽang-hsi

on the latter. The practical lesson is, that in following the Tao we must try to be like it. ↩︎

41

虛用, “The Use of Emptiness.” Quiet and unceasing is the operation of the Tao, and effective is the rule of the sage in accordance with it.

The grass-dogs in par. 1 were made of straw tied up in the shape of dogs, and used in praying for rain; and afterwards, when the sacrifice was over, were thrown aside and left uncared for. Heaven and earth and the sages dealt so with all things and with the people; but the illustration does not seem a happy one. Both Chuang-tzŭ and Huai-nan mention the grass-dogs. See especially the former, XIV, 25 a, b. In that book there is fully developed the meaning of this chapter. The illustration in par. 2 is better. The Chinese bellows is difference to look at from ours, but the principle is the same in the construction of both. The par. concludes in a way that lends some countenance to the later Taoism’s dealing with the breath. ↩︎

42

成象, “The Completion of Material Forms.” This title rightly expresses the import of this enigmatical chapter; but there is a foundation laid in it for the development of the later Taoism, which occupies itself with the prolongation of life by the management of the breath (氣) or vital force.

“The valley” is used metaphorically as a symbol of “emptiness” or “vacancy;” and “the spirit of the valley” is the something invisible, yet almost personal, belonging to the Tao, which constitutes the Tê (德) in the name of our

Ching

. “The spirit of the valley” has come to be a name for the activity of the Tao in all the realm of its operation. “The female mystery” is the Tao with a name of chapter 1, which is “the Mother of all things.” All living beings have a father and mother. The processes of generation and production can hardly be imaged by us but by a recognition of this fact; and so Laozi thought of the existing realm of nature—of life—as coming through an evolution (not a creation) from the primal air or breath, dividing into two, and thence appearing in the forms of things, material and immaterial. The chapter is found in Lieh-tzŭ (I 1 b) quoted by him from a book of Huang-ti; and here Laozi has appropriated it, and made it his own. See the Introduction. ↩︎

43

韜光, “Sheathing the Light.” The chapter teaches that one’s best good is realised by not thinking of it, or seeking for it. Heaven and earth afford a pattern to the sage, and the sage affords a pattern to all men. ↩︎

44

易性, “The Placid and Contented Nature.” Water, as an illustration of the way of the Tao, is repeatedly employed by Laozi.

The various forms of what is excellent in par. 2 are brought forward to set forth the more, by contrast, the excellence of the humility indicated in the acceptance of the lower place without striving to the contrary. ↩︎

45

運夷; but I cannot give a satisfactory rendering of this title. The teaching of the chapter is, that fullness and complacency in success are contrary to the Tao.

The first clauses of the two sentences in par. 1, 持而盈之, 揣而銳之, 銳而揣之, are instances of the “inverted” style not uncommon in the oldest composition. “The way of Heaven” = “the Heavenly Tao” exemplified by man. ↩︎

46

能爲, “Possibilities.” This chapter is one of the most difficult to understand and translate in the whole work. Even Chu Hsi was not able to explain the first member satisfactorily. The text of that member seems well supported; but I am persuaded the first clause of it is somehow corrupt.

The whole seems to tell what can be accomplished by one who is possessed of the Tao. In par. 3 he appears free from all self-consciousness in what he does, and of all self-satisfaction in the results of his doing. The other two paragraphs seem to speak of what he can do under the guidance of the Tao for himself and for others. He can by his management of his vital breath bring his body to the state of Taoistic perfection, and keep his intelligent and animal souls from being separated, and he can rule men without purpose and effort. “The gates of heaven” in par. 2 is a Taoistic phrase for the nostrils as the organ of the breath;—see the commentary of Ho-shang Kung. ↩︎

47

無用, “The Use of what has no Substantive Existence.” The three illustrations serve to set forth the freedom of the Tao from all preoccupation and purpose, and the use of what seems useless. ↩︎

48

檢欲, “The Repression of the Desires.” Government in accordance with the Tao seeks to withdraw men from the attractions of what is external and pleasant to the senses and imagination, and to maintain the primitive simplicity of men’s ways and manners. Compare chap. 2. The five colours are black, red, green or blue, white, and yellow; the five notes are those of the imperfect Chinese musical scale, our G, A, B, D, E; the five tastes are salt, bitter, sour, acrid, and sweet.

I am not sure that Wang Pi has caught exactly the author’s idea in the contrast between satisfying the belly and satisfying the eyes; but what he says is ingenious: “In satisfying the belly one nourishes himself; in gratifying the eyes he makes a slave of himself.” ↩︎

49

厭恥, “Loathing Shame.” The chapter is difficult to construe, and some disciples of Chu Hsi had to ask him to explain it as in the case of ch. 10. His remarks on it are not to my mind satisfactory. Its object seems to be to show that the cultivation of the person according to the Tao, is the best qualification for the highest offices, even for the government of the world. Par. 3 is found in

Chuang-tzŭ

(XI 18 b) in a connection which suggests this view of the chapter. It may be observed, however, that in him the position of the verbal characters in the two clauses of the paragraph is the reverse of that in the text of Ho-shang Kung, so that we can hardly accept the distinction of meaning of the two characters given in his commentary, but must take them as synonyms. Professor Gabelentz gives the following version of

Chunag-tzŭ

: “Darum, gebraucht er seine Person achtsam in der Verwaltung des Reiches, so mag man ihm die Reichsgewalt anvertrauen; … liebend (schonend) … übertragen.” ↩︎

50

贊玄, “The Manifestation of the Mystery.” The subject of par. 1 is the Tao, but the Tao in its operation, and not the primal conception of it, as entirely distinct from things, which rises before the mind in the second paragraph. The Chinese characters which I have translated “the equable,” “the inaudible,” and “the subtle,” are now pronounced, yi, hsi, and wei, and in 1823 Rémusat fancied that they were intended to give the Hebrew Tetragrammaton יהוה‎ which he thought had some to Laozi somehow from the west, or been found by him there. It was a mere fancy or dream; and still more so is the recent attempt to revive the notion by Victor von Strauss in 1870, and Dr. Edkins in 1884. The idea of the latter is specially strange, maintaining, as he does, that we should read the characters according to their old sounds. Laozi has not in the chapter a personal being before his mind, but the procedure of his mysterious Tao, the course according to which the visible phenomena take place, incognisable by human sense and capable of only approximate description by term appropriate to what is within the domain of sense. See the “Introduction” ch. 3, par. 8. ↩︎

51

顯德, “The Exhibition of the Quality,” that is, of the Tao, which has been set forth in the preceding chapter. Its practical outcome is here described in the masters of it of old, who in their own weakness were yet strong in it, and in their humility were mighty to be to be co-workers with it for the good of the world.

The variety of the reading in par. 4 is considerable, but not so as to affect the meaning. This par. is found in

Huai-nan

(XII, 23 a) with an unimportant variation. From the illustration to which it is subjoined he understood the fullness, evidently as in ch. 9, as being that of a vessel filled to overflowing. Both here and there such fullness is used metaphorically of a man overfull of himself; and then Laozi slides into another metaphor, that of a worn-out garment. The text of par. 3 has been variously tampered with. I omit the 久 of the current copies, after the example of the editors of the great recension of the Yung-lê period (AD 1403–1424) of the Ming dynasty. ↩︎

52

歸根, “Returning to the Root.” The chapter exhibits the operation of the Tao in nature, in man, and in government; an operation silent, but all-powerful; unaccompanied with any demonstration of its presence, but great in its results.

An officer receives a charge or commission from his superior (受命); when he reports the execution of it he is said 復命. So all animate things, including men, receive their charge from the Tao as to their life, and when they have fulfilled it they are represented as reporting that fulfilment; and the fulfilment and report are described as their unchanging rule, so that they are the Tao’s impassive instruments, having no will or purpose of their—according to Laozi’s formula of “doing nothing and yet doing all things (無爲而無不爲).”

The getting to possess the Tao, or to be an embodiment of it, follows the becoming of heaven or heaven-like; and this is in accordance with the saying in the fourth chapter that “the Tao might seem to have been before God.” But, in

Chuang-tzŭ

especially, we often find the full possession of the Tao is exempt from all danger of decay, is generally illustrated by a reference to the utterances in ch. 50; as if Laozi did indeed see in the Tao a preservative against death. ↩︎

53

淳風, “The Unadulterated Influence.” The influence is that of the Tao, as seen in the earliest and paradisiacal times. The two chapters that follow are closely connected with this, showing how the silent, passionless influence of the Tao was gradually and injuriously superseded by “the wisdom of the world,” in the conduct of government. In the first sentence there is a small various reading of 不 for 下, but it does not affect the meaning of the passage. The first clause of par. 2 gives some difficulty; 其貴言, “they made their words valuable or precious,” i.e. “they seldom spake;” cp. 1 Sam. iii 1. ↩︎

54

俗薄, “The Decay of Manners.” A sequel to the preceding chapter, and showing also how the general decay of manners afforded opportunity for the display of certain virtues by individuals. Observe “the Great Tao,” occurring here for the first time as the designation of “the Tao.” ↩︎

55

還淳, “Return to the Unadulterated Influence.” The chapter desires a return to the simplicity of the Tao, and shows how superior the result would be to that of the more developed systems of morals and government which had superseded it. It is closely connected with thte two chapters that precede. Laozi’s call for the renunciation of the methods of the sages and rulers in lieu of his fancied paradisiacal state is repeated ad nauseam by Chuang-tzŭ. ↩︎

56

異俗, “Being Different from Ordinary Men.” The chapter sets forth the difference to external appearance which the pursuit and observance of the Tao produces between its votaries and others; and Laozi speaks in it as himself an example of the former. In the last three chapters he has been advocating the cause of the Tao against the learning and philosophy of the other school of thinkers in the country. Here he appears as having renounced learning, and found an end to the troubles and anxieties of his own mind; but at the expense of being misconceived and misrepresented by others. Hence the chapter has an autobiographical character.

Having stated the fact following the renunciation of learning, he proceeds to dwell upon the troubles of learning in the rest of par. 1. Until the votary of learning knows everything, he has no rest. But the instances which he adduces of his are not striking nor easily understood. I cannot throw any light on the four lines about the “yes” and the “yea.”

Confucius (

Ana.

XVI, viii) specifies three things of which the superior man stands in awe; and these and others of a similar nature may have been the things which Laozi had in his mind. The nursing-mother at the end is, no doubt, the Tao in operation, “with a name,” as in ch. 1; “the mysterious virtue” of chapters 51 and 52. ↩︎

57

虛心, “The Empty Heart.” But I fail to see the applicability of the title. The subject of the chapter is the Tao in its operation. This is the significance of the 德 in the first clause or line, and to render it by “virtue,” as Julien and Chalmers do, only serves to hide the meaning. Julien, however, says that “the virtue is that of the Tao;” and he is right in taking 從, the last character of the second line, as having the sense of “from,” “the source from,” and not, as Chalmers does, in the sense of “following.”

Laozi’s mind is occupied with a very difficult subject—to describe the production of material forms of the Tao; how or from what, he does not say. What I have rendered “semblances,” Julien “les images,” and Chalmers, “forms,” seems, as the latter says, in some way to correspond to the “Eternal Ideas” of Plato in the Divine Mind. But Laozi had no idea of “personality” in the Tao. ↩︎

58

益謙, “The Increase granted to Humility.” This title rightly expresses the subject-matter of the chapter. I cannot translate the first clause otherwise than I have done. It was an old saying, which Laozi found and adopted. Whether it was intended to embrace all the cases which are mentioned may be questioned, but he employs it so as to make it do so.

“The emptiness” which becomes full is literally the hollowness of a cavity in the ground which is sure to be filled by overflowing water;—see

Mencius

, IV ii 18. “The worn out” is explained by the withered foliage of a tree, which comes out new and fresh in the next spring. I have taken the first sentence of par. 2 as Wu Chʽêng does;—see his commentary in loc. ↩︎

59

虛無, “Absolute Vacancy.” This, I think, is the meaning of the title, “Emptiness and Nothingness,” as entire conformity to the Tao in him who professes to be directed by it. Such a one will be omnipotent in his influence in all others. The Tao in him will restrain all (spasmodic) loquacity. Those who are described in par. 2 as “failing” are not to be thought of as bad men, men given up, as Julien has it, au crime. They are simply ordinary men, who have failed in their study of the Tao and practice of it, but are won to truth and virtue by the man whom the author has in mind. As we might expect, however, the mention of such men has much embarrassed the commentators.

Compare the concluding sentence with the one at the end of par. 1 in ch. 17. ↩︎

60

苦恩, “Painful Graciousness.” The chapter should be so designated. This concludes the subject of the two previous chapters—pursuing the course, the course of the unemotional Tao without vain effort or display.

The remnants of food were not used as sacrificial offerings;—see the

Li Chi

(vol. xxvii p. 82). In what I have rendered by “a tumour attached to the body,” the 行 is probably, by a mistake, for 形;—see a quatation by Wu Chʽêng from Ssŭ-ma Chʽien. “Which all dislike” is, literally, “Things are likely to dislike them,” the “things” being “spirits and men,” as Wu explains the term. ↩︎

61

象玄, “Representations of the Mystery.” In this chapter Lao approaches very near to give an answer to the questions as to what the Tao is, and yet leaves the reader disappointed. He commences by calling it “a thing (物);” but that term does not necessitate our regarding it as “material.” We have seen in the preceding chapter that it is used to signify “spirits and men.” Nor does his going on to speak of it as “chaotic (混成)” necessarily lead us to conceive it as made up of the “material elements of things;” we have the same term applied in ch. 14 to the three immaterial constituents there said to be blended in the idea of it.

“He does not know its name,” and he designates it by the term denoting a course of way (Tao, 道), and indicating the phenomenal attribute, the method in which all phenomena come before our observation, in their development or evolution. And to distinguish it from all other methods of evolution, he would call it “the Great Method,” and so he employs that combination as its name in ch. 18 and elsewhere; but it cannot be said that this name has fully maintained it self in the writings of his followers. But understood thus, he here says, as in ch. 1, that it is “the Mother of all things.” And yet, when he says that “it was before Heaven and Earth were produced,” he comes very near his affirmations in chapters 1 and 4, that “the nameless Tao was the beginning (or originating cause) of Heaven and Earth,” and “might seem to have been before God.” Was he groping after God if haply he might find Him? I think he was, and he gets so far as to conceive of Him as “the Uncaused Cause,” but comes short of the idea of His personality. The other subordinate causes which he mentions all get their force or power from the Tao, but after all the Tao is simply a spontaneity, evolving from itself, and not acting from a personal will, consciously in the direction of its own wisdom and love. “Who can by searching find out God? Who can find out the Almighty to perfection?”

The predicate of the Tao in the chapter, most perplexing to myself, is “It returns,” in par.3. “It flows away, far away, and comes back;”—are not the three statements together equal to “It is everywhere?” ↩︎

62

重德, “The Quality of Gravity.” Gravity and stillness are both attributes of the Tao; and he who cultivates it must not give way to lightness of mind, or hasty action.

The rule for a leader not to separate from his baggage waggons is simply the necessity of adhering ot gravity. I have adopted from Han Fei the reading of “the wise prince” for “the sage,” which is found in Ho-shang Kung; and later on the reading of “has lost his root” for his “loses his ministers,” though the latter is found also in Han Fei. ↩︎

63

巧用, “Dexterity in Using,” that is, in the application of the Tao. This is the substance of the chapter, celebrating the effective but invisible operation of the Tao, and the impartial exercise of it for the benefit of all men and all things.

I have given the most natural construction of the two characters at the end of par. 1, the only possible construction of them, so far as I can see, suitable to the context. The action of the Tao (non-acting and yet all-efficient) and that of the sage in accordance with it, are veiled by their nature of the sight of ordinary men.

It is more difficult the catch the scope and point of par. 2. If there were not the conditions described in it, it would be hard for even an intelligent onlooker to distinguish between the man who had the skill and the man without it, between his who possessed the Tao, and him who had it not, which would be strange indeed. ↩︎

64

反樸, “Returning to Simplicity.” The chapter sets forth humility and simplicity, and artless freedom from all purpose, as characteristic of the man of Tao, such as he was in the primeval time. “The sage” in par. 2 may be “the Son of Heaven,”—the head of all rule in the kingdom, or the feudal lord in a state. ↩︎

65

無爲, “Taking no Action.” All efforts made with a purpose are sure to fail. The nature of the Tao necessitates their doing so, and the uncertainty of things and events teaches the same lesson.

That the kingdom or throne is a “spirit-like vessel” has become a common enough saying among the Chinese. Julien has, “L’Empire est comme un vase divin;” but I always shrink from translating 神 by “divine.” Its English analogue is “spirit,” and the idea in the text is based on the immunity of spirit from all material law, and the uncertain issue of attempts to deal with it according to ordinary methods. Wu Chʽêng takes the phrase as equivalent to “superintended by spirits,” which is as inadmissible as Julien’s “divin.” The Tao forbids action with a personal purpose, and all such action is sure to fail in the greatest things as well as in the least. ↩︎

66

儉武, “A Caveat against War.” War is contrary to the spirit of the Tao, and, as being so, is productive of misery, and leads to early ruin. It is only permissible in a case of necessity, and even then its spirit and tendencies must be guarded against.

In translating 果 by “striking a decisive blow,” I have, no doubt, followed Julien’s “frapper un coup décisif.” The same 果 occurs six times in par. 3, followed by 而, and Chiao Hung says that in all but the first instance the 而 should be taken as equivalent to 於, so that we should have to translate, “He is determined against being vain,” etc. But there is no necessity for such a construction of 而.

“Weakness” and not “strength” is the character of the Tao; hence the lesson in par. 4. ↩︎

67

偃武, “Stilling War.” The chapter continues the subject of the preceding. The imperially-appointed editors of Wang Pi’s

Text and Commentary

(1765) say that from the beginning of par. 2 to the end, there is the appearance of text and commentary being mixed together; but they make no alteration in the text as it is found in Ho-shang Kung, and in all other ancient copies.

The concluding sentence will suggest to some readers the words of the Duke of Wellington, that to gain a battle was the saddest thing next to losing it. ↩︎

68

聖德. Chalmers translates this by “sagely virtue.” But I cannot adopt that rendering, and find it difficult to supply a better. The “virtue” is evidently the attribute of the Tao come out from the condition of the absolute, and capable of being named. In the former state it has no name; in the latter, it has. Par. 1 and the commencement of par. 4 must both be explained from ch. 1.

The “primordial simplicity” in par. 2 is the Tao in its simplest conception, alone, and by itself, and the 始制 in par. 4 is that Tao come forth into operation and become Tê, the Tê which affords a law for men. From this to the end of the paragraph is very obscure. I have translated from the text of Wang Pi. The text of Ho-shang Kung is different, and he comments upon it as it stands, but to me it is inexplicable. ↩︎

69

辨德, “Discriminating between (different) Attributes.” The teaching of the chapter is that the possession of the Tao confers the various attributes which are here most distinguished. It has been objected to it that elsewhere the Tao is represented as associated with dullness and not intelligence, and with weakness and not with strength. But these seem to be qualities viewed from without, and acting on what is beyond itself. Inwardly, its qualities are the very opposite, and its action has the effect of enlightening what is dark, and overcoming what is strong.

More interesting are the predicates in par. 2. Chiao Hung gives the comment on it of the Indian monk, Kumārajīva, “one of the four suns of Buddhism,” and who went to China in AD 401: “To be alive and yet not alive may well be called long; to die and yet not be dead may well be called longevity.” He also gives the view of Lu Nung-shih (AD 1042–1102) that the freedom from change of Lieh-tzŭ, from the death of Chuang-tzŭ, and from extinction of the Buddhists, have all the same meaning as the concluding saying of Laozi here; that the human body is like the covering of the caterpillar or the skin of the snake; that we occupy it but for a passing sojourn. No doubt, Laozi believed in another life for the individual after the present. Many passages in Chuang-tzŭ indicate the same faith. ↩︎

70

任成, “The Task of Achievement.” The subject is the greatness of what the Tao, called here by Lao’s own name for it in ch. 25, does; and the unconscious simplicity with which it does it; and then the achievements of the sage who is permeated by the Tao. Par. 2 is descriptive of the influence of the Tao in the vegetable world. The statements and expressions are much akin to those in parts of chapters 2, 10, and 51, and for Ho-shang Kung’s difficult reading of 不名有 some copies give 而不居, as in chapter 2. ↩︎

71

仁德, “The Attribute of Benevolence.” But there seems little appropriateness in this title. The subject of the chapter is the inexhaustible efficacy of the Tao for the good of the world.

The Great Image (of the invisible Tao) is a name for the Tao in its operation; as in chapters 14 and 41. He who embodies this in his government will be a centre of attraction for all the world. Or the 天下住 may be taken as a predicate of the holder of the Great Image:—“If he go all under heaven teaching the Tao.” Both constructions are maintained by commentators of note. In par. 2 the attraction of the Tao is contrasted with that of ordinary pleasures and gratifications. ↩︎

72

微明, “Minimising the Light;” equivalent, as Wu Chʽêng has pointed out, to the 襲明 of ch. 27.

The gist of the chapter is to be sought in the second paragraph, where we have two instances of the action of the Tao by contraries, supposed always to be for good.

But there is a difficulty in seeing the applicability to this cases mentioned in par. 1. The first case, indeed is merely a natural phenomenon, having no moral character; but the others, as they have been illustrated from historical incidents, by Han Fei and others at least, belong to schemes of selfish and unprincipled ambitious strategy, which it would be injurious to Laozi to suppose that he intended.

Par. 3 is the most frequently quoted of all the passages in our

Ching

, unless it be the first part of ch. 1. Fishes taken from the deep, and brought into shallow water, can be easily taken or killed; that is plain enough. “The sharp instruments of a state” are not its “weapons of war,” nor its “treasures,” nor its “instruments of government,” that is, its rewards and punishments, though this last is the interpretation often put on them, and sustained by a foolish reference to an incident, real or coined, in the history of the dukedom of Sung. The li chʽi are “contrivances for gain,” machines, and other methods to increase the wealth of a state, but, according to the principles of Laozi, really injurious to it. These should not be shown to the people, whom the Taoistic system would keep in a state of primitive simplicity and ignorance. This interpretation is in accordance with the meaning of the characters, and with the general teaching of Taoism. In no other way can I explain the paragraph so as to justify the place undoubtedly belonging to it in the system. ↩︎

73

爲政, “The Exercise of Government.” This exercise should be according to the Tao, doing without doing, governing without government.

The subject of the third paragraph is a feudal prince of the king, and he is spoken of in the first person, to give more vividness to the style, unless the 吾, “I,” may, possibly, be understood of Laozi himself, personating one of them. ↩︎

74

論德, “About the Attributes;” of Tao, that is. It is not easy to render Tê here by any other English term than “virtue,” and yet there would be a danger of its thus misleading us in the interpretation of the chapter.

The “virtue” is the activity or operation of the Tao, which is supposed to have come out of its absoluteness. Even Han Fei so defines it here—“Tê is the meritorious work of the Tao.”

In par. 5 we evidently have a resume of the preceding paragraphs, and, as it is historical, I translate them in the past tense; though what took place on the early stage of the world may also be said to go on taking place in the experience of every individual. With some considerable hesitation I have given the subjects in those paragraphs in the concrete, in deference to the authority of Ho-shang Kung and most other commentators. The former says, “By ‘the highest Tê’ is to be understood the rulers of the greatest antiquity, without name or designation, whose virtue was great, and could not be surpassed.” Most ingenious, and in accordance with the Taoistic system, is the manner in which Wu Chʽêng construes the passage, and I am surprised that it has not been generally accepted. By “the higher Tê” he understands, “the Tao,” that which is prior to and above the Tê (上德者, 在德之上, 道也); by “the lower Tê,” benevolence, that which is after and below the Tê which is above benevolence; by “the higher righteousness,” the benevolence which is above righteousness; and by “the higher propriety,” the righteousness which is above propriety. Certainly in the summation of these four paragraphs which we have in the fifth, the subjects of them would appear to have been in the mind of Laozi as thus defined by Wu.

In the reminder of the chapter he goes on to speak depreciatingly of ceremonies and knowledge, so that the whole chapter must be understood as descriptive of the process of decay and deterioration from the early time in which the Tao and its attributes swayed the societies of men. ↩︎

75

法本, “The Origin of the Law.” In this title there is a reference to the law given to all things by the Tao, as described in the conclusion of chapter 25. And the Tao affords that law by its passionless, undemonstrative nature, through which in its spontaneity, doing nothing for the sake of doing, it yet does all things.

The difficulty of translation is in the third paragraph. The way in which princes and kings speak depreciatingly of themselves in adduced as illustrating how they have indeed got the spirit of the Tao; and I accept the last epithet as given by Ho-shang Kung, “naveless” (轂), instead of 穀 (= “the unworthy”), which is found in Wang Pi, and has been adopted by nearly all subsequent editors. To see its appropriateness here, we have only to refer back to chapter 11, where the thirty spokes, and the nave, empty to receive the axle, are spoken of, and it is shown how the usefulness of the carriage is derived from that emptiness of the nave. This also enables us to give a fair and consistent explanation of the difficult clause which follows, in which also I have followed the text of Ho-shang Kung. For his 車, Wang Pi has 輿, which also is found in a quotation of it by Huai-nan Tzŭ; but this need not affect the meaning. In the translation of the clause we are assisted by a somewhat similar illustration about a horse in the twenty-fifth of Chuang-tzŭ’s books, par. 10. ↩︎

76

去用, “Dispensing with the Use (of Means);”—with their use, that is, as it appears to us. The subject of the brief chapter is the action of the Tao by contraries, leading to a result the opposite of what existed previously, and by means which might seem calculated to produce a contrary result.

In translating par. 2 I have followed Chiao Hung, who finds the key to it in ch. 1. Having a name, the Tao is “the mother of all things;” having no name, it is “the originator of heaven and earth.” But here is the teaching of Laozi:—“If Tao seem to be before God,” Tao itself sprang from nothing. ↩︎

77

同異, “Sameness and Difference.” The chapter is a sequel of the preceding, and may be taken as an illustration of the Tao’s proceeding by contraries.

Who the sentence-makers were whose sayings are quoted we cannot tell, but it would have been strange if Laozi had not had a large store of such sentences at this command. The fifth and sixth of those employed by him here are found in

Lieh-tzŭ

(II 15 a), spoken by Lao in reproving Yang Chu, and in VII 3 a, that heretic appears quoting an utterance of the same kind, with the words, “according to an old saying (古語有之).” ↩︎

78

道化, “The Transformations of the Tao.” In par. 2 we have the case of the depreciating epithets given to themselves by kings and princes, which we found before in ch. 39, and a similar lesson is drawn from it. Such depreciation leads to exaltation, and the contrary course of self-exaltation leads to abasement. This latter case is stated emphatically in par. 3, and Laozi says that it was the basis of his teaching. So far therefore we have in this chapter a repetition of the lesson that “the movement of the Tao is by contraries,” and that its weakness is the sure precursor of strength. But the connection between this lesson and what he says in par. 1 it is difficult to trace. Up to this time at least it has baffled myself. The passage seems to give us a cosmogony. “The Tao produced One.” We have already seen that the Tao is “The One.” Are we to understand here that the Tao and The One were one and the same? In this case what would be the significance of the 生 (“produced”)?—that the Tao which had been previously “non-existent” now became “existent,” or capable of being named? This seem to be the view of Ssŭ-ma Kuang (AD 1009–1086).

The most singular form which this view assumes is in one of the treatises on our

Ching

, attributed to the Taoist patriarch Lü (呂祖道德經解), that “the One is Heaven, which was formed by the congealing of the Tao.” According to another treatise, also assigned to the same Lü (道德真經合解), the One was “the primordial ether;” the Two, “the separation of that into its Yin and Yang constituents;” and the Three, “the production of heaven, earth, and man by these.” In quoting the paragraph, Huai-nan Tzŭ omits 道生一, and commences with 一生二, and his glossarist, Kao Yu, makes out the One to be the Tao, the Two to be Spiritual Intelligences (神明), and the Three to be the Harmonising Breath. From the mention of the Yin and Yang that follows, I believe that Laozi intended by the Two these two qualities or elements in the primordial ether, which would be “the One.” I dare not hazard a guess as to what “the Three” were. ↩︎

79

徧用, “The Universal Use (of the action in weakness of the Tao).” The chapter takes us back to the lines of ch. 40, that

“Weakness marks the course
Of Tao’s mighty deeds.”

By “the softest thing in the world” it is agreed that we are to understand “water,” which will wear away the hardest rocks. “Dashing against and overcoming” is a metaphor taken from hunting. Ho-shang Kung says that “what has no existence” is the Tao; it is better to understand by it the unsubstantial air (氣) which penetrates everywhere, we cannot see how.

Compare par. 2 with ch. 2, par. 3. ↩︎

80

立戒, “Cautions.” The chapter warns men to let nothing come into competition with the value which they set on the Tao. The Tao is not named, indeed, but the idea of it was evidently in the writer’s mind.

The whole chapter rhymes after a somewhat peculiar fashion; familiar enough, however, to one who is acquainted with the old rhymes of the

Book of Poetry

. ↩︎

81

洪德, “Great or Overflowing Virtue.” The chapter is another illustration of the working of the Tao by contraries.

According to Wu Chʽêng, the action which overcomes cold is that of the yang element in the developing primordial ether; and the stillness which overcomes heat is that of the contrary yin element. These may have been in Laozi’s mind, but the statements are so simple as hardly to need any comment. Wu further says that the purity and stillness are descriptive of the condition of non-action. ↩︎

82

儉欲, “The Moderating of Desire or Ambition.” The chapter shows how the practice of the Tao must conduce to contentment and happiness.

In translating par. 1 I have, after Wu Chʽêng, admitted a 車 after the 糞, his chief authority for doing so being that it is so found in a poetical piece by Chang Hêng (AD 78–139). Chu Hsi also adopted this reading (朱子大全, XVIII 7 a). In par. 2 Han Ying has a tempting variation of 多欲 for 可欲, but I have not adopted it because the same phrase occurs elsewhere. ↩︎

83

鑒遠, “Surveying what is Far-off.” The chapter is a lesson to men to judge of things according to their internal conviction of similar things in their own experience. Short as the chapter is, it is somewhat mystical. The phrase, “The Tao” or way of Heaven, occurs in it for the first time; and it is difficult to lay down its precise meaning. Laozi would seem to teach that man is a microcosm; and that, if he understand the movements of his own mind, he can understand the movements of all other minds. There are various readings, of which it is not necessary to speak.

I have translated par. 2 in the past tense, and perhaps the first should also be translated so. Most of it is found in Han Ying, preceded by “formerly” or “anciently.” ↩︎

84

忘知, “Forgetting Knowledge;”—the contrast between Learning and the Tao. It is only by the Tao that the world can be won.

Chiao Hung commences his quotations of commentary on this chapter with the following Kumārajīva on the second par.:—“He puts it away till he has forgotten all that was bad in it. He then puts away all that is fine about him. He does so till he has forgotten all that was good in it. But the bad was wrong, and the good is right. Having diminished the wrong, and also diminished the right, the process is carried on till they are both forgotten. Passion and desire are both cut off; and his virtue and the Tao are in such union that he does nothing; but though he does nothing, he allows all things to do their own doing, and all things are done.” Such is a Buddhistic view of the passage, not very intelligible, and which I do not endorse.

In a passage in the

Narratives of the School

(Bk. IX Art. 2), we have a Confucian view of the passage:—“Let perspicacity, intelligence, shrewdness, and wisdom be guarded by stupidity, and the service of the possessor will affect the whole world; let them be guarded by complaisance, and his daring and strength will shake the age; let them be guarded by timidity, and his wealth will be all within the four seas; let them be guarded by humility, and there will be what we call the method of ‘diminishing it, and diminishing it again.’ ” But neither do I endorse this.

My own view of the scope of the chapter has been given above in a few words. The greater part of it is found in

Chuang-tzŭ

. ↩︎

85

任德, “The Quality of Indulgence.” The chapter shows how that quality enters largely into the dealing of the sage with other men, and exercises over them a transforming influence, dominated as it is in him by the Tao.

My version of par. 1 is taken from Dr. Chalmers. A good commentary on it was given by the last emperor but one of the earlier of the two great Sung dynasties, in the period AD 1111–1117:—“The mind of the sage is free from preoccupation and able to receive; still, and able to to respond.”

In par. 2 I adopt the reading of 得 (“to get”) instead of the more common 德 (“virtue” or “quality”). There is a passage in Han Ying (IX 3 b, 4 a), the style of which, most readers will probably agree with me in thinking, was moulded on the text before us, though nothing is said of any connection between it and the saying of Laozi. I must regard it as a sequel to the conversation between Confucius and some of his disciples about the principle (Lao’s principle) that “Injury should be recompensed with kindness,” as recorded in the

Con. Ana.

XIV 36. We read:—“Tzŭ-lu said, ‘When men are good to me, I will also be good to them; when they are not good to me, I will also be not good to them.’ Tzŭ-kung said, ‘When men are good to me, I will also be good to them; when they are not good to me, I will simply lead them on, forwards it maybe or backwards.’ Yen Hui said, ‘When men are good to me, I will also be good to them; when they are not good to me, I will still be good to them.’ The views of the three disciples being thus different, they referred the point to the Master, who said, ‘The words of Tzŭ-lu are such as might be expected among the (wild tribes of) the Man and the Mo; those of Tzŭ-kung, such as might be expected among friends; those of Hui, such as might be expected among relatives and near connections.’ ” This is all. The Master was still far from Laozi’s standpoint, and that of his own favourite disciple, Yen Hui. ↩︎

86

貴生, “The Value set on Life.” The chapter sets forth the Tao as an antidote against decay and death.

In par. 1 life is presented to us as intermediate between two non-existences. The words will suggest to many readers those in

Job

i 21.

In pars. 2 and 3 I translate the characters 十有三 by “three in ten,” instead of by “thirteen,” as Julien and other translators have done. The characters are susceptible of either translation according to the tone in which we read the 有. They were construed as I have done by Wang Pi; and many of the best commentators have followed in his wake. “The ministers of life to themselves” would be those who eschewed all things, both internal and external, tending to injure health; “the ministers of death,” those who pursued courses likely to cause disease and shorten life; the third three would be those who thought that by mysterious and abnormal courses they could prolong life, but only injured it. Those three classes being thus disposed of, there remains only one in ten rightly using the Tao, and he is spoken of in the next paragraph.

This par. 4 is easy of translation, and the various readings in it are unimportant, differing in this respect from those in par. 3. But the aim of the author in it is not clear. In ascribing such effects to the possession of the Tao, is he “trifling,” as Dr. Chalmers thinks? or indulging the play of his poetical fancy? or simply saying that the Taoist will keep himself out of danger? ↩︎

87

養德, “The Operation (of the Tao) in Nourishing Things.” The subject of the chapter is the quiet passionless operation of the Tao in nature, in the production and nourishing of things throughout the seasons of the year;—a theme dwelt on by Laozi, in II 4, X 3, and other places.

The Tao is the subject of all the predicates in par. 1, and what seem the subjects in all but the first member should be construed adverbially.

On par. 2 Wu Chʽêng says that the honour of the Son of Heaven is derived from his appointment by God, and that then the nobility of the feudal princes is derived from him; but in the honour given to the Tao and the nobility ascribed to its operation, we are not to think of any external ordination. There is a strong reading of two of the members of par. 3 in Wang Pi, viz. 亭之毒之 for 成之熟之. This is quoted and predicated of “heaven,” in the Nestorian Monument of Xi’an in the eighth century. ↩︎

88

歸元, “Returning to the Source.” The meaning of the chapter is obscure, and the commentators give little help in determining it. As in the preceding chapter, Laozi treats of the operation of the Tao on material things, he seems in this to go on to the operation of it in man, or how he, with his higher nature, should ever be maintaining it in himself.

For the understanding of paragraph 1 we must refer to the first chapter of the treatise, where the Tao, “having no name,” appears as “the Beginning” or “First Cause” of the world, and then, “having a name,” as its “Mother.” It is the same thing or concept in both of its phases, the ideal or absolute, and the manifestation of it in its passionless doings. The old Jesuit translators render this par. by “Mundus principium et causam suam habet in Divino 有 seu actione Divinae sapientiae quae dici potest ejus mater.” So far I may assume that they agreed with me in understanding that the subject of the par. was the Tao.

Par. 2 lays down the law of life for man thus derived from the Tao. The last clause of it is given by the same translators as equivalent to “Unde fit ut post mortem nihil ei timendum sit,”—a meaning which the characters will not bear. But from that clause, and the next par., I am obliged to conclude that even in Laozi’s mind there was the germ of sublimation of the material frame which issued in the asceticism and life-preserving arts of the later Taoism.

Par. 3 seems to indicate the method of “guarding the mother in man,” by watching over the breath, the proto-plastic “one” of ch. 42, the ethereal matter out of which all material things were formed. The organs of this breath in man are the mouth and nostrils (nothing else should be understood here by 兌 and 門;—see the explanations of the former in the last par. of the fifth of the appendixes to the

Yi

in vol. xvi p. 432); and the management of the breath is the mystery of the esoteric Buddhism and Taoism.

In par. 4 “The guarding what is soft” is derived from the used of “the soft lips” in hiding and preserving the hard and strong teeth.

Par. 5 gives the gist of the chapter:—Man’s always keeping before him the ideal of the Tao, and, without purpose, simply doing whatever he finds to do; Tao-like and powerful in all his sphere of action.

I have followed the reading of the last character but one, which is given by Chiao Hung instead of that found in Ho-shang Kung and Wang Pi. ↩︎

89

益證, “Increase of Evidence.” The chapter contrasts government by the Tao with that conducted in a spirit of ostentation and by oppression.

In the “I” of paragraph 1 does Laozi speak of himself? I think he does. Wu Chʽêng understands it of “any man,” i.e. any one in the exercise of government;—which is possible. What is peculiar to my version is the pregnant meaning given to 有如, common enough in the mouth of Confucius. I have adopted it here because of a passage in Liu Hsiang’s

Shuo-yüan

(XX 13 b), where Laozi is made to say “Excessive is the difficulty of practising the Tao at the present time,” adding that the princes of his age would not receive it from him. On the “Great Tao,” see chapter 25, 34, et al. From the twentieth book of

Han Fei

(12 b and 13 a) I conclude that he had the whole of this chapter in his copy of our

Ching

, but he broke it up, after his fashion, into fragmentary utterances, confused and confounding. He gives also some remarkable various readings, one of which (竽, instead of Ho-shang Kung and Wang Pi’s 夸, character 48) is now generally adopted. The passage is quoted in the

Kʽang-hsi dictionary

under 竽 with this reading. ↩︎

90

修觀, “The Cultivation (of the Tao), and the Observation (of its Effects).” The sentiment of the first paragraph is found in the twenty-seventh and other previous chapters—that the noiseless and imperceptible acting of the Tao is irresistible in its influence; and this runs through to the end of the chapter with the additional appeal to the influence of its effects. The introduction of the subject of sacrifices, a religious rite, though not presented to the highest object, will strike the reader as peculiar in our

Ching

.

The Tê mentioned five times in par. 2 is the “virtue” of the Tao embodied in the individual, and extending from him in all the spheres of his occupation, and is explained differently by Han Fei according to its application; and his example I have to some extent followed.

The force of pars. 3 and 4 is well given by Ho-shang Kung. On the first clause he says, “Take the person of one who cultivates the Tao, and compare it with that of one who does not cultivate it;—which is in a state of decay? and which is in a state of preservation? ↩︎

91

玄符, “The Mysterious Charm;” meaning, apparently, the entire passivity of the Tao.

With pars. 1 and 2, compare what is said about the infant in chapters 10 and 20, and about the immunity from dangers such as here described of the disciples of the Tao in ch. 50. My “evil” in the second triplet of par. 3 has been translated by “felicity;” but a reference to the

Kʽang-hsi

dictionary will show that the meaning which I give to 祥 is well authorised. It is the only meaning allowable here. The third and fourth 曰 in this par. appear in Ho-shang Kung’s text as 日, and he comments on the clauses accordingly; but 曰 is now the received reading. Some light is thrown on this paragraph and the next by an apocryphal conversation attributed to Laozi in Liu Hsiang’s

Shuo-yüan

, X, 4 a. ↩︎

92

玄德, “The Mysterious Excellence.” The chapter gives us a picture of the man of Tao, humble and retiring, oblivious of himself and of other men, the noblest man under heaven.

Par. 1 is found in

Chuang-tzŭ

(XIII 20 b), not expressly mentioned, as taken from Laozi, but at the end of a string of sentiments, ascribed the “the Master,” some of them, like the two clause here, no doubt belonging to him, and the others, probably Chuang-tzŭ’s own.

Par. 2 is all found in chapters 4 and 52, excepting the short clause in the conclusion. ↩︎

93

淳風, “The Genuine Influence.” The chapter shows how government by the Tao is alone effective, and of universal application; contrasting it with the failure of other methods.

After the “weapons of war” in par. 1, one is tempted to take “the sharp implements” in par. 2 as such weapons, but the meaning which I finally adopted, especially after studying chapters 36 and 80, seems more consonant with Laozi’s scheme of thought. In the last member of the same par., Ho-shang Kung has the strange reading of 法物, and uses it in his commentary; but the better text of 法令 is found both in

Huai-nan

and

Ssŭ-ma Chʽien

, and in

Wang Pi

.

We do not know if the writer were quoting any particular sage in par. 3, or referring generally to the sages of the past;—men like the “sentence-makers” of ch. 41. ↩︎

94

順化, “Transformation according to Circumstances;” but this title does not throw light on the meaning of the chapter; nor are we helped to an understanding of it by Han Fei, with his additions and comments (XII 3 b, 4 b), nor by Huai-nan with his illustrations (XII 21 a, b). The difficulty of it is increased by its being separated form the preceding chapter of which it is really the sequel. It contrasts still further government by the Tao with that by the method of correction. The sage is the same in both chapters, his character and government both marked by the opposites or contraries which distinguish the procedure of the Tao as stated in ch. 40. ↩︎

95

守道, “Guarding the Tao.” The chapter shows how it is the guarding of the Tao that ensures a continuance of long life, with vigour and success. The abuse of it and other passages in our

Ching

helped on, I must believe, the later Taoist dreams about the elixir vitae and life-preserving pills. The whole of it, with one or two various readings, is found in

Han Fei

(VI 4 b–6 a), who speaks twice in his comments of the book.

Par. 1 has been translated, “In governing men and in serving Heaven, there is nothing like moderation.” But by “Heaven” there is not intended “the blue sky” above us, nor any personal Power above it, but the Tao embodied in our constitution, the heavenly element in our nature. The “moderation” is the opposite of what we call “living fast,” “burning the candle at both ends.”

In par. 2 I must read 復, instead of the more common 服. Its meaning is the same as in 復歸其明 in ch. 52, par. 5. Tê is not “virtue” in our common meaning of the term, but “the attributes of the Tao,” as almost always with Laozi. ↩︎

96

居位, “Occupying the Throne;” occupying it, that is, according to the Tao, noiselessly and purposelessly, so that the people enjoy their lives, free from all molestation seen and unseen.

Par. 1, that is, in the most quiet and easy manner. The whole of the chapter is given and commented on by Han Fei (VI 6 a–7 b); but very unsatisfactorily.

The more one thinks and reads about the rest of the chapter the more does he agree with the words of Julien:—“It presents the frequent recurrence of the same characters, and appears as insignificant as it is unintelligible, if we give to the Chinese characters their ordinary meaning.”—The reader will observe that we have here the second mention of spirits (the manes;

Chalmers

, “the ghosts;”

Julien

, les démons). See ch. 39.

Whatever Laozi meant to teach in par. 2, he laid in it a foundation for the superstition of the later and present Taoism about the spirits of the dead;—such as appeared a few years ago in the “tail-cutting” scare. ↩︎

97

謙德, “The Attribute of Humility;”—a favourite theme with Laozi; and the illustration of it from the low-lying stream to which smaller streams flow is also a favourite subject with him. The language can hardly but recall the words of a greater than Laozi:—“He that humbleth himself shall be exalted.” ↩︎

98

爲道, “Practising the Tao.” 貴道, “The value set on the Tao,” would have been a more appropriate title. The chapter sets forth that value in various manifestations of it.

Par. 1 For the meaning of 奧, see

Confucian Analects

, III ch. 13.

Par. 2 I am obliged to adopt the reading of the first sentence of this paragraph given by Huai-nan, 美言可以市尊, 美行可以加人;—see especially his quotation of it in XVIII 10 a, as from a superior man, I have not found his reading anywhere else.

Par. 3 is not easily translated, or explained. See the rules on presenting offerings at the court of a ruler or the kind, in vol. xxvii of the

Sacred Books of the East

, p. 84, note 3, and also a narrative in the

Tso Chuan

under the thirty-third year of duke Hsi. ↩︎

99

思始, “Thinking in the Beginning.” The former of these two characters is commonly misprinted 恩, and this has led Chalmers to mistranslate them by “The Beginning of Grace.” The chapter sets forth the passionless method of the Tao, and how the sage accordingly accomplishes his objects easily by forestalling in his measures all difficulties. In par. 1 the clauses are indicative, and not imperative, and therefore we have to supplement the text in translating in some such way, as I have done. They give us a cluster of aphorisms illustrating the procedure of the Tao “by contraries,” and conclude with one, which is the chief glory of Laozi’s teaching, though I must think that its value is somewhat diminished by the method in which he reaches it. It has not the prominence in the later teaching of Taoist writers which we should expect, nor is it found (so far as I know) in

Chuang-tzŭ

,

Han Fei

, or

Huai-nan

. It is quoted, however, twice by Liu Hsiang;—see my note on par. 2 of ch. 49.

It follows from the whole chapter that the Taoistic “doing nothing” was not an absolute quiescence and inaction, but had a method in it. ↩︎

100

守微, “Guarding the Minute.” The chapter is a continuation and enlargement of the last. Wu Chʽêng, indeed, unites the two, blending them together with some ingenious transpositions and omissions, which is not necessary to discuss. Compare the first part of par. 3 with the last part of par. 1, ch. 29. ↩︎

101

淳德, “Pure, unmixed Excellence.” The chapter shows the powerful and beneficent influence of the Tao in government, in contrast with the applications and contrivances of human wisdom. Compare ch. 19. My “simple and ignorant” is taken from Julien. More literally the translation would be “to make them stupid.” My “scourge” in par. 2 is also after Julien’s fléau. ↩︎

102

後己, “Putting one’s self Last.” The subject is the power of the Tao, by its display of humility in attracting men. The subject and the way in which it is illustrated are frequent themes in the

Ching

. See chapters 8, 22, 39, 42, 61, et al.

The last sentence of par. 3 is found also in ch. 22. There seem to be no quotations from the chapter in

Han Fei

or

Huai-nan

; but Wu Chʽêng quotes passages from Tung Chung-shu (of the second century BC), and Yang Hsiung (BC 53–AD 18), which seem to show that the phraseology of it was familiar to them. The former says:—“When one places himself in his qualities below others, his person is above them; when he places them behind those of others, his person is before them;” the other, “Men exalt him who humbles himself below them; and give the precedence to him who puts himself behind them.” ↩︎

103

三寶, “The Three Precious Things.” This title is taken from par. 2, and suggests to us how the early framer of these titles intended to express by them the subject-matter of their several chapters. The three things are the three distinguishing qualities of the possessor of the Tao, the three great moral qualities appearing in its followers, the qualities, we may venture to say, of the Tao itself. The same phrase is now the common designation of Buddhism in China—the Tri-ratna or Ratna-traya, “the Precious Buddha,” “the Precious Law,” and “the Precious Priesthood (or rather Monkhood) or Church;” appearing also in the “Tri-śaraṇa,” or “formula of the Three Refuges,” what Dr. Eitel calls “the most primitive formula fidei of the early Buddhists, introduced before Southern and Northern Buddhism separated.” I will not introduce the question of whether Buddhism borrowed this designation of Taoism, after its entrance into China. It is in Buddhism the formula of a peculiar church or religion; in Taoism a rule for the character, or the conduct which the Tao demands from all mean. “My Tao” in par. 1 is the reading of Wang Pi; Ho-shang Kung’s text is simply 我. Wang Pi’s reading is now generally adopted.

The concluding sentiment of the chapter is equivalent to the saying of Mencius (VII ii iv 2), “If the ruler of a state love benevolence, he will have no enemy under heaven.” “Heaven” is equivalent to “the Tao,” the course of events—Providence, as we should say. ↩︎

104

配天, “Matching Heaven.” The chapter describes the work of the practiser of the Tao as accomplished like that of Heaven, without striving or crying. He appears under the figure of a mailed warrior (士) of the ancient chariot. The chapter is a sequel of the preceding, and is joined on to it by Wu Chʽêng, as is also the next. ↩︎

105

玄用, “The Use of the Mysterious (Tao).” Such seems to be the meaning of the title. The chapter teaches that, if war were carried on, or rather avoided, according to the Tao, the result would be success. Laozi’s own statements appear as so many paradoxes. They are examples of the procedure of the Tao by “contraries,” or opposites.

We do not know who the master of the military art referred to was. Perhaps the author only adopted the style of quotation to express his own sentiments. ↩︎

106

知難, “The Difficulty of being (rightly) Known.” The Tao comprehends and rules all Laozi’s teachings, as the members of a clan were all in the loins of their first father (宗), and continue to look up to him; and the people of a state are all under the direction of their ruler; yet the philosopher had to complain of not being known. Laozi’s principle and rule or ruler was the Tao. His utterance here is very important. Compare the words of Confucius in the

Analects

, XIV ch. 37, et al.

Par. 2 is twice quoted by Huai-nan, though his text is not quite the same in both cases. ↩︎

107

知病, “The Disease of Knowing.” Here, again, we have the Tao working “by contraries,”—in the matter of knowledge. Compare par. 1 with Confucius’s account of what knowledge is in the

Analects

, II ch. 17. The par. 1 is found in one place in

Huai-nan

, lengthened out by the addition of particles; but the variation is unimportant. In another place, however, he seems to have had the correct text before him.

Par. 2 in

Han Fei

also lengthened out, but with an important variation (不病 for 病病), and I cannot construe his text. His 不 is probably a transcriber’s error. ↩︎

108

愛己, “Loving one’s Self.” This title is taken from the expression in par. 4; and the object of the chapter seems to be to show how such loving should be manifested, and to enforce the lesson by the example of the “sage,” the true master of the Tao.

In par. 1 “the great dread” is death, and the things which ought to be feared and maybe feared, are the indulgences of the appetites and passions, which, if not eschewed, tend to shorten life and accelerate the approach of death.

Pars. 2 and 3 are supplementary to 1. For 狹, the second character of Ho-shang Kung’s text in par. 2, Wang Pi reads 狎, which has the same name as the other; and according to the

Kʽang-hsi’s dictionary

, the two characters are interchangeable. I have also followed Wu Chʽêng in adopting 狎 for the former of the two 厭 in par. 3. Wu adopted this reading from a commentator Liu of Lu-ling. It gives a good meaning, and is supported by the structure of other sentences made on similar lines.

In par. 4 “the sage” must be “the ruler who is a sage,” a master of the Tao, “the king” of ch. 25. He “loves himself,” i.e. his life, and takes the right measures to prolong his life, but without any demonstration that he is doing so.

The above is, I conceive, the correct explanation of the chapter; but as to the Chinese critics and foreign translators of it, it maybe said, “Quot homines, tot sententiae.” In illustration of this I venture to subjoin what is found on it in the old version of the Jesuit missionaries, which has not been previously printed:—

Prima explicatio juxta interpretes.

Populus, ubi jam principis iram non timet, nihil non audet ut jugum excutiat, resque communis ad extremum discrimen adducitur.

Ambitio principis non faciat terram angustiorem, et vectigalium magnitudine alendo populo insufficientem; numquam populus patriae pertaesus alias terras quaeret.

Vitae si non taedet, neque patrii soli taedebit.

Quare sanctus sibi semper attentus potentiam suam non ostentat.

Quia vere se amat, non se pretiosum facit; vel quia sibi recte consulit non se talem aestimat cujus felicitati et honori infelices populi unice servire debeant, immo potius eum se reputat qui populorum felicitati totum se debeat impendere.

Ergo illud resecat, istud amplectitur.

Alia explicatio.

Populus si non ita timet principis majestatem, sed facile ad eum accedit, majestas non minuitur, immo ad summum pervenit.

Vectigalibus terra si non opprimitur, suâ quisque contentus alias terras non quaeret, si se non vexari populus experitur.

Vitae si non taedet, nec patrii soli taedebit.

Quare sanctus majestatis fastum non affectat, immo similem se caeteris ostendit.

Sibi recte consulens, populorum amans, non se pretiosum et inaccessibilem facit.

Quidquid ergo timorem incutere potest, hoc evitat; quod amorem conciliat et benignitatem, se demonstrat hoc eligi et ultro amplectitur.

↩︎

109

任爲. “Allowing Men to take their Course.” The chapter teaches that rulers should not be hasty to punish, especially by the infliction of death. Though they may seem to err in leniency, yet heaven does not allow offenders to escape.

While heaven hates the ill-doer, yet we must not always conclude from its judgements that every one who suffers from them is an ill-doer; and the two lines which rhyme, and illustrate this point, are equivalent to the sentiment in our

Old Book

, “Clouds and darkness are round about Him.” They are ascribed to Laozi by Lieh-tzŭ (VI 7 a); but, it has been said, that they are quoted by him “in an entirely different connection.” But the same text in two different sermons may be said to be in different connections. In

Lieh-tzŭ

and our

Ching

the lines have the same meaning, and substantially the same application. Indeed Chang Chan, of our fourth century, the commentator of

Lieh-tzŭ

, quotes the comment of Wang Pi on this passage, condensing it into, “Who can know the mind of Heaven? Only the sage can do so.” ↩︎

110

制惑, “Restraining Delusion.” The chapter sets forth the inefficiency of capital punishment, and warns rulers against the infliction of it. Who is it that superintends the infliction of death? The answer of Ho-shang Kung is very clear:—“It is Heaven, which, dwelling on high and ruling all beneath, takes note of the transgressions of men.” There is a slight variation in the readings of the second sentence of par. 2 in the texts of Ho-shang Kung and Wang Pi, and the reading adopted by Chiao Hung differs a little from them both; but the meaning is the same in them all.

This chapter and the next are rightly joined on to the preceding by Wu Chʽêng. ↩︎

111

貪損, “How Greediness Injures.” The want of the nothing-doing Tao leads to the multiplication of exactions by the government, and to the misery of the people, so as to make them think lightly of death. The chapter is a warning for both rulers and people.

It is not easy to determine whether rulers, or people or both, are intended in the concluding sentence of par. 2. ↩︎

112

戒強, “A Warning against (trusting in) Strength.” To trust in one’s force is contrary to the Tao, whose strength is more in weakness and humility.

In par. 1 the two characters which I have rendered by “(so it is with) all things” are found in the texts of both Ho-shang Kung and Wang Pi, but Wu Chʽêng and Chiao Hung both reject them. I should also have neglected them, but they are also found in Liu Hsiang’s

Shuo Wên

(X 4 a), with all the rest of pars. 1 and 2, as from Laozi. They are an anacoluthon, such as is elsewhere found in our

Ching

; e.g.天下之牝 in ch. 21, par. 2.

The “above” and “below” in par. 4 seem to be merely a play on the words, as capable of meaning “more and less honourable.” ↩︎

113

天道, “The Way of Heaven;” but the chapter contrasts that way, unselfish and magnanimous, with the way of man, selfish and contracted, and illustrates the point by the method of stringing a bow. This must be seen as it is done in China fully to understand the illustration. I have known great athletes in this country tasked to the utmost of their strength to adjust and bend a large Chinese bow from Peking.

The “sage” of par. 4 is the “King” of ch. 25. Compare what is said of him with ch. 2, par. 4, et al. ↩︎

114

任信, “Thing to be Believed.” It is difficult to give a short and appropriate translation of this title. The chapter shows how the most unlikely results follow from action according to the Tao.

Par. 1. Water was Laozi’s favourite emblem of the Tao. Compare chapters 8, 66, et al.

Par. 2. Compare ch. 36, par. 2.

Par. 3. Of course we do not know who the sage was from whom Laozi got the lines of this paragraph. They may suggest to some readers the lines of Burns, as they have done to me:—

“This honest man, though e’er so poor,
Is king o’ men for a’ that.”

But the Taoist of Laozi is a higher ideal than Burn’s honest man.

Par. 4 is separated from this chapter, and made to begin the next by Wu Chʽêng. ↩︎

115

任契, “Adherence to Bond or Covenant.” The chapter shows, but by no means clearly, how he who holds fast to the Tao will be better off in the end than he who will rather try to secure his own interests.

Par. 1 presents us with a case which the statements of the chapter are intended to meet:—two disputants, one good, and the other bad; the latter, though apparently reconciled, still retaining a grudge, and ready to wreak his dissatisfaction, when he has an opportunity. The 爲 = “for,” “for the good of.”

Par. 2 is intended to solve the question. The terms of a contract or agreement were inscribed on a slip of wood, which was then divided into two; each party having one half of it. At the settlement, if the halves perfectly fitted to each other, it was carried through. The one who had the right in the dispute has his part of the agreement, but does not insist on it, and is forbearing; the other insists on the conditions being even now altered in his favour. The characters by which this last case is expressed, are very enigmatical, having reference to the satisfaction of the government dues of Laozi’s time—a subject into which it would take much space to go.

Par. 3 decides the question by the action of heaven, which is only another name for the course of the Tao. ↩︎

116

獨立, “Standing Alone.” The chapter sets forth what Laozi conceived the ancient government of simplicity was, and what he would have government in all time to be. He does not use the personal pronoun “I” as the subject of the thrice-recurring 使, but it is most natural to suppose that he is himself that subject; and he modestly supposes himself in charge of a little state and a small population. The reader can judge for himself of the consummation that would be arrived at;—a people rude and uninstructed, using quippos, abstaining from war and all travelling, kept aloof from intercourse even with their neighbours, and without the appliances of what we call civilisation.

The text is nearly all found in Ssŭ-ma Chʽien and Chuang-tzŭ. The first member of par. 1, however is very puzzling. The old Jesuit translators, Julien, Chalmers, and V. von Strauss, all differ in their views of it. Wu Chʽêng and Chiao Hung take what I have now rendered by “abilities,” as meaning “implements of agriculture,” but their view is based on a custom of the Han dynasty, which is not remote enough for the purpose, and on the suppression, after Wang Pi, of a 人 in Ho-shang Kung’s text. ↩︎

117

顯質, “The Manifestation of Simplicity.” The chapter shows how quietly and effectively the Tao proceeds, and by contraries in a way that only the master of it can understand. The author, says Wu Chʽêng, “sums up in this the subject-matter of the two parts of his treatise, showing that in all its five thousand characters, there is nothing beyond what is here said.”

Par. 2 suggests to Dr. Chalmers the well-known lines of Bunyan as an analogue of it:—

“A man there was, though some did count him mad,
The more he gave away, the more he had.”

Wu Chʽêng brings together two sentences from

Chuang-tzŭ

(XXXIII 21 b, 22 a), written evidently with the characters of this text in mind, which as from a Taoist mint, are a still better analogue, and I venture to put them into rhyme:—

“Amassing but to him a sense of need betrays;
He hoards not, and thereby his affluence displays.”

I have paused long over the first pair of contraries in par. 3 (利 and 害). Those two characters primarily mean “sharpness” and “wounding by cutting;” they are also often used in the sense of “being beneficial,” and “being injurious;”—“contraries,” both of them. Which “contrary” had Laozi in mind? I must think the former, though differing in this from all previous translators. The Jesuit version is, “Celestis Tao natura ditat omnes, nemini nocet;” Julien’s, “Il est utile aux êtres, et ne leur nuit point;” Chalmers’s, “Benefits and does not injure;” and V. von Strauss’s, “Des Himmels Weise ist wolthun und nicht beschädigen.” ↩︎

Preface by James Legge

In the “Preface” to the third volume of these

Sacred Books of the East

(1879), I stated that I proposed giving in due course, in order to exhibit the System of Taoism, translations of the

Tao Te Ching

by Laozi (sixth century BC),[1] the

Writings of Chuang-tzŭ

(between the middle of the fourth and third centuries BC), and the

Treatise of “Actions and Their Retributions”

(of our eleventh century); and perhaps also of one or more of the other characteristic Productions of the System.

The two volumes now submitted to the reader are a fulfilment of the promise made so long ago. They contain versions of the three works which were specified, and, in addition, as appendixes, four other shorter treatises of Taoism; analyses of several of the books of Chuang-tzŭ by Lin Hsi-chung; a list of the stories which form so important a part of those books; two essays by two of the greatest Scholars of China, written the one in AD 586 and illustrating the Taoistic beliefs of that age, and the other in AD 1078 and dealing with the four books of Chuang-tzŭ, whose genuineness is frequently called in question. The concluding index is confined very much to proper names. For subjects the reader is referred to the tables of contents, the introduction to the books of Chuang-tzŭ (vol. xxxix pp. 127–163), and the introductory notes to the various appendixes.[2]

The

Treatise of Actions and their Retributions

exhibits to us the Taoism of the eleventh century in its moral or ethical aspects; in the two earlier works we see it rather as a philosophical speculation than as a religion in the ordinary sense of that term. It was not till after the introduction of Buddhism into China in our first century that Taoism began to organise itself as a religion, having its monasteries and nunneries, its images and rituals. While it did so, it maintained the superstitions peculiar to itself:—some, like the cultivation of the Tao as a rule of life favourable to longevity, come down from the earliest times, and others which grew up during the decay of the Chou dynasty, and subsequently blossomed;—now in mystical speculation; now in the pursuits of alchemy; now in the search for the pills of immortality and the elixir vitae; now in astrological fancies; now in visions of spirits and in magical arts to control them; and finally in the terrors of its purgatory and everlasting hell. Its phases have been continually changing, and at present it attracts our notice more as a degraded adjunct of Buddhism than as a development of the speculations of Laozi and Chuang-tzŭ. Up to its contact with Buddhism, it subsisted as an opposition to the Confucian system, which, while admitting the existence and rule of the Supreme Being, bases its teaching on the study of man’s nature and the enforcement of the duties binding on all men from the moral and social principles of their constitution.

It is only during the present century that the Texts of Taoism have begun to receive the attention which they deserve. Christianity was introduced into China by Nestorian missionaries in the seventh century; and from the Xi’an Monument, which was erected by their successors in 781, nearly 150 years after their first entrance, we perceive that they were as familiar with the books of Laozi and Chuang-tzŭ as with the Confucian literature of the empire, but that monument is the only memorial of them that remains. In the thirteenth century the Roman Catholic Church sent its earliest missionaries to China, but we hardly know anything of their literary labours.

The great Romish mission which continue to the present day began towards the end of the sixteenth century; and there exists now in the India Office a translation of the

Tao Te Ching

in Latin, which was brought to English by a Mr. Matthew Raper, and presented by him to the Royal Society, of which he was a Fellow, on January 10th, 1788. The manuscript is in excellent preservation, but we do not know by whom the version was made. It was presented, as stated in the “Introduction,” par. 1, to Mr. Raper by P. de Grammont, Missionarius Apostolicus, ex-Jesuita. The chief object of the translator or translators was to show that “the Mysteries of the Most Holy Trinity and of the Incarnate God were anciently known to the Chinese nation.” The version as a whole is of little value. The reader will find, in endnotes 97, its explanation of Lao’s seventy-second chapter;—the first morsel of it that has appeared in print.

Protestant missions to China commenced in 1807; but it was not till 1868 that the Rev. Dr. Chalmers, a member of one of them, published his

Speculations on Metaphysics, Polity, and Morality of “The Old Philosopher,” Laozi

. Meanwhile, Abel-Rémusat had aroused the curiosity of scholars throughout Europe, in 1823, by his

Memoir on the Life and Opinions of Laozi, a Chinese Philosopher of the sixth century before our era, who professed the opinions commonly attributed to Pythagoras, to Plato, and to their disciples

. Rémusat was followed by one who had received from him his first lessons in Chinese, and had become a truly great Chinese scholar—the late Stanislas Julien. He published in 1842 “a complete translation for the first time of this memorable work, which is regarded with reason as the most profound, the most abstract, and the most difficult of all Chinese literature.” Dr. Chalmers’s translation was also complete, but his comments, whether original or from Chinese sources, were much fewer than those supplied by Julien. Two years later, two German versions of the treatise were published at Leipzig;—by Reinhold von Plänckner and Victor von Strauss, differing much from each other, but both marked by originality and ability.

I undertook myself, as stated above, in 1879 to translate for

The Sacred Books of the East

the texts of Taoism which appear in these volumes; and, as I could find time from my labours on

The Texts of Confucianism

, I had written out more than one version of Lao’s work by the end of 1880. Though not satisfied with the result, I felt justified in exhibiting my general views of it in an article in the

British Quarterly Review

of July, 1883.

In 1884 Mr. F. H. Balfour published at Shanghai a version of

Taoist Texts, Ethical, Political, and Speculative

. His Texts were ten in all, the

Tao Te Ching

being the first and longest of them. His version of this differed in many points from all previous versions; and Mr. H. A. Giles, of H.M.’s Consular Service in China, vehemently assailed it and also Dr. Chalmers’s translation, in the

China Review

for March and April, 1886. Mr. Giles, indeed, occasionally launched a shaft also at Julien and myself; but his main object in his article was to discredit the genuineness and authenticity of the

Tao Te Ching

itself. “The work,” he says, “is undoubtedly a forgery. It contains, indeed, much that Laozi did say, but more that he did not.” I replied, so far as was necessary, to Mr. Giles in the same

Review

for January and February, 1888; and a brief summary of my reply is given in the second chapter of the “Introduction” in this volume. My confidence has never been shaken for a moment in the

Tao Te Ching

as genuine relic of Laozi, one of the most original minds of the Chinese race.

In preparing the version now published, I have used:—

First,

The Complete Works of the Ten Philosophers

;—a Suzhou reprint in 1804 of the best editions of the

Philosophers

, nearly all belonging more or less to the Taoist school, included in it. It is a fine specimen of Chinese printing, clear and accurate. The

Treatise

of Laozi of course occupies the first place, as edited by Kuei Yu-kuang (better known as Kuei Chên-chʽuan) of the Ming dynasty. The text and commentary are those of Ho-shang Kung (Introd., par. 7), along with the division of the whole into parts and eighty-one chapters, and the titles of the several chapters, all attributed to him. Along the top of the page, there is a large collection of notes from celebrated commentators and writers down to the editor himself.

Second, the

Text and Commentary of Wang Pi

(called also Fu-ssŭ), who died AD 249, at the early age of twenty-four. See “Introduction,” par. 8.

Third, Helps (lit. Wings) to Laozi; by Chiao Hung (called also Jo-hou), and prefaced by him in 1587. This is what Julien calls “the most extensive and most important contribution to the understanding of Laozi, which we yet possess.” Its contents are selected from the ablest writings on the

Treatise

from Han Fei (Introd., par. 3) downwards, closing in many chapters with the notes made by the compiler himself in the course of his studies. Altogether the book sets before us the substance of the views of sixty-four writers on our short

Ching

. Julien took the trouble to analyse the list of them, and found it composed of three emperors, twenty professed Taoists, seven Buddhists, and thirty-four Confucianists or members of the literati. He says, “These last constantly explain Laozi according to the ideas peculiar to the school of Confucius, at the risk of misrepresenting him, and with the express intention of throttling his system;” then adding, “The commentaries written in such a spirit have no interest for persons who wish to enter fully into the thought of Laozi, and obtain a just idea of his doctrine. I have thought it useless, therefore, to specify the names of such commentaries and their authors.”

I have quoted these sentences of Julien, because of a charge brought by Mr. Balfour, in a prefatory note to his own version of the

Tao Te Ching

, against him and other translators. “One prime defect,” he says, though with some hesitation, “lies at the root of every translation that has been published hitherto; and this is, that not one seems to have been based solely and entirely on commentaries furnished by members of the Taoist school. The Confucian element enters largely into all; and here, I think, an injustice has been done to Laozi. To a Confucianist the Taoist system is in every sense of the word a heresy, and a commentator holding his opinion is surely not the best expositor. It is as a grammarian rather than as a philosopher that a member of the Ju Chia deals with the

Tao Te Ching

; he gives the sense of a passage according to the syntactical construction rather than according to the genius of the philosophy itself; and in attempting to explain the text by his own canons, instead of by the canons of Taoism, he mistakes the superficial and apparently obvious meaning for the hidden and esoteric interpretation.”

Mr. Balfour will hardly repeat his charge of imperfect or erroneous interpretation against Julien; and I believe that is equally undeserved by most, if not all, of the other translators against whom it is directed. He himself adopted as his guide the

Explanations of the Tao Te Ching

, current as the work of Lü Yen (called also Lü Tsu, Lü Tung-pin, and Lü Chʽung-yang), a Taoist of the eighth century. Through Mr. Balfour’s kindness I have had an opportunity of examining this edition of Lao’s

Treatise

; and I am compelled to agree with the very unfavourable judgement on it pronounced by Mr. Giles as both “spurious” and “ridiculous.” All that we are told of Lü Yen is very suspicious; much of it evidently false. The editions of our little book ascribed to him are many. I have for more than twenty years possessed one with the title of

The Meaning of the Tao Te Ching Explained by the True Man of Chʽung-yang

, being a reprint of 1690, and as different as possible from the work patronised by Mr. Balfour.

Fourth, the

Tʽai Shang Hsüan Yüan Tao Te Ching

—a work of the present dynasty, published at Shanghai, but when produced I do not know. It is certainly of the Lü Tsu type, and is worth purchasing as one of the finest specimens of block-printing. It professes to be the production of “The Immortals of the Eight Grottoes,” each of whom is styled “a Divine Ruler (Ti Chün).” The eighty-one chapters are equally divided for commentary among them, excepting that “the Divine Ruler, the Universal Refiner,” has the last eleven assigned to him. The text is everywhere broken up into short clauses, which are explained in a very few characters by “God, the True Helper,” the same, I suppose, who is also styled, “The Divine Ruler, the True Helper,” and comments at length on chapters 31 to 40. I mention these particulars as an illustration of how the ancient Taoism has become polytheistic and absurd. The name “God, the True Helper,” is a title, I imagine, given to Lü Tsu. With all this nonsense, the composite commentary is a good one, the work, evidently, of one hand. One of the several recommendatory preface is ascribed to Wên Chʽang, the god of literature; and he specially praises the work, as “explaining the meaning by examination of the text.”

Fifth, a

Collection of the Most Important Treatises of the Taoist Fathers

(

Tao Tsu Chên Chʽuan Chi Yao

). This was reprinted in 1877 at Changzhou in Jiangsu; beginning with the

Tao Te Ching

, and ending with the

Kan Ying Pʽien

. Between these there are fourteen other treatises, mostly short, five of them being among Mr. Balfour’s

Taoist Texts

. The collection was edited by a Lu Yü; and the commentary selected by him, in all but the last treatise, was by a Li Hsi-yüeh, who appears to have been a recluse in a monastery on a mountain in the department of Pao-ning, Sichuan, if, indeed, what is said of him be not entirely fabulous.

Sixth, the

Commentary on the Tao Te Ching

, by Wu Chʽêng (AD 1249–1333) of Lin Chʽuan. This has been of the highest service to me. Wu Chʽêng was the greatest of the Yüan scholars. He is one of the literati quoted from occasionally by Chiao Hung in his

Wings

; but by no means so extensively as Julien supposes (“Observations Détachées” p. xli). My own copy of his work is in the 12th section of the large

Collection of the Yüeh-ya Hall

, published in 1853. Writing of Wu Chʽêng in 1865 (“Proleg.” to the

Shu

, p. 36), I said that he was “a bold thinker and a daring critic, handling his text with a freedom which I had not seen in any other Chinese scholar.” The subsequent study of his writings has confirmed me in this opinion of him. Perhaps he might be characterised as an independent, rather than as a bold, thinking, and the daring of his criticism must not be supposed to be without caution. (See “Introd.,” p. 9.)[3]

I have thus set forth all that is necessary to be said here by way of preface. For various information about the treatises comprised in the appendixes,[4] the reader is referred to the preliminary notes, which preceded the translation of most of them. I have often sorely missed the presence of a competent native scholar who would have assisted me in the quest of references, and in talking over difficult passages. Such a helper would have saved me much time; but the result, I think, would scarcely have appeared in any great alteration of my versions.

J. L.
Oxford,
December 20, 1890.

Introduction

Was Taoism Older Than Laozi?
The Texts of the

Tao Te Ching

and

Chuang-Tzŭ Shu

What Is the Meaning of the Name Tao? And the Chief Points of the Belief in Taoism
Accounts of Laozi and Chuang-Tzŭ Given by Ssŭ-Ma Chʽien

Was Taoism Older Than Laozi?

In writing the preface to the third volume of these

Sacred Books of the East

in 1879, I referred to Laozi as “the acknowledged founder” of the system of Taoism. Prolonged study and research, however, have brought me to the conclusion that there was a Taoism earlier than his; and that before he wrote his

Tao Te Ching

, the principles taught in it had been promulgated, and the ordering of human conduct and government flowing from them inculcated.

For more than a thousand years “the Three Religions” has been a stereotyped phrase in China, meaning what we call Confucianism, Taoism, and Buddhism. The phrase itself simply means “the Three Teachings,” or systems of instruction, leaving the subject-matter of each “Teaching” to be learned by inquiry. Of the three, Buddhism is of course the most recent, having been introduced into China only the first century of our Christian era. Both the others were indigenous to the country, and are traceable to a much greater antiquity, so that it is a question to which the earlier origin should be assigned. The years of Confucius’s life lay between BC 551 and 478; but his own acknowledgement that he was “a transmitter and not a maker,” and the testimony of his grandson, that “he handed down the doctrines of Yao and Shun (BC 2300), and elegantly displayed the regulations of Wên and Wu (BC 1200), taking them as his model,” are well known.

Laozi’s birth is said, in the most likely account of it, to have taken place in the third year of king Ting of the Chou dynasty, (BC) 604. He was thus rather more than fifty years older than Confucius. The two men seem to have met more than once, and I am inclined to think that the name Laozi, as the designation of the other, arose from Confucius’s styling him to his disciples “The Old Philosopher.” They met as heads of different schools or schemes of thought; but did not touch, so far as we know, on the comparative antiquity of their views. It is a peculiarity of the

Tao Te Ching

that any historical element in it is of the vaguest nature possible, and in all its chapters there is not a single proper name. Yet there are some references to earlier sages whose words the author was copying out, and to “sentence-makers” whose maxims he was introducing to illustrate his own sentiments.[5] In the most distant antiquity he saw a happy society in which his highest ideas of the Tao were realised, and in the seventeenth chapter he tells us that in the earliest times the people did not know that there were their rulers, and when those rulers were most successful in dealing with them, simply said, “We are what we are of ourselves.” Evidently mean existed to Laozi at first in a condition of happy innocence—in what we must call a paradisiacal state, according to his idea of what such a state was likely to be.

When we turn from the treatise of Laozi to the writings of Chuang-tzŭ, the greatest of his followers, we are not left in doubt as to his belief in an early state of paradisiacal Taoism. Huang Ti, the first year of whose reign is placed in BC 2697, is often introduced as a seeker of the Tao, and is occasionally condemned as having been one of the first to disturb its rule in men’s minds and break up “the State of Perfect Unity.” He mentions several sovereigns of whom we can hardly find a trace in the records of history as having ruled in the primeval period, and gives us more than one description of the condition of the world during that happy time.[6]

I do not think that Chuang-tzŭ had any historical evidence for the statements which he makes about those early days, the men who flourished in them, and their ways. His narratives are for the most part fictions, in which the names and incidents are of his own devising. They are no more true as matters of fact than the accounts of the characters in Bunyun’s

Pilgrim’s Progress

are true, with reference to any particular individuals; but as these last are grandly true of myriads of minds in different ages, so may we read in Chuang-tzŭ’s stories the thoughts of Taoistic men beyond the restrictions of place and time. He believed that those thoughts were as old as the men to whom he attributed them. I find in his belief a ground for believing myself that to Taoism, as well as to Confucianism, we ought to attribute a much earlier origin than the famous men whose names they bear. Perhaps they did not differ so much at first as they came afterwards to do in the hands of Confucius and Laozi, both great thinkers, the one more of a moralist, and the other more of a metaphysician. When and how, if they were ever more akin than they came to be; their divergence took place, are difficult questions on which it may be well to make some remarks after we have tried to set forth the most important principles of Taoism.

Those principles have to be learned from the treatise of Laozi and the writings of Chuang-tzŭ. We can hardly say that the Taoism taught in them is the Taoism now current in China, or that has been current in it for many centuries; but in an inquiry into the nature and origin of religions these are the authorities that must be consulted for Taoism, and whose evidence must be accepted. The treatise,

Actions and the Responses to them

, will show one of the phases of it at a much later period.

The Texts of the

Tao Te Ching

and

Chuang-Tzŭ Shu

, as Regards Their Authenticity and Genuineness, and the Arrangement of Them.

I will now state briefly, first, the grounds on which I accept the

Tao Te Ching

as a genuine production of the age to which it has been assigned, and the truth of its authorship by Laozi to whom it has been ascribed. It would not have been necessary a few years ago to write as if these points could be called in question, but in 1886 Mr. Herbert A. Giles, of Her Majesty’s Consular Service in China, and one of the ablest Chinese scholars living, vehemently called them in question in an article in the

China Review

for the months of March and April. His strictures have been replied to, and I am not going to revive here the controversy which they produced, but only to state a portion of the evidence which satisfies my own mind on the two points just mentioned.

It has been said above that the year BC 604 was, probably, that of Laozi’s birth. The year of his death is not recorded. Ssŭ-ma Chʽien, the first great Chinese historian, who died in about BC 85, commences his “Biographies” with a short account of Laozi. He tells us that the philosopher had been a curator of the Royal Library of Chou, and that, mourning over the decadence of the dynasty, he wished to withdraw from the world, and proceeded to the pass or defile of Hangu,[7] leading from China to the west. There he was recognised by the warden of the pass, Yin Hsi (often called Kuan Yin), himself a well-known Taoist, who insisted on his leaving him a writing before he went into seclusion. Laozi then wrote his views on

The Tao and its Characteristics

, in two parts or sections, containing more than 5,000 characters, gave the manuscript to the warden, and went his way;[8] “nor is it known where he died.” This account is strange enough, and we need not wonder that it was by and by embellished with many marvels. It contains, however, the definite statements that Laozi wrote the

Tao Te Ching

in two parts, and consisting of more than 5,000 characters. And that Chʽien was himself well acquainted with the treatise is apparent from his quotations from it, with, in almost every case, the specification of the author. He thus adduces part of the first chapter, and a large portion of the last chapter but one. His brief reference also to Laozi and his writings are numerous.

But between Laozi and Ssŭ-ma Chʽien there were many Taoist writers whose works remain. I may specify of them Lieh-tzŭ (assuming that his chapters, though not composed in their present form by him, may yet be accepted as fair specimens of his teaching); Chuang-tzŭ (of the fourth century BC. We find him refusing to accept high office from king Wei of Chʽu, BC 339–299); Han Fei, a voluminous author, who died by his own hand in BC 230; and Liu An, a scion of the Imperial House of Han, king of Huai-nan, and better known to us as Huan-nan Tzŭ, who also died by his own hand in BC 122. In the books of all these men we find quotations of many passages that are in our treatise. They are expressly said to be, many of them, quotations from Laozi; Han Fei several times all but shows the book beneath his eyes. To show how numerous the quotations by Han Fei and Liu An are, let it be borne in mind that the

Tao Te Ching

has come down to us as divided into eighty-one short chapters; and that the whole of it is shorter than the shortest of our

Gospels

. Of the eighty-one chapters, either the whole or portions of seventy-one are found in those two writers. There are other authors not so decidedly Taoistic, in whom we find quotations from the little book. These quotations are in general wonderfully correct. Various readings indeed there are; but if we were sure that the writers did trust to memory, their differences would only prove that copies of the text had been multiplied from the very first.

In passing on from quotations to the complete text, I will clinch the assertion that Chʽien was well acquainted with our treatise, by a passage from the

History of the Former Han Dynasty

(BC 206–AD 24), which was begun to be compiled by Pan Ku, who died however in 92, and left a portion to be completed by his sister, the famous Pan Chao. The thirty-second chapter of his “Biographies” is devoted to Ssŭ-ma Chʽien, and towards the end it is said that “on the subject of the Great Tao he preferred Huang and Lao to the six ching.” “Huang and Lao” must there be the writings of Huang Ti and Laozi. The association of the two names also illustrates the antiquity claimed for Taoism, and the subject of endnote 4.

We go on from quotations to complete texts, and turn, first, to the catalogue of the Imperial Library of Han, as compiled by Liu Hsin, not later than the commencement of our Christian era. There are entered in it Taoist works by thirty-seven different authors, containing in all 993 chapters or sections (pʽien). Yi Yin, the premier of Chʽêng Tʽang (BC 1766), heads the list with fifty-one sections. There are in it four editions of Laozi’s work with commentaries:—by a Mr. Lin, in four sections; a Mr. Fu, in thirty-seven sections; a Mr. Hsü, in six sections; and by Liu Hsiang, Hsin’s own father, in four sections. All these four works have since perished, but there they were in the Imperial Library before our era began. Chuang-tzŭ is in the same list in fifty-two books or sections, the greater part of which have happily escaped the devouring tooth of time.

We turn now to the twentieth chapter of Chʽien’s “Biographies”, in which he gives an account of Yüeh Yi, the scion of a distinguished family, and who himself played a famous part, both as a politician and military leader, and became prince of Wang-chu under the kingdom of Chao in BC 279. Among his descendants was a Yüeh Chʽên, who learned in Chʽi “the words,” that is, the Taoistic writings “of Huang Ti and Laozi from an old man who lived on the ho-side.” The origin of this old man was not known, but Yüeh Chʽên taught what he learned from him to a Mr. Ko, who again became preceptor to Tsʽao Tsʽan, the chief minister of Chʽi, and afterwards of the new dynasty of Han, dying in BC 190.

Referring now to the catalogue of the Imperial Library of the dynasty of Sui (AD 502–556), we find that it containd many editions of Lao’s treatise with commentaries. The first mentioned is

The Tao Te Ching

, with the commentary of the old man of the ho-side, in the time of the emperor Wên of Han (BC 179–142). It is added in a note that the dynasty of Liang (AD 502–556) had possessed the edition of “the old man of the ho-side, of the time of the Warring States; but that with some other texts and commentaries it had disappeared.” I find it difficult to believe that there had been two old men of the ho-side,[9] both teachers of Taoism and commentators on our

Ching

, but I am willing to content myself with the more recent work, and accept the copy that has been current—say from BC 150, when Ssŭ-ma Chʽien could have been little more than a boy. Taoism was a favourite study with many of the Han emperors and their ladies. Huai-nan Tzŭ, of whose many quotations from the text of Lao I have spoken, was an uncle of the emperor Wên. To emperor Ching (BC 156–143), the son of Wên, there is attributed the designation of Lao’s treatise as a ching, a work of standard authority. At the beginning of his reign, we are told, some one was commending to him four works, among which were those of Laozi and Chuang-tzŭ. Deeming that the work of Huang-tzŭ and Laozi was of a deeper character than the others, he ordered that it should be called a ching, established a board for the study of Taoism, and issued an edict that the book should be learned and recited at court, and throughout the country.[10] Thenceforth it was so styled. We find Huang-fu Mi (AD 215–282) referring to it as the

Tao Te Ching

.

The second place in the Sui catalogue is given to the text and commentary of Wang Pi or Wang Fu-ssŭ, an extraordinary scholar who died in AD 249, at the early age of twenty-four. This work has always been much prized. It was its text which Lu Tê-ming used in his

Explanation of the Terms and Phrases of the Classics

, in the seventh century. Among the editions of it which I possess is that printed in 1794 with the imperial moveable metal types.

I need not speak of editions or commentaries subsequent to Wang Pi’s. They soon begin to be many, and are only not so numerous as those of the Confucian Classics.

All the editions of the book are divided into two parts, the former called “Tao”, and the latter “Tê”, meaning the Qualities or Characteristics of the Tao, but this distinction of subjects is by no means uniformly adhered to.

I referred already to the division of the whole into eighty-one short chapters (37 + 44), which is by common tradition attributed to Ho-shang Kung, or “The old man of the ho-side.” Another very early commentator, called Yen Tsun or Yen Chün-ping, made a division into seventy-two chapters (40 + 32), under the influence, no doubt, of some mystical considerations. His predecessor, perhaps, had no better reason for his eighty-one; but the names of his chapters were, for the most part, happily chosen, and have been preserved. Wu Chʽêng arranged the two parts in sixty-seven chapters (31 + 36). It is a mistake, however, to suppose, as even Mr. Wylie with all his general accuracy did,[11] that Wu “curtails the ordinary text to some extent.” He does not curtail, but only rearranges according to his fashion, uniting some of Ho-shang Kung’s chapters in one, and sometimes altering the order their clauses.

Ssŭ-ma Chʽien tells us that, as the treatise came from Laozi, it contained more than 5,000 characters; that is, as one critic says, “more than 5,000 and fewer than 6,000.” Ho-shang Kung’s text has 5,350, and one copy 5,590; Wang Pi’s, 5,683, and one copy 5,610. Two other early texts have been counted, giving 5,720 and 5,635 characters respectively. The brevity arises from the terse conciseness of the style, owing mainly to the absence of the embellishment of particles, which forms so striking a peculiarity in the composition of

Mencius

and

Chuang-tzŭ

.

In passing on to speak, secondly and more briefly, of the far more voluminous writings of Chuang-tzŭ, I may say that I do not know of any other book so ancient a date as the

Tao Te Ching

, of which the authenticity of the origin and genuineness of the text can claim to be so well substantiated.[12]

What Is the Meaning of the Name Tao? And the Chief Points of the Belief in Taoism.

The first translation of the

Tao Te Ching

into a western language was executed in Latin by some of the Roman Catholic missionaries, and a copy of it was brought to England by a Mr. Matthew Raper, F.R.S., and presented by him to the Society at a meeting on the 10th January, 1788—being the gift to him of P. Jos. de Grammont, Missionarius Apostolicus, ex-Jesuita. In this version Tao is taken in the sense of “ratio,” or the “supreme reason of the divine being, the creator and governor.”

M. Abel-Rémusat, the first professor of Chinese in Paris, does not seem to have been aware of the existence of the above version in London, but his attention was attracted to Lao’s treatise about 1820, and, in 1823, he wrote of the character Tao, “Ce mot me semble ne pas pouvoir être bien traduit, si ce n’est par le mot λόγος dans le triple sense de souverain Être, de raison, et de parole.”

Rémusat’s successor in the chair of Chinese, the late Stanislas Julien, published in 1842 a translation of the whole treatise. Having concluded from an examination of it, and the earliest Taoist writers, such as Chuang-tzŭ, Ho-kuan Tzŭ, and Ho-shang Kung, that the Tao was devoid of action, of thought, of judgement, and of intelligence, he concluded that it was impossible to understand by it “the primordial reason, or the sublime intelligence which created, and which governs the world.” and to this he subjoined the following note:—“Quelque étrange que puisse paraître cette idée de Laozi, elle n’est pas sans exemple dans l’histoire de la philosophie. Le mot nature n’a-t-il pas été employee par certains philosophes, que la religion et la raison condamnent, pour désigner une cause première, également dépourvue de pensée et d’intelligence?” Julien himself did not doubt that Lao’s idea of the character was that it primarily and properly meant “a way,” and hence he translated the title

Tao Te Ching

by

Le Livre de la Voie et de la Vertu

, transferring at the same time the name Tao to the text of his version.

The first English writer who endeavoured to give a distinct account of Taoism was the late Archdeacon Hardwick, while he held the office of Christian Advocate in the University of Cambridge. In his

Christ and other Masters

(vol. ii p. 67), when treating of the religions of China, he says, “I feel disposed to argue that the centre of the system founded by Laozi had been awarded to some energy or power resembling the ‘nature’ of modern speculators. The indefinite expression Tao was adopted to denominate an abstract cause, or the initial principle of life and order, to which worshippers were able to assign the attributes of immateriality, eternity, immensity, invisibility.”

It was, probably, Julien’s reference in his note to the use of the term nature, which suggested to Hardwick his analogy between Laozi’s Tao, and “the nature of modern speculation.” Canon Farrar has said, “We have long personified under the name of nature the sum total of God’s laws as observed in the physical world; and now the notion of nature as a distinct, living, independent entity seems to be ineradicable alike from our literature and our systems of philosophy.”[13] But it seems to me that this metaphorical or mythological use of the word nature for the cause and ruler of it, implies the previous notion of Him, that is, of God, in the mind. Does not this clearly appear in the words of Seneca?—“Vis illum (h.e. Jovem Deum) naturam vocare, non peccabis:—hic est ex quo nata sunt omnia, cujus spiritu vivimus.”[14]

In his translation of the

Works of Chuang-tzŭ

in 1881, Mr. Balfour adopted Nature as the ordinary rendering of the Chinese Tao. He says, “When the word is translated Way of Nature—her processes, her methods, and her laws; when translated Reason, it is the same as li—the power that works in all created things, producing, preserving, and life-giving—the intelligent principle of the world; when translated Doctrine, it refers to the true doctrine respecting the laws the mysteries of Nature.” He calls attention also to the point that “he uses nature in the sense of Natura naturans, while the Chinese expression wan wu (= all things) denotes Natura naturata.” But this really comes to the metaphorical use of nature which has been touched upon above. It can claim as its patrons great names like those of Aquinas, Giordano Bruno, and Spinoza, but I have never been able to see that its barbarous phraseology makes it more than a figure of speech.[15]

The term Nature, however, is so handy, and often fits so appropriately into a version, that if Tao had ever such a signification I should not hesitate to employ it as freely as Mr. Balfour has done; but as it has not that signification, to try to put a non-natural meaning into it, only perplexes the mind, and obscures the idea of Laozi.

Mr. Balfour himself says, “The primary signification of Tao is simply ‘road.’ ” Beyond question this meaning underlies the use of it by the great master of Taoism and by Chuang-tzŭ.[16] Let the reader refer to the version of the twenty-fifth chapter of Lao’s treatise, and to the notes subjoined to it. There Tao appears as the spontaneously operating cause of all movement in the phenomena of the universe; and the nearest the writer can come to a name for it is “the Great Tao.” Having established this name, he subsequently uses it repeatedly; see chh. xxxiv and liii. In the third paragraph of his twentieth chapter, Chuang-tzŭ uses a synonymous phrase instead of Lao’s “Great Tao,” calling it the “Great Tʽu,” about which there can be no dispute, as meaning “the Great Path,” “Way,” or “Course.”[17] In the last paragraph his twenty-fifth book, Chuang-tzŭ again sets forth the metaphorical origin of the name Tao. “Tao,” he says, “cannot be regarded as having a positive existence; existences cannot be regarded as nonexistent. The name Tao is a metaphor used for the purpose of description. To say that it exercises some causation, or that it does nothing, is speaking of it from the phase of a thing;—how can such language serve as a designation of it in its greatness? If words were sufficient for the purpose, we might in a day’s time exhaust the subject of the Tao. Words not being sufficient, we may talk about it the whole day, and the subject of discourse will only have been a thing. Tao is the extreme to which things conduct us. Neither speech nor silence is sufficient to convey the notion of it. When we neither speak nor refrain from speech, our speculations about it reach their highest point.”

The Tao therefore is a phenomenon; not a positive being, but a mode of being. Lao’s idea of it may become plainer as we proceed to other points of his system. In the meaning time, the best way of dealing with it in translating is to transfer it to the version, instead of trying to introduce an English equivalent of it.

Next in importance to Tao is the name Tʽien, meaning at first the vaulted sky or the open firmament of heaven. In the Confucian Classics, and in the speech of the Chinese people, this name is used metaphorically as it is by ourselves for the Supreme Being, with reference especially to His will and rule. So it was that the idea of God arose among the Chinese fathers; so it was that they proceeded to fashion a name for God, calling Him Ti, and Shang Ti, “the Ruler,” and “the Supreme Ruler.” The Taoist fathers found this among their people; but in their idea of the Tao they had already a supreme concept which superseded the necessity of any other. The name Ti for God only occurs once in the

Tao Te Ching

; in the well-known passage of the fourth chapter, where, speaking of the Tao, Laozi says, “I do not know whose son it is; it might seem to be before God.”

Nor is the name Tʽien very common. We have the phrase, “heaven and earth,” used for the two great constituents of the cosmos, owing their origin to the Tao, and also for a sort of binomial power, acting in harmony with the Tao, covering, protecting, nurturing, and maturing all things. Never once is Tʽien used in the sense of God, the Supreme Being. In its peculiarly Taoistic employment, it is more an adjective than a noun. “The Tao of heaven” means the Tao that is heavenly, the course that is quiet and undemonstrative, that is free from motive and effort, such as is seen in the processes of nature, grandly proceeding and successful without any striving or crying. The Tao of man, not dominated by this Tao, is contrary to it, and shows will, purpose, and effort, till, submitting to it, it becomes “the Tao or Way of the sages,” which in all its action has no striving.

The characteristics both of heaven and man are dealt with more fully by Chuang than by Lao. In the conclusion of his eleventh book, for instance, he says:—“What do we mean by Tao? There is the Tao (or Way) of heaven, and there is the Tao of man. Acting without action, and yet attracting all honour, is the Way of heaven. Doing and being embarrassed thereby is the Way of man. The Way of heaven should play the part of lord; the Way of man, the part of minister. The two are far apart, and should be distinguished from each other.”

In his next book, (par. 2), Chuang-tzŭ tells us what he intends by “Heaven:”—“Acting without action—this is what is called heaven.” Heaven thus taken its law from the Tao. “The oldest sages and sovereigns attained to do the same,”—it was for all men to aim at the same achievement. As they were successful, “vacancy, stillness, placidity, tastelessness, quietude, silence, and non-action” would be found to be their characteristics, and they would go on to the perfection of the Tao.[18]

The employment of Tʽien by the Confucianists, as of heaven by ourselves, must be distinguished therefore from the Taoistic use of the name to denote the quiet but mighty influence of the impersonal Tao; and to translate it by “God” only obscures the meaning of the Taoist writers. The has been done by Mr. Giles in his version of

Chuang-tzŭ

, which is otherwise for the most part so good. Everywhere on his pages there appears the great name “God;”—a blot on his translation more painful to my eyes and ears than the use of “Nature” for Tao by Mr. Balfour. I know that Mr. Giles’s plan in translating is to use strictly English equivalents for all kinds of Chinese terms.[19] The plan is good where there are in the two languages such strict equivalents; but in the case before us there is no ground for its application. The exact English equivalent for the Chinese tʽien is our heaven. The Confucianists often used tʽien metaphorically for the personal being whom they denominated Ti (God) and Shang Ti (the Supreme God), and a translator may occasionally, in working on books of Confucian literature, employ our name God for it. But neither Lao nor Chuang ever attached anything like our idea of God to it; and when one, in working on books of early Taoist literature, translates tʽien by God, such a rendering must fail to produce in an English reader a correct apprehension of the meaning.

There is also in

Chuang-tzŭ

a peculiar usage of the name Tʽien. He applies it to the being whom he introduces as masters of the Tao, generally with mystical appellations in order to set forth his own views. Two instances from book XI will suffice in illustration of this. In par. 4, Huang-ti does reverence to his instructor Kuang Chʽêng-tzŭ,[20] saying, “In Kuang Chʽêng-tzŭ we have an example of what is called heaven,” which Mr. Giles renders “Kuang Chʽêng-tzŭ is surely God.” In par. 5, again, the mystical Yün-chiang is made to say to the equally fabulous and mystical Hung-mêng, “O heaven, have you forgotten me?” and, farther on, “O heaven, you have conferred on me (the knowledge of) your operation, and revealed to me the mystery of it;” in both passages Mr. Giles renders tʽien by “your holiness.”

But Mr. Giles seems to agree with me that the old Taoist had no idea of a personal God, when they wrote of Tʽien or Heaven. On his sixty-eighth page, near the beginning of book VI, we meet with the following sentence, having every appearance of being translated from the Chinese text:—“God is a principle which exists by virtue of its own intrinsicality, and operates without self-manifestation.” By an inadvertence he has introduced his own definition of “God” as if it were Chuang-tzŭ’s; and though I can find no characters in the text of which I can suppose that he intends it to be the translation, it is valuable as helping us to understand the meaning to be attached to the great name in his volume.

I have referred above (par. 11) to the only passage in Lao’s treatise, where he uses the name Ti or God in its highest sense, saying that “the Tao might seem to have been before him.” He might well say so, for his first chapter he describes the Tao, “(conceived of as) having no name, as the originator of heaven and earth, and (conceived of as) having a name, as the mother of all things.” The reader will also find the same predicates of the Tao at greater length in his fifty-first chapter.

The character Ti is also of rare occurrence in

Chuang-tzŭ

, excepting as applied to the five ancient Tis. In bk. III par. 4, and in one other place we find it indicating the Supreme Being, but the usage is ascribed to the ancients. In bk. XV par. 3, in a description of the human spirit, its name is said to be “Tʽung Ti”, which Mr. Giles renders “Of God;” Mr. Balfour, “One with God;” while my own version is “The divinity in man.” In bk. XII par. 6, we have the expression “the place of God;” in Mr. Giles, “the kingdom of God;” in Mr. Balfour, “the home of God.” In this and the former instance, the character seems to be used with the ancient meaning which had entered into folklore of the people. But in bk. VI par. 7, there is passage which shows clearly the relative position of Tao and Ti in the Taoistic system; and having called attention to it, I will go on to other points. Let the reader mark well the following predicates of the Tao:—“Before there were heaven and earth, form of old, there it was, securely existing. From it came the mysterious existence of spirits; from it the mysterious existence of Ti (God). It produced heaven, it produced earth.”[21] This says more than the utterance of Lao—that “the Tao seemed to be before God;”—does it not say that Tao was before God, and that He was what He is by virtue of its operation?

Among the various personal names given to the Tao are those of Tsao Hua, “maker and transformer,” and Tsao Wu Chê, “maker of things.” Instances of both these names are found in bk. VI parr. 9, 10. “Creator” and “God” have both been employed for them; but there is no idea of creation in Taoism.

Again and again Chuang-tzŭ entertains the question of how it was at the first beginning of things. Different views are stated. In bk. II par. 4, he says:—“Among the men of old their knowledge reached the extreme point. What was that extreme point?

“Some held that at first there was not anything. This is the extreme point—the utmost limit to which nothing can be added.

“A second class held that there was something, but without any responsive recognition of it (on the part of man).

“A third class held that there was such recognition, but there had not begun to be any expression of different opinions about it. It was through the definite expression of different opinions about it that there ensued injury to the (doctrine of the) Tao.”[22]

The first of these three views was that which Chuang-tzŭ himself preferred. The most condensed expression of it is given in bk. XII par. 8:—“In the grand beginning of all things there was nothing in all the vacancy of space; there was nothing that could be name.[23] It was in this state that there arose the first existence; the first existence, but still without bodily shape. From this things could be produced, (receiving) what we call their several characters. That which had no bodily shape was divided, and then without intermission there was what we call the process of conferring. (The two processes) continued to operate, and things were produced. As they were completed, there appeared the distinguishing lines of each, which we call the bodily shape. That shape was the body preserving in it the spirit, and each had its peculiar manifestation which we call it nature.”

Such was the genesis of things; the formation of heaven and earth and all that in them is, under the guidance of the Tao. It was an evolution and not a creation. How the Tao itself came—I do not say into existence, but into operation—neither Lao nor Chuang ever thought of saying anything about. We have seen that it is nothing material.[24] It acted spontaneously of itself. Its sudden appearance in the field of nonexistence, producer, transformer, beautifier, surpasses my comprehension. To Lao it seemed to be before God. I am compelled to accept the existence of God, as the ultimate Fact, bowing before it with reverence, and not attempting to explain it, the one mystery, the sole mystery of the universe.

“The bodily shape was the body preserving in it the spirit, and each had its peculiar manifestation which we call its nature.” So it is said in the passage quoted above Chuang-tzŭ’s twelfth book, and the language shows how Taoism, in a loose and indefinite way, considered man to be composed of body and spirit, associated together, yet not necessarily dependent on each other. Little is found bearing on his tenet in the

Tao Te Ching

. The concluding sentence of ch. 33, “He who dies and yet does not perish, has longevity,” is of doubtful acceptation. More pertinent is the description of life as “a coming forth,” and of death as “an entering;”[25] but Chuang-tzŭ expounds more fully, though after all unsatisfactorily, the teaching of their system on the subject.

At the conclusion of his third book, writing of the death of Laozi, he says, “When the master came, it was at the proper time; when he went away, it was the simple sequence (of his coming). Quiet acquiescence in what happens at its proper time, and quietly submitting (to its sequence), afford no occasion for grief or for joy. The ancients described (death) as the loosening of the cord on which God suspended (the life). What we can point to are the faggots that have been consumed; but the fire is transmitted elsewhere, and we know not that it is over and ended.”

It is, however, in connection with the death of his own wife, as related in the eighteenth book, that his views most fully—I do not say “clearly”—appear. We are told that when that event took place, his friend Hui-tzŭ went to condole with him, and found him squatted on the ground, drumming on the vessel (of ice), and singing. His friend said to him, “When a wife has lived with her husband, brought up children, and then dies in her old age, not to wail for her is enough. When you go on to drum on the vessel and sing, is it not an excessive (and strange) demonstration?” Chuang-tzŭ replied, “It is not so. When she first died, was it possible for me to be singular, and not affected by the event? But I reflected on the commencement of her being, when she had not yet been born to life. Not only had she no life, but she had no bodily form. Not only had she no bodily form, but she had no breath. Suddenly in this chaotic condition there ensued a change, and there was breath; another change, and there was the bodily form; a further change, and she was born to life; a change no again, and she is dead. The relation between those changes is like the procession of the four seasons—spring, autumn, winter, and summer. There she lies with her face up, sleeping in the Great Chamber;[26] and if I were to fall sobbing and going on to wail for her, I should think I did not understand what was appointed for all. I therefore restrained myself.”

The next paragraph of the same book contains another story about two ancient men, both deformed, who, when looking at the graves on Kunlun, begin to feel in their own frames the symptoms of approaching dissolution. One says to the other, “Do you dread it?” and gets the reply, “No. Why should I dread it? Life is a borrowed thing. The living frame thus borrowed is but so much dust. Life and death are like day and night.”

In every birth, it would thus appear, there is, somehow, a repetition of what it is said, as we have seen, took place at “the grand beginning of all things,” when out of the primal nothingness, the Tao somehow appeared, and there was developed through its operation the world of things—material things and the material body of man, which enshrines or enshrouds an immaterial spirit. This returns to the Tao that gave it, and may be regarded indeed as that Tao operating in the body during the time of life, and in due time receives a new embodiment.

In these notions of Taoism there was preparation for the appreciation by its followers of the Buddhistic system when it came to be introduced into the country, and which forms a close connection between the two at the present day, Taoism itself constantly becoming less definite and influential on the minds of the Chinese people. The book which tells us of the death of Chuang-tzŭ’s wife concludes with a narrative about Lieh-tzŭ and an old bleached skull,[27] and to this is appended a passage about the metamorphoses of things, ending with the statement that “the panther produces the horse, and the horse the man, who then again enters into the great machinery (of evolution), from which all things come forth (at birth) and into which they re-enter (at death).” Such representations need not be characterised.

Chu Hsi, “the prince of literature,” described the main object of Taoism to be “the preservation of the breath of life;” and Liu Mi, probably of our thirteenth century,[28] in his

Dispassionate Comparison of the Three Religions

, declared that “its chief achievement is the prolongation of longevity.” Such is the account of Taoism originality given by Confucian and Buddhist writers, but our authorities, Lao and Chuang, hardly bear out this representation of it as true of their time. There are chapters of the

Tao Te Ching

which presuppose a peculiar management of the breath, but the treatise is singularly free from anything to justify what Mr. Balfour well calls “the antics of kung-fu, or system of mystic and recondite calisthenics.” Lao insists, however, on the Tao as conducive to long life, and in Chuang-tzŭ we have references to it as discipline of longevity, though even he mentions rather with disapproval “those who kept blowing and breathing with open mouth, inhaling and exhaling the breath, expelling the old and taking in new; passing their time like the (dormant) bear, and stretching and twisting (their necks) like birds” He says that “all this simply shows their desire for longevity, and is what the scholars who manage the breath, and men who nourish the body and wish to live as long as Pʽêng-tsu, are fond of doing.”[29] My own opinion is that the methods of the Tao were first cultivated for the sake of the longevity which they were thought to promote, and that Lao, discountenancing such a use of them, endeavoured to give the doctrine a higher character; and this view is favoured by passages in

Chuang-tzŭ

. In the seventh paragraph, for instance, of his book VI, speaking of parties who had obtained the Tao, he begins with a prehistoric sovereign, who “got and by it adjusted heaven and earth.” Among his other instances in Pʽêng Tsu, who got it in the time of Shun, and lived on to the time of the five leading princes of Chou—a longevity of more than 1,800 years, greater than that ascribed to Methuselah! In the paragraph that follows there appear a Nü Yü, who is addressed by another famous Taoist in the words, “You are old, sir, while your complexion is like that of a child;—how is it so?” and the reply is, “I became acquainted with the Tao.”

I will adduce only one more passage of

Chuang

. In his eleventh book, and the fourth paragraph, he tells us of interviews between Huang-ti, in the nineteenth year of his reign, which would be BC 2679, and his instructor Kuang Chʽêng-tzŭ. The Taoist sage is not redily prevailed on to unfold the treasures of his knowledge to the sovereign, but at last his reluctance is overcome, and he says to him, “Come, and I will tell you about the perfect Tao. Its essence is surrounded with the deepest obscurity; its highest reach is in darkness and silence. There is nothing to be seen, nothing to be heard. When it holds the spirit in its arms in stillness, then the bodily form will of itself become correct. You must be still, you must be pure; not subjecting your body to toil, not agitating your vital force:—then you may live for long. When your eyes see nothing, your ears hear nothing, and your mind knows nothing, your spirit will keep your body, and the body will live long. Watch over what is within you; shut up the avenues that connect you with what is external;—much knowledge is pernicious. I will proceed with you to the summit of the Grand Brilliance, where we come to the bright and expanding (element); I will enter with you the grate of the dark and depressing element. There heaven and earth have their controllers, there the yin and yang have their repositories. Watch over and keep your body, and all things will of themselves give it vigour. I main the (original) unity (of these elements). In this way I have cultivated myself for 1,200 years, and my bodily form knows no decay.” Add 1,200 to 2,679, and we obtain 3879 as the year BC of Kuang Chʽêng-tzŭ’s birth!

Laozi describes some other and kindred results of cultivating the Tao in terms which are sufficiently startling, and which it is difficult to accept. In his fiftieth chapter he says, “He who is skilful in managing his life travels on land without having to shun rhinoceros or tiger, and enter a host without having avoid buff coat or sharp weapon. The rhinoceros finds no place in him into which to thrust its horn, nor the tiger a place in which to fix its claws, nor the weapon a place to admit its point. And for what reason? Because there is in him no place of death.” To the same effect he says in his fifty-fifth chapter, “He who has in himself abundantly the attributes (of the Tao) is like an infant. Poisonous insects will not sting him; fierce beasts will not seize him; birds of prey will not strike him.”

Such assertions startle us by their contrariety to our observation and experience, but so does most of the teaching of Taoism. What can seem more absurd than the declaration that “the Tao does nothing, and so there is nothing that it does not do?” And yet this is one of the fundamental axioms of the system. The thirty-seventh chapter, which enunciates it, goes on to say, “If princes and kings were able to maintain (the Tao), all things would of themselves be transformed by them.” This principle, if we can call it so, is generalised in the fortieth, one of the shortest chapters, and partly in rhyme:—

“The movement of the Tao
By contraries proceeds;
And weakness marks the course
Of Tao’s mighty deeds

All things under heaven sprang from it as existing (and named); that existence sprang from it as nonexistent (and not named).”

Ho-shang Kung, or whoever gave their names to the chapters of the

Tao Te Ching

, styles this fortieth chapter “Dispensing with the use (of means).” If the wish to use means arise in the mind, the nature of the Tao as “the nameless simplicity” has been vitiated; and this nature is celebrated in lines like those just quoted:—

“Simplicity without a name
Is free from all external aim.
With no desire, at rest and still,
All things go right, as of their will.”

I do not cull any passages from

Chuang-tzŭ

to illustrate these points. In his eleventh book his subject is government by “Let-a-be and the exercise of forbearance.”

This Tao ruled men at first, and then the world was in a paradisiacal state. Neither of our authorities tells us how long this condition lasted, but as Lao observes in his eighteenth chapter, “the Tao ceased to be observed.” Chuang-tzŭ, however, gives us more than one description of what he considered the paradisiacal state was. He calls it “the age of perfect virtue.” In the thirteenth paragraph of his twelfth book he says, “In this age, they attached no value to wisdom, nor employed men of ability. Superiors were (but) as the higher branches of a tree; and the people were like the deer of the wild. They were upright and correct, without knowing that to be so was righteousness; they loved one another, without knowing that to do so was benevolence; they were honest and leal-hearted, without knowing that it was loyalty; they fulfilled their engagements, without knowing that to do so was good faith; in their movements they employed the services of one another, without thinking that they were conferring or receiving any gift. Therefore their actions left no trace, and there was no record of their affairs.”

Again, in the fourth paragraph of his tenth book, addressing an imaginary interlocutor, he says, “Are you, Sir, unacquainted with the age of perfect virtue?” He then gives the names of twelve sovereigns who ruled in it, of the greater number of whom we have no other means of knowing anything, and goes on:—“In their times the people used knotted cords in carrying on their business. They thought their (simple) food pleasant, and their (plain) clothing beautiful. They were happy in their (simple) manners, and felt at rest in their (poor) dwellings. (The people of) neighbouring states might be able to descry one another; the voices of their cocks and dogs might be heard from one to the other; they might not die till they were old; and yet all their life they would have no communication together. In those times perfect good order prevailed.”

One other description of the primeval state is still more interesting. It is in the second paragraph of bk. IX:—“The people had their regular and constant nature:—they wove and made themselves clothes; they tilled the ground and got food. This was their common faculty. They were all one in this, and did not for themselves into separate classes; so were they constituted and left to their natural tendencies. Therefore in the age of perfect virtue men walked along with slow and grave step, and with their looks steadily directed forwards. On the hills there were no footpaths nor exacted passages; on the lakes there were no boats nor dams. All creatures lived in companies, and their places of settlement were made near to one another. Birds and beasts multiplied to flocks and herds; the grass and trees grew luxuriant and long. The birds and beasts might be led about without feeling the constraint; the nest of the magpie might be climbed to, and peeped into. Yes, in the age of perfect virtue, men lived in common with birds and beasts, and were on terms of equality with all creatures, as forming one family;—how could they know among themselves the distinctions of superior men and small men? Equally without knowledge, they did not leave the path of their natural virtue; equally free from desires, they were in the state of pure simplicity. In their pure simplicity, their nature was what it ought to be.”

Such were the earliest Chinese of whom Chuang-tzŭ could venture to give any account. If ever their ancestors had been in a ruder or savage condition, it must have been at a much antecedent time. These had long passed out of such a state; they were tillers of the ground, and acquainted with the use of the loom. They lived in happy relations with one another, and in kindly harmony with the tribes of inferior creatures. But there is not the slightest allusion to any sentiment of piety as animating them individually, or to any ceremony of religion as observed by them in common. This surely is a remarkable feature in their condition. I call attention to it, but I do not dwell upon it.

But by the time of Lao and Chuang the cultivation of the Tao had fallen into disuse. The simplicity of life which it demanded, with its freedom from all disturbing speculation and action, was no longer to be found in individual or in government. It was the general decay of manners and of social order which unsettled the mind Lao, made him resign his position as curator of the Royal Library, and determine to withdraw from China and hide himself among the rude peoples beyond it. The cause of the deterioration of the Tao and of all the evils of the nation was attributed to the ever-growing pursuit of knowledge, and of what we call the arts of culture. It had commenced very long before;—in the time of Huang-ti, Chuang says in one place;[30] and in another he carries it still higher to Sui-jên and Fu-hsi.[31] There had been indeed, all along the line of history, a grouping for the rules of life, as indicated by the constitution of man’s nature. The results were embodied in the ancient literature which was the lifelong study of Confucius. He had gathered up that literature; he recognised the nature of man as the gift of heaven or God. The monitions of God as given in the convictions of man’s mind supplied him with a Tao or path of duty very different from the Tao or mysterious way of Lao. All this was gall and wormwood to the dreaming librarian or brooding recluse, and made him say, “If we could renounce our sageness and discard our wisdom, it would be better for the people a hundredfold. If we could renounce our benevolence and discard our righteousness, the people would again become filial and kindly. If we could renounce our artful contrivances and discard our (scheming for) gain, there would be no thieves nor robbers.”[32]

We can laugh at this. Taoism was wrong in its opposition to the increase of knowledge. Man exists under a law of progress. In pursuing it there are demanded discretion and justice. Moral ends must rule over material ends, and advance in virtue be ranked higher than advance in science. So have good and evil, truth and error, to fight out the battle on the field of the world, and in all the range of time; but there is no standing still for the individual or for society. Even Confucius taught his countrymen to set too high a value on the examples of antiquity. The school of Laozi fixing themselves in an unknown region beyond antiquity—a prehistoric time between “the grand beginning of all things” out of nothing, and the unknown commencement of societies of men—has made no advance but rather retrograded, and is represented by the still more degenerated Taoism of the present day.

There is a short parabolic story of Chuang-tzŭ, intended to represent the antagonism between Taoism and knowledge, which has always struck me as curious. The last paragraph of his seventh book is this:—“The ruler (or god Ti) of the southern ocean was Shu (that is, Heedless); the ruler of the northern ocean was Hu (that is, Hasty); and the ruler of the centre was Hun-tun (that is, Chaos). Shu and Hu were continually meeting in the land of Hun-tun, who treated them very well. They consulted together how they might repay his kindness, and said, ‘Men have all seven orifices for the purposes of seeing, hearing, eating, and breathing while this (poor) ruler along has not one. Let us try and make them for him.’ Accordingly they dug one orifice in him every day; and at the end of seven days Chaos died.”

So it was that Chaos passed away before light. So did the nameless simplicity of the Tao disappear before knowledge. But it was better that the Chaos should give place to the cosmos. “Heedless” and “Hasty” did a good deed.

I have thus set forth eight characteristics of the Taoistic system, having respect mostly to what is peculiar and mystical in it. I will not conclude my exhibition of it by bringing together under one head the practical lessons of its author for men individually, and for the administration of government. The praise of whatever excellence these possess belongs to Lao himself: Chuang-tzŭ devotes himself mainly to the illustration of the abstruse and difficult points.

First, it does not surprise us that in his rules for individual man, Lao should place humility in the foremost place. A favourite illustration with him of the Tao is water. In his eighth chapter he says:—“The highest excellence is like that of water. The excellence of water appears in its benefiting all things, and in its occupying, without striving to the contrary, the low ground which all men dislike. Hence (its way) is near to that of the Tao.” To the same effect in the seventy-eighth chapter:—“There is nothing in the world more soft and weak than water, and yet for attacking things that are firm and strong there is nothing that can take precedence of it. Every one in the world knows that the soft overcomes the hard, and the weak the strong; but no one is able to carry it out in practice.”

In his sixty-seventh chapter Lao associates with humility two other virtues, and calls them his three Precious Things, or Jewels. They are gentleness, economy, and shrinking from taking precedence of others. “With that gentleness,” he says, “I can be bold; with that economy I can be liberal; shrinking from taking precedence of others, I can become a vessel of the highest honour.”

And in his sixty-third chapter, he rise to a still loftier height of morality. He says, “(It is the way of the Tao) to act without (thinking of) acting, to conduct affairs without (feeling) the trouble of them; to taste without discerning any flavour, to consider the small as great, and the few as many, and to recompense injury with kindness.”

Here is the grand Christian precept, “Render to no man evil for evil. If thine enemy hunger, feed him; if he thirst, give him drink. Be not overcome with evil, but overcome evil with good.” We know that the maxim made some noise in its author’s lifetime; that the disciples of Confucius consulted him about it, and that he was unable to received it.[33] It comes in with less important matters by virtue of the Taoistic “rule of contraries.” I have been surprised to find what little reference to it I have met with in the course of my Chinese reading. I do not think that Chuang-tzŭ takes notice of it to illustrate it after his fashion. There, however, it is in the

Tao Te Ching

. The fruit of it has yet to be developed

Second, Lao laid down the same rule for the policy of the state as for the life of the individual. He says in his sixty-first chapter, “What makes a state great is its being like a low-lying, down-flowing stream;—it becomes the centre to which tend all (the small states) under heaven.” He then uses an illustration which will produce a smile:—“Take the case of all females. The female always overcomes the male by her stillness. Stillness may be considered (a sort of) abasement.” Resuming his subject, he adds, “Thus it is that a great state, by condescending to small states, gains them for itself; and that small states, by abasing themselves to a great state, win it over to them. In the one case the abasement tends to gaining adherents; in the other case, to procuring favour. The great state only wishes to unite men together and nourish them; a small state only wishes to be received by, and to serves, the other. Each gets what it desires, but the great state must learn to abase itself.”

“All very well in theory,” someone will exclaim, “but, the world has not seen it yet reduced to practice.” So it is. The fact is deplorable. No one saw the misery arising from it, and exposed its unreasonableness more unsparingly, than Chuang-tzŭ. But it was all in vain in his time, as it has been in all the centuries that have since rolled their course. Philosophy, philanthropy, and religion have still to toil on, “faint, yet pursuing,” believing that in the time will yet come when humility and love shall secure the reign of peace and good will among the nations of men.

While enjoining humility, Lao protested against war. In his thirty-first chapter he says, “Arms, however beautiful, are instruments of evil omen; hateful, it may be said, to all creatures. They who have the Tao do not like to employ them.” Perhaps in his sixty-ninth chapter he allows defensive war, but he adds, “There is no calamity greater than that of lightly engaging in war. To do that is near losing the gentleness which is so precious. Thus it is that when weapons are (actually) crossed, he who deplores the (situation) conquers.”

There are some other points in the practical lessons of Taoism to which I should like to call the attention of the reader, but I must refer him for them to the chapters of the

Tao Te Ching

, and the books of Chuang-tzŭ. Its salient features have been set forth somewhat fully. Notwithstanding the scorn poured so freely on Confucius by Chuang-tzŭ and other Taoist writers, he proved in the course of time too strong for Lao as the teacher of their people. The entrance of Buddhism, moreover, into the country in our first century, was very injurious to Taoism, which still exists, but is only the shadow of its former self. It is tolerated by the government, but not patronised as it was when emperors and empresses seemed to think more of it than of Confucianism. It is by the spread of knowledge, which it had always opposed, that its overthrow and disappearance will be brought about ere long.

Accounts of Laozi and Chuang-Tzŭ Given by Ssŭ-Ma Chʽien.

It seems desirable, before passing from Lao and Chuang in this “Introduction,” to give a place in it to what is said about them by Ssŭ-ma Chʽien. I have said that not a single proper name occurs in the

Tao Te Ching

. There is hardly an historical allusion in it. Only one chapter, the twentieth, has somewhat of an autobiographical character. It tells us, however, of no incidents of his life. He appears alone in the world through his cultivation of the Tao, melancholy and misunderstood, yet binding that Tao more closely to his bosom.

The books of Chunag-tzŭ are of a different nature, abounding in pictures of Taoist life, in anecdotes and narratives, graphic, argumentative, often satirical. But they are not historical. Confucius and many of his disciples, Lao and members of his school, heroes and sages of antiquity, and men of his own day, move across his pages; but the incidents in connection with which they are introduced are probably fictitious, and devised by him “to point his moral or adorn his tale.” His names of individuals and places are often like those of Bunyan in his

Pilgrim’s Progress

or his

Holy War

, emblematic of their characters and the doctrines which he employs them to illustrate. He often comes on the stage himself, and there is an air of verisimilitude in his descriptions, possibly also a certain amount of fact about them; but we cannot appeal to them as historical testimony. It is only to Ssŭ-ma Chʽien that we can go for this; he always writes in the spirit of a historian; but what he has to tell us of the two men is not much.

And first, as to his account of Laozi. When he wrote, about the beginning of the first century BC, the Taoist master was already known as Laozi. Chʽien, however, tells us that his surname was Li, and his name Êrh, meaning “Ear,” which gave place after his death to Tan, meaning “Long-eared,” form which we may conclude that he was named from some peculiarity in the form of his ears. He was a native of the state of Chʽu, which had then extended far beyond its original limits, and his birthplace was in the present province of Henan or of Anhui. He was a curator in the Royal Library; and when Confucius visited the capital in the year BC 517, the two men met. Chʽien says that Confucius’s visit to Luoyang was that he might question Lao on the subject of ceremonies. He might have other objects in mind as well; but however that was, the two met. Li said to Kʽung, “The men about whom you talk are dead, and their bones are mouldered to dust; only their words are left. Moreover, when the superior man gets his opportunity, he mounts aloft; but when the time is against him, he is carried along by the force of circumstances.[34] I have heard that a good merchant, though he have rich treasures safely stored, appears as if he were poor; and that the superior man, though his virtue be complete, is yet to outward seeming stupid. Put away your proud air and many desires, your insinuating habit and wild will. They are of no advantage to you;—this is all I have to tell you.” Confucius is made to say to his disciples after the interview: “I know how birds can fly, fishes can swim, and animals run. But the runner may be snared, the swimmer hooked, and the flyer shot by the arrow. But there is the dragon:—I cannot tell how he mounts on the wind through the clouds, and rises to heaven. Today I have seen Laozi, and can only compare him to the dragon.”

In this speech of Confucius we have, I believe, the origin of the name Laozi, as applied to the master of Taoism. Its meaning is “The Old Philosopher,” or “The Old Gentleman.”[35] Confucius might well so style Li Êrh. At the time of this interview he was himself in his thirty-fifth year, and the other was in his eighty-eighth. Chʽien adds, “Laozi cultivated the Tao and its attributes, the chief aim of his studies being how to keep himself concealed and remain unknown. He continued to reside at (the capital of) Chou, but after a long time, seeing the decay of the dynasty, he left it and went away to the barrier-gate, leading out of the kingdom on the northwest. Yin Hsi, the warden of the gate, said to him, ‘You are about to withdraw yourself out of sight. Let me insist on your (first) composing for me a book.’ On this, Laozi wrote a book in two parts, setting forth his views on the Tao and its attributes, in more than 5000 characters. He then went away, and it is not known where he died. He was a superior man, who liked to keep himself unknown.”

Chʽien finally traces Lao’s descendants down to the first century BC, and concludes by saying, “Those who attach themselves to the doctrine of Laozi condemn that of the literati, and the literati on their part condemn Laozi, verifying the saying, ‘Parties whose principles are different cannot take counsel together.’ Li Êrh taught that by doing nothing others are as a matter of course transformed, and that rectification in the same way ensues from being pure and still.”

This morsel is all that we have of historical narrative about Laozi. The account of writing of the

Tao Te Ching

at the request of the warden of the barrier-gate has a doubtful and legendary appearance. Otherwise, the record is free from anything to raise suspicion about it. It says nothing about previous existences of Lao, and nothing of his travelling to the west, and learning there the doctrines which are embodied in his work. He goes through the pass out of the domain of Chou, and died no one knowing where.

It is difficult, however, to reconcile this last statement with a narrative in the end of Chuang-tzŭ’s third book. There we see Laozi dead, and a crowd of mourners wailing round the corpse, and giving extraordinary demonstration of grief, which offend a disciple of a higher order, who has gone to the house to offer his condolences on the occasion. But for the peculiar nature of most of Chuang-tzŭ’s narratives, we should say, in opposition to Chʽien, that the place and time of Lao’s death were well known. Possibly, however, Chuang-tzŭ may have invented the whole story, to give him the opportunity of setting forth what, according to his ideal of it, the life of a Taoist master should be, and how even Laozi himself fall short of it.

Second, Chʽien’s account of Chuang-tzŭ is still more brief. He was a native, he tells us, of the territory of Mêng, which belonged to the kingdom of Liang or Wei, and held an office, he does not say what, in the city of Chʽi-yüan. Chuang was thus of the same part of China as Laozi, and probably grew up familiar with all his speculations and lessons. He lived during the reigns of kings Hui of Liang, Hsüan of Chʽi, and Wei of Chʽu. We cannot be wrong therefore in assigning his period to the latter half of the third, and earlier part of the fourth century BC. He was thus a contemporary of Mencius. They visited at the same courts, and yet neither ever mentions the other. They were the two ablest debaters of their day, and fond of exposing what they deemed heresy. But it would only be a matter of useless speculation to try to account for their never having come into argumentative collision.

Chʽien says: “Chuang had made himself well acquainted with all the literature of his time, but preferred the views of Laozi, and ranked himself among his followers, so that of the more than ten myriads of characters contained in his published writings the greater part are occupied with metaphorical illustrations of Lao’s doctrines. He made ‘the old fisherman,’ ‘the robber of chih,’ and ‘the cutting open satchels,’ to satirize and expose the disciples of Confucius, and clearly exhibit the sentiments of Lao. Such names and characters as ‘Wei-lei Hsü’ and ‘Kʽang-sang Tzŭ’ are fictitious, and the pieces where they occur are not to be understood as narratives of real events.[36]

“But Chuang was an admirable writer and skilful composer, and by his instances and truthful descriptions hit and exposed the Mohists and literati. The ablest scholars of his day could not escape his satire nor reply to it, while he allowed and enjoyed himself with his sparkling, dashing style; and thus it was that the greatest men, even kings and princes, could not use him for their purposes.

“King Wei of Chʽu, having heard of the ability of Chuang-chou, sent messengers with large gifts to bring him to his court, and promising also that he would make him his chief minister. Chuang-tzŭ, however, only laughed and said to them, ‘A thousand ounces of silver are a great gain to me, and to be a high noble and minister is most honourable position. But have you not seen the victim-ox for the border sacrifice? It is carefully fed for several years, and robed with rich embroidery that it may be fit to enter the Grand Temple. When the time comes for it to do so, it would prefer to be a little pig, but it cannot get to be so. Go away quickly, and do not soil me with your presence. I had rather amuse and enjoy myself in the midst of a filthy ditch than be subject to the rules and restrictions in the court of a sovereign. I have determined never to take office, but prefer the enjoyment of my own free will.’ ”

Chʽien concludes his account of Chuang-tzŭ with the above story, condensed by him, probably, from two of Chuang’s own narratives, in par. 11 of bk. XVII, and 13 of XXXII, to the injury of them both. Paragraph 14 of XXXII brings before us one of the last scenes of Chung-tzŭ’s life, and we may doubt whether it should be received as from his own pencil. It is interesting in itself, however, and I introduce it here: “When Chuang-tzŭ was about to die, his disciples signified their wish to give him a grand burial. ‘I shall have heaven and earth,’ he said, ‘for my coffin and its shell; the sun and moon for my two round symbols of jade; the stars and constellations for my pearls and jewels;—will not the provisions for my interment be complete? What would you add to them?’ The disciples replied, ‘We are afraid that the crows and kites will eat our master.’ Chuang-tzŭ rejoined, ‘Above, the crows and kites will eat me; below, the mole-crickets and ants will eat me; to take from those and give to these would only show your partiality.’ ”

Such were among the last words of Chuang-tzŭ. His end was not so impressive as that of Confucius; but it was in keeping with the general magniloquence and strong assertion of independence that marked all his course.

The way you can go
isn’t the real way.
The name you can say
isn’t the real name.

Heaven and earth
begin in the unnamed:
name’s the mother
of the ten thousand things.

So the unwanting soul
sees what’s hidden,
and the ever-wanting soul
sees only what it wants.

Two things, one origin,
but different in name,
whose identity is mystery.
Mystery of all mysteries!
The door to the hidden.

Everybody on earth knowing
that beauty is beautiful
makes ugliness.

Everybody knowing
that goodness is good
makes wickedness.

For being and nonbeing
arise together;
hard and easy
complete each other;
long and short
shape each other;
high and low
depend on each other;
note and voice
make the music together;
before and after
follow each other.

That’s why the wise soul
does without doing,
teaches without talking.

The things of this world
exist, they are;
you can’t refuse them.

To bear and not to own;
to act and not lay claim;
to do the work and let it go:
for just letting it go
is what makes it stay.

Not praising the praiseworthy
keeps people uncompetitive.

Not prizing rare treasures
keeps people from stealing.

Not looking at the desirable
keeps the mind quiet.

So the wise soul
governing people
would empty their minds,
fill their bellies,
weaken their wishes,
strengthen their bones,
keep people unknowing,
unwanting,

keep the ones who do know
from doing anything.

When you do not-doing,
nothing’s out of order.

The way is empty,
used, but not used up.
Deep, yes! ancestral
to the ten thousand things.

Blunting edge,
loosing bond,
dimming light,
the way is the dust of the way.

Quiet,
yes, and likely to endure.
Whose child? born
before the gods.

Heaven and earth aren’t humane.
To them the ten thousand things
are straw dogs.

Wise souls aren’t humane.
To them the hundred families
are straw dogs.

Heaven and earth
act as a bellows:

Empty yet structured,
it moves, inexhaustibly giving.

The valley spirit never dies.
Call it the mystery, the woman.

The mystery,
the Door of the Woman,
is the root
of earth and heaven.

Forever this endures, forever.
And all its uses are easy.

Heaven will last,
earth will endure.
How can they last so long?
They don’t exist for themselves
and so can go on and on.

So wise souls
leaving self behind
move forward,
and setting self aside
stay centered.
Why let the self go?
To keep what the soul needs.

True goodness
is like water.
Water’s good
for everything.
It doesn’t compete.

It goes right
to the low loathsome places,
and so finds the way.

For a house,
the good thing is level ground.
In thinking,
depth is good.
The good of giving is magnanimity;
of speaking, honesty;
of government, order.
The good of work is skill,
and of action, timing.

No competition,
so no blame.

Brim-fill the bowl,
it’ll spill over.
Keep sharpening the blade,
you’ll soon blunt it.

Nobody can protect
a house full of gold and jade.

Wealth, status, pride,
are their own ruin.
To do good, work well, and lie low
is the way of the blessing.

Can you keep your soul in its body,
hold fast to the one,
and so learn to be whole?
Can you center your energy,
be soft, tender,
and so learn to be a baby?

Can you keep the deep water still and clear,
so it reflects without blurring?
Can you love people and run things,
and do so by not doing?

Opening, closing the Gate of Heaven,
can you be like a bird with her nestlings?
Piercing bright through the cosmos,
can you know by not knowing?

To give birth, to nourish,
to bear and not to own,
to act and not lay claim,
to lead and not to rule:
this is mysterious power.

Thirty spokes
meet in the hub.
Where the wheel isn’t
is where it’s useful.

Hollowed out, clay
makes a pot.
Where the pot’s not is
where it’s useful.

Cut doors and windows
to make a room.
Where the room isn’t,
there’s room for you.

So the profit in what is
is in the use of what isn’t.

The five colors
blind our eyes.
The five notes
deafen our ears.
The five flavors
dull our taste.

Racing, chasing, hunting,
drives people crazy.
Trying to get rich
ties people in knots.

So the wise soul
watches with the inner
not the outward eye,
letting that go,
keeping this.

To be in favor or disgrace
is to live in fear.
To take the body seriously
is to admit one can suffer.

What does that mean,
to be in favor or disgrace
is to live in fear?
Favor debases:
we fear to lose it,
fear to win it.
So to be in favor or disgrace
is to live in fear.

What does that mean,
to take the body seriously
is to admit one can suffer?
I suffer because I’m a body;
if I weren’t a body,
how could I suffer?

So people who set their bodily good
before the public good
could be entrusted with the commonwealth,
and people who treated the body politic
as gently as their own body
would be worthy to govern the commonwealth.

Look at it: nothing to see.
Call it colorless.
Listen to it: nothing to hear.
Call it soundless.
Reach for it: nothing to hold.
Call it intangible.

Triply undifferentiated,
it merges into oneness,
not bright above,
not dark below.

Never, oh! never
can it be named.
It reverts, it returns
to unbeing.
Call it the form of the unformed,
the image of no image.

Call it unthinkable thought.
Face it: no face.
Follow it: no end.

Holding fast to the old Way,
we can live in the present.
Mindful of the ancient beginnings,
we hold the thread of the Tao.

Once upon a time
people who knew the Way
were subtle, spiritual, mysterious, penetrating, unfathomable.

Since they’re inexplicable
I can only say what they seemed like:
Cautious, oh yes, as if wading through a winter river.
Alert, as if afraid of the neighbors.
Polite and quiet, like houseguests.
Elusive, like melting ice.
Blank, like uncut wood.
Empty, like valleys.
Mysterious, oh yes, they were like troubled water.

Who can by stillness, little by little
make what is troubled grow clear?
Who can by movement, little by little
make what is still grow quick?

To follow the Way
is not to need fulfillment.

Unfulfilled, one may live on
needing no renewal.

Be completely empty.
Be perfectly serene.
The ten thousand things arise together;
in their arising is their return.
Now they flower,
and flowering
sink homeward,
returning to the root.

The return to the root
is peace.
Peace: to accept what must be,
to know what endures.
In that knowledge is wisdom.
Without it, ruin, disorder.

To know what endures
is to be openhearted,
magnanimous,
regal,
blessed,

following the Tao,
the way that endures forever.

The body comes to its ending,
but there is nothing to fear.

True leaders
are hardly known to their followers.
Next after them are the leaders
the people know and admire;
after them, those they fear;
after them, those they despise.

To give no trust
is to get no trust.

When the work’s done right,
with no fuss or boasting,
ordinary people say,
Oh, we did it.

In the degradation of the great way
come benevolence and righteousness.
With the exaltation of learning and prudence
comes immense hypocrisy.
The disordered family
is full of dutiful children and parents.
The disordered society
is full of loyal patriots.

Stop being holy, forget being prudent,
it’ll be a hundred times better for everyone.
Stop being altruistic, forget being righteous,
people will remember what family feeling is.
Stop planning, forget making a profit,
there won’t be any thieves and robbers.

But even these three rules
needn’t be followed; what works reliably
is to know the raw silk,
hold the uncut wood.
Need little,
want less.
Forget the rules.
Be untroubled.

How much difference between yes and no?
What difference between good and bad?

What the people fear
must be feared.
O desolation!
Not yet, not yet has it reached its limit!

Everybody’s cheerful,
cheerful as if at a party,
or climbing a tower in springtime.
And here I sit unmoved,
clueless, like a child,
a baby too young to smile.

Forlorn, forlorn.
Like a homeless person.
Most people have plenty.
I’m the one that’s poor,
a fool right through.

Ignorant, ignorant.
Most people are so bright.
I’m the one that’s dull.
Most people are so keen.
I don’t have the answers.
Oh, I’m desolate, at sea,
adrift, without harbor.

Everybody has something to do.
I’m the clumsy one, out of place.
I’m the different one,
for my food
is the milk of the mother.

The greatest power is the gift
of following the Way alone.
How the Way does things is
hard to grasp, elusive.
Elusive, yes, hard to grasp,
yet there are thoughts in it.
Hard to grasp, yes, elusive,
yet there are things in it.
Hard to make out, yes, and obscure,
yet there is spirit in it,
veritable spirit.
There is certainty in it.
From long, long ago till now
it has kept its name.
So it saw
the beginning of everything.

How do I know
anything about the beginning?
By this.

Be broken to be whole.
Twist to be straight.
Be empty to be full.
Wear out to be renewed.
Have little and gain much.
Have much and get confused.

So wise souls hold to the one,
and test all things against it.

Not showing themselves,
they shine forth.
Not justifying themselves,
they’re self-evident.
Not praising themselves,
they’re accomplished.
Not competing,
they have in all the world no competitor.

What they used to say in the old days,
“Be broken to be whole,”
was that mistaken?
Truly, to be whole
is to return.

Nature doesn’t make long speeches.
A whirlwind doesn’t last all morning.
A cloudburst doesn’t last all day.
Who makes the wind and rain?
Heaven and earth do.
If heaven and earth don’t go on and on,
certainly people don’t need to.

The people who work with Tao
are Tao people,
they belong to the Way.
People who work with power
belong to power.
People who work with loss
belong to what’s lost.

Give yourself to the Way
and you’ll be at home on the Way.
Give yourself to power
and you’ll be at home in power.
Give yourself to loss
and when you’re lost you’ll be at home.

To give no trust
is to get no trust.

You can’t keep standing on tiptoe
or walk in leaps and bounds.
You can’t shine by showing
off or get ahead by pushing.
Self-satisfied people do no good,
self-promoters never grow up.

Such stuff is to the Tao
as garbage is to food
or a tumor to the body,
hateful.
The follower of the Way
avoids it.

There is something
that contains everything.
Before heaven and earth
it is.
Oh, it is still, unbodied,
all on its own, unchanging,

all-pervading,
ever-moving.
So it can act as the mother
of all things.
Not knowing its real name,
we only call it the Way.

If it must be named,
let its name be Great.
Greatness means going on,
going on means going far,
and going far means turning back.

So they say: “The Way is great,
heaven is great,
earth is great,
and humankind is great;
four greatnesses in the world,
and humanity is one of them.”

People follow earth,
earth follows heaven,
heaven follows the Way,
the Way follows what is.

Heavy is the root of light.
Still is the master of moving.

So wise souls make their daily march
with the heavy baggage wagon.

Only when safe
in a solid, quiet house
do they lay care aside.

How can a lord of ten thousand chariots
let his own person
weigh less in the balance than his land?
Lightness will lose him his foundation,
movement will lose him his mastery.

Good walkers leave no track.
Good talkers don’t stammer.
Good counters don’t use their fingers.
The best door’s unlocked and unopened.
The best knot’s not in a rope and can’t be untied.

So wise souls are good at caring for people,
never turning their back on anyone.
They’re good at looking after things,
never turning their back on anything.
There’s a light hidden here.

Good people teach people who aren’t good yet;
the less good are the makings of the good.
Anyone who doesn’t respect a teacher
or cherish a student
may be clever, but has gone astray.
There’s a deep mystery here.

Knowing man
and staying woman,
be the riverbed of the world.
Being the world’s riverbed
of eternal unfailing power
is to go back again to be newborn.

Knowing light
and staying dark,
be a pattern to the world.
Being the world’s pattern
of eternal unerring power
is to go back again to boundlessness.

Knowing glory
and staying modest,
be the valley of the world.
Being the world’s valley
of eternal inexhaustible power
is to go back again to the natural.

Natural wood is cut up
and made into useful things.
Wise souls are used
to make into leaders.
Just so, a great carving
is done without cutting.

Those who think to win the world
by doing something to it,
I see them come to grief.
For the world is a sacred object.
Nothing is to be done to it.
To do anything to it is to damage it.
To seize it is to lose it.

Under heaven some things lead, some follow,
some blow hot, some cold,
some are strong, some weak,
some are fulfilled, some fail.

So the wise soul keeps away
from the extremes, excess, extravagance.

A Taoist wouldn’t advise a ruler
to use force of arms for conquest;
that tactic backfires.

Where the army marched
grow thorns and thistles.
After the war
come the bad harvests.
Good leaders prosper, that’s all,
not presuming on victory.
They prosper without boasting,
or domineering, or arrogance,
prosper because they can’t help it,
prosper without violence.

Things flourish then perish.
Not the Way.
What’s not the Way
soon ends.

Even the best weapon
is an unhappy tool,
hateful to living things.
So the follower of the Way
stays away from it.

Weapons are unhappy tools,
not chosen by thoughtful people,
to be used only when there is no choice,
and with a calm, still mind,
without enjoyment.
To enjoy using weapons
is to enjoy killing people,
and to enjoy killing people
is to lose your share in the common good.

It is right that the murder of many people
be mourned and lamented.
It is right that a victor in war
be received with funeral ceremonies.

The way goes on forever nameless.
Uncut wood, nothing important,
yet nobody under heaven
dare try to carve it.
If rulers and leaders could use it,
the ten thousand things
would gather in homage,
heaven and earth would drop sweet dew,
and people, without being ordered,
would be fair to one another.

To order, to govern,
is to begin naming;
when names proliferate
it’s time to stop.
If you know when to stop
you’re in no danger.

The Way in the world
is as a stream to a valley,
a river to the sea.

Knowing other people is intelligence,
knowing yourself is wisdom.
Overcoming others takes strength,
overcoming yourself takes greatness.
Contentment is wealth.

Boldly pushing forward takes resolution.
Staying put keeps you in position.

To live till you die
is to live long enough.

The Great Way runs
to left, to right,
the ten thousand things
depending on it,
living on it,
accepted by it.

Doing its work,
it goes unnamed.
Clothing and feeding
the ten thousand things,
it lays no claim on them
and asks nothing of them.
Call it a small matter.
The ten thousand things
return to it,
though it lays no claim on them.
Call it great.

So the wise soul
without great doings
achieves greatness.

Hold fast to the great thought
and all the world will come to you,
harmless, peaceable, serene.

Walking around, we stop
for music, for food.
But if you taste the Way
it’s flat, insipid.
It looks like nothing much,
it sounds like nothing much.
And yet you can’t get enough of it.

What seeks to shrink
must first have grown;
what seeks weakness
surely was strong.
What seeks its ruin
must first have risen;
what seeks to take
has surely given.

This is called the small dark light:
the soft, the weak prevail
over the hard, the strong.

The Way never does anything,
and everything gets done.
If those in power could hold to the Way,
the ten thousand things
would look after themselves.
If even so they tried to act,
I’d quiet them with the nameless,
the natural.

In the unnamed, in the unshapen,
is not wanting.
In not wanting is stillness.
In stillness all under heaven rests.

Great power, not clinging to power,
has true power.
Lesser power, clinging to power,
lacks true power.
Great power, doing nothing,
has nothing to do.
Lesser power, doing nothing,
has an end in view.

The good the truly good do
has no end in view.
The right the very righteous do
has an end in view.
And those who act in true obedience to law
roll up their sleeves
and make the disobedient obey.

So: when we lose the Way we find power;
losing power we find goodness;
losing goodness we find righteousness;
losing righteousness we’re left with obedience.

Obedience to law is the dry husk
of loyalty and good faith.
Opinion is the barren flower of the Way,
the beginning of ignorance.

So great-minded people
abide in the kernel not the husk,
in the fruit not the flower,
letting the one go, keeping the other.

Those who of old got to be whole:

Heaven through its wholeness is pure;
earth through its wholeness is steady;
spirit through its wholeness is potent;
the valley through its wholeness flows with rivers;
the ten thousand things through their wholeness live;
rulers through their wholeness have authority.
Their wholeness makes them what they are.

Without what makes it pure, heaven would
disintegrate;
without what steadies it, earth would crack apart; without what makes it potent, spirit would fail;
without what fills it, the valley would run dry;
without what quickens them, the ten thousand
things would die;
without what authorizes them, rulers would fall.

The root of the noble is in the common,
the high stands on what’s below.
Princes and kings call themselves
“orphans, widowers, beggars,”
to get themselves rooted in the dirt.

A multiplicity of riches
is poverty.
Jade is praised as precious,
but its strength is being stone.

Return is how the Way moves.
Weakness is how the Way works.

Heaven and earth and the ten thousand things
are born of being.
Being is born of nothing.

Thoughtful people hear about the Way
and try hard to follow it.
Ordinary people hear about the Way
and wander onto it and off it.
Thoughtless people hear about the Way
and make jokes about it.
It wouldn’t be the Way
if there weren’t jokes about it.

So they say:
The Way’s brightness looks like darkness;
advancing on the Way feels like retreating;
the plain Way seems hard going.
The height of power seems a valley;
the amplest power seems not enough;
the firmest power seems feeble.
Perfect whiteness looks dirty.
The pure and simple looks chaotic.

The great square has no corners.
The great vessel is never finished.
The great tone is barely heard.
The great thought can’t be thought.

The Way is hidden
in its namelessness.
But only the Way
begins, sustains, fulfills.

The Way bears one.
The one bears two.
The two bear three.
The three bear the ten thousand things.
The ten thousand things
carry the yin on their shoulders
and hold in their arms the yang,
whose interplay of energy
makes harmony.

People despise
orphans, widowers, outcasts.
Yet that’s what kings and rulers call themselves. Whatever you lose, you’ve won.
Whatever you win, you’ve lost.

What others teach, I say too:
violence and aggression
destroy themselves.
My teaching rests on that.

What’s softest in the world
rushes and runs
over what’s hardest in the world.

The immaterial
enters
the impenetrable.

So I know the good in not doing.

The wordless teaching,
the profit in not doing—
not many people understand it.

Which is nearer,
name or self?
Which is dearer,
self or wealth?
Which gives more pain,
loss or gain?

All you grasp will be thrown away.
All you hoard will be utterly lost.

Contentment keeps disgrace away.
Restraint keeps you out of danger
so you can go on for a long, long time.

What’s perfectly whole seems flawed,
but you can use it forever.
What’s perfectly full seems empty,
but you can’t use it up.

True straightness looks crooked.
Great skill looks clumsy.
Real eloquence seems to stammer.

To be comfortable in the cold, keep moving;
to be comfortable in the heat, hold still;
to be comfortable in the world, stay calm and clear.

When the world’s on the Way,
they use horses to haul manure.
When the world gets off the Way,
they breed warhorses on the common.

The greatest evil: wanting more.
The worst luck: discontent.
Greed’s the curse of life.

To know enough’s enough
is enough to know.

You don’t have to go out the door
to know what goes on in the world.
You don’t have to look out the window
to see the way of heaven.
The farther you go,
the less you know.

So the wise soul
doesn’t go, but knows;
doesn’t look, but sees;
doesn’t do, but gets it done.

Studying and learning daily you grow larger.
Following the Way daily you shrink.
You get smaller and smaller.
So you arrive at not doing.
You do nothing and nothing’s not done.

To run things,
don’t fuss with them.
Nobody who fusses
is fit to run things.

The wise have no mind of their own,
finding it in the minds
of ordinary people.

They’re good to good people
and they’re good to bad people.
Power is goodness.
They trust people of good faith
and they trust people of bad faith.
Power is trust.

They mingle their life with the world,
they mix their mind up with the world.
Ordinary people look after them.
Wise souls are children.

To look for life
is to find death.
The thirteen organs of our living
are the thirteen organs of our dying.
Why are the organs of our life
where death enters us?
Because we hold too hard to living.

So I’ve heard
if you live in the right way,
when you cross country
you needn’t fear to meet a mad bull or a tiger;
when you’re in a battle
you needn’t fear the weapons.
The bull would find nowhere to jab its horns,
the tiger nowhere to stick its claws,
the sword nowhere for its point to go.
Why? Because there’s nowhere in you
for death to enter.

The Way bears them;
power nurtures them;
their own being shapes them;
their own energy completes them.
And not one of the ten thousand things
fails to hold the Way sacred
or to obey its power.

Their reverence for the Way
and obedience to its power
are unforced and always natural.
For the Way gives them life;
its power nourishes them,
mothers and feeds them,
completes and matures them,
looks after them, protects them.

To have without possessing,
do without claiming,
lead without controlling:
this is mysterious power.

The beginning of everything
is the mother of everything.
Truly to know the mother
is to know her children,
and truly to know the children
is to turn back to the mother.
The body comes to its ending
but there is nothing to fear.

Close the openings,
shut the doors,
and to the end of life
nothing will trouble you.
Open the openings,
be busy with business,
and to the end of life
nothing can help you.

Insight sees the insignificant.
Strength knows how to yield.
Use the way’s light, return to its insight,
and so keep from going too far.
That’s how to practice what’s forever.

If my mind’s modest,
I walk the great way.
Arrogance
is all I fear.

The great way is low and plain,
but people like shortcuts over the mountains.

The palace is full of splendor
and the fields are full of weeds
and the granaries are full of nothing.

People wearing ornaments and fancy clothes,
carrying weapons,
drinking a lot and eating a lot,
having a lot of things, a lot of money:
shameless thieves.
Surely their way isn’t the way.

Well planted is not uprooted,
well kept is not lost.
The offerings of the generations
to the ancestors will not cease.

To follow the way yourself is real power.
To follow it in the family is abundant power.
To follow it in the community is steady power.
To follow it in the whole country is lasting power.
To follow it in the world is universal power.

So in myself I see what self is,
in my household I see what family is,
in my town I see what community is,
in my nation I see what a country is,
in the world I see what is under heaven.

How do I know the world is so?
By this.

Being full of power
is like being a baby.
Scorpions don’t sting,
tigers don’t attack,
eagles don’t strike.
Soft bones, weak muscles,
but a firm grasp.
Ignorant of the intercourse
of man and woman,
yet the baby penis is erect.
True and perfect energy!
All day long screaming and crying,
but never getting hoarse.
True and perfect harmony!

To know harmony
is to know what’s eternal.
To know what’s eternal
is enlightenment.
Increase of life is full of portent:
the strong heart exhausts the vital breath.
The full-grown is on the edge of age.
Not the Way.
What’s not the Way soon dies.

Who knows
doesn’t talk.
Who talks
doesn’t know.
Closing the openings,
shutting doors,

blunting edge,
loosing bond,
dimming light,
be one with the dust of the way.
So you come to the deep sameness.

Then you can’t be controlled by love
or by rejection.
You can’t be controlled by profit
or by loss.
You can’t be controlled by praise
or by humiliation.
Then you have honor under heaven.

Run the country by doing what’s expected.
Win the war by doing the unexpected.
Control the world by doing nothing.
How do I know that?
By this.

The more restrictions and prohibitions in the world, the poorer people get.
The more experts the country has
the more of a mess it’s in.
The more ingenious the skillful are,
the more monstrous their inventions.
The louder the call for law and order,
the more the thieves and con men multiply.

So a wise leader might say:
I practice inaction, and the people look after
themselves.
I love to be quiet, and the people themselves find
justice.
I don’t do business, and the people prosper on their
own.
I don’t have wants, and the people themselves are
uncut wood.

When the government’s dull and confused,
the people are placid.
When the government’s sharp and keen,
the people are discontented.
Alas! misery lies under happiness,
and happiness sits on misery, alas!
Who knows where it will end?
Nothing is certain.

The normal changes into the monstrous,
the fortunate into the unfortunate,
and our bewilderment
goes on and on.

And so the wise
shape without cutting,
square without sawing,
true without forcing.
They are the light that does not shine.

In looking after your life and following the way,
gather spirit.
Gather spirit early,
and so redouble power,
and so become invulnerable.

Invulnerable, unlimited,
you can do what you like with material things.
But only if you hold to the Mother of things
will you do it for long.
Have deep roots, a strong trunk.
Live long by looking long.

Rule a big country
the way you cook a small fish.

If you keep control by following the Way,
troubled spirits won’t act up.
They won’t lose their immaterial strength,
but they won’t harm people with it,
nor will wise souls come to harm.
And so, neither harming the other,
these powers will come together in unity.

The polity of greatness
runs downhill like a river to the sea,
joining with everything,
woman to everything.

By stillness the woman
may always dominate the man,
lying quiet underneath him.

So a great country
submitting to small ones, dominates them;
so small countries,
submitting to a great one, dominate it.

Lie low to be on top,
be on top by lying low.

The way is the hearth and home
of the ten thousand things.
Good souls treasure it,
lost souls find shelter in it.

Fine words are for sale,
fine deeds go cheap;
even worthless people can get them.

So, at the coronation of the Son of Heaven
when the Three Ministers take office,
you might race out in a four-horse chariot
to offer a jade screen;
but wouldn’t it be better to sit still
and let the Way be your offering?

Why was the Way honored
in the old days?
Wasn’t it said: Seek, you’ll find it.
Hide, it will shelter you.
So it was honored under heaven.

Do without doing.
Act without action.
Savor the flavorless.
Treat the small as large,
the few as many.

Meet injury
with the power of goodness.

Study the hard while it’s easy.
Do big things while they’re small.
The hardest jobs in the world start out easy,
the great affairs of the world start small.

So the wise soul,
by never dealing with great things,
gets great things done.

Now, since taking things too lightly makes them
worthless,
and taking things too easy makes them hard,
the wise soul,
by treating the easy as hard,
doesn’t find anything hard.

It’s easy to keep hold of what hasn’t stirred,
easy to plan what hasn’t occurred.
It’s easy to shatter delicate things,
easy to scatter little things.
Do things before they happen.
Get them straight before they get mixed up.

The tree you can’t reach your arms around
grew from a tiny seedling.
The nine-story tower rises
from a heap of clay.
The ten-thousand-mile journey
begins beneath your foot.

Do, and do wrong;
Hold on, and lose.
Not doing, the wise soul
doesn’t do it wrong,
and not holding on,
doesn’t lose it.
(In all their undertakings,
it’s just as they’re almost finished
that people go wrong.

Mind the end as the beginning,
then it won’t go wrong.)

That’s why the wise
want not to want,
care nothing for hard-won treasures,
learn not to be learned,
turn back to what people overlooked.
They go along with things as they are,
but don’t presume to act.

Once upon a time
those who ruled according to the Way
didn’t use it to make people knowing
but to keep them unknowing.

People get hard to manage
when they know too much.
Whoever rules by intellect
is a curse upon the land.
Whoever rules by ignorance
is a blessing on it.
To understand these things
is to have a pattern and a model,
and to understand the pattern and the model
is mysterious power.

Mysterious power
goes deep.
It reaches far.
It follows things back,
clear back to the great oneness.

Lakes and rivers are lords of the hundred valleys.
Why? Because they’ll go lower.
So they’re the lords of the hundred valleys.

Just so, a wise soul,
wanting to be above other people,
talks to them from below
and to guide them
follows them.

And so the wise soul
predominates without dominating,
and leads without misleading.
And people don’t get tired
of enjoying and praising
one who, not competing,
has in all the world
no competitor.

Everybody says my way
is great but improbable.

All greatness
is improbable.
What’s probable
is tedious and petty.

I have three treasures.
I keep and treasure them.
The first, mercy,
the second, moderation,
the third, modesty.
If you’re merciful you can be brave,
if you’re moderate you can be generous,
and if you don’t presume to lead
you can lead the high and mighty.

But to be brave without compassion,
or generous without self-restraint,
or to take the lead,
is fatal.

Compassion wins the battle
and holds the fort;
it is the bulwark set
around those heaven helps.

The best captain doesn’t rush in front.
The fiercest fighter doesn’t bluster.
The big winner isn’t competing.
The best boss takes a low footing.
This is the power of noncompetition.
This is the right use of ability.
To follow heaven’s lead
has always been the best way.

The expert in warfare says:
Rather than dare make the attack
I’d take the attack;
rather than dare advance an inch
I’d retreat a foot.

It’s called marching without marching,
rolling up your sleeves without flexing your muscles,
being armed without weapons,
giving the attacker no opponent.
Nothing’s worse than attacking what yields.
To attack what yields is to throw away the prize.

So, when matched armies meet,
the one who comes to grief
is the true victor.

My words are so easy to understand,
so easy to follow,

and yet nobody in the world
understands or follows them.

Words come from an ancestry,
deeds from a mastery:
when these are unknown, so am I.

In my obscurity
is my value.
That’s why the wise
wear their jade under common clothes.

To know without knowing is best.
Not knowing without knowing it is sick.

To be sick of sickness
is the only cure.

The wise aren’t sick.
They’re sick of sickness,
so they’re well.

When we don’t fear what we should fear
we are in fearful danger.
We ought not to live in narrow houses,
we ought not to do stupid work.

If we don’t accept stupidity
we won’t act stupidly.
So, wise souls know but don’t show themselves,
look after but don’t prize themselves,
letting the one go, keeping the other.

Brave daring leads to death.
Brave caution leads to life.
The choice can be the right one
or the wrong one.

Who will interpret
the judgment of heaven?
Even the wise soul
finds it hard.

The way of heaven
doesn’t compete
yet wins handily,
doesn’t speak
yet answers fully,
doesn’t summon
yet attracts.
It acts
perfectly easily.

The net of heaven
is vast, vast,
wide-meshed,
yet misses nothing.

When normal, decent people don’t fear death,
how can you use death to frighten them?
Even when they have a normal fear of death,
who of us dare take and kill the one who doesn’t?
When people are normal and decent and death-fearing,
there’s always an executioner.
To take the place of that executioner
is to take the place of the great carpenter.
People who cut the great carpenter’s wood
seldom get off with their hands unhurt.

People are starving.
The rich gobble taxes,
that’s why people are starving.

People rebel.
The rich oppress them,
that’s why people rebel.

People hold life cheap.
The rich make it too costly,
that’s why people hold it cheap.

But those who don’t live for the sake of living
are worth more than the wealth-seekers.

Living people
are soft and tender.
Corpses are hard and stiff.
The ten thousand things,
the living grass, the trees,
are soft, pliant.
Dead, they’re dry and brittle.

So hardness and stiffness
go with death;
tenderness, softness,
go with life.

And the hard sword fails,
the stiff tree’s felled.
The hard and great go under.
The soft and weak stay up.

The Way of heaven
is like a bow bent to shoot:
its top end brought down,
its lower end raised up.
It brings the high down,
lifts the low,
takes from those who have,
gives to those who have not.

Such is the Way of heaven,
taking from people who have,
giving to people who have not.
Not so the human way:
it takes from those who have not
to fill up those who have.
Who has enough to fill up everybody?
Only those who have the Way.

So the wise
do without claiming,
achieve without asserting,
wishing not to show their worth.

Nothing in the world
is as soft, as weak, as water;
nothing else can wear away
the hard, the strong,
and remain unaltered.
Soft overcomes hard,
weak overcomes strong.
Everybody knows it,
nobody uses the knowledge.

So the wise say:
By bearing common defilements
you become a sacrificer at the altar of earth;
by bearing common evils
you become a lord of the world.

Right words sound wrong.

After a great enmity is settled
some enmity always remains.
How to make peace?
Wise souls keep their part of the contract
and don’t make demands on others.
People whose power is real fulfill their obligations;
people whose power is hollow insist on their claims.

The Way of heaven plays no favorites.
It stays with the good.

Let there be a little country without many people.
Let them have tools that do the work of ten or
a hundred,
and never use them.
Let them be mindful of death
and disinclined to long journeys.
They’d have ships and carriages,
but no place to go.
They’d have armor and weapons,
but no parades.
Instead of writing,
they might go back to using knotted cords.
They’d enjoy eating,
take pleasure in clothes,
be happy with their houses,
devoted to their customs.

The next little country might be so close
the people could hear cocks crowing
and dogs barking there,
but they’d get old and die
without ever having been there.

True words aren’t charming,
charming words aren’t true.
Good people aren’t contentious,
contentious people aren’t good.
People who know aren’t learned,
learned people don’t know.

Wise souls don’t hoard;
the more they do for others the more they have,
the more they give the richer they are.
The Way of heaven profits without destroying.
Doing without outdoing
is the Way of the wise.

Notes

01

Here, for the words in the third verse that I render “what it wants,” I use the

Ma wang tui

text. The words in the standard text mean boundaries, or limits, or outcomes. This version seems to follow more comprehensibly from the preceding lines.

And yet the idea of what can be delimited or made manifest is relevant. In the last verse, the two “whose identity is mystery” may be understood to be the hidden, the unnameable, the limitless vision of the freed soul—and the manifest, the nameable, the field of vision limited by our wants. But the endlessness of all that is, and the limitation of mortal bodily life, are the same, and their sameness is the key to the door.

05

As I said above, in a few of the poems I leave out lines which I find weaken the coherence of the text to the point that I believe them to be a long-ago reader’s marginal notes which got incorporated in later copyings. My authority for these omissions is strictly personal and aesthetic. Here I omit the last two lines. Translations of them vary greatly; my version is:

Mere talk runs dry.
Best keep to the center.

12

There are times Lao Tzu sounds very like Henry David Thoreau, but Lao Tzu was kinder. When Thoreau says to distrust any enterprise that requires new clothes, I distrust him. He is macho, flaunting his asceticism. Lao Tzu knows that getting all entangled with the external keeps us from the eternal, but (see chapter 80) he also understands that sometimes people like to get dressed up.

13

T’ien hsia, “under heaven,” i.e. the Empire, or the world: here I render it as “the public good,” “the commonwealth,” and “the body politic.”

J. P. Seaton comments: “When Lao Tzu mentions ‘the Empire’ or ‘all under heaven,’ he does so with the assumption that all his readers know that it is a commonwealth where only the ruler who rules by virtue of virtue alone is legitimate.”

17, 18, 19

Henricks considers these three chapters (17, 18, 19) to belong together. The last two lines of 19 are usually printed as the first two lines of 20, but Henricks thinks they belong here, and I follow him.

In 18, line 6, the words hsiao tzu are traditionally translated as “filial piety and paternal affection,” a Confucian ideal. In that chapter Lao Tzu cites these dutiful families as a symptom of social disorder. But in chapter 19, line 4, hsiao tzu appears as the good that will result when people cease being moralistic. Unable to reconcile these contradictory usages, and feeling that Lao Tzu was far more likely to use Confucian language satirically than straightforwardly, I fudged the translation in chapter 19, calling it “family feeling.” Evidently we aren’t the only society or generation to puzzle over what a family is and ought to be.

Sometimes I translate the characters su and p’u with such words as simple, natural. Though the phrase “the uncarved block” has become familiar to many, yet metaphor may distance ideas and weaken a direct statement. But sometimes, as here, I use the traditional metaphors, because the context so clearly implies knowing something as an artist knows her materials, keeping hold on something solid.

20

The standard texts ask what’s the difference between wei and o, which might be translated “yes” and “yessir.” The

Ma wang tui

has wei and ho: “yes” and “no.” This is parallel with the next line (“good and bad” in the standard text, “beautiful and ugly” in the

Ma wang tui

). Here’s a case where the older text surely is correct, the later ones corrupt.

In the first two lines of the second verse, the

Ma wang tui

text is perfectly clear: “A person whom everyone fears ought to be feared.” The standard text is strange, obscure: “What the people fear must be feared.” Yet the next lines follow from it as they don’t from the

Ma wang tui

; and after much pondering I followed the standard text.

23

In the second verse the word shih, “loss,” gives trouble to all the translators. Waley calls it “the reverse of the power” and “inefficacy,” and Waley’s interpretations are never to be ignored. All the same, I decided to take it not as the opposite of the Way and the power, but as a kind of shadow-Way. Identify yourself with loss, failure, the obscure, the unpossessible, and you’ll be at home even there.

24

My version of the first four lines of the second verse doesn’t follow any of the scholarly translations, and is quite unjustified, but at least, unlike them, it makes sense without horrible verbal contortions.

25

In all the texts, the fourth verse reads:

So they say: “The Way is great,
heaven is great,
earth is great,
and the king is great.
Four greatnesses in the world,
and the king is one of them.”

Yet in the next verse, which is the same series in reverse order, instead of “the king” it’s “the people” or “humanity.” I think a Confucian copyist slipped the king in. The king garbles the sense of the poem and goes against the spirit of the book. I dethroned him.

The last words of the chapter, tzu jan, which I render “what is,” bear many interpretations. Waley translates them as “the Self-So,” glossing them as “the unconditioned” or “what is so of itself”; Henricks, “what is so on its own”; Lau, “that which is naturally so”; Gibbs-Cheng, “Nature”; Feng-English, “what is natural”; Lafargue, “things as they are.” I came out closest to Lafargue in this case.

26

I follow the

Ma wang tui

text for the third verse, which fits the theme much better than the non-sequitur standard text, “Amid fine sights they sit calm and aloof.” The syntax of the

Ma wang tui

also clarifies the last verse, relating it to the last verse of chapter 13.

27

The first two lines of the third verse say that the not-good are the t’zu: “the capital” (Carus), or “the charge” (Feng-English), or “the stock in trade” (Waley), or “the raw material” (Henricks) of the good. Lafargue has “the less excellent are material for the excellent,” and Gibbs-Cheng, “mediocre people have the potential to be good people.” The latter two interpretations seemed the most useful to me. And so I call these makings, this raw material, “a student”—somebody learning to be or know better.

The last lines of the second and third verses are translated in wildly various ways; my “hidden light” and “deep mystery” are justified if, as I believe, Lao Tzu is signaling that his apparently simple statements have complex implications and need thinking about. Of course, this is true of everything in the book.

28

“The natural” and “natural wood” are the same word, p’u, which I talked about in the note to chapter 19. Given the amount of cutting up and carving that goes on in the last verse (which seems a kind of footnote to the first three), we really seem to be talking about wood.

Chinese lends itself to puns, and this last verse is rife with them. Waley says that ch’i (“useful things”) can mean “vessels” or “vassals,” and chih can mean “carving” or “governing.” A great government wouldn’t chop and hack at human nature, trying to make leaders out of sow’s ears. But the paradox of the last two lines surely exceeds any single interpretation.

29

The phrase t’ien hsia occurs only in the first verse, where I translate it “the world.” I begin the second verse with the literal translation of it, “under heaven.” I wanted the phrase in the poem as a reminder that the world of these extremes—of hot and cold, weakness and strength, gain and loss—is the sacred object, the place under heaven.

31

I have omitted certain lines included by the translators who are my sources and guides. In all the texts, the second verse begins:

A courteous person
in peacetime honors the left,
in wartime, the right.

And the last verse begins:

In celebrations the left is the place of honor,
in mourning the right is the place of honor:
so lesser officers stand on the left,
the generalissimo on the right,
just as they would at a funeral.

I consider these passages to be commentaries or marginal glosses that got copied into the text. J. P. Seaton says, “What were once supports by analogy to common ceremonial practice are now relevant only to the historian.” Here they confuse the clear, powerful statement that culminates in the last four lines. The confusion already existed when the

Ma wang tui

version was written, and there seems to be no way of sorting it out now except by radical surgery.

33

This chapter sounds like Polonius, incontrovertible but banal, until the last verse, which is a doozer. Here are some other versions of the last six words, Sss erh pu wang che shou:

Carus (word for word): “[Who] dies / yet / not / perishes, / the-one / islong-lived [immortal].”

Carus’s free translation: “One who may die but does not perish has life everlasting.”

Waley: “When one dies one is not lost; there is no other longevity.”

Feng-English: “To die but not to perish is to be eternally present.”

Henricks: “To die but not be forgotten—that’s [true] long life.”

Bynner: “Vitality cleaves to the marrow / Leaving death behind.”

Lafargue: “One who dies and does not perish is truly long-lived.”

Gibbs-Cheng: “One who dies yet still remains has longevity.”

Lau: “He who lives out his days has had a long life.”

Under J. P. Seaton’s guidance I finally came to feel that I had a handle on the line, and that Lau’s rendition was the most useful. One thing is certain, Lao Tzu is not saying that immortality or even longevity is desirable. The religion called Taoism has spent much imagination on ways to prolong life interminably or gain immortality, and the mythologized Lao Tzu was supposed to have run Methuselah a close race; but the Lao Tzu who wrote this had no truck with such notions.

36

Wei ming—this phrase in the first line of the second verse (and the chapter title)—is tricky:

Carus (word for word): “the secret’s / explanation”;

Carus’s free translation: “explanation [i.e., enlightenment] of the secret”

Feng-English: “perception of the nature of things”

Gibbs-Cheng: “wonderfully minute and obscure, yet brilliant”

Lafargue: “subtle clarity”

Henricks: “subtle light”

Bynner: “a man with insight”

Waley: “dimming one’s light”

Ming is “light” or “enlightenment.” Waley explains that wei means obscure because very small, and also obscure because dark. I use this second meaning to make an oxymoron.

37

The words in the first verse I translate as “the nameless, the natural” and in the next verse as “the unnamed, the unshapen” are the same four words: wu ming chih p’u; more literally, “the naturalness of the unnamed.” “The unnamed” is a key phrase in the first chapter and elsewhere, as is “not wanting,” “unwanting.” P’u is the natural, the uncut wood, or, as Waley glosses it here, “uncarvedwood quality.”

38

The series here is of familiar Confucian principles: jen, li, i—“good, humane, human-hearted, altruistic”; “righteous, moral, ethical”; “laws, rites, rules, law and order.” But Lao Tzu reverses and subverts the Confucian priorities.

Chien shih in the fourth verse is “premature knowledge” in Carus and “foreknowledge” in Lau, Henricks, and Waley (who explains it as part of Confucian doctrine). Henricks interprets it as having “one’s mind made up before one enters a new situation about what is ‘right’ and ‘wrong’ and ‘proper’ and ‘acceptable’ and so on.” Prejudice, that is, or opinion. Buddhists and Taoists agree in having a very low opinion of opinion.

39

Yi, “one, the one, unity, singleness, integrity,” is here translated as “whole, wholeness.”

Waley explains the last two verses as comments on the first three, but their relevance is pretty tenuous. The last verse is very difficult and the translations are various and ingenious. Henricks reads the

Ma wang tui

text of the first two lines of it as meaning “too many carriages is the same as no carriage,” and I picked up on the idea of multiplicity as opposed to the singleness or wholeness spoken of in the first verses. The meaning of the lines about jade seems to be anybody’s guess.

41

I moved the line about perfect whiteness down to keep the three lines about power together, in parallel structure with the three lines about the Way. In the last line of the second verse (and in chapters 21 and 35) I translate hsiang as “thought.” The word connotes “form, shape, image, idea” Waley explains it as the form which is formless, the Tao which can’t be tao’d.

42

In the sixth line, does the word fu mean “carry on one’s back” or “turn one’s back on”? Lafargue is the only translator I found that made the second choice. I don’t follow him because I don’t think the “ten thousand things” would or can make the mistake of turning their backs on the yin to embrace only yang. (But a great many of us do make that mistake, which is why Lao Tzu keeps reminding us to value yin, the soft, the dark, the weak, earth, water, the Mother, the Valley.)

Lafargue’s reading, however, lets the next stanza follow more coherently— orphans, the bereaved, the outcast are what we turn our backs on; winning is yang, losing is yin. Through loss we win…

The last stanza is uncharacteristic in its didactic tone and in assimilating the teaching to a tradition. Lao Tzu usually cites “what others teach” only to dissociate himself from it. I was inclined to dismiss it as a marginal note by someone who was teaching and annotating the text. But J. P. Seaton, who does teach the text, persuaded me to keep it in the body of the poem, saying, “It’s a message that for all its flat moralism does connect Taoism to Confucianism and even to Buddhism with a single solid thread—averting a hundred holy wars, if nothing else.”

44

The intense, succinct, beautiful language of the first verses of a poem is sometimes followed by a verse or two in a more didactic tone, smaller in scope, and far more prosaic. I believe some of these verses are additions, comments, and examples, copied into the manuscripts so long ago that they became holy writ. They usually have their own charm and validity, but—as here, and in chapter 39 and other places—they bring a tremendous statement down to a rather commonplace ending. But then, Lao Tzu values the commonplace.

47

The last line, literally “not do, yet accomplish,” is a direct statement of one of the fundamental themes of the book. When I came up with a slightly mealy version of it (“doesn’t do, but it’s done”) J. P. Seaton reminded me that “doing without doing is doing, not not doing.”

48

Shi (my “fuss,” Carus’s “diplomacy”) is translated by Lafargue as “work,” by Lau as “meddling,” by Waley and Feng-English as “interference,” by Henricks as “concern,” by Gibbs-Cheng as “act for gain.”

49

Following some of Carus’s interpretations, the first lines of the third verse might be read, “Wise souls live in the world carefully, handling it carefully, making their mind universal.” I can’t make much sense of any of the other versions except Henricks’s beautiful reading:

As for the Sage’s presence in the world, he is one with it.
And with the world he merges his mind.

50

Those who read shih yu san as “thirteen,” rather than as “three out of ten,” make better sense of the difficult first verse. The thirteen “companions of life” (Waley, Henricks), which I translate “organs,” may be physical, the limbs and passages and cavities of the body—or physio/psychological, the emotions and sensations.

My “mad bull” occurs variously as a rhinoceros and a wild buffalo. The idea seems to be a big irritable animal with horns.

My “live in the right way” is literally “take care of your life,” or “hold on to your life.” The context indicates care without anxiety, holding without grasping. I read the poem as saying that if you can take life as it comes, it doesn’t come at you as your enemy. Lao Tzu’s “nowhere for death to enter” isn’t a promise of invulnerability or immortality; his concern is how to live rightly, how to “live till you die.”

52

The last two lines of the first verse are the same as the last two lines of chapter 16. I wonder if some of these repetitions were insertions by people studying and copying the book, who were reminded of one poem by another and noted down the relevant lines. They are indeed relevant here, but they don’t fit with perfect inevitability, as they do in chapter 16. This is of course a purely aesthetic judgment, subject to destruction by scholarship at any moment.

54

Gibbs and Cheng, finding both the language and the message “discordant with the teachings of Lao Tzu,” won’t even discuss this chapter. Waley’s reading saves it, but the listing “self, family, community, country, empire/world” (a conventional series in ancient Chinese thought), and the list of rules and results is uncharacteristically mechanical. Though he uses many commonplaces, familiar phrases, rhymed sayings, and so on, Lao Tzu’s thought and language are usually more unconventional and unpredictable than this.

56

Another repetition: the first four lines of the second verse are the same as the second verse of chapter 4. They carry a different weight here. I vary my translation of them in the fourth line to make it connect to the next.

Hsuan t’ung, “the deep sameness”: hsuan is “deep” or “mysterious”; t’ung is variously translated “identification,” “oneness,” “sameness,” “merging,” “leveling,” “assimilation.” It is an important theme, met with before in chapter 49.

57

The phrase “How do I know? By this,” has become a kind of tag by its third repetition; but as Waley points out, it still implies intuitive knowing, beyond reason—knowing the way.

The words I translate “experts” literally mean “sharp weapons,” but the term implies “pundits, know-it-alls.” I was tempted to say “smart bombs,” which is too cute and topical, but which would certainly lead neatly to the next lines.

58

Waley points out that words in the last verse, with such meanings as “square, right, angular,” are typical Confucian virtues. Henricks remarks that all these words and operations refer to carpentry. The verse is about how to cut the uncut wood without cutting it.

59

Se, my “gather spirit,” is variously translated “frugality,” “moderation,” “restraint,” “being sparing,” or, by Waley, “laying up a store.” Evidently the core idea is that of saving.

The chapter is usually presented in the manual-for-princes mode. Waley makes sense out of it by complex technical references; other versions make only gleams of sense. To persuade or coerce it into the personal mode meant a more radical interpretation than I usually dare attempt, but Waley’s reading, which points to the symbology of the breath (ch’i) and the “long look” of the meditator, gave me the courage to try. Here is a version closer to the conventional ones:

In controlling people and serving heaven
it’s best to go easy.
Going easy from the start
is to gather power from the start,
and gathered power keeps you safe.

Safe, you can do what you like.
Do what you like, the country’s yours.
If you can make the country’s
Mother yours, you’ll last a long time.
You’ll have deep roots and a strong trunk.
The way to live long is to look long.

61

The first seven lines continue the themes of “sameness” or assimilation, and of “being woman,” “being water,” the uses of yin. From there on, the language goes flat, and may be interpolated commentary. There’s an even feebler fourth verse:

A big country needs more people,
A small one needs more room.
Each can get what it needs,
but the big one needs to lie low.

Because the

Ma wang tui

texts are older, one longs to see them as more authentic, less corrupt. But though they are invaluable in offering variant readings, some of the variants may themselves be corruptions. In this chapter, the

Ma wang tui

reads “Small countries, submitting to a great one, are dominated,” and in the next verse, “Some by lying low stay on top, but some by lying low stay on the bottom.” Both versions are truisms, but the

Ma wang tui

version isn’t even a Taoistic truism.

62

The first and last verses hang together; the two middle verses are difficult and rather incoherent. Waley says the enigmatic second verse refers to sophists and sages who went about selling their “fine words” to the highest bidder, like our pop gurus and TV pundits.

64

I think the advice about being careful at the end of an undertaking was added, perhaps to balance the advice that the right time to act is before the beginning. It confuses the argument a bit, and I put it in parentheses.

The line I give as “turn back to what people overlooked” is rendered by Lafargue as “turns back to the place all others have gone on from”; FengEnglish, “brings men back to what they have lost”; Henricks, “returns to what the masses have passed by”; Waley, “turning all men back to the things they have left behind.” Each version brings out a different color in the line, like different lights on an opal.

65

A dictator and his censors might all too easily cite from this chapter. A democrat might agree that the more people know, the harder they are for a ruler to govern—since the more they know, the better they are at governing themselves. Anyone might agree that an intellectual agenda pursued without reality-checking is indeed a curse upon the land. From the divine right of kings through the deadly teachings of Hitler and Mao to the mumbojumbo of economists, government by theory has done endless ill. But why is Lao Tzu’s alternative to it a people kept in ignorance? What kind of ignorance? Ignorance of what? Lao Tzu may be signalling us to ask such questions when he speaks of “understanding these things.”

69

Waley is my guide to the interpretation of the second verse, but I make very free with the last two lines of it. If they aren’t a rather vapid statement that one should never underestimate one’s foe, they must follow from what went before and lead to the extraordinary last verse. It all comes down to the last line and the word shwai. Carus translates it as “the weaker [the more compassionate],” and Bynner uses the word “compassion.” Waley translates it as “he who does not delight in war,” Henricks as “the one who feels grief,” Gibbs-Cheng as “the one stung by grief,” Feng-English as “the underdog,” Lafargue as “the one in mourning.” A man of sorrows, and acquainted with grief.

71

I follow Henricks in choosing the

Ma wang tui

text, which has a double negative in the second line. Most other texts have “not knowing knowing is sickness.”

72

I take the liberty of reading this chapter as a description of what we, we ordinary people, should fear. The usual reading is in the manual-for-princes mode. In that case “what should be feared” is the ruler, the rightful authority, and the advice that follows is evidently directed to that ruler. It’s certainly what William Blake would have told the oligarchs of the Industrial Revolution, who still control our lives:

When people don’t fear what should be feared
they are in fearful danger.
Don’t make them live in narrow houses,
don’t force them to do stupid work.

When they’re not made stupid
they won’t act stupidly.

74

I follow the

Ma wang tui

text, but make very free with the word Henricks renders as “constant [in their behavior].” If I understand Henricks’ version, it says that if people were consistent in behaving normally and in fearing death, and if death were the penalty for abnormal behavior, nobody would dare behave abnormally; and so there would be no executions and no executioners. But this is not the case; as Lao Tzu says, there are times when even normal people lose their normal fear of death. So what is the poem about? I read it as saying that since we are inconsistent both in our behavior and in our fear of death, no person can rightfully take on the role of executioner, and should leave the death penalty to the judgment of heaven or nature.

80

To dismiss this Utopia as simply regressivist or anti-technological is to miss an interesting point. These people have labor-saving machinery, ships and land vehicles, weapons of offense and defense. They “have them and don’t use them.” I interpret: they aren’t used by them. We’re used, our lives shaped and controlled, by our machines, cars, planes, weaponry, bulldozers, computers. These Taoists don’t surrender their power to their creations.

The eleventh line, however, is certainly regressive if it says knotted cords are to replace written literature, history, mathematics, and so on. It might be read as saying it’s best not to externalize all our thinking and remembering (as we do in writing and reading), but to keep it embodied, to think and remember with our bodies as well as our verbalizing brains.

81

This last poem is self-reflexive, wrapping it all up tight in the first verse, then opening out again to praise the undestructive, uncompetitive generosity of the spirit that walks on the Way.

To my mind, the best reason for following the

Ma wang tui

text in reversing the order of the books is that the whole thing ends with a chapter (37) that provides a nobler conclusion than this one. But if you reverse the order, chapter 1 turns up in the middle of the book, and I simply cannot believe that that’s right. That poem is a beginning. It is the beginning.

Introduction

The

Tao Te Ching

was probably written about twenty-five hundred years ago, perhaps by a man called Lao Tzu, who may have lived at about the same time as Confucius. Nothing about it is certain except that it’s Chinese, and very old, and speaks to people everywhere as if it had been written yesterday.

The first

Tao Te Ching

I ever saw was the Paul Carus edition of 1898, bound in yellow cloth stamped with blue and red Chinese designs and characters. It was a venerable object of mystery, which I soon investigated, and found more fascinating inside than out. The book was my father’s; he read in it often. Once I saw him making notes from it and asked what he was doing. He said he was marking which chapters he’d like to have read at his funeral. We did read those chapters at his memorial service.

I have the book, now ninety-eight years old and further ornamented with red binding-tape to hold the back on, and have marked which chapters I’d like to have read at my funeral. In the Notes, I explain why I was so lucky to discover Lao Tzu in that particular edition. Here I will only say that I was lucky to discover him so young, so that I could live with his book my whole life long.

I also discuss other aspects of my version in the Notes—the how of it. Here I want to state very briefly the why of it.

The

Tao Te Ching

is partly in prose, partly in verse; but as we define poetry now, not by rhyme and meter but as a patterned intensity of language, the whole thing is poetry. I wanted to catch that poetry, its terse, strange beauty. Most translations have caught meanings in their net, but prosily, letting the beauty slip through. And in poetry, beauty is no ornament; it is the meaning. It is the truth. We have that on good authority.

Scholarly translations of the

Tao Te Ching

as a manual for rulers use a vocabulary that emphasizes the uniqueness of the Taoist “sage,” his masculinity, his authority. This language is perpetuated, and degraded, in most popular versions. I wanted a Book of the Way accessible to a present-day, unwise, unpowerful, and perhaps unmale reader, not seeking esoteric secrets, but listening for a voice that speaks to the soul. I would like that reader to see why people have loved the book for twenty-five hundred years.

It is the most lovable of all the great religious texts, funny, keen, kind, modest, indestructibly outrageous, and inexhaustibly refreshing. Of all the deep springs, this is the purest water. To me, it is also the deepest spring.

—Ursula K. Le Guin

Preface

This is a rendition, not a translation. I do not know any Chinese. I could approach the text at all only because Paul Carus, in his 1898 translation of the

Tao Te Ching

, printed the Chinese text with each character followed by a transliteration and a translation. My gratitude to him is unending.

To have the text thus made accessible was not only to have a Rosetta Stone for the book itself, but also to have a touchstone for comparing other English translations one with another. If I could focus on which word the translators were interpreting, I could begin to understand why they made the choice they did. I could compare various interpretations and see why they varied so tremendously; could see how much explanation, sometimes how much bias, was included in the translation; could discover for myself that several English meanings might lead me back to the same Chinese word. And, finally, for all my ignorance of the language, I could gain an intuition of the style, the gait and cadence, of the original, necessary to my ear and conscience if I was to try to reproduce it in English.

Without the access to the text that the Carus edition gave me, I would have been defeated by the differences among the translations, and could never have thought of following them as guides towards a version of my own. As it was, working from Carus’s text, I learned how to let them lead me into it, always using their knowledge, their scholarship, their decisions, as my light in darkness.

When you try to follow the Way, even if you wander off it all the time, good things happen though you do not deserve them. My work on the

Tao Te Ching

was very wandering indeed. I started in my twenties with a few chapters. Every decade or so I’d do another bit, and tell myself I’d sit down and really get to it, some day. The undeserved good thing that happened was that a true and genuine scholar of ancient Chinese and of Lao Tzu, Dr. J. P. Seaton of the University of North Carolina, saw some of my versions of bits of the

Tao Te Ching

(scurvily quoted without attribution by myself). He reprinted them with honor, and asked me for more. I do not think he knew what he was getting into. Of his invaluable teaching, his encouragement, his generosity, I can say only what Lao Tzu says at the end of the book:

Wise souls don’t hoard;
the more they do for others the more they have,
the more they give the richer they are.

As for the Way, the Way that can be spoken of is not the constant Way;
As for names, the name that can be named is not the constant name.
The nameless is the beginning of the ten thousand things;
The named is the mother of the ten thousand things.

Therefore, those constantly without desires, by this means will perceive its subtlety.
Those constantly with desires, by this means will see only that which they yearn for and seek.

These two together emerge;
They have different names yet they’re called the same;
That which is even more profound that the profound—
The gateway of all subtleties.

When everyone in the world knows the beautiful as beautiful, ugliness comes into being;
When everyone knows the good, then the not good comes to be.
The mutual production of being and nonbeing,
The mutual completion of difficult and easy,
The mutual formation of long and short,
The mutual filling of high and low,
The mutual harmony of tone and voice,
The mutual following of front and back—
These are all constants.

Therefore the Sage dwells in nonactive affairs and practices the wordless teaching.
The ten thousand things arise, but he doesn’t begin them;
He acts on their behalf, but he doesn’t make them dependent;
He accomplishes his tasks, but he doesn’t dwell on them;
It is only because he doesn’t dwell on them, that they therefore do not leave them.

By not elevating the worthy, you bring it about that people will not compete.
By not valuing goods that are hard to obtain, you bring it about that people will not act like thieves.
By not displaying the desirable you bring it about that people will not be confused.

Therefore, in the government of the Sage:
He empties their minds,
An fills their bellies.
Weakens their ambition,
And strengthens their bones.

He constantly causes the people to be without knowledge and without desires.
If he can bring it about that those with knowledge simply do not dare to act,
Then there is nothing that will not be in order.

The Way is empty;
Yet when you use it, you never need fill it again.
Like an abyss! It seems to be the ancestor of the ten thousand things.

If files down sharp edges;
Unties the tangles;
Softens the glare;
And settles the dust.

Submerged! It seems perhaps to exist.
We don’t know whose child it is;
It seems to have [even] preceded the Lord.

Heaven and Earth are not humane;
They regard the the thousand things as straw dogs.
The Sage is not humane;
He regards the common people as straw dogs.

The space between Heaven and Earth—is it not like a bellow?
It is empty and yet not depleted;
Move it and more [always] comes out.
Much learning means frequent exhaustions.
That’s not so good as holding on to the mean.

The valley spirit never dies;
We call it the mysterious female.
The gates of the mysterious female—
These we call the roots of Heaven and Earth.
Subtle yet everlasting! It seems to exist.
In being used, it is not exhausted.

Heaven endures; Earth lasts a long time.
The reason why Heaven and Earth can endure and last a long time—
Is that they do not live for themselves.
Therefore they can long endure.

Therefore the Sage:
Puts himself in the background yet finds himself in the foreground;
Puts self-concern out of [his mind], yet finds self-concern in the fore;
Puts self-concern out of [his mind], yet finds that his self-concern is preserved.
Is it not because he has no self-interest,
That he is therefore able to realize his self-interest?

The highest good is like water;
Water is good at benefiting the ten thousand things and yet it [does not] compete [with them].
It dwells in places the masses of people detest,
Therefore it is close to the Way.

In dwelling, the good thing is the land;
In the mind, the good thing is depth;
In giving, the good thing is [being like] Heaven;
In speaking, the good thing is sincerity;
In governing, the good thing is order;
In affairs, the good thing is ability;
In activity, the good thing is timeliness.

It is only because it does not compete, that therefore it is without fault.

To hold it upright and fill it,
Is not so good as stopping [in time].
When you pound it out and give it a point,
It won’t be preserved very long.
When gold and jade fill your rooms,
You’ll never be able to protect them.
Arrogance and pride with wealth and rank,
On their own bring on disaster.
When the deed is accomplished you retire;
Such is Heaven’s Way!

In nourishing the soul and embracing the One—can you do it without letting them leave?
In concentrating your breath and making it soft—can you [make it like that of] a child?
In cultivating and cleaning your profound mirror—can you do it so that it has no blemish?
In loving the people and giving life to the state—can you do it without using knowledge?
In opening and closing the gates of Heaven—can you play the part of the female?
In understanding all within the four reaches—can you do it without using knowledge?

Give birth to them and nourish them.
Give birth to them but don’t try to own them;
Help them to grow but don’t rule them.
This is called Profound Virtue.

Thirty spokes unite in one hub;
It is precisely where there is nothing, that we find the usefulness of the wheel.
We fire clay and make vessels;
It is precisely where there’s no substance, that we find the usefulness of clay pots.
We chisel out doors and windows;
It is precisely in these empty spaces, that we find the usefulness of the room.
Therefore, we regard having something as beneficial;
But having nothing as useful.

The five colors cause one’s eyes to go blind.
Racing horses and hunting cause one’s mind to go mad.
Goods that are hard to obtain pose an obstacle to one’s travels.
The five flavors confuse one’s palate.
The five tones cause one’s ears to go deaf.

Therefore, in the government of the Sage:
He’s for the belly and not for the eyes.
Thus he rejects that and take this.

“Regard favor and disgrace with alarm.”
“Respect great distress as you do your own person.”
What do I mean I say “Regard favor and disgrace with alarm”?
Favor is inferior.
If you get it—be alarmed!
If you lose it—be alarmed!
This is what I mean when I say “Regard favor and disgrace with alarm.”
What do I mean when I say “Respect great distress as you do your won person”?
The reason why I have distress
Is that I have a body.
If I had no body, what distress would I have?
Therefore, to one who values acting for himself over acting on behalf of the world,
You can entrust the world.
And to one who in being parsimonious regards his person as equal to the world,
You can turn over the world.

We look at it but do not see it;
We name this “the minute.”
We listen to it but do not hear it;
We name this “the rarefied.”
We touch it but do not hold it;
We name this “the level and smooth.”

These three cannot be examined to the limit.
Thus they merge together as one.
“One”—there is nothing more encompassing above it,
And nothing smaller below it.
Boundless, formless! It cannot be named,
And returns to the state of no-thing.

This is called the formless form,
The substanceless image.
This is called the subtle and indistinct.
Follow it and you won’t see its back;
Greet it and you won’t see its head.
Hold on to the Way of the present—
To manage the things of the present,
And to know the ancient beginning.
This is called the beginning of the thread of the Way.

The one who was skilled at practicing the Way in antiquity,
Was subtle and profound, mysterious and penetratingly wise.
His depth cannot be known.
It is only because he cannot be known
That therefore were I forced to describe him I’d say:

Hesitant was he! Like someone crossing a river in winter.
Undecided was he! As though in fear of his neighbors on all four sides.
Solemn and polite was he! Like a guest.
Scattered and dispersed was he! Like an ice as it melts
Genuine, unformed was he! Like uncarved wood.
Merged, undifferentiated was he! Like muddy water.
Broad and expansive was he! Like a valley.

If you take muddy water and still it, it gradually becomes clear.
If you bring something to rest in order to move it, it gradually comes alive.
The one who preserved this Way does not desire to be full;
Therefore he can wear out with no need to be renewed.

Take emptiness to the limit;
Maintain tranquility in the center.

The ten thousand things—side-by-side they arise;
And by this I see their return.
Things [come forth] in great numbers;
Each one returns to its root.
This is called tranquility.
“Tranquility”—This means to return to your fate.
To return to your fate is to be constant;
To know the constant is to be wise.
Not to know the constant is to be reckless and wild;
If you’re reckless and wild, your actions will lead to misfortune.

To know the constant is to be all-embracing;
To be all-embracing is to be impartial;
To be impartial is to be kingly;
To be kingly is to be [like] Heaven;
To be [like] Heaven is to be [one with] the Dao;
If you’re [one with] the Dao, to the end of your days you’ll suffer no harm.

With the highest [kind of rulers], those below simply know they exist.
With those one step down—they love and praise them.
With those one further step down—they fear them.
And with those at the bottom—they ridicule and insult them.

When trust is insufficient, there will be no trust [in them].
Hesitant, undecided! Like this is his respect for speaking.

Therefore, when the Great Way is rejected, it is then that we have the virtues of humanity and righteousness;
When knowledge and wisdom appear, it is then that there is great hypocrisy;
When the six relations are not in harmony, it is then that we have filial piety and compassion;
And when the country is in chaos and confusion, it is then that there are virtuous officials.

Eliminate sageliness, throw away knowledge,
And the people will benefit a hundredfold.
Eliminate humanity, throw away righteousness,
And the people will return to filial piety and compassion.
Eliminate craftiness, throw away profit,
Then we will have no robbers and thieves.

These three sayings—
Regard as a text are not yet complete.
Thus, we must see to it that they have the following appended:

Manifest plainness and embrace the genuine;
Lessen self-interest and make few your desires;
Eliminate learning and have no undue concern.

Agreement and angry rejection;
How great is the difference between them?
Beautiful and ugly;
What’s it like—the difference between them?
The one who is feared by others,
Must also because of this fear other men.
Wild, unrestrained! It will never come to an end!

The multitudes are peaceful and happy;
Like climbing a terrace in springtime to feast at the tai-lao sacrifice.
But I’m tranquil and quiet—not yet having given any sign.
Like a child who has not yet smiled.
Tired and exhausted—as though I have no place to return.
The multitudes all have a surplus.
I alone seem to be lacking.
Mine is the mind of a fool—ignorant and stupid!
The common people see things clearly;
I alone am in the dark.
The common people discriminate and make fine distinctions;
I alone am muddled and confused.
Formless am I! Like the ocean;
Shapeless am I! As though I have nothing in which I can rest.
The masses all have their reasons [for acting];
I alone am stupid and obstinate like a rustic.
But my desires alone differ from those of others—
For I value drawing sustenance from the Mother.

The character of great virtue follows alone from the Way.
As for the nature of the Way—it’s shapeless and formless.
Formless! Shapeless! Inside there are images.
Shapeless! Formless! Inside there are things.
Hidden! Obscure! Inside there are essences.
These essences are very real;
Inside them is the proof.

From the present back to the past,
Its name has never gone away.
It is by this that we comply with the father of the multitude [of things].
How do I know that the father of the multitude is so?
By this.

Bent over, you’ll be preserved whole;
When twisted, you’ll be upright;
When hollowed out, you’ll be full;
When worn out, you’ll be renewed;
When you have little, you’ll attain [much];
With much, you’ll be confused.

Therefore the Sage holds on to the One and in this way becomes the shepherd of the world.
He does not show himself off; therefore he becomes prominent.
He does not put himself on display; therefore he brightly shines.
He does not brag about himself; therefore he receives credit.
He does not praise his own deeds; therefore he can long endure.

It is only because he does not compete that, therefore, no one is able to compete with him.
The so-called “Bent over you’ll be preserved whole” of the ancients
Was an expression that was really close to it!
Truly “wholeness” will belong to him.

To rarely speak—such is [the way of] Nature.
Fierce winds don’t last the whole morning;
Torrential rains don’t last the whole day.
Who makes these things?
If even Heaven and Earth can’t make these last long—
How much the more is this true for man?!

Therefore, one who devotes himself to the Way is one with the Way;
One who [devotes himself to] Virtue is one with that Virtue;
And one who [devotes himself to] losing is one with that loss.
To the one who is one with Virtue, the Way also gives Virtue;
While for the one who is one with his loss, the Way also disregards him.

One who boasts is not established;
One who shows himself off does not become prominent;
One who puts himself on display does not brightly shine;
One who brags about himself gests no credit;
One who praises himself does not long endure.

In the Way, such things are called:
“Surplus food and redundant action.”
And with things—there are those who hate them.
Therefore, the one with the Way in them does not dwell.

There was something formed out of chaos,
That was born before Heaven and Earth.
Quiet and Still! Pure and deep!
It stands on its own and does not change.
It can be regarded as the mother of Heaven and Earth.
I do not yet know its name:
I “style” it “the Way.”
Were I forced to give it a name, I would call it “the Great.”

“Great” means “to depart”;
“To depart” means “to be far away”;
And “to be far away” means “to return.”

The Way is great;
Heaven is great;
Earth is great;
And the king is also great.
In the country there are four greats, and the king occupies one place among them.

Man models himself on the Earth;
The Earth models itself on Heaven;
Heaven models itself on the Way;
And the Way models itself on that which is so on its own.

The heavy is the root of the light;
Tranquility is the loard of agitation.

Therefore the gentleman, in traveling all day, does not get far away from his luggage carts.
When he’s safely inside a walled-in [protected] hostel and resting at ease—only then does he transcend all concern.
How can the king of ten thousand chariots treat his own person more lightly than the whole world?!

If you regard things too lightly, then you lose the basic;
If you’re agitated, you lose the “lord.”

The good traveler leaves no track behind;
The good speaker [speaks] without blemish or flaw;
The good counter doesn’t use tallies or chips;
The good closer of doors does so without bolt or lock, and yet the door cannot be opened;
The good tier of knots ties without rope or cord, yet his knots can’t be undone.

Therefore the Sage is constantly good at saving men and never rejects anyone;
And with things, he never rejects useful goods.
This is called Doubly Bright.

Therefore the good man is the teacher of the good,
And the bad man is the raw material for the good.
To not value one’s teacher and not cherish the raw goods—
Though one had great knowledge, he would still be greatly confused.
This is called the Essential of the Sublime.

When you know the male yet hold on to the female,
You’ll be the ravine of the country.
When you’re the ravine of the country,
Your constant virtue will not leave.
And when your constant virtue doesn’t leave,
You’ll return to the state of the infant.

When you know the pure yet hold on to the soiled,
You’ll be the valley of the country.
When you’re the valley of the country,
Your constant virtue is complete.
And when your constant virtue is complete,
You’ll return to the state of uncarved wood.

When you know the white yet hold on to the black,
You’ll be the model for the country.
And when you’re the model for the country,
Your constant virtue will not go astray.
And when your constant virtue does not go astray,
You’ll return to the condition which has no limit.

When uncarved wood is cut up, it’s turned into vessels;
When the Sage is used, he becomes the Head of Officials.
Truly, great carving is done without splitting up.

For those who would like to take control of thw world and act on it—
I see that with this they simply will not succeed.
The world is a sacred vessel;
It is not something that can be acted upon.
Those who act on it destroy it;
Those who hold on to it lose it.

With things—some go forward, others follow;
Some are hot, others submissive and weak;
Some rise up while others fall down.
Therefore the Sage:
Rejects the extreme, the excessive, and the extravagant.

Those who assist their rulers with the Way,
Don’t use weapons to commit violence in the world.
Such deeds easily rebound.
In places where armies are stationed, thorns and brambles will grow.
The good [general] achieves his result and that’s all;
He does not use the occasion to seize strength from it.

He achieves his result but does not become arrogant;
He achieves his result but does not praise his deeds;
He achieves his result and yet does not brag.
He achieves his result, yet he abides with the result because he has no choice.
This is called achieving one’s result [without] using force.

When things reach their primes, they get old;
We called this “not the Way.”
What is not the Way will come to an early end.

As for weapons—they are instruments of ill omen.
And among things there are those that hate them.
Therefore, the one who has the Way, with them does not dwell.
When the gentleman is at home, he honors the left;
When at war, he honors the right.
Therefore, weapons are not the instrument of the gentleman—
Weapons are instruments of ill omen.
When you have no choice but to use them, it’s best to remain tranquil and calm.
You should never look upon them as things of beauty.
If you see them as beautiful things—this is to delight in the killing of men.
And when you delight in the killing of men, you’ll not realize your goal in the land.

Therefore, in happy events we honor the left,
But in mourning we honor the right.
Therefore, the lieutenant general stands on the left;
And the supreme general stands on the right.
Which is to say, they arrange themselves as they would at a funeral.
When multitudes of people are killed, we stand before them in sorrow and grief.
When we’re victorious in battle, we treat the occasion like a funeral ceremony.

The Dao is constantly nameless.
Though in its natural state it seems small, no one in the world dares to treat it as a subject.
Were marquises and kings able to maintain it,
The ten thousand things would submit to them on their own,
And Heaven and Earth would unite to send forth sweet dew.
By nature it would fall equally on all things, with no one among the people ordering that it be so.

As soon as we start to establish a system, we have names.
And as soon as there are set names,
Then you must also know that it’s time to stop.
By knowing to stop—in this way you’ll come to no harm.
The Way’s presence in the world
Is like the relationship of small valley [streams] to rivers and seas.

To understand others is to be knowledgeable;
To understand yourself is to be wise.
To conquer others is to have strength;
To conquer yourself is to be strong.
To know when you have enough is to be rich.
To go forward with strength is to have ambition.
To not lose your place is to last long.
To die but not be forgotten—that’s [true] long life.

The Way floats and drifts;
It can go left or right.
It accomplishes its tasks and completes its affairs, and yet for this it is not given a name.
The ten thousand things entrust their lives to it, and yet it does not act as their master.
Thus it is constantly without desires.
It can be named with the things that are small.
The ten thousand things entrust their lives to it, and yet it does not act as their master.
It can be named with the things that are great.

Therefore the Sage’s ability to accomplish the great
Comes from his not playing the role of the great.
Therefore he is able to accomplish the great.

Hold on to the Great Image and the whole world will come to you.
Come to you and suffer no harm; but rather know great safety and peace.
Music and food—for these passing travelers stop.
Therefore, of the Dao’s speaking, we say:
Insipid, it is! It’s lack of flavor.
When you look at it, it’s not sufficient to be seen;
When you listen to it, it’s not sufficient to be heard;
Yet when you use it, it can’t be used up.

If you wish to shrink it,
You must certainly stretch it.
If you wish to weaken it,
You must certainly strengthen it.
If you wish to desert it,
You must certainly work closely with it.
If you wish to snatch something from it,
You must certainly give something to it.
This is called the Subtle Light.
The submissive and weak conquer the strong.

Fish should not be taken out of the depths;
The state’s sharp weapons should not be shown to the people.

The Dao is constantly nameless.
Were Marquises and kings able to maintain it,
The ten thousand things would transform on their own.
Having transformed, were their desires to become active,
I would subdue them with the nameless simplicity.
Having subdued them with the nameless simplicity,
I would not disgrace them.
By not being disgraced, they will be tranquil.
And Heaven and Earth will of themselves be correct and right.

The highest virtue is not virtuous; therefore it truly has virtue.
The lowest virtue never loses sight of its virtue; therefore it has no true virtue.

The highest virtue takes no action, yet it has no reason for acting this way;
The highest humanity takes action, yet it has no reason for acting this way;
The highest righteousness takes action, and it has its reason for acting this way;
The highest propriety takes action, and when no one responds to it, then it angrily rolls up its sleeves and forces people to comply.

Therefore, when the Way is lost, only then do we have virtue;
When virtue is lost, only then do we have humanity;
When humanity is lost, only then do we have righteousness;
And when righteousness is lost, only then do we have propriety.

As for propriety, it’s but the thin edge of loyalty and sincerity, and the beginning of disorder.
And foreknowledge is but the flower of the Way, and the beginning of stupidity.

Therefore the Great Man
Dwells in the thick and doesn’t dwell in the thin;
Dwells in the fruit and doesn’t dwell in the flower.
Therefore, he rejects that and takes this.

Of those in the past that attained the One—
Heaven, by attaining the One became clear;
Earth, by attaining the One became stable;
Gods, by attaining the One became divine;
Valley, by attaining the One became full;
Marquises and kings, by attaining the One made the whole land ordered and secure.

Taking this to its logical conclusion we would say—
If Heaven were not by means of it clear, it would, I’m afraid, shatter;
If the Earth were not by means of it stable, it would, I’m afraid, let go.
If the gods were not by means of it divine, they would, I’m afraid, be powerless.
If valley were not by means of it full, they would, [I’m afraid,] dry up.
And if marquises and kings were not by means of it noble and high, they would, I’m afraid, topple and fall.

Therefore, it must be the case that the noble has the base as its root;
And it must be the case that the high has the low for its foundation.
Thus, for this reason, marquises and kings call themselves “The Orphan,” “The Widower,” and “The One Without Grain.”
This is taking the base as one’s root, is it not?!

Therefore, they regard their large numbers of carriages as having no carriage.
And because of this, they desire not to dazzle and glitter like jade,
But to remain firm and strong like stone.

“Reversal” is the movement of the Dao;
“Weakness” is the function of the Dao.

The things of the world originate in being,
And being originates in nonbeing.

When the highest type of men hear the Way, with diligence thye’re able to practice it;
When the average men hear the Way, some things they retain and others they lose;
When the lowest type of men hear the Way, they laugh out loud at it.
If they didn’t laught at it, it couldn’t be regarded as the Way.

Therefore, there is a set saying about this that goes:
The bright Way appears to be dark;
The Way that goes forward appears to retreat;
The smooth Way appears to be uneven;
The highest virtue [is empty] like a valley;
The purest white appears to be soiled;
Vast virtue appears to be insufficient;
Firm virtue appears thin and weak;
The simplest reality appears to change.

The Great Square has no corners;
The Great Vessel takes long to complete;
The Great Tone makes little sound;
The Great Image has no shape.

The Way is Great but has no name.
Only the Way is good at beginning things and also good at bringing things to completion.

The Way gave birth to the One.
The One gave birth to the Two.
The Two gave birth to the Three.
And the Three gave birth to the ten thousand things.
The ten thousand things carry Yin on their backs and wrap their arms around Yang.
Through the blending of the qi they arrive at a state of harmony.

The things that are hated by the whole world
Are to be orphaned, widowed, and have no grain.
Yet kings and dukes take these as their names.
Thus with all things—some are increased by taking away;
While some are diminished by adding on.

Therefore, what other men teach,
[I] will also consider and then teach to others.
Thus, “The strong and violent do not come to a natural end.”
I will take this as the father of my studies.

The softest, most pliable thing in the world runs roughshod over the firmest things in the world.
that which has no substance gets into that which has no spaces or cracks.
I therefore know that there is benefit in taking no action.
The wordless teaching, the benefit of taking no action—
Few in the world can realize these!

Fame or your body—which is more dear?
Your body or possessions—which is worth more?
Gain or loss—in which is there harm?
If your desires are great, you’re bound to be extravagant;
If your store much away, you’re bound to lose a great deal.
Therefore, if you know contentment, you’ll not be disgraced.
If you know when to stop, you’ll suffer no harm.
And in this way you can last a very long time.

Great completion seems incomplete;
Yet its usefulness is never exhausted.
Great fullness seems to be empty;
Yet its usefulness is never used up.
Great straightness seems to be bent.
Great skill seems to be clumsy.
Great surplus seems to stammer.
Activity overcomes cold;
Tranquility overcomes heat.
If you’re quiet and tranquil you can become the ruler of the world.

When the world has the Way, ambling horses are retired to fertilize [fields].
When the world lacks the Way, war horses are reared in the suburbs.

Of crimes—none is greater than having things that one desires;
Of disasters—none is greater than not knowing when one has enough.
Of defects—none brings more sorrow than one desire to attain.
Therefore, the contentment one has when he knows that he has enough, is abiding contentment indeed.

No need to leave your door to know the whole world;
No need to peer through your windows to know the Way of Heaven.
The farther you go, the less you know.

Therefore the Sage knows without going,
Names without seeing,
And completes without doing a thing.

Those who work at their studies increase day after day;
Those who have heard the Dao decrease day after day.
They decrease and decrease, till they get to the point where they do nothing.
They do nothing and yet there’s nothing left undone.
When someone wants to take control of the world, he must always be unconcerned with affairs.
For in a case where he’s concerned with affairs,
He’ll be unworthy, as well, of taking control of the world.

The Sage constantly has no [set] mind;
He takes the mind of the common people as his mind.
Those who are good he regards as good;
Those who are not good he also regards as good.
[In this way] he attains goodness.
Those who are trustworthy he trusts;
And those who are not trustworthy he also trusts.
[In this way] he gets their trust.
As for the Sage’s presence in the world—he is one with it.
And with the world he merges his mind.
The common people all fix their eyes and ears on him.
And the Sage treats them all as his children.

We come out into life and go back into death.
The companions of life are thirteen;
The companions of death are thirteen;
And yet people, because they regard life as LIFE, in all of their actions move towards the thirteen that belong to the realm of death.
Now, why is this so?
It’s because they regard life as LIFE.

You’ve no doubt heard of those who are good at holding on to life:
When walking through hills, they don’t avoid rhinos and tigers;
When they go into battle, they don’t put on armor or shields;
The rhino has no place to probe with its horn;
The tiger finds no place to put its claws.
And weapons find no place to hold their blades.
Now, why is this so?
Because there is no place for death in them.

The Way gives birth to them and Virtue nourishes them;
Substance gives them form and their unique capacities complete them.
Therefore the ten thousand things venerate the Way and honor Virtue.
As for their veneration of the Way and their honoring of Virtue—
No one rewards them for it; it’s constantly so on its own.

The Way gives birth to them, nourishes them, matures them, completes them, rests them, rears them, supports them, and protects them.
It gives birth to them but doesn’t try to own them;
It acts on their behalf but doesn’t make them dependent;
It matures them but doesn’t rule them.
This we call Profound Virtue.

The world had a beginning,
Which can be considered the mother of the world.
Having attained the mother, in order to understand her children.
If you return and hold on to the mother, till the end of your life you’ll suffer no harm.

Block up the holes;
Close the doors;
And till the end of your life you’ll not labor.
Open the holes;
Meddle in affairs;
And till the end of your life you’ll not be saved.

To receive the small is called “discernment.”
To hold on to the pliant is called “strength.”
If you use the rays to return to the bright light,
You’ll not abandon your life to peril.
This is called Following the Constant.

Were I to have the least bit of knowledge, in walking on a Great Rod, it’s only going astray that I would fear.
The Great Way is very level;
But people greatly delight in tortuous paths.

The courts are swept very clean;
While the fields are full of weeds;
And the granaries are all empty.
Their clothing—richly embroidered and colored;
While at their waists they carry sharp swords.
They gorge themselves on food, and of possessions and goods they have plenty.

This is called thievery!
And thievery certainly isn’t the Way!

What is firmly set up can’t be pulled down;
What is firmly embraced cannot slip free.
And your sons and grandsons, as a result, will sacrifice without end.

When you cultivate it in your person, your virtue will then be genuine;
When you cultivate it in your family, your virtue will then be overflow;
When you cultivate it in your village, your virtue will then be long lasting;
When you cultivate it in your state, your virtue will then be abundant;
And when you cultivate it throughout the world, your virtue will then be widespread.

Use the individual to examine the individual;
Use the family to examine the family;
Use the village to examine the village;
Use the state to examine the state;
And use the world to examine the world;
How do I know that the world is so?
By this.

One who embraces the fullness of Virtue,
Can be compared to a newborn babe.
Wasps and scorpions, snakes and vipers do not sting him;
Birds of prey and fierce beasts do not seize him;
His bones and muscles are weak and pliant, yet his grasp is firm;
He does not yet know the meeting of male and female, yet his organ is aroused—
This is because his essence is at its height.
He can scream all day, yet he won’t become hoarse—
This is because his harmony is at its height.

To know harmony is called “the constant”;
To know the constant is called “being wise”;
To add on to life is called a “bad omen”;
For the mind to control the breath—that’s called “forcing things.”

When things reach their prime they get old;
This is called “not the Way.”
What is not the Way will come to an early end.

Those who know don’t talk about it; those who talk don’t know it.

He blocks up his holes,
Closes his doors,
Softens the glare,
Settles the dust,
Files down the sharp edges,
And unties the tangles.
This is called Profound Union.

Therefore, there is no way to get intimate with him,
But there is also no way to shun him.
There is no way to benefit him,
But there is also no way to harm him.
There is no way to ennoble him,
But there is also no way to debase him.
For this very reason he’s the noblest thing in the world.

Use the upright and correct to order the state;
Use surprise tactics when you use troops;
Use unconcern with affairs to take control of the world.

How do I know that this is so?
Well, the more taboos and prohibitions there are in the world, the poorer the people will be;
The more sharp weapons the people possess, the more muddled the states will be;
The more knowledge and skill people have, the more novel things will appear;
The more legal matters are made prominent, the more robbers and thieves there will be.

Therefore, the words of the Sage say:
I do nothing, and the people of themselves are transformed;
I love tranquility, and the people of themselves are upright;
I’m unconcerned with affairs, and the people of themselves become rich.
I desire not to desire, and the people of themselves are [genuine and simple, like] uncarved wood.

When the government is muddled and confused,
The people are genuine and sincere.
When the government is discriminate and clear,
The state is crafy and cunning.

Disaster is that on which good fortune depends.
Good fortune is that in which disaster’s concealed.
Who knows where it will end?
For there is no [fixed] “correct.”
The “correct” turns into the “deviant”;
And “good” turns into “evil.”
People’s state of confusion
Has certainly existed for a long time.
Therefore be square but don’t cut;
Be sharp but don’t stab;
Be straightforward but not unrestrained;
Be bright but don’t dazzle.

For ordering humanity and serving Heaven, nothing’s so good as being sparing.
For only if you are sparing can you, therefore, early submit [to the Way].
Early submission—this is called to repeatedly accumulate Virtue.
If you repeatedly accumulate Virtue, then there is nothing you can’t overcome.
When there is nothing you can’t overcome, no one knows where it will end.
When no one knows where it will end, you can possess the state.
And when you possess the mother of the state, you can last a very long time.
This is called [having] deep roots and a firm base,
It’s the Way of long life and long-lasting vision.

Ruling a large state is like cooking small fish.

When you use the Way to govern the world, evil spirits won’t have godlike power.
Actually, it’s not that evil spirits won’t have godlike power,
It’s that their power will not harm men.
But it’s not [just] that their power won’t harm men,
The Sage, also, will not harm them.
Since these two do not harm others,
Therefore their Virtues intermingle and return to them.

The large state is like the lower part of a river;
It is the female of the world;
It is the meeting point of the world.
The female constantly overcomes the male with tranquility.
Because she is tranquil, therefore she is fittingly underneath.

The large state—if it is below the small state, then it takes over the small state;
The small state—if it is below the large state, then it is taken over by the large state.
Therefore some by being low take over,
And some by being low are taken over.

Therefore the large state merely desires to unite and rear others;
While the small state merely desires to enter and serve others.
If both get what they want,
Then the large state should fittingly be underneath.

The Way is that toward which all things flow.
It is the treasure of the good man,
And that which protects the bad.

Beautiful words can be bought and sold;
Honored deeds can be presented to others as gifts;
[Even with] things that people regard as no good—will they be rejected?
Therefore, when the So of Heaven is being enthroned or the Three Ministers installed,
Though you might salture them which disks of jade preceded by teams of four horses,
That’s not so good as sitting still and offering this.
The reason why the ancients valued this—what was it?
Did they not say, “Those who seek, with this will attain, and those who commit offenses, with this will escape”?!
Therefore, it’s the most valued thing in the world.

Act without acting;
Serve without concern for affairs;
Find flavor in what has no flavor.

Regard the small as large and the few as many,
And repay resentment with kindness.
Plan for the difficult while it is easy;
Act on the large while it’s minute.
The most difficult things in the world begin as things that are easy;
The largest things in the world arise from the minute.
Therefore the Sage, to the end does not strive to do the great,
And as a result, he is able to accomplish the great;
Those who too lightly agree will necessarily be trusted by few;
And those who regard many things as easy will necessarily [end up] with many difficulties.
Therefore, even the Sage regards things as difficult,
And as a result, in the end he has no difficulty.

What is at rest is easy to hold;
What has not yet given a sign is easy to plan for;
The brittle is easily shattered;
The minute is easily scattered;
Act on it before it comes into being;
Order it before it turns into chaos.

A tree [so big] that it takes both arms to surround starts out as the tiniest shoot;
A nine-story terrace rises up from a basket of dirt.
A high place one hundred, one thousand feet high begins from under your feet.

Those who act on it ruin it;
Those who hold on to it lose it.
Therefore the Sage does not act,
And as a result, he doesn’t ruin [things];
He does not hold on to [things],
And as a result, he doesn’t lose [things];
In people’s handling of affairs, they always ruin things when they’re right at the point of completion.
Therefore we say, “If you’re as careful at the end as you were at the beginning, you’ll have no failures.”
Therefore the Sage desires not to desire and doesn’t value goods that are hard to obtain;
He learns not to learn and returns to what the masses pass by;
He could help all things to be natural, yet he dare not do it.

Those who practiced the Way in antiquity,
Did not use it to enlighten the people.
Rather, they used it to make them dumb.
Now the reason why people are difficult to rule is because of their knowledge;
As a result, to use knowledge to rule the state
Is thievery of the state;
To use ignorance to rule the state
Is kindness to the state.
One who constantly understands these two,
Also [understands] the principle.
To constantly understand the principle—
This is called Profound Virtue.
Profound Virtue is deep, is far-reaching,
And together with things it returns.
Thus we arrive at the Great Accord.

The reason why rivers and oceans are able to be the kings of the one hundred valleys is that they are good at being below them.
for this reason they are able to be the kings of the one hundred valleys.

Therefore in the Sage’s desire to be above the people,
He must in his speech be below them.
And in his desire to be at the front of the people,
He must in his person be behind them.
Thus he dwells above, yet the people do not regard him as heavey;
And he dwells in front, yet the people do not see him as posing a threat.
The whole world delights in his praise and never tires of him.
Is it not because he is not contentious,
That, as a result, no one in the world can contend with him?!

The whole world says, I’m Great;
Great, yet unlike [everyone else],
But it’s precisely because I’m unlike [everyone else], that I’m therefore able to be Great.
Were I like [everyone else], for a long time now I’d have seemed insignificant and small.

I constantly have three treasures;
Hold on to them and treasure them.
The first is compassion;
The second is frugality;
And the third is not presuming to be at the forefront in the world.
Now, it’s because I’m compassionate that I therefore can be courageous;
And it’s because I’m frugal that I therefore can be magnamimous;
And it’s because I don’t presume to be at the forefront in the world that I therefore can be the head of those with complete talent.
Now, if you abandon this compassion and yet try to be courageous,
And if you abandon this frugality and yet try to be magnanimous,
And if you abandon this staying behind and yet go to the fore,
Then you will die.
If with compassion you attack, then you’ll win;
If you defend, then you’ll stand firm.

When Heaven’s about to establish him,
It’s as though he surrounds him with the protective wall of compassion.

Therefore, one who is good at being a warrior doesn’t make a show of his might;
One who is good in battle doesn’t get angry;
One who is good at defeating the enemy doesn’t engage him.
And one who is good at using men places himself below them.
This is called the virtue of not competing;
This is called [correctly] using men;
This is called matching Heaven.
It’s the high point of the past.

Those who use weapons have a saying which goes:
“I don’t presume to act like the host, and instead play the part of the guest;
I don’t advance an inch, but rather retreat a foot.”
This is called moving forward without moving forword—
Rolling up one’s sleeves without baring one’s arms—
Grasping firmly without holding a weapon—
And enticing to fight when there’s no opponent.
Of disasters, none is greater than [thinking] you have no rival.
To think you have no rival is to come close to losing my treasures.
Therefore, when weapons are raised and [the opponents] are farily well matched,
Then it’s the one who feels grief that will win.

My words are easy to understand,
And easy to put into practice.
Yet no one in the world can understand them,
And no one can put them into practice.
Now my words have an ancestor, and my deeds have a lord,
And it’s simply because [people] have no understanding [of them], that they therefore don’t understand me.
But when those who understand me are few, then I’m of great value.
Therefore the Sage wears coarse woolen cloth, but inside it he holds on to jade.

To know you don’t know is best.
Not to know you [don’t] know is a flaw.
Therefore, the Sage’s not being flawed
Stems from his recognizing a flaw as a flaw.
Therefore, he is flawless.

When the people don’t respect those in power, then what they greatly fear is about to arrive.

Don’t narrow the size of the places in which they live;
Don’t oppress them in their means of livelihood.
It’s simply because you do not oppress them, that they therefore will not be fed up.
Therefore the Sage knows himself but doesn’t show himself;
he cherishes himself but doesn’t value himself.
For this reason, he rejects that and takes this.

If you’re brave in being daring, you’ll be killed;
If you’re brave in not being daring, you’ll live.
With these two things, in one case there’s profit, in the other there’s harm.
The things Heaven hates—who knows why?
The Way of Heaven is not to fight yet to be good at winning—
Not to speak yet skillfully respond—
No one summons it, yet it comes on its own—
To be at ease yet carefully plan.
Heaven’s net is large and vast;
Its mesh may be coarse yet nothing slips through.

If the people were constant [in their behavior] and yet did not fear death,
How could you use execution to intimidate them?
If you brought it about that the people were constant [in their behavior] and moreover feared, and [we] took those who behaved in abnormal ways and killed them—who would dare act in this way?!
If the people are constant and moreover necessarily fear death, then we constantly have the one in charge of executions.
Now killing people in place of the one in charge of executions, this [is like] cutting wood in place of the head carpenter.
And of those who cut wood in place of the head carpenter, very few do not hurt their hands!

The reason why people starve,
Is because they take so much in tax-grain.
Therefore they starve.
The reason why the common people cannot be ruled,
Is because their superiors have their reason for acting.
Therefore they cannot be ruled.

The reason why people take death lightly,
Is because they so avidly seek after life.
Therefore they take death lightly.
Only those who do not act for the purpose of living—
Only these are superior to those who value life.

When people are born, they’re supple and soft;
Whey they die, they end up stretched out firm and rigid;
When the ten thousand things and grasses and trees are alive, they’re supple and pliant;
When they’re dead, they’re withered and dried out.
Therefore we say that the firm and rigid are compassions of death,
While the supple, the soft, the weak, and the delicate are compassions of life.
If a soldier is rigid, he won’t win;
If a tree is rigid, it will come to its end.
Rigidity and power occupy the inferior position;
Suppleness, softness, weakness, and delicateness occupy the superior position.

The Way of Heaven is like the flexing of a bow.
The high it presses down; the low it raises up.
From those with a surplus it takes away; to those without enough it adds on.
Therefore the way of Heaven—
Is to reduce the excessive and increase the insufficient;
The Way of Man—
Is to reduce the insufficient and offer more to the excessive.
Now, who is able to have a surplus and use it to offer to Heaven?
Clearly, it’s only the one who possesses the Way.
Therefore the Sage—
Take actions but does not possess them;
Accomplishes his tasks but does not dwell on them.
Like this, is his desire not to make a display of his worthiness.

In the whole world, nothing is softer and weaker than water.
And yet for attacking the hard and strong, nothing can bear it,
Because there is nothing you can use to replace it.
That water can defeat the unyielding—
That the weak can defeat the strong—
There is no one in the whole world who doesn’t know it,
And yet there is no one who can put it into practice.
For this reason, the words of the Sage say:
To take on yourself the disgrace of the state—this is called being the lord of [the altars of] earth and grain;
To assume responsibility for all ill-omened events in the state—this is called being the king of the world.
Correct words seem to say the reverse [of what you expect them to say].

To make peace where there has been great resentment, there is bound to be resentment left over.
How could this be regarded as good?
Therefore the Sage [holds] the right tally yet makes no demands of others.
For this reason, those who have virtue are in charge of the tally;
Those without virtue are in charge of the taxes.
The Way of Heaven has no favorites,
It’s always with the good man.

Let the country be small and people few—
Bring it about that there are weapons for “tens” and “hundreds,” yet let no one use them;
Have the people regard death gravely and put migrating far from their minds.
Though they might have boats and carriages, no one will ride them;
Though they might have armor and spears, no one will display them.
Have the people return to knotting cords and using them.

They will relish their food,
Regard their clothing as beautiful,
Delight in their customs,
And feel safe and secure in their homes.
Neighboring states might overlook one another,
And the sounds of chickens and dogs might be overheard,
Yet the people will arrive at old age and death with no comings and goings between them.

Sincere words are not showy;
Showy words are not sincere.
Those who know are not “widely learned”;
Those “widely learned” do not know.
The good do not have a lot;
Those with a lot are not good.

The Sage accumulates nothing.
Having used what he had for others,
He has even more.
Having given what he had to others,
What he has is even greater.
Therefore, the Way of Heaven is to benefit and not cause any harm;
The Way of Man is to act on behalf of others and not to compete with them.

The Way that can be followed is not the eternal Way.
The name that can be named is not the eternal name.
The nameless is the origin of heaven and earth
While naming is the origin of the myriad things.
Therefore, always desireless, you see the mystery
Ever desiring, you see the manifestations.
These two are the same—
When they appear they are named differently.

This sameness is the mystery,
Mystery within mystery;

The door to all marvels.

All in the world recognize the beautiful as beautiful.
Herein lies ugliness.
All recognize the good as good.
Herein lies evil.

Therefore
Presence and absence produce each other.
Difficulty and ease bring about each other.
Long and short delimit each other.
High and low rest on each other.
Sound and voice harmonize each other.
Front and back follow each other.

Therefore the sage abides in the condition of wu-wei (unattached action).
And carries out the wordless teaching.
Here, the myriad things are made, yet not separated.

Therefore the sage produces without possessing,
Acts without expectations
And accomplishes without abiding in her accomplishments.

It is precisely because she does not abide in them
That they never leave her.

If you do not adulate the worthy, you will make others non-contentious.
If you do not value rare treasures, you will stop others from stealing.
If people do not see desirables, they will not be agitated.

Therefore, when the sage governs,
He clears people’s minds,
Fills their bellies,
Weakens their ambition and
Strengthens their bones.

If the people are kept without cleverness and desire
It will make the intellectuals not dare to meddle.

Acting without contrivance, there is no lack of manageability.

The Way is so vast that when you use it, something is always left.
How deep it is!
It seems to be the ancestor of the myriad things.
It blunts sharpness
Untangles knots
Softens the glare
Unifies with the mundane.
It is so full!
It seems to have remainder.

It is the child of I-don’t-know-who.
And prior to the primeval Lord-on-high.

Heaven and Earth are not humane,
And regard the people as straw dogs.
The sage is not humane,
And regards all things as straw dogs.
The space between Heaven and Earth is just like a bellows:
Empty it, it is not exhausted.
Squeeze it and more comes out.

Excessive verbiage is usually a dead end
Is not as good as holding to the center.

The valley spirit never dies.
It is called “the mysterious female.”
The opening of the mysterious female
Is called “the root of Heaven and Earth.”
Continuous, seeming to remain.

Use it without exertion.

Heaven and Earth last forever.
The reason that Heaven and Earth are able to last forever
Is because they do not give birth to themselves.
Therefore, they are always alive.
Hence, the sage puts herself last and is first.
She is outside herself and therefore her self lasts.

Is it not through her selflessness
That she is able to perfect herself?

The highest goodness is like water.
Water easily benefits all things without struggle.
Yet it abides in places that men hate.
Therefore it is like the Way.

For dwelling, the Earth is good.
For the mind, depth is good.
The goodness of giving is in the timing.
The goodness of speech is in honesty.
In government, self-mastery is good.
In handling affairs, ability is good.

If you do not wrangle, you will not be blamed.

To hold until full is not as good as stopping.
An oversharpened sword cannot last long.
A room filled with gold and jewels cannot be protected.
Boasting of wealth and virtue brings your demise.
After finishing the work, withdraw.

This is the Way of Heaven.

Pacifying the agitated material soul and holding to oneness:
Are you able to avoid separation?
Focusing your energy on the release of tension:
Can you be like an infant?
In purifying your insight:
Can you un-obstruct it?
Loving the people and ruling the state:
Can you avoid over-manipulation?
In opening and closing the gate of Heaven:
Can you be the female?
In illuminating the whole universe:
Can you be free of rationality?

Give birth to it and nourish it.
Produce it but don’t possess it.
Act without expectation.
Excel, but don’t take charge.

This is called Mysterious Virtue.

Thirty spokes join together in the hub.
It is because of what is not there that the cart is useful.
Clay is formed into a vessel.
It is because of its emptiness that the vessel is useful.
Cut doors and windows to make a room.
It is because of its emptiness that the room is useful.
Therefore, what is present is used for profit.

But it is in absence that there is usefulness.

The five colors blind our eyes.
The five tones deafen our ears.
The five flavors confuse our taste.
Racing and hunting madden our minds.
Possessing rare treasures brings about harmful behavior.
Therefore the sage acts from his gut, and not from his eyes.

He lets go of that and chooses this.

Accept humiliation as a surprise.
Value great misfortune as your own self.

What do I mean by “Accept humiliation as a surprise”?
When you are humble
Attainment is a surprise
And so is loss.
That’s why I say, “Accept humiliation as a surprise.”

What do I mean by “Value great misfortune as your own self”?

If I have no self, how could I experience misfortune?

Therefore, if you dedicate your life for the benefit of the world,
You can rely on the world.
If you love dedicating yourself in this way,
You can be entrusted with the world.

Look for it, it cannot be seen.
It is called the distant.
Listen for it, it cannot be heard.
It is called the rare.
Reach for it, it cannot be gotten.
It is called the subtle.
These three ultimately cannot be fathomed.
Therefore they join to become one.

Its top is not bright;
Its bottom is not dark;
Existing continuously, it cannot be named and it returns to no-thingness.

Thus, it is called the formless form,
The image of no-thing.
This is called the most obscure.

Go to meet it, you cannot see its face.
Follow it, you cannot see its back.

By holding to the ancient Way
You can manage present existence
And know the primordial beginning.

This is called the very beginning thread of the Way.

The ancient masters of the Way
Had subtle marvelous mystic penetration
A depth that cannot be known.
It is exactly because that they are unknowable
That we are forced to pay attention to their appearance.
Hesitant, like one crossing an ice-covered river.
Ready, like one afraid of his neighbors on all sides.
Dignified, like a guest.
Loose, like ice about to melt.
Straightforward, like an uncarved block of wood.
Open, like a valley.
Obscure, like muddy water.

Who can be muddled, and use clarity to gradually become lucid?
Who can be calm, and use constant application for eventual success?

The one who holds to this path does not crave fulfillment.
Precisely because he does not crave fulfillment
He can be shattered
And do without quick restitution.

Effect vacuity to the extreme.
Keep stillness whole.
Myriad things act in concert.
I therefore watch their return.
All things flourish and each returns to its root.

Returning to the root is called quietude.
Quietude is called returning to life.
Return to life is called constant.
Knowing this constant is called illumination.
Acting arbitrarily without knowing the constant is harmful.
Knowing the constant is receptivity, which is impartial.

Impartiality is kingship.
Kingship is Heaven.
Heaven is the Way
the Way is eternal.

Though you lose the body, you do not die.

From great antiquity forth they have known and possessed it.
Those of the next level loved and praised it.
The next were in awe of it.
And the next despised it.

If you lack sincerity no one will believe you.

How careful she is with her precious words!
When her work is complete and her job is finished,
Everybody says: “We did it!”

When the great Way perishes
There is humaneness and justice.
When intelligence is manifest
There is great deception.
When the six relationships are not in harmony
There is filial piety and compassion.
When the country is in chaos
Loyal ministers appear.

Get rid of “holiness” and abandon “wisdom” and the people will benefit a hundredfold.

Get rid of “humaneness” and abandon “rightness” and the people will return to filial piety and compassion.

Get rid of cleverness and abandon profit, and thieves and gangsters will not exist.

Since the above three are merely words, they are not sufficient.
Therefore there must be something to include them all.

See the origin and keep the non-differentiated state.
Lessen selfishness and decrease desire.

Get rid of “learning” and there will be no anxiety.
How much difference is there between “yes” and “no”?
How far removed from each other are “good” and “evil”?
Yet what the people are in awe of cannot be disregarded.

I am scattered, never having been in a comfortable center.
All the people enjoy themselves, as if they are at the festival of the great sacrifice,
Or climbing the Spring Platform.
I alone remain, not yet having shown myself.
Like an infant who has not yet laughed.
Weary, like one despairing of no home to return to.

All the people enjoy extra
While I have left everything behind.
I am ignorant of the minds of others.
So dull!
While average people are clear and bright, I alone am dull and dim.
Average people know everything.
To me alone all seems covered.
So flat!
Like the ocean.
Blowing around!
It seems there is no place to rest.
Everybody has a goal in mind.
I alone am as ignorant as a bumpkin.
I alone differ from people.

I enjoy being nourished by the mother.

The form of great virtue is something that only the Way can follow.
The Way as a “thing” is only vague and obscure.
How obscure! How vague! In it there is form.
How vague! How obscure! In it are things.
How deep! How dark! In it there is an essence.

The essence is so real—therein is belief.

From the present to antiquity, its name has never left it, so we can examine all origins.
How do I know the form of all origins?

By this.

The imperfect is completed.
The crooked is straightened.
The empty is filled.
The old is renewed.
With few there is attainment.
With much there is confusion.
Therefore the sage grasps the one and becomes the model for all.

She does not show herself, and therefore is apparent.
She does not affirm herself, and therefore is acknowledged.
She does not boast and therefore has merit.
She does not strive and is therefore successful.
It is exactly because she does not contend, that nobody can contend with her.

How could the ancient saying, “The imperfect is completed” be regarded as empty talk?

Believe in the complete and return to it.

To speak little is natural.
Therefore a gale does not blow a whole morning
Nor does a downpour last a whole day.
Who does these things? Heaven and Earth.
If even Heaven and Earth cannot force perfect continuity
How can people expect to?

Therefore there is such a thing as aligning one’s actions with the Way.
If you accord with the Way you become one with it.
If you accord with virtue you become one with it.
If you accord with loss you become one with it.

The Way accepts this accordance gladly.
Virtue accepts this accordance gladly.
Loss also accepts accordance gladly.

If you are untrustworthy, people will not trust you.

Standing on tiptoe, you are unsteady.
Straddle-legged, you cannot go.
If you show yourself, you will not be seen.
If you affirm yourself, you will not shine.
If you boast, you will have no merit.
If you promote yourself, you will have no success.

Those who abide in the Way call these

Leftover food and wasted action
And all things dislike them.

Therefore the person of the Way does not act like this.

There is something that is perfect in its disorder
Which is born before Heaven and Earth.

So silent and desolate! It establishes itself without renewal.
Functions universally without lapse.
We can regard it as the Mother of Everything.

I don’t know its name.

Hence, when forced to name it, I call it “Way.”
When forced to categorize it, I call it “great.”

Greatness entails transcendence.
Transcendence entails going-far.
Going-far entails return.

Hence, the Way is great, Heaven is great, the Earth is great
And the human is also great.

Within our realm there are four greatnesses and the human being is one of them.

Human beings follow the Earth.
Earth follows Heaven
Heaven follows the Way
The Way follows things as they are.

Heaviness is the root of lightness.
Composure is the ruler of instability.
Therefore the sage travels all day
Without putting down his heavy load.
Though there may be spectacles to see
He easily passes them by.

This being so
How could the ruler of a large state
Be so concerned with himself as to ignore the people?

If you take them lightly you will lose your roots.
If you are unstable, you will lose your rulership.

A good traveler leaves no tracks.
Good speech lacks faultfinding.
A good counter needs no calculator.
A well-shut door will stay closed without a latch.
Skillful fastening will stay tied without knots.

It is in this manner that the sage is always skillful in elevating people.
Therefore she does not discard anybody.

She is always skillful in helping things
Therefore she does not discard anything.
This is called “the actualization of her luminosity.”

Hence, the good are the teachers of the not-so-good.
And the not-so-good are the charges of the good.

Not valuing your teacher or not loving your students:
Even if you are smart, you are gravely in error.

This is called Essential Subtlety.

Know the Masculine, cleave to the Feminine
Be a valley for everyone.
Being a valley for everyone
You are always in virtue without lapse
And you return to infancy.

Know the White, but cleave to the Black.[1]
Be a model for everyone.
Being a model for everyone
You are always in virtue and free from error
You return to limitlessness.
Know Glory but cleave to Humiliation
Be the valley for everyone.
When your constancy in virtue is complete
You return to the state of the “uncarved block.”

The block is cut into implements.
If the sage uses it, he ends up being an official.

Therefore the great tailor does not cut.

If you want to grab the world and run it
I can see that you will not succeed.
The world is a spiritual vessel, which can’t be controlled.

Manipulators mess things up.
Grabbers lose it. Therefore:

Sometimes you lead
Sometimes you follow
Sometimes you are stifled
Sometimes you breathe easy
Sometimes you are strong
Sometimes you are weak
Sometimes you destroy
And sometimes you are destroyed.

Hence, the sage shuns excess
Shuns grandiosity
Shuns arrogance.

If you used the Way as a principle for ruling
You would not dominate the people by military force.

What goes around comes around.

Where the general has camped
Thorns and brambles grow.
In the wake of a great army
Come years of famine.
If you know what you are doing
You will do what is necessary and stop there, not daring to use force.

Accomplish but don’t boast
Accomplish without show
Accomplish without arrogance
Accomplish without grabbing
Accomplish without forcing.

When things flourish they decline.

This is called non-Way
The non-Way is short-lived.

Sharp weapons are inauspicious instruments.
Everyone hates them.
Therefore the man of the Way is not comfortable with them.

In the domestic affairs of the gentleman
The left is the position of honor.
In military affairs the right is the position of honor.
Since weapons are inauspicious instruments, they are not the instruments of the gentleman
So he uses them without enjoyment
And values plainness.

Victory is never sweet.

Those for whom victory is sweet
Are those who enjoy killing.
If you enjoy killing, you cannot gain the trust of the people.

On auspicious occasions the place of honor is on the left.
On inauspicious occasions the place of honor is on the right.
The lieutenant commander stands on the left.
The commander-in-chief stands on the right.
And they speak, using the funerary rites to bury them.

The common people, from whom all the dead have come
Weep in lamentation.
The victors bury them with funerary rites.

The Way is always nameless.
And even though a sapling might be small
No one can make it be his subject.
If rulers could embody this principle
The myriad things would follow on their own.
Heaven and Earth would be in perfect accord
And rain sweet dew.
Without being ordered, the people naturally govern themselves.

And so you have the beginning of division into names.
Once there is a name sort something,
Then you should stop.
Knowing where to stop, you can avoid trouble.

The Way’s existence in the world

Is like valley streams running into the rivers and seas.

If you understand others you are smart.
If you understand yourself you are illuminated.
If you overcome others you are powerful.
If you overcome yourself you have strength.
If you know how to be satisfied you are rich.
If you can act with vigor, you have a will.
If you don’t lose your objectives you can be long-lasting.

If you die without loss, you are eternal.

The great Way flows over, spreading in every direction.
The myriad things are produced relying on it, but it does not distinguish them.
It brings them to completion without claiming possession.
It clothes and feeds all things without lording over them.

Always desireless, it can be called “the small.”
The myriad things rely on it and it doesn’t true to rule them
Thus it can be called “great.”
Till the end, it does not regard itself as Great.

Therefore it able to be great.

Grasping to the Great Form
All in the world go proceed forth.[2]
Proceeding forth unharmed, they rest in calm peace.

It is for food and music that the passing traveler stops.

When the Way emerges from its opening
It is insipid, having no taste.
Look at it, you cannot see it.
Listen, you cannot hear it.
Use it

You cannot exhaust it.

That which will be shrunk
Must first be stretched.
That which will be weakened
Must first be strengthened.
That which will be torn down
Must first be raised up.
That which will be taken
Must first be given.

This is called “subtle awareness.”

The soft and weak overcomes the hard and strong.

A fish should not leave the depths of the waters.

The country’s potent weapons
Should not be shown to its people.

The Way is always “not-doing”
Yet there is nothing it doesn’t do.
If the rulers are were able to embody it
Everyone will naturally be changed.

Being changed, they desire to do things.

So I must restrain them, using the nameless “uncarved block.”

Using the nameless uncarved block
They become desireless.
Desireless, they are tranquil and
All-under-Heaven is naturally settled.

Superior virtue is not virtuous
Therefore it has virtue.
Inferior virtue never fails to be virtuous
Therefore it has no virtue.

Superior virtue does not “act”
And has no intentions.
Inferior virtue “acts”
And always has intentions.
Superior humaneness “acts”
But has no intentions.
Superior justice “acts”
But but has intentions.
Superior propriety “acts” and if you don’t respond

They will roll up their sleeves and threaten you.

Thus, when the Way is lost there is virtue
When virtue is lost there is humaneness
When humaneness is lost there is justice
And when justice is lost there is propriety.

Now “propriety” is the external appearance of loyalty and sincerity
And the beginning of disorder.

Occult abilities are just flowers of the Way
And the beginning of foolishness.

Therefore the Great Person dwells in the substantial
And not in the superficial.
Rests in the fruit and not in the flower.

So let go of that and grasp this.

These in the past have attained wholeness:

Heaven attains wholeness with its clarity;
The Earth attains wholeness with its firmness;
The Spirit attains wholeness with its transcendence;
The Valley attain wholeness when filled;
The Myriad Things attain wholeness in life;
The Ruler attains wholeness in the correct governance of the people.

In effecting this:
If Heaven lacked clarity it would be divided;
If the Earth lacked firmness it would fly away;
If the spirit lacked transcendence it would be exhausted;
If the valley lacked fullness it would be depleted;
If the myriad things lacked life they would vanish.
If the ruler lacks nobility and loftiness he will be tripped up.

Hence
Nobility has lowliness as its root
The High has the Low as its base.
Thus the kings call themselves “the orphan, the lowly, the unworthy.”

Is this not taking lowliness as the fundamental? Isn’t it?

In this way you can bring about great effect without burden.
Not desiring the rarity of gems
Or the manyness of grains of sand.

Return is the motion of the Way.
Softening is its function.
All things in the cosmos arise from being.
Being arises from non-being.

When superior students hear of the Way
They strive to practice it.
When middling students hear of the Way
They sometimes keep it and sometimes lose it.
When inferior students hear of the Way
They have a big laugh.

But “not laughing” in itself is not sufficient to be called the Way, and therefore it is said:

The sparkling Way seems dark
Advancing in the Way seems like regression.
Settling into the Way seems rough.
True virtue is like a valley.
The immaculate seems humble.
Extensive virtue seems insufficient.
Established virtue seems deceptive.
The face of reality seems to change.
The great square has no corners.
Great ability takes a long time to perfect.
Great sound is hard to hear.
The great form has no shape.

The Way is hidden and nameless.

This is exactly why the Way is good at developing and perfecting.

The Way produces one, one produces two.
The two produce the three and the three produce all things.
All things submit to yin and embrace yang.
They soften their energy to achieve harmony.

People hate to think of themselves as “orphan,” “lowly,” and “unworthy”
Yet the kings call themselves by these names.

Some lose and yet gain,
Others gain and yet lose.
That which is taught by the people
I also teach:
“The forceful do not choose their place of death.”
I regard this as the father of all teachings.

The softest thing in the world
Will overcome the hardest.
Non-being can enter where there is no space.
Therefore I know the benefit of unattached action.
The wordless teaching and unattached action

Are rarely seen.

Which is dearer, fame or your life?
Which is greater, your life or possessions?
Which is more painful, gain or loss?
Therefore we always pay a great price for excessive love
And suffer deep loss for great accumulation.
Knowing what is enough, you will not be humiliated.
Knowing where to stop, you will not be imperiled

And can be long-lasting.

Great perfection seems flawed, yet functions without a hitch.
Great fullness seems empty, yet functions without exhaustion.
Great straightness seems crooked,
Great skill seems clumsy,
Great eloquence seems stammering.

Excitement overcomes cold, stillness overcomes heat.
Clarity and stillness set everything right.

When the Way prevails in the land
Fine horses leisurely graze and fertilize the ground.
When the Way is lacking in the land
War horses are bred outside the city.
There is no greater disaster as bad as not knowing what is enough.
No greater than not wanting more.

Therefore the sufficiency that comes from knowing what is enough is an eternal sufficiency.

Without going out the door, knowing everything,
Without peeking out the window shades, seeing the Way of Heaven.

The further you go, the less you know.

Hence the sage
Understands without having to go through the whole process.
Discerns[3] without looking.
Is perfected without striving.

In studying, each day something is gained.
In following the Way, each day something is lost.
Lost and again lost.
Until there is nothing left to do.
Not-doing, nothing is left undone.
You can possess the world by never manipulating it.
No matter how much you manipulate
You can never possess the world.

The sage has no fixed mind,
She takes the mind of the people as her mind.

I treat the good as good, I also treat the evil as good.
This is true goodness.
I trust the trustworthy, I also trust the untrustworthy.
This is real trust.

When the sage lives with people, she harmonizes with them
And conceals her mind for them.
The sages treat them as their little children.

Coming into life and entering death,
The followers of life are three in ten.
The followers of death are three in ten.
Those whose life activity is their death ground are three in ten.
Why is this?
Because they live life grasping for its rich taste.

Now I have heard that those who are expert in handling life
Can travel the land without meeting tigers and rhinos,
Can enter battle without being wounded.
The rhino has no place to plant its horn,
The tiger has no place to place its claws,
Weapons find no place to receive their sharp edges.
Why?

Because he has no death-ground.

Way gives birth to it,
Virtue rears it,
Materiality shapes it,
Activity perfects it.
Therefore, there are none of the myriad things who do not venerate the Way or esteem its virtue.
This veneration of the Way and esteeming of its virtue is something they do naturally, without being forced.
Therefore, the Way gives birth.
Its virtue rears, develops, raises, adjusts and disciplines,
Nourishes, covers and protects,
Produces but does not possess,
Acts without expectation,
Leads without forcing.

This is called “Mysterious Virtue.”

All things have a beginning, which we can regard as their Mother.
Knowing the mother, we can know its children.
Knowing the children, yet still cleaving to the mother
You can die without pain.

Stop up the holes
Shut the doors,
You can finish your life without anxiety.

Open the doors,
Increase your involvements,
In the end you can’t be helped.

Seeing the subtle is called illumination.
Keeping flexible is called strength.
Use the illumination, but return to the light.
Don’t bring harm to yourself.

This is called “practicing the eternal.”

If I had just a little bit of wisdom
I should walk the Great Path and fear only straying from it.
Though the Way is quite broad
People love shortcuts.

The court is immaculate,
While the fields are overgrown with weeds,
And the granaries are empty.
They wear silk finery,
Carry sharp swords,
Sate themselves on food and drink
Having wealth in excess.
They are called thieving braggarts.

This is definitely not the Way.

The well-established cannot be uprooted.
The well-grasped does not slip away.
Generation after generation carries out the ancestor worship without break.

Cultivate it in yourself and virtue will be real.
Cultivate it in the family and virtue will overflow.
Cultivate it in the town and virtue will be great.
Cultivate it in the country and virtue will abundant.
Cultivate it in the world and virtue will be everywhere.

Therefore, take yourself and observe yourself.
Take the family and observe the family.
Take the town and observe the town.
Take the country and observe the country.
Take the world and observe the world.

How do I know the world as it is?

By this.

One who remains rich in virtuous power
Is like a newborn baby.
Bees, scorpions and venomous snakes do not bite it,
The wild beasts do not attack it,
Birds of prey do not sink their claws into it.
Though its bones are weak
And muscles soft,
Its grip is strong.
Without knowing of the blending of male and female
S/he is a perfect production,
The ultimate in vitality.
S/he cries all day without getting hoarse.
S/he is the ultimate in harmony.

Understanding harmony is called the Constant.
Knowing the Constant is called illumination.
Nourishing life is called blessing.
Having control of your breath is called strength.

After things blossom they decay, and
This is called the non-Way.

The non-Way expires quickly.

One who knows does not speak.
One who speaks does not know.
Close your holes, shut your doors,
Soften your sharpness, loosen your knots.
Soften your glare and merge with the everyday.

This is called mysteriously attaining oneness.

Though you cannot possess it, you are intimate with it
And at the same time, distant.
Though you cannot possess it, you are benefitted by it,
And harmed by it.
You cannot possess it, but are esteemed through it
And humbled by it.

Therefore the world values you.

Use fairness in governing the state.
Use surprise tactics in war.
Be unconcerned and you will have the world.
How do I know it is like this?
Because:
The more regulations there are,
The poorer people become.
The more people own lethal weapons,
The more darkened are the country and clans.
The more clever the people are,
The more extraordinary actions they take.
The more picky the laws are,
The more thieves and gangsters there are.

Therefore the sages say:
I do not force my way and the people transform themselves.
I enjoy my serenity and the people correct themselves.
I do not interfere and the people enrich themselves.

I have no desires

And the people find their original mind.

When the government is laid back
The people are relaxed.
When the government is nitpicking
The people have anxiety.
Misfortune depends upon fortune.
Fortune conceals misfortune.
What has a definite delimitation?
Or abnormality?
The normal reverts to strangeness.
Goodness reverts to perversion.

People certainly have been confused for a long time.

Therefore the sage squares things without cutting.
Edges without separating.
Straightens without lining up.

Shines but does not glare.

In governing the country and serving Heaven
There is nothing like frugality.
Only by being frugal can you recover quickly.
When you recover quickly you accumulate virtue.
Having accumulated virtue,
There is nothing you can’t overcome.
When there is nothing you can’t overcome
Who knows the limits of your capabilities?
These limits being unfathomable
You can possess the country.

The Mother who possesses the country can be long-living.
This is called “planting the roots deeply and firmly.”

The way to long life and eternal vision.

Governing a large country is like cooking a small fish.[4]
When you govern people with the Way
Unhappy ghosts[5] will have no power.[6]
Not that they don’t have power,
But their power will not harm people.

Not only does their power not harm people:
The sage also doesn’t harm people,
Since the two do not harm each other.

Their virtue converges.[7]

The great state should be like a river basin.
The mixing place of the world,
The feminine of the world.
The feminine always overcomes the masculine by softness
Because softness is lesser.
Therefore if a large state serves a small state
It will gain the small state.
If a small state serves a large state
It will gain the large state.

Therefore some serve in order to gain
And some gain despite their servitude.

The large state wants nothing more
Than to unite and feed its people.
The small state wants nothing more
Than to enter into the service of the right person.
Thus both get what they want.

Greatness lies in placing oneself below.

The Way is hidden deeply in all things.
It is the treasure of the good
And the refuge of the not-so-good.
With skillful words you can be successful.
With honorable actions you can be included.

People may not be so good, but how can you deny them?

Therefore, even though there are great jewels brought in by teams of horses at the coronation of the emperor and the installation of the three princes,
This is not as good as staying where you are
And advancing in this Way.

Why did the ancients so value the Way?

You can’t say that it was for seeking gain
Or to have punishments to deter crime.

Therefore it is the most prized in the world.

Do without “doing.”
Get involved without manipulating.
Taste without tasting.
Make the great small,
The many, few.
Respond to anger with virtue.
Deal with difficulties while they are still easy.
Handle the great while it is still small.

The difficult problems in life
Always start off being simple.
Great affairs always start off being small.
Therefore the sage never deals with the great
And is able to actualize his greatness.

Now light words generate little belief,
Much ease turns into much difficulty.
Therefore the sage treats things as though they were difficult,

And hence, never has difficulty.

That which is at rest is easy to grasp.
That which has not yet come about is easy to plan for.
That which is fragile is easily broken.
That which is minute is easily scattered.
Handle things before they arise.
Manage affairs before they are in a mess.

A thick tree grows from a tiny seed.
A tall building arises from a mound of earth.
A journey of a thousand miles starts with one step.
Contriving, you are defeated;
Grasping, you lose.

The sage doesn’t contrive, so she isn’t beaten.
Not grasping, she doesn’t lose.
When people are carrying out their projects
They usually blow it at the end.

If you are as careful at the end
As you were at the beginning,
You won’t be disappointed.

Therefore the sage desires non-desire,
Does not value rare goods,
Studies the unlearnable
So that she can correct the mistakes of average people
And aid all things in manifesting their true nature

Without presuming to take the initiative.

The ancients who were skillful at the Way
Did not illuminate the people
But rather kept them simple.
When the people are difficult to rule
It is because of their cleverness.
Therefore
If you use cleverness to rule the state
You are a robber of the state.
If you don’t use cleverness to rule the state
You are a blessing to the state.

If you understand these two points, you know the proper norm for governing.
To be continuously understanding the proper norm is called Mysterious Virtue.
How deep and far-reaching Mysterious Virtue is!
It makes all return

Until they reach the Great Norm.

The reason the river and sea can be regarded as
The rulers of all the valley streams
Is because of their being below them.
Therefore they can be their rulers.
So if you want to be over people
You must speak humbly to them.
If you want to lead them
You must place yourself behind them.

Thus the sage is positioned above
And the people do not feel oppressed.
He is in front and they feel nothing wrong.
Therefore they like to push him front and never resent him.

Since he does not contend

No one can contend with him.

The reason everybody calls my Way great
Is because there is nothing quite like it.
It is exactly because it isgreat
That there is nothing quite like it.
If there were something that were consistently like it

How could it be small?

I have three treasures thatI hold and cherish.
The first is compassion,
The second is frugality,
The third is not daring to put myself ahead of everybody.

Having compassion, I can be brave.
Having frugality, I can be generous.
Not daring to put myself ahead of everybody
I can take the time to perfect my abilities.
Now if I am brave without compassion
Generous without frugality, or
Go to the fore without putting my own concerns last,
I might as well be dead.

If you wage war with compassion you will win.
If you protect yourself with compassion you will be impervious.
Heaven will take care of you,

Protecting you with compassion.

The best warrior is never aggressive.
The best fighter is never angry.
The best tactician does not engage the enemy.
The best utilizer of people’s talents places himself below them.

This is called the virtue of non-contention.
It is called the ability to engage people’s talents.
It is called the ultimate in merging with Heaven.

Strategists have a saying:
I prefer to be able to move, rather than be in a fixed position
I prefer to retreat a foot rather than advancing an inch.

This is called progress without advancing;
Preparing without showing off;
Smashing where there is no defense;
Taking him without a fight.

There is no greater danger than under-estimating your opponent.
If I under-estimate my opponent
I will lose that which is most dear.
Therefore
When opponents clash

The one who is sorry about it will be the winner.

My words are easy to understand
And easy to practice.
Yet nobody understands them or practices them.
My words have an origin;
My actions have a principle.
It is only because of your not understanding this
That you do not understand me.
Since there are few who understand me
I am valued.
Therefore the sage wears coarse clothes.
Yet hides a jewel in his bosom.

There is nothing better than to know that you don’t know.
Not knowing, yet thinking you know—
This is sickness.
Only when you are sick of being sick
Can you be cured.
The sage’s not being sick

Is because she is sick of sickness.

Therefore she is not sick.

When the people do not fear your might
Then your might has truly become great.
Don’t interfere with their household affairs.
Don’t oppress their livelihood.

If you don’t oppress them they won’t feel oppressed.

Thus the sage understands herself
But does not show herself.
Loves herself
But does not prize herself.
Therefore she lets go of that

And takes this.

If you are courageous in daring you will die.
If you are courageous in not-daring you will live.
Among these two, one is beneficial and the other is harmful.

Who understands the reason why Heaven dislikes what it dislikes?
Even the sage has difficulty in knowing this.

The Way of Heaven is to win easily without struggle.
To respond well without words,
To naturally come without special invitation,
To plan well without anxiety.

Heaven’s net is vast.
It is loose.

Yet nothing slips through.

If the people don’t fear death
How will you scare them with death?
If you make the people continuously fear death
By seizing anybody who does something out of the ordinary
And killing them,
Who will dare to move?

There is always an official executioner to handle this.
If you play the role of the official executioner
It is like cutting wood in the capacity of Master Carpenter.

There are few who will not cut their hands.

The reason people starve
Is because their rulers tax them excessively.
They are difficult to govern
Because their rulers have their own ends in mind.

The reason people take death lightly
Is because they want life to be rich.
Therefore they take death lightly.
It is only by not living for your own ends
That you can go beyond valuing life.

When people are born they are gentle and soft.
At death they are hard and stiff.
When plants are alive they are soft and delicate.
When they die, they wither and dry up.
Therefore the hard and stiff are followers of death.
The gentle and soft are the followers of life.

Thus, if you are aggressive and stiff, you won’t win.
When a tree is hard enough, it is cut. Therefore
The hard and big are lesser,
The gentle and soft are greater.

The Way of Heaven
Is like stretching a bow.
The top is pulled down,
The bottom is pulled up.
Excess string is removed
Where more is needed, it is added.

It is the Way of Heaven
To remove where there is excess
And add where there is lack.
The way of people is different:
They take away where there is need
And add where there is surplus.

Who can take his surplus and give it to the people?
Only one who possesses the Way.

Therefore the sage acts without expectation.
Does not abide in his accomplishments.
Does not want to show his virtue.

Nothing in the world is softer than water,
Yet nothing is better at overcoming the hard and strong.
This is because nothing can alter it.

That the soft overcomes the hard
And the gentle overcomes the aggressive
Is something that everybody knows
But none can do themselves.
Therefore the sages say:
The one who accepts the dirt of the state
Becomes its master.
The one who accepts its calamity
Becomes king of the world.

Truth seems contradictory.

After settling down for great anger
There are always resentments left over.
How can this be considered as good?
Therefore the sage keeps her part of the deal,[8]
And doesn’t badger the other party.

The virtuous ascertain the content of the contract itself;
Those without virtue are concerned about it’s being exacted.[9]

The Heavenly Way has no favorites:
It always raises up the Good.[10]

Let there be a small country with few people,
Who, even having much machinery, don’t use it.
Who take death seriously and don’t wander far away.
Even though they have boats and carriages, they never ride in them.
Having armor and weapons, they never go to war.
Let them return to measurement by tying knots in rope.

Sweeten their food, give them nice clothes, a peaceful abode and a relaxed life.
Even though the next country can be seen and its doges and chickens can be heard,

The people will grow old and die without visiting each other’s land.

True words are not pretty.
Pretty words are not true.
The good are not argumentative.
The argumentative are not good.
The one who really knows is not broadly learned,
The broadly learned do not really know.
The sage does not hoard,
She gives people her surplus.
Giving her surplus to others she is enriched.

The way of Heaven is to help and not harm.
The way of the Sage is to act without wrangling.

Notes

1 The “black” is the deep, religious, mystic part of our experience. The “white” is our involvement in mundane affairs. We should well understand how the conventional world operates, but our priority should lie in adhering to deeper principles. ↩︎

2 As far as I can tell, I am the only translator who takes 往 as “going forth” rather than “come.” Where in any other text do we see the rendering of “come”? I take it to mean that if people will hold on to the Dao as they go out in the world, they won't have trouble, and will enjoy peace and calm. This seems to accord with the general message of the

Daodejing

. ↩︎

3 The commentarial tradition reads 名 as meaning 明. ↩︎

4 A small fish can be cooked without a great deal of preparation, cleaning, spicing, etc. Ruling with the Dao means ruling without interfering. ↩︎

5 Spirits of people who died early, in some unfortunate way, or without descendants, who mingle in the world and plague people. ↩︎

6 Translated elsewhere as “numinousity,” “spiritual power,” etc. ↩︎

7 The interpretation of this final line varies widely among translators; we decided to try to remain terse and close to the literal meaning here. ↩︎

8 左契 literally means the “left side of the tally.” Ancient contracts in East Asia were made by writing the agreement on a wooden board that would be broken in half, and rematched when the contract had been fulfilled. ↩︎

9 The interpretation of 司契 and 司徹 here varies considerably among translators. We take it as one of the plethora of expressions of the pervasive notion of wu-wei in the

Daodejing

, which implies doing things by focusing on the content, and what one can actual do well, rather than on expectations of a rapid conclusion. Cf. the translations by D.C. Lau, Richard Llynn, Ellen Chen, John Wu, and others. ↩︎

10 Cf.

Analects

4:10: The Master said: “When the noble man deals with the world he is not prejudiced for or against anything. He does what is Right.” 子曰。君子之於天下也、無適也、無莫也、義之與比。 ↩︎

The Tao that can be told is not the eternal Tao.
The name that can be named is not the eternal name.

The nameless is the beginning of heaven and Earth.
The named is the mother of the ten thousand things.

Ever desireless, one can see the mystery.
Ever desiring, one sees the manifestations.

These two spring from the same source but differ in name; this appears as darkness.

Darkness within darkness.
The gate to all mystery.

Under heaven all can see beauty as beauty only because there is ugliness.
All can know good as good only because there is evil.

Therefore having and not having arise together.
Difficult and easy complement each other.
Long and short contrast each other:
High and low rest upon each other;
Voice and sound harmonize each other;
Front and back follow one another.

Therefore the sage goes about doing nothing, teaching no-talking.
The ten thousand things rise and fall without cease,
Creating, yet not.
Working, yet not taking credit.
Work is done, then forgotten.
Therefore it lasts forever.

Not exalting the gifted prevents quarreling.
Not collecting treasures prevents stealing.
Not seeing desirable things prevents confusion of the heart.

The wise therefore rule by emptying hearts and stuffing bellies, by weakening ambitions and strengthening bones.

If men lack knowledge and desire, then clever people will not try to interfere.

If nothing is done, then all will be well.

The Tao is an empty vessel; it is used, but never filled.
Oh, unfathomable source of ten thousand things!
Blunt the sharpness,
Untangle the knot,
Soften the glare,
Merge with dust.
Oh, hidden deep but ever present!
I do not know from whence it comes.
It is the forefather of the gods.

Heaven and Earth are impartial;
They see the ten thousand things as straw dogs.
The wise are impartial;
They see the people as straw dogs.

The space between heaven and Earth is like a bellows.
The shape changes but not the form;
The more it moves, the more it yields.

More words count less.
Hold fast to the center.

The valley spirit never dies;
It is the woman, primal mother.
Her gateway is the root of heaven and Earth.
It is like a veil barely seen.
Use it; it will never fail.

Heaven and Earth last forever.
Why do heaven and Earth last forever?
They are unborn,
So ever living.
The sage stays behind, thus he is ahead.
He is detached, thus at one with all.
Through selfless action, he attains fulfillment.

The highest good is like water.
Water give life to the ten thousand things and does not strive.
It flows in places men reject and so is like the Tao.

In dwelling, be close to the land.
In meditation, go deep in the heart.
In dealing with others, be gentle and kind.
In speech, be true.
In ruling, be just.
In daily life, be competent.
In action, be aware of the time and the season.

No fight: No blame.

Better to stop short than fill to the brim.
Oversharpen the blade, and the edge will soon blunt.
Amass a store of gold and jade, and no one can protect it.
Claim wealth and titles, and disaster will follow.
Retire when the work is done.
This is the way of heaven.

Carrying body and soul and embracing the one,
Can you avoid separation?
Attending fully and becoming supple,
Can you be as a newborn babe?
Washing and cleansing the primal vision,
Can you be without stain?
Loving all men and ruling the country,
Can you be without cleverness?
Opening and closing the gates of heaven,
Can you play the role of woman?
Understanding and being open to all things,
Are you able to do nothing?
Giving birth and nourishing,
Bearing yet not possessing,
Working yet not taking credit,
Leading yet not dominating,
This is the Primal Virtue.

Thirty spokes share the wheel’s hub;
It is the center hole that makes it useful.
Shape clay into a vessel;
It is the space within that makes it useful.
Cut doors and windows for a room;
It is the holes which make it useful.
Therefore benefit comes from what is there;
Usefulness from what is not there.

The five colors blind the eye.
The five tones deafen the ear.
The five flavors dull the taste.
Racing and hunting madden the mind.
Precious things lead one astray.

Therefore the sage is guided by what he feels and not by what he sees.
He lets go of that and chooses this.

Accept disgrace willingly.
Accept misfortune as the human condition.

What do you mean by “Accept disgrace willingly”?
Accept being unimportant.
Do not be concerned with loss or gain.
This is called “accepting disgrace willingly.”

What do you mean by “Accept misfortune as the human condition”?
Misfortune comes from having a body.
Without a body, how could there be misfortune?

Surrender yourself humbly; then you can be trusted to care for all things.
Love the world as your own self; then you can truly care for all things.

Look, it cannot be seen – it is beyond form.
Listen, it cannot be heard – it is beyond sound.
Grasp, it cannot be held – it is intangible.
These three are indefinable;
Therefore they are joined in one.

From above it is not bright;
From below it is not dark:
An unbroken thread beyond description.
It returns to nothingness.
The form of the formless,
The image of the imageless,
It is called indefinable and beyond imagination.

Stand before it and there is no beginning.
Follow it and there is no end.
Stay with the ancient Tao,
Move with the present.

Knowing the ancient beginning is the essence of Tao.

The ancient masters were subtle, mysterious, profound, responsive.
The depth of their knowledge is unfathomable.
Because it is unfathomable,
All we can do is describe their appearance.
Watchful, like men crossing a winter stream.
Alert, like men aware of danger.
Courteous, like visiting guests.
Yielding like ice about to melt.
Simple, like uncarved blocks of wood.
Hollow, like caves.
Opaque, like muddy pools.

Who can wait quietly while the mud settles?
Who can remain still until the moment of action?
Observers of the Tao do not seek fulfillment.
Not seeking fulfillment, they are not swayed by desire for change.

Empty yourself of everything.
Let the mind become still.
The ten thousand things rise and fall while the Self watches their return.
They grow and flourish and then return to the source.
Returning to the source is stillness, which is the way of nature.
The way of nature is unchanging.
Knowing constancy is insight.
Not knowing constancy leads to disaster.
Knowing constancy, the mind is open.
With an open mind, you will be openhearted.
Being openhearted, you will act royally.
Being royal, you will attain the divine.
Being divine, you will be at one with the Tao.
Being at one with the Tao is eternal.
And though the body dies, the Tao will never pass away.

The very highest if barely known.
Then comes that which people know and love.
Then that which is feared,
Then that which is despised.

Who does not trust enough will not be trusted.

When actions are performed
Without unnecessary speech,
People say, “We did it!”

When the great Tao is forgotten,
Kindness and morality arise.
When wisdom and intelligence are born,
The great pretense begins.

When there is no peace within the family,
Filial piety and devotion arise.
When the country is confused and in chaos,
Loyal ministers appear.

Give up sainthood, renounce wisdom,
And it will be a hundred times better for everyone.

Give up kindness, renounce morality,
And men will rediscover filial piety and love.

Give up ingenuity, renounce profit,
And bandits and thieves will disappear.

These three are outward forms alone; they are not sufficient in themselves.
It is more important
To see the simplicity,
To realize one’s true nature,
To cast off selfishness
And temper desire.

Give up learning, and put an end to your troubles.

Is there a difference between yes and no?
Is there a difference between good and evil?
Must I fear what others fear? What nonsense!
Other people are contented, enjoying the sacrificial feast of the ox.

In spring some go to the park, and climb the terrace,
But I alone am drifting, not knowing where I am.
Like a newborn babe before it learns to smile,
I am alone, without a place to go.
Others have more than they need, but
I alone have nothing.
I am a fool. Oh, yes! I am confused.
Others are clear and bright,
But I alone am dim and weak.
Others are sharp and clever,
But I alone am dull and stupid.
Oh, I drift like the waves of the sea,
Without direction, like the restless wind.
Everyone else is busy,
But I alone am aimless and depressed.
I am different.
I am nourished by the great mother.

The greatest Virtue is to follow Tao and Tao alone.
The Tao is elusive and intangible.
Oh, it is intangible and elusive, and yet within is image.
Oh, it is elusive and intangible, and yet within is form.
Oh, it is dim and dark, and yet within is essence.
This essence is very real, and therein lies faith.
From the very beginning until now its name has never been forgotten.
Thus I perceive the creation.
How do I know the ways of creation?
Because of this.

Yield and overcome;
Bend and be straight;
Empty and be full;
Wear out and be new;
Have little and gain;
Have much and be confused.

Therefore the wise embrace the one
And set an example to all.
Not putting on a display,
They shine forth.
Not justifying themselves,
They are distinguished.
Not boasting,
They receive recognition.
Not bragging,
They never falter.
They do not quarrel,
So no one quarrels with them.
Therefore the ancients say, “Yield and overcome.”
Is that an empty saying?
Be really whole,
And all things will come to you.

To talk little is natural.
High winds do not last all morning.
Heavy rain does not last all day.
Why is this? Heaven and Earth!
If heaven and Earth cannot make things eternal,
How is it possible for man?
He who follows the Tao
Is at one with the Tao.
He who is virtuous
Experiences Virtue.
He who loses the way
Is lost.
When you are at one with the Tao,
The Tao welcomes you.
When you are at one with Virtue,
The Virtue is always there.
When you are at one with loss,
The loss is experienced willingly.

He who does not trust enough
Will not be trusted.

He who stands on tiptoe is not steady.
He who strides cannot maintain the pace.
He who makes a show is not enlightened.
He who is self-righteous is not respected.
He who boasts achieves nothing.
He who brags will not endure.
According to followers of the Tao,
“These are extra food and unnecessary luggage.”
They do not bring happiness.
Therefore followers of the Tao avoid them.

Something mysteriously formed,
Born before heaven and Earth.
In the silence and the void,
Standing alone and unchanging,
Ever present and in motion.
Perhaps it is the mother of ten thousand things.
I do not know its name
Call it Tao.
For lack of a better word, I call it great.

Being great, it flows
It flows far away.
Having gone far, it returns.

Therefore, “Tao is great;
Heaven is great;
Earth is great;
The king is also great.”
These are the four great powers of the universe,
And the king is one of them.

Man follows Earth.
Earth follows heaven.
Heaven follows the Tao.
Tao follows what is natural.

The heavy is the root of the light.
The still is the master of unrest.

Therefore the sage, traveling all day,
Does not lose sight of his baggage.
Though there are beautiful things to be seen,
He remains unattached and calm.

Why should the lord of ten thousand chariots act lightly in public?
To be light is to lose one’s root.
To be restless is to lose one’s control.

A good walker leaves no tracks;
A good speaker makes no slips;
A good reckoner needs no tally.
A good door needs no lock,
Yet no one can open it.
Good binding requires no knots,
Yet no one can loosen it.

Therefore the sage takes care of all men
And abandons no one.
He takes care of all things
And abandons nothing.

This is called “following the light.”

What is a good man?
A teacher of a bad man.
What is a bad man?
A good man’s charge.
If the teacher is not respected,
And the student not cared for,
Confusion will arise, however clever one is.
This is the crux of mystery.

Know the strength of man,
But keep a woman’s care!
Be the stream of the universe!
Being the stream of the universe,
Ever true and unswerving,
Become as a little child once more.

Know the white,
But keep the black!
Be an example to the world!
Being an example to the world,
Ever true and unwavering,
Return to the infinite.

Know honor,
Yet keep humility.
Be the valley of the universe!
Being the valley of the universe,
Ever true and resourceful,
Return to the state of the uncarved block.

When the block is carved, it becomes useful.
When the sage uses it, he becomes the ruler.
Thus, “A great tailor cuts little.”

Do you think you can take over the universe and improve it?
I do not believe it can be done.

The universe is sacred.
You cannot improve it.
If you try to change it, you will ruin it.
If you try to hold it, you will lose it.

So sometimes things are ahead and sometimes they are behind;
Sometimes breathing is hard, sometimes it comes easily;
Sometimes there is strength and sometimes weakness;
Sometimes one is up and sometimes down.

Therefore the sage avoids extremes, excesses, and complacency.

Whenever you advise a ruler in the way of Tao,
Counsel him not to use force to conquer the universe.
For this would only cause resistance.
Thorn bushes spring up wherever the army has passed.
Lean years follow in the wake of a great war.
Just do what needs to be done.
Never take advantage of power.

Achieve results,
But never glory in them.
Achieve results,
But never boast.
Achieve results,
But never be proud.
Achieve results,
Because this is the natural way.
Achieve results,
But not through violence.

Force is followed by loss of strength.
This is not the way of Tao.
That which goes against the Tao comes to an early end.

Good weapons are instruments of fear; all creatures hate them.
Therefore followers of Tao never use them.
The wise man prefers the left.
The man of war prefers the right.

Weapons are instruments of fear; they are not a wise man’s tools.
He uses them only when he has no choice.
Peace and quiet are dear to his heart,
And victory no cause for rejoicing.
If you rejoice in victory, then you delight in killing;
If you delight in killing, you cannot fulfill yourself.

On happy occasions precedence is given to the left,
On sad occasions to the right.
In the army the general stands on the left,
The commander-in-chief on the right.
This means that war is conducted like a funeral.
When many people are being killed,
They should be mourned in heartfelt sorrow.
That is why a victory must be observed like a funeral.

The Tao is forever undefined.
Small though it is in the unformed state, it cannot be grasped.
If kings and lords could harness it,
The ten thousand things would come together
And gentle rain fall.
Men would need no more instruction and all things would take their course.

Once the whole is divided, the parts need names.
There are already enough names.
One must know when to stop.
Knowing when to stop averts trouble.
Tao in the world is like a river flowing home to the sea.

Knowing others is wisdom;
Knowing the self is enlightenment.
Mastering others requires force;
Mastering the self needs strength.

He who knows he has enough is rich.
Perseverance is a sign of willpower.
He who stays where he is endures.
To die but not to perish is to be eternally present.

The great Tao flows everywhere, both to the left and to the right.
The ten thousand things depend upon it; it holds nothing back.
It fulfills its purpose silently and makes no claim.

It nourishes the ten thousand things,
And yet is not their lord.
It has no aim; it is very small.

The ten thousand things return to it,
Yet it is not their lord.
It is very great.

It does not show greatness,
And is therefore truly great.

All men will come to him who keeps to the one,
For there lie rest and happiness and peace.

Passersby may stop for music and good food,
But a description of the Tao
Seems without substance or flavor.
It cannot be seen, it cannot be heard,
And yet it cannot be exhausted.

That which shrinks
Must first expand.
That which fails
Must first be strong.

That which is cast down
Must first be raised.
Before receiving
There must be giving.

This is called perception of the nature of things.
Soft and weak overcome hard and strong.

Fish cannot leave deep waters,
And a country’s weapons should not be displayed.

Tao abides in non-action,
Yet nothing is left undone.
If kings and lords observed this,
The ten thousand things would develop naturally.
If they still desired to act,
They would return to the simplicity of formless substance.
Without for there is no desire.
Without desire there is.
And in this way all things would be at peace.

A truly good man is not aware of his goodness,
And is therefore good.
A foolish man tries to be good,
And is therefore not good.

A truly good man does nothing,
Yet leaves nothing undone.
A foolish man is always doing,
Yet much remains to be done.

When a truly kind man does something, he leaves nothing undone.
When a just man does something, he leaves a great deal to be done.
When a disciplinarian does something and no one responds,
He rolls up his sleeves in an attempt to enforce order.

Therefore when Tao is lost, there is goodness.
When goodness is lost, there is kindness.
When kindness is lost, there is justice.
When justice is lost, there ritual.
Now ritual is the husk of faith and loyalty, the beginning of confusion.
Knowledge of the future is only a flowery trapping of Tao.
It is the beginning of folly.

Therefore the truly great man dwells on what is real and not what is on the surface,
On the fruit and not the flower.
Therefore accept the one and reject the other.

These things from ancient times arise from one:
The sky is whole and clear.
The earth is whole and firm.
The spirit is whole and strong.
The valley is whole and full.
The ten thousand things are whole and alive.
Kings and lords are whole, and the country is upright.
All these are in virtue of wholeness.

The clarity of the sky prevents its falling.
The firmness of the earth prevents its splitting.
The strength of the spirit prevents its being used up.
The fullness of the valley prevents its running dry.
The growth of the ten thousand things prevents their drying out.
The leadership of kings and lords prevents the downfall of the country.

Therefore the humble is the root of the noble.
The low is the foundation of the high.
Princes and lords consider themselves “orphaned”, “widowed” and “worthless”.
Do they not depend on being humble?

Too much success is not an advantage.
Do not tinkle like jade
Or clatter like stone chimes.

Returning is the motion of the Tao.
Yielding is the way of the Tao.
The ten thousand things are born of being.
Being is born of not being.

The wise student hears of the Tao and practices it diligently.
The average student hears of the Tao and gives it thought now and again.
The foolish student hears of the Tao and laughs aloud.
If there were no laughter, the Tao would not be what it is.

Hence it is said:
The bright path seems dim;
Going forward seems like retreat;
The easy way seems hard;
The highest Virtue seems empty;
Great purity seems sullied;
A wealth of Virtue seems inadequate;
The strength of Virtue seems frail;
Real Virtue seems unreal;
The perfect square has no corners;
Great talents ripen late;
The highest notes are hard to hear;
The greatest form has no shape;
The Tao is hidden and without name.
The Tao alone nourishes and brings everything to fulfillment.

The Tao begot one.
One begot two.
Two begot three.
And three begot the ten thousand things.

The ten thousand things carry yin and embrace yang.
They achieve harmony by combining these forces.

Men hate to be “orphaned,” “widowed,” or “worthless,”
But this is how kings and lords describe themselves.

For one gains by losing
And loses by gaining.

What others teach, I also teach; that is:
“A violent man will die a violent death!”
This will be the essence of my teaching.

The softest thing in the universe
Overcomes the hardest thing in the universe.
That without substance can enter where there is no room.
Hence I know the value of non-action.

Teaching without words and work without doing
Are understood by very few.

Fame or self: Which matters more?
Self or wealth: Which is more precious?
Gain or loss: Which is more painful?

He who is attached to things will suffer much.
He who saves will suffer heavy loss.
A contented man is never disappointed.
He who knows when to stop does not find himself in trouble.
He will stay forever safe.

Great accomplishment seems imperfect,
Yet it does not outlive its usefulness.
Great fullness seems empty,
Yet cannot be exhausted.

Great straightness seems twisted.
Great intelligence seems stupid.
Great eloquence seems awkward.

Movement overcomes cold.
Stillness overcomes heat.
Stillness and tranquility set things in order in the universe.

When the Tao is present in the universe,
The horses haul manure.
When the Tao is absent from the universe,
War horses are bred outside the city.

There is no greater sin than desire,
No greater curse than discontent,
No greater misfortune than wanting something for oneself.
Therefore he who knows that enough is enough will always have enough.

Without going outside, you may know the whole world.
Without looking through the window, you may see the ways of heaven.
The farther you go, the less you know.

Thus the sage knows without traveling;
He sees without looking;
He works without doing.

In the pursuit of learning, every day something is acquired.
In the pursuit of Tao, every day something is dropped.

Less and less is done
Until non-action is achieved.
When nothing is done, nothing is left undone.

The world is ruled by letting things take their course.
It cannot be ruled by interfering.

The sage has no mind of his own.
He is aware of the needs of others.

I am good to people who are good.
I am also good to people who are not good.
Because Virtue is goodness.
I have faith in people who are faithful.
I also have faith in people who are not faithful.
Because Virtue is faithfulness.

The sage is shy and humble – to the world he seems confusing.
Others look to him and listen.
He behaves like a little child.

Between birth and death,
Three in ten are followers of life,
Three in ten are followers of death,
And men just passing from birth to death also number three in ten.
Why is this so?
Because they live their lives on the gross level.

He who knows how to live can walk abroad
Without fear of rhinoceros or tiger.
He will not be wounded in battle.
For in him rhinoceroses can find no place to thrust their horn,
Tigers no place to use their claws,
And weapons no place to pierce.
Why is this so?
Because he has no place for death to enter.

All things arise from Tao.
They are nourished by Virtue.
They are formed from matter.
They are shaped by environment.
Thus the ten thousand things all respect Tao and honor Virtue.
Respect of Tao and honor of Virtue are not demanded,
But they are in the nature of things.

Therefore all things arise from Tao.
By Virtue they are nourished,
Developed, cared for,
Sheltered, comforted,
Grown, and protected.
Creating without claiming,
Doing without taking credit,
Guiding without interfering,
This is Primal Virtue.

The beginning of the universe
Is the mother of all things.
Knowing the mother, on also knows the sons.
Knowing the sons, yet remaining in touch with the mother,
Brings freedom from the fear of death.

Keep your mouth shut,
Guard the senses,
And life is ever full.
Open your mouth,
Always be busy,
And life is beyond hope.

Seeing the small is insight;
Yielding to force is strength.
Using the outer light, return to insight,
And in this way be saved from harm.
This is learning constancy.

If I have even just a little sense,
I will walk on the main road and my only fear will be of straying from it.
Keeping to the main road is easy,
But people love to be sidetracked.

When the court is arrayed in splendor,
The fields are full of weeds,
And the granaries are bare.
Some wear gorgeous clothes,
Carry sharp swords,
And indulge themselves with food and drink;
They have more possessions than they can use.
They are robber barons.
This is certainly not the way of Tao.

What is firmly established cannot be uprooted.
What is firmly grasped cannot slip away.
It will be honored from generation to generation.

Cultivate Virtue in your self,
And Virtue will be real.
Cultivate it in the family,
And Virtue will abound.
Cultivate it in the village,
And Virtue will grow.
Cultivate it in the nation,
And Virtue will be abundant.
Cultivate it in the universe,
And Virtue will be everywhere.

Therefore look at the body as body;
Look at the family as family;
Look at the village as village;
Look at the nation as nation;
Look at the universe as universe.

How do I know the universe is like this?
By looking!

He who is filled with Virtue is like a newborn child.
Wasps and serpents will not sting him;
Wild beasts will not pounce upon him;
He will not be attacked by birds of prey.
His bones are soft, his muscles weak,
But his grip is firm.
He has not experienced the union of man and woman, but is whole.
His manhood is strong.
He screams all day without becoming hoarse.
This is perfect harmony.

Knowing harmony is constancy.
Knowing constancy is enlightenment.

It is not wise to rush about.
Controlling the breath causes strain.
If too much energy is used, exhaustion follows.
This is not the way of Tao.
Whatever is contrary to Tao will not last long.

Those who know do not talk.
Those who talk do not know.

Keep your mouth closed.
Guard your senses.
Temper your sharpness.
Simplify your problems.
Mask your brightness.
Be at one with the dust of the Earth.
This is primal union.

He who has achieved this state
Is unconcerned with friends and enemies,
With good and harm, with honor and disgrace.
This therefore is the highest state of man.

Rule a nation with justice.
Wage war with surprise moves.
Become master of the universe without striving.
How do I know that this is so?
Because of this!

The more laws and restrictions there are,
The poorer people become.
The sharper men’s weapons,
The more trouble in the land.
The more ingenious and clever men are,
The more strange things happen.
The more rules and regulations,
The more thieves and robbers.

Therefore the sage says:
I take no action and people are reformed.
I enjoy peace and people become honest.
I do nothing and people become rich.
I have no desires and people return to the good and simple life.

When the country is ruled with a light hand
The people are simple.
When the country is ruled with severity,
The people are cunning.

Happiness is rooted in misery.
Misery lurks beneath happiness.
Who knows what the future holds?
There is no honesty.
Honesty becomes dishonest.
Goodness becomes witchcraft.
Man’s bewitchment lasts for a long time.

Therefore the sage is sharp but not cutting,
Pointed but not piercing,
Straightforward but not unrestrained,
Brilliant but not blinding.

In caring for others and serving heaven,
There is nothing like using restraint.
Restraint begins with giving up one’s own ideas.
This depends on Virtue gathered in the past.
If there is a good store of Virtue, then nothing is impossible.
If nothing is impossible, then there are no limits.
If a man knows no limits, then he is fit to be a ruler.
The mother principle of ruling holds good for a long time.
This is called having deep roots and a firm foundation,
The Tao of long life and eternal vision.

Ruling the country is like cooking a small fish.
Approach the universe with Tao,
And evil is not powerful,
But its power will not be used to harm others.
Not only will it do no harm to others,
But the sage himself will also be protected.
They do not hurt each other,
And the Virtue in each one refreshes both.

A great country is like low land.
It is the meeting ground of the universe,
The mother of the universe.

The female overcomes the male with stillness,
Lying low in stillness.

Therefore if a great country gives way to a smaller country,
It will conquer the smaller country.
And if a small country submits to a great country,
It can conquer the great country.

Therefore those who would conquer must yield,
And those who conquer do so because they yield.

A great nation needs more people;
A small country needs to serve.
Each gets what it wants.
It is fitting for a great nation to yield.

Tao is source of the ten thousand things.
It is the treasure of the good man, and the refuge of the bad.
Sweet words can buy honor;
Good deeds can gain respect.
If a man is bad, do not abandon him.
Therefore on the day the emperor is crowned,
Or the three officers of state installed,
Do not send a gift of jade and a team of four horses,
But remain still and offer the Tao.
Why does everyone like the Tao so much at first?
Isn’t it because you find what you seek and are forgiven when you sin?
Therefore this is the greatest treasure of the universe.

Practice non-action.
Work without doing.
Taste the tasteless.
Magnify the small, increase the few.
Reward bitterness with care.

See simplicity in the complicated.
Achieve greatness in little things.

In the universe the difficult things are done as if they are easy.
In the universe great acts are made up of small deeds.
The sage does not attempt anything very big,
And thus achieved greatness.

Easy promises make for little trust.
Taking things lightly results in great difficulty.
Because the sage always confronts difficulties,
He never experiences them.

Peace is easily maintained;
Trouble is easily overcome before it starts.
The brittle is easily shattered;
The small is easily scattered.

Deal with it before it happens.
Set things in order before there is confusion.

A tree as great as a man’s embrace springs up from a small shoot;
A terrace nine stories high begins with a pile of earth;
A journey of a thousand miles starts under one’s feet.

He who acts defeats his own purpose;
He who grasps loses.
The sage does not act, and so is not defeated.
He does not grasp and therefore does not lose.

People usually fail when they are on the verge of success.
So give as much care to the end as to the beginning;
Then there will be no failure.

Therefore the sage seeks freedom from desire.
He does not collect precious things.
He learns not to hold on to ideas.
He brings men back to what they have lost.
He help the ten thousand things find their own nature,
But refrains from action.

In the beginning those who knew the
Tao did not try to enlighten others,
But kept it hidden.
Why is it so hard to rule?
Because people are so clever.
Rulers who try to use cleverness
Cheat the country.
Those who rule without cleverness
Are a blessing to the land.
These are the two alternatives.
Understanding these is Primal Virtue.
Primal Virtue is deep and far.
It leads all things back
Toward the great oneness.

Why is the sea king of a hundred streams?
Because it lies below them.
Therefore it is the king of a hundred streams.

If the sage would guide the people, he must serve with humility.
If he would lead them, he must follow behind.
In this way when the sage rules, the people will not feel oppressed;
When he stands before them, they will not be harmed.
The whole world will support him and will not tire of him.

Because he does not compete,
He does not meet competition.

Everyone under heaven says that my
Tao is great and beyond compare.
Because it is great, it seems different.
If it were not different, it would have vanished long ago.

I have three treasures which I hold and keep.
The first is mercy; the second is economy;
The third is daring not to be ahead of others.
From mercy comes courage; from economy comes generosity;
From humility comes leadership.

Nowadays men shun mercy, but try to be brave;
They abandon economy, but try to be generous;
They do not believe in humility, but always try to be first.
This is certain death.

Mercy brings victory in battle and strength in defense.
It is the means by which heaven saves and guards.

A good soldier is not violent.
A good fighter is not angry.
A good winner is not vengeful
A good employer is humble.
This is known as the Virtue of not striving.
This is known as ability to deal with people.
This since ancient times has been known as the ultimate unity with heaven.

There is a saying among soldiers:
I dare not make the first move but would rather play the guest;
I dare not advance and inch but would rather withdraw a foot.

This is called marching without appearing to move,
Rolling up your sleeves without showing your arm,
Capturing the enemy without attacking,
Being armed without weapons.

There is no greater catastrophe than underestimating the enemy.
By underestimating the enemy, I almost lost what I value.

Therefore when the battle is joined,
The underdog will win.

My words are easy to understand and easy to perform,
Yet no man under heaven knows them or practices them.

My words have ancient beginnings.
My actions are disciplined.
Because men do not understand, they have no knowledge of me.

Those that know me are few;
Those that abuse me are honored.
Therefore the sage wears rough clothing and holds the jewel in his heart.

Knowing ignorance is strength.
Ignoring knowledge is sickness.

If one is sick of sickness, then one is not sick.
The sage is not sick because he is sick of sickness.
Therefore he is not sick.

When men lack a sense of awe, there will be disaster.

Do not intrude in their homes.
Do not harass them at work.
If you do not interfere, they will not weary of you.

Therefore the sage knows himself but makes no show,
Has self-respect but is not arrogant.
He lets go of that and chooses this.

A brave and passionate man will kill or be killed.
A brave and calm man will always preserve life.
Of these two which is good and which is harmful?
Some things are not favored by heaven. Who knows why?
Even the sage is unsure of this.

The Tao of heaven does not strive, and yet it overcomes.
It does not speak, and yet is answered.
It does not ask, yet is supplied with all its needs.
It seems to have no aim and yet its purpose is fulfilled.

Heaven’s net casts wide.
Though its meshes are course, nothing slips through.

If men are not afraid to die,
It is no avail to threaten them with death.

If men live in constant fear of dying,
And if breaking the law means that a man will be killed,
Who will dare to break the law?

There is always an official executioner.
If you try to take his place,
It is like trying to be a master carpenter and cutting wood.
If you try to cut wood like a master carpenter, you will only hurt your hand.

Why are the people starving?
Because the rulers eat up the money in taxes.
Therefore the people are starving.

Why are the people rebellious?
Because the rulers interfere too much.
Therefore they are rebellious.

Why do the people think so little of death?
Because the rulers demand too much of life.
Therefore the people take death lightly.

Having little to live on, one knows better than to value life too much.

A man is born gentle and weak.
At his death he is hard and stiff.
Green plants are tender and filled with sap.
At their death they are withered and dry.

Therefore the stiff and unbending is the disciple of death.
The gentle and yielding is the disciple of life.

Thus an army without flexibility never wins a battle.
A tree that is unbending is easily broken.

The hard and strong will fall.
The soft and weak will overcome.

The Tao of heaven is like the bending of a bow.
The high is lowered, and the low is raised.
If the string is too long, it is shortened;
If there is not enough, it is made longer.

The Tao of heaven is to take from those who have too much and give to those who do not have enough.
Man’s way is different.
He takes from those who do not have enough and give to those who already have too much.
What man has more than enough and gives it to the world?
Only the man of Tao.

Therefore the sage works without recognition.
He achieves what has to be done without dwelling on it.
He does not try to show his knowledge.

Under heaven nothing is more soft and yielding than water.
Yet for attacking the solid and strong, nothing is better;
It has no equal.
The weak can overcome the strong;
The supple can overcome the stiff.
Under heaven everyone knows this,
Yet no one puts it into practice.
Therefore the sage says:
He who takes upon himself the humiliation of the people is fit to rule them.
He who takes upon himself the country’s disasters deserves to be king of the universe.
The truth often sounds paradoxical.

After a bitter quarrel, some resentment must remain.
What can one do about it?
Therefore the sage keeps his half of the bargain
But does not exact his due.
A man of Virtue performs his part,
But a man without Virtue requires others to fulfill their obligations.
The Tao of heaven is impartial.
It stays with good men all the time.

A small country has fewer people.
Though there are machines that can work ten to a hundred times faster than man, they are not needed.
The people take death seriously and do not travel far.
Though they have boats and carriages, no one uses them.
Though they have armor and weapons, no one displays them.
Men return to the knotting of rope in place of writing.
Their food is plain and good, their clothes fine but simple, their homes secure;
They are happy in their ways.
Though they live within sight of their neighbors,
And crowing cocks and barking dogs are heard across the way,
Yet they leave each other in peace while they grow old and die.

Truthful words are not beautiful.
Beautiful words are not truthful.
Good men do not argue.
Those who argue are not good.
Those who know are not learned.
The learned do not know.

The sage never tries to store things up.
The more he does for others, the more he has.
The more he gives to others, the greater his abundance.
The Tao of heaven is pointed but does no harm.
The Tao of the sage is work without effort.

The Tao that can be spoken of is not the eternal Tao.
The name that can be named is not the eternal name.

The nameless is the beginning of heaven and earth.
The name is the mother of the ten thousand things.

Send your desires away and you will see the mystery.
Be filled with desire
and you will see only the manifestation.

As these two come forth they differ in name.
Yet at their source they are the same.
This source is called a mystery.

Darkness within darkness,
the gateway to all mystery.

All under heaven see beauty as beauty
only because they also see ugliness.
All announce that good is good
only because they also denounce what is bad.

Therefore, something and nothing give birth to one another.
Difficult and easy complete one another.
Long and short fashion one another.
High and low arise from one another.
Notes and tones harmonize with one another.
Front and back follow one another.

Thus, the True Person acts without striving
and teaches without words.

Deny nothing to the ten thousand things.

Nourish them without claiming authority,
Benefit them without demanding gratitude,
Do the work, then move on.

And, the fruits of your labor will last forever.

Not exalting the talented prevents rivalry.
Not valuing goods that are hard to obtain
prevents stealing.
Not displaying desirable things
prevents confusion of the heart.

Therefore, the True Person governs by
emptying the heart of desire
and filling the belly with food,
weakening ambitions
and strengthening bones.

If the people are simple and free from desire,
then the clever ones never dare to interfere.

Practice action without striving
and all will be in order.

The Tao is like an empty bowl,
yet it may be used
without ever needing to be filled.
It is the deep and unfathomable source
of the ten thousand things.

Blunt the sharpness.
Untie the knot.
Soften the glare.
Settle with the dust.

It is hidden deep yet ever present.
I do not know whose child it is.
It existed before the common ancestor.

Heaven and earth are not moved
by offerings of straw-dogs.
The Trne Person is not moved
by offerings of straw-dogs.

The space between heaven and earth is like a bellows.
It is empty and yet never exhausted.
The more it works the more comes out.

Many words lead to exhaustion.
Better to hold fast to your center.

The valley spirit never dies.
It is the unknown first mother,
whose gate is the root
from which grew heaven and earth.
It is dimly seen, yet always present.
Draw from it all you wish;
it will never run dry.

Heaven and earth last forever.
The reason why heaven and earth last forever
is that they do not live for themselves.
Hence, they last forever.

Therefore, the True Person
leaves self behind
and thus is found in front,
is not guarded and thus is preserved,
is self-free and thus is able
to find fulfillment.

The highest good is like water.
For water benefits the ten thousand things without striving.
It settles in places that people avoid
and so is like the Tao.

In choosing your horne look to the land.
In preparing your heart go deep.
In associating with others value gentleness.
In speaking exhibit good faith.
In governing pruvide good order.
In the conduct of business be competent.
In action be timely.

Then there is no strife, nothing goes amiss.

Better to stop in time than to fill to the brim.
Hone a blade to the sharpest point,
and it will soon be blunt.
Fill your house with gold and jade,
and no one can protect it.
Be prideful about wealth and position,
and you bring disasters upon yourself.
Retire when the work is done.
This is the way of heaven.

While carrying your active life on your head
can you embrace the quiet spirit in your arms,
and not let go?
While being fully focused on vour vital breath
can you make it soft like that of a newborn babe?
While cleaning your inner mirror
can you leave it without blemish?
While loving the people and ruling the country
can you dispense with cleverness?
While opening and closing the gates of heaven
can you be like a mother bird?
While penetrating the four quarters with your insight
can you remain simple?

Help the people live!
Nourish the people!

Help them live yet lay no claim to them.
Benefit them yet seek no gratitude.
Guide thern yet do not control them.
This is called the hidden Virtue.

Thirty spokes connect to the wheel’s hub;
yet, it is the center hole
that makes it useful.
Clay is shaped into a vessel;
yet, it is the emptiness within
that makes it useful.
Doors and windows are cut for a room;
yet it is the space where there is nothing
that makes it useful.

Therefore, though advantage comes from what is;
usefulness comes from what is not.

The five colors blind the eye.
The five notes deafen the ear.
The five flavors dull the palate.
Racing and hunting drive the heart wild.
Goods that are hard to obtain hinder the journey.

Therefore, the True Person
is guided more by the belly than the eye,
and prefers this within to that without.

Both favor and disgrace bring fear.
Great trouble comes from having a body.

What is meant by:
“Both favor and disgrace bring fear”?
Favor leads to a fear of losing it and
disgrace leads to a fear of greater trouble.

What is meant by:
“Great trouble comes from having a body”?
The reason you have trouble is that
you are self-conscious.
No trouble can befall a self-free person.

Therefore, surrender your self-interest.
Love others as much as you love yourself.
Then you can be entrusted with all things under heaven.

Look at it, you cannot see it.
It is invisible.
Listen to it, you cannot hear it.
It is inaudible.
Reach for it, you cannot grasp it.
It is intangible.

These three qualities are unfathomable
and so they fuse together and become one.

The upper part is not bright.
The lower part is not dark.
Ceaselessly the Unnamed moves back to nothingness.
It has the form of the formless,
the image of the imageless.
It is indefinable and shadowy.
Go up to it and you will not see its front.
Follow it and you will not see its back.

Yet, hold fast to this ancient Tao and
you will experience the present now-moment.

Know its beginnings and
you can follow the path of the Tao.

The ancient followers of the Tao
were subtle, mysterious, and penetrating.
They were too deep to be fathomed.
All we can do is describe their appearance.
Hesitant, as if crossing a winter stream.
Watchful, as if aware of neighbors on all sides.
Respectful, like a visiting guest.
Yielding, like ice beginning to melt.
Simple, like an uncarved block.
Open, like a valley.
Obscure, like muddy water.

Who else can be still and let the muddy water
slowly become clear?
Who else can remain at rest and slowly come to life?

Those who hold fast to the Tao
do not try to fill themselves to the brim.
Because thev do not try to be full
they can be worn out and yet ever new.

Empty everything out;
hold fast to your stillness.
Even though all things are stirring together,
watch for the movement of return.
The ten thousand things flourish and then
each returns to the root from which it came.
Returning to the root is stillness.
Through stillness each fulfills its destiny.
That which has fulfilled its destiny
becomes part of the Always-so.
To be aware of the Always-so is to awaken.

Those who innovate while in ignorance of the Always-so
move toward disaster.
Those who act wirh awareness of the Always-so
embrace all, are not possessed by particular desire
and move toward the Tao.
Those who are at one with the Tao abide forever.
Even after their bodies waste away,
they are safe and whole.

The best leader is one whose existence
is barely known by the people.
Next comes one whom they love and praise.
Next comes one they fear.
Next comes one they defy.

If you do not trust enough, you will not be trusted.

True Persons do not offer words lightly.
When their task is accomplished
and their work is completed,
the people say, “It happened to us naturally.”

When the great Tao is forgotten,
benevolence and moral codes arise.
When shrewdness and cleverness appear,
great hypocrisy follows.
When there is no harmony in the family,
filial manners are developed
When the country is in disorder,
ministers appear as loyal servants.

Stop being learned and your troubles will end.

Give up wisdom, discard cleverness,
and the people will benefit a hundredfold.

Give up benevolence, discard moral judgments,
and the people will rediscover natural compassion.

Give up shrewdness, discard gain,
and thieves and robbers will disappear.

These three false adornments are not enough to live by.
They must give way to something more solid.
Look for what is simple and hold onto the Uncarved Block.
Diminish thoughts of self and restrain desires.

How great is the difference between “yea” and “yeah”?
How great is the distinction between “good” and “evil”?

Must I fear what others fear? How silly!

Everyone else is joyous as if enjoying the greatest feast,
or going up the terraces in spring.
I alone am drifting without direction,
like a baby who has not yet smiled.
I alone am moping as if I had no home.
Everyone else has more than they need,
I alone seem in want.
I have the mind of a fool, how confused I am!
Other people are bright and clever,
I alone am dark.
Other people are alert and self-assured,
If alone am dull and muddled.
I am unsettled like the waves of the sea,
like the restless wind.
Everyone else has a purpose,
I alone am stubborn and awkward.
I am different from other people,
Even so, I am nourished by the Great

The Great Virtue is to follow the Tao and only the Tao.

The Tao is shadowy and intangible.
Intangible and evasive, and yet within it is a form.
Evasive and intangible, and yet within it is a substance.
Shadowy and dark, and vet within it is a vital force.
This vital force is real and can be relied upon.

From ancient times to the present the Tao’s instructions
have not been forgotten.
Through it can be perceived the beginning of the story
of life.
How do I know how it was at the beginning of the story
of life?
Because of what is within me.

Yield and overcome;
bend and be straight.
Empty out and be full;
wear out and be renewed.
Have little and gain;
have much and be confused.

Therefore, the True Person embraces the One
and becorrles a model for all.

Do not look only at yourself,
and you will see much.
Do not justify yourself,
and you will be distinguished.
Do not brag,
and you will have merit.
Do not be prideful,
and your work will endure.

It is because you do not strive
that no one under heaven can strive with you.

The saying of the Old Ones, “Yield and Overcome,”
is not an empty phrase.
True wholeness is achieved
by blending with life.

To talk little is to follow nature.

A whirlwind does not last all morning.
A sudden shower does not last all day.
Who produces these things?
Heaven and earth!
Even heaven and earth cannot make
wild things last long.
How then can people hope to do so?

People of the Tao
conform to the Tao.
People of Virtue
conform to Virtue.
People who lose the way
conform to the loss.
Those who conform to the Tao
are welcomed into the Tao.
Those who conform to Virtue
are welcomed into Virtue.
Those who conform to the loss
are welcomed into the loss.

Those who do not trust enough
will not be trusted.

The person on tiptoe is not steady.
The person with legs astride cannot walk.

Those who look only at thernselves see little.
Those who justify themselves are not distinguished.
Those who brag have no merit.
The work of prideful people will not endure.

From the standpoint of the Tao,
these things are
“excessive food and tumors of the body.”
As they bring sickness, followers of the Tao do not linger around them.

Something formless yet complete,
existing before heaven and earth.
Silent and limitless,
it stands alone and does not change.
Reaching everywhere, it does not tire.
Perhaps it is the Mother of all things under heaven.
I do not know its name
so I call it “Tao.”

When I have to describe it I call it “great.”
Being great it flows.
It flows far away.
Having gone far away, it returns.

Therefore, the Tao is great.
Heaven is great.
Earth is great.
People are also great.
Thus, people constitute one of the
four great things of the universe.

People conform to the earth.
The earth conforms to heaven.
Heaven conforms to the Tao.
The Tao conforms to its own nature.

Whe solid must be the root of the light.
The still must be the master of thc restless.

Therefore, wise people when traveling all day
do not lose sight of their baggage cart.
Although there are beautiful scenes to see,
they remain quietly in their own place.
Should a lord of ten thousand chariots
appear more frivolous than a simple traveler?

To be light is to lose the root.
To be restless is to lose the master.

A skillful traveler leaves no track.
A skillful speaker makes no slip.
A skillful reckoner needs no counting rod.
A skillfully made door requires no bolts,
yet it cannot be opened.
A skillful binding has no cords or knots,
yet it cannot be untied.

Therefore, the True Person is skillful in assisting people,
and abandons nobody;
In skillful in assisting things,
and abandons nothing.
This is called “Following the lnner Light.”

Therefore, the skillful person is the teacher
of the person without skill.
The person withont skill is the material
for the skillfirl person.
If you do not respect the teacher,
if you do not care for the material,
you are on the road to confusion
and your cleverness will not save you.

This is an essential principle.

Develop the strength of a man,
but live as gently as a woman.
Become a brook and receive all things under heaven.
If you are such a brook
then Virtue will constantly flow into you
and you will become a simple child again.

Know thew pure
but live the life of the sullied.
Become a fountain to all things under heaven.
If you bccome such a fountain
then you will have abundant Virtue
and you will return to the state of the Uncarved Block.

When the Uncarved Block is cut up into pieces,
it is turned into specialized instruments.
But the True Person makes use of it whole
and becomes the master of the instruments.

Hence, it is said, “The finest carver cuts little.”

Whoever wishes to take over the world
will not succeed.
The world is a sacred vessel
and nothing should be done to it.
Whoever tries to tamper with it
will mar it.
Whoever tries to grab it
will lose it.

Hence, there is a time to go ahead
and a tirne to stay behind.
There is a time to breathe easy
and a time to breathe hard.
There is a tirne to be vigorous
and a tirrle to be gentle.
There is a tine to gather
and a time to release.

Therefore, the True Person avoids extremes,
self-indulgence, and extravagance.

If you would assist leaders of people
by way of the Tao,
you will oppose the use of armed force to overpower
the world.

Those who use weapons will be harmed by them.
Where troops have camped only thorn bushes grow.
Bad harvests follow in the wake of a great army.

The skillful person strikes the blow and stops,
without taking advantage of victory.
Bring it to a conclusion but do not be vain.
Bring it to a conclusion but do not be boastful.
Bring it to a conclusion but do not be arrogant.
Bring it to a conclusion but only when there is no choice.
Bring it to a conclusion but without violence.

When force is rlsed, youthful strength decays.
This is not the way of Tao.
And that which goes against the Tao
will quickly pass away.

Weapons are ill-omened things.

Among gentle people the left side
is the place of honor when at home,
but in war the right side is the place of honor.

Weapons are not proper instruments for gentle people;
they use them only when they have no other choice.
Peace and quiet are what they value.
They do not glory in victory.
to glorify it is to delight in the slaughter of people.
Those who delight in the slaughter of people will
never thrive among all that dwell under heaven.

The army that has killed people
should be received with sorrow.
Conquerors should be received with the rites of mourning.

The Tao is forever nameless.

Though the Uncarved Block is small,
it is not inferior to anything under heaven.
lf leaders could keep hold of it,
the ten thousand things would submit to them freely.
Heaven and earth would unite and sweet dew would fall.
The people would live in harmony
without any law or decree.

Only when the Block is carved are there names.
As soon as there are names
it is timc to stop.
Knowing when to stop prevents trouble.

All under heaven will return to the Tao
as brooks and streams flow home to the sea.

Knowing others is to be clever.
Knowing yourself is to be enlightened.
Overcoming others requires force.
Overcoming yourself requires strength.

To know that you have enough is to be rich.
Push through and you may get your way,
but return home and you will endure.
Live out your days and you have had a long life.

The great Tao covers everything like a flood.
lt flows to the left and to the right.
The ten thousand things depend upon it
and it denies none of them.
It accomplishes its task yet claims no reward.
It clothes and feeds the ten thousand things
yet it does not attempt to control them.
Therefore, it may be called “the little.”

The ten thousand things return to it,
even though it does not control them.
Therefore, it may be called “the great.”

So it is that the True Person does not wish to be great
and therefore becomes truly great.

Hold on to the Great Image
and all under heaven will approach you.
Coming to you and not being harmed,
they will find rest, peace, and security.

A passing guest will pause at the sound of music
and the smell of fancy food.
By comparison the Tao is mild and flavorless.
It is not solid enough to be seen,
nor loud enough to be heard.
Yet, it lasts forever.

That which is to be shrunk
must first be stretched out.
That which is to be weakened
must first be strengthened.
That which is to be cast down
must first be raised up.
That which is to be taken
must first be given.

There is wisdom in dimming your light.
For the soft and gentle
will overcome the hard and powerful.

Fish are best left in deep waters.
And, weapons are best kept out of sight.

The Tao never strives,
yet nothing is left undone.
If leaders were able to adhere to it
the ten thousand things would develop
of their own accord.
If after they have developed
they experience desires to strive,
they can bury those desires
under the nameless Uncarved Block.

The nameless Uncarved Block can protect
against desire.
When desires are restrained there will be peace,
and then all under heaven will be at rest.

THE SECOND BOOK: Te (Virtue)

A person of high virtue is not conscious of virtue
and therefore possesses Virtue.
A person of little virtue tries to be virtuous
and therefore lacks Virtue.
A person of high vir-tue does not make a fuss
and is not seen.
A person of little virtue always makes a fuss
and is always seen.
A truly good person functions without ulterior motive.
A moralist acts out of private desires.
A ritualist acts and, when no one responds,
rolls up a sleeve and marches.

When we lose the Tao, we turn to Virtue.
When we lose Virtue, we turn to kindness.
When we lose kindness, we turn to morality.
When we lose morality, we turn to ritual.

Ritual is the mere husk of good faith and loyalty
and the beginning of disorder.
Knowledge of what is to come
may be a flower of the Tao,
but it is the beginning of folly.

Hence, the well-formed person relies on what is solid
and not on what is flimsy,
on the fruit and not the flower.
Therefore, such a person lets go of that without
and is cont:ent with this within.

From ancient times these things have arisen from the One:

Heaven is clear because of the One,
The earth is firm because of the One,
The Spirit is strong because of the One,
The valley is full because of thc One,
The ten thousand things reprodnce because of the One,
Leaders are able to lead because of the One.

All of this comes from the One.

If heaven were not clear it would soon split.
If the earth were not firm it would soon bend and break.
If the Spirit were not strong it would soon wear out.
If the valley were not full it would soon dry up.
If the ten thousand things did not reproduce
they would soon die out.
If leaders could not lead they would soon fall.

Therefore, greatness has its source in the little.
The low is the foundation of the high.

Princes call themselves “alone,” “helpless,” “worthless.”
Is this not acknowledging a humble root?

Enumerate the parts of a carriage
and you have not defined a carriage.

Better to resound like stone chimes
than to tinkle like jade bells.

Returning is the direction of the Tao.
Yielding is the way of the Tao.

The ten thousand things are born of Being
and Being is born of Nonbeing.

The wise student on hearing the Tao
diligently puts it into practice.
The average student on hearing the Tao
keeps it one minute and loses it the next.
The mediocre student on hearing the Tao
laughs at it loudly.
If this student did not laugh it would not be the Tao.

Therefore, the ancient proverb says:

The bright path seems dull.
The path that goes torward seems to lead backward.
The even path seems up and down.
The greatest whiteness seems soiled.

High Virtue seems like a canyon.
Abundant Virtue seems deficient.
Vigorous Virtue seems limp.
Simple Virtue seems faded.

The greatest square has no corners.
The greatest vessel takes long to complete.
The greatest note is hard to hear.
The greatest image has no shape.

The Tao is hidden and nameless;
yet, it is the Tao alone that supports all thing
and brings them to completion.

The Tao gives birth to the One.
The One gives birth to two.
Two gives birth to three.
And three gives birth to the ten thousand things.

The ten thousand things have their backs in the shadow
while they embrace the light.
Harmony is achieved by blending
the breaths of these two forces.

People dislike the words “alone,” “helpless,” “worthless,”
yet this is how Princes describe them selves.

So it is that sometimes a thing is increased
by being diminished and
diminished by being increased.

What others teach I also teach:
“A violent person will not die a natural death.”
I shall make this the basis of my teaching.

The most yielding of all things
overcomes the hardest of all things.
That which has no substance
enters where there is no crevice.

Hence, I know the value of action without striving.

Few things under heaven bring more benefit than
the lessons learned from silence and
the actions taken without striving.

Your integrity or your body:
Which is more important?
Your body or your possessions
Which is worth more?
Gain or loss:
Which is more harmful?
Thus it is that the miser will pay much.
The hoarder will suffer great loss.
Be content with what you have
and you will not be disgraced.
Know when to stop
and you will be preserved from danger.
Only in this way will you long endure.

Great accomplishment seems incomplete,
yet its use is not impaired.
Great filllness seems empty,
yet it will never be drained.

Great straightness looks crooked.
Great skill appears clumsy.
Great eloquence sounds like stammering.

Movement overcomes cold,
stillness overcomes heat.

The calm and quiet set right
everything under heaven.

When the Tao prevails in the world
swift horses are used to fertilize the fields.
When the Tao is unheeded
war horses are bred on the border lands.

There is no greater offense than harboring desires.
There is no greater disaster than discontent.
There is no greater misfortune than wanting more.

Hence, if you are content
You will always have enough.

Without going outside
you can know the ways of the world.
Without looking through the window
you can see the way of heaven.
The farther you go
the less you know.

Therefore, the Trne Person
arrives without traveling,
perceives without looking,
and acts without striving.

In the pursuit of learning,
every day something isadded.
In the pursuit of the Tao,
every day something is dropped.

Less and less is done
until you come to action with striving.
When you follow this practice,
nothing remains undone.

All under heaven is won by
letting things take their cuurse.
Nothing can be gained by interfering.

The True Person does not have an individual heart
but uses the heart of the people.

I am kind to those who are kind.
I am also kind to those who are not kind.
Thus, there is an increase in kindness.
I keep faith with those who are in good faith.
I also keep faith with those WhO lack good faith.
Thus, there is an increase of good faith.

The True Person is detached and humble
and to the world appears confusing.
The people all strain their eyes and ears, yet the True Person remains childlike.

When going off one way means living
and going off the other way means dying,
three in ten are companions of Life,
three in ten are companions of Death, and
three in ten value Life but drift toward Death.

Why is all this so?
Because, these people are too greedy about living.

It is said:
People who are skillful in caring
for the life that has been given to them
travel abroad without fear of wild ox or tiger,
and enter a battle without concern for sharp weapons.
There is no place for the wild ox to thrust its horns,
there is no place for the tiger to put its claws,
there is no place for a weapon to lodge.

How is this so?
Because, there is no place for Death to enter in!

The Tao gives life to all things,
and its Virtue nourishes them,
forms each according to its nature
and gives to each its inner strengrth.

Therefore, the ten thousand things all venerate the Tao
and honor its Virtue.
It has never bccn decreed that the Tao be venerated
and its Virtue be honored;
they have always been so treated spontaneously.

Thus, the Tao gives life to all things;
and its Virtue raises them, nourishes them,
brings them to their full growth,
feeds, shelters, and protects them.

Giving life without claiming authority,
benefiting without demanding gratitude,
guiding without control.
This is called hidden Virtue.

All things under heaven had a common beginning,
and that beginning could be considered
the Mother of all things.
When you know the Mother
you will also know the children.
Know the children, yet hold fast to the Mother,
and to the end of your days
you will be free from danger.

Block the passages!
Shut the doors!
And, to the end of your days
your strength will not fail you.
Open the passages!
Increase your activities!
And, to the end of your days
you will be beyond help.

See the small and develop clear vision.
Practice yielding and develop strength.
Use the outer light to return to the inner light,
and save yourself from harm.

This is known as following the Always-so.

If I have even little sense,
I will walk upon the great path of Tao
and only fear straying from it.
This Great Way is straight and smooth
yet people often prefer the side roads.

The courtyard is well kept
but the fields are full of weeds,
and the granaries stand empty.
Still, there are those of us
who wear elegant clothes, carry sharp swords,
pamper ourselvcs with food and drink
and have more possessions than we can use.
These are the actions of robbers.

This is certainly far from the Tao.

What is well rooted cannot be pulled up.
What is firmly grasped will not slip loose.
It will be honored from generatlon to generation.

When cultivated in your person, Virtue will be real.
When cultivated in your household, Virtue will be plentiful.
When cultivated in your village, Virtue will endure.
When cultivated in your country, Virtue will abound.
When cultivated in your world, Virtue will be universal.

Hence, through yourself look at Self.
Through your household look at Household.
Through your community look at Community.
Through yonr country look at Country.
Through your world look at World.

How do I know that the world is like this?
Because of what is within me.

A person who is filled with Virtue
is like a newborn child.
Poisonons insects will not sting,
wild animals will not pounce,
birds of prey will not swoop down.
Although bones are soft and sinews weak,
a child’s grip is firm.
The union of man and woman is not known,
yet there is completeness,
because a child’s vital force is at its height.
Crying all day will not produce hoarseness,
because there is perfect harmony.

To know harmony is to know the Always-so.
To know the Always-so is to be awakened.

Trying to fill life to the brim invites a curse.
For the mind to Inake demands upon the breath of life
brings strain.

Whatever has been forced to a peak of vigor
approaches its decay.
This is not the way of Tao.
And that which goes against the Tao
will quickly pass away.

Those who know do not speak.
Those who speak do not know.

Block the passages!
Shut the doors!
Blunt the sharpness!
Untangle the knots!
Soften the glare!
Settle with the dust!
This is the Mystery of Evenness.

Those who have achieved this cannot be enclosed
nor kept at a distance;
they cannot be bene fited nor harmed,
honored nor disgraced.

Therefore, this is the noblest state under heaven.

Govern the country by being straightforward.
Wage war by being crafty.
Win all under heaven by not meddling.

How do I know that this is so?
By what is within me.

The more restrictions there are,
the poorer are the people.
The more pointed the people’s weapons,
the more disorder there is in the country.
The more ingenious and clever the people,
the more strange the contrivances that appear.
The more laws and edicts that are posted,
the more thieves and robbers that arise.

Hence an Old One has said:
I act without striving and the
people transform themselvey.
I love stillness and the
people straighten themselves.
I do not meddle and the
people prosper by themselves.
I am free from desires and the
people themselves return to the simplicily
of the Uncarved Block.

When the government is unseen
the people are simple and happy.
When the government is lively
the people are cunning and discontented.

On misery perches happiness.
Beneath happiness crouches misery.

Who knows when this will cease?
The straight changes into the crooked.
The good becomes the ominous.
Surely the people
have been confused for a long time.

Therefore, the True Person squares without cutting,
carves without hacking,
straightens without dislocating,
gives forth light without blinding.

For governing others and serving heaven
there is nothing better than moderation.
A person who is moderate returns to the path.
Returning to the path brings an abundance of Virtue.
This good store of Virtue cannot be conquered.
Virtue that cannot be conquered knows no limit.
Only a person who has lirnitiess Virtue is fit to lead.
Only the leader who possesses the Mother of the country
will long endure.
This is called making the roots go deep
by restraining the trunk.
Learn to focus your life and you will see many days.

Governing a big country is like cooking a small fish.

Let all under heaven be governed in accordance with the Tao,
and demons will not manifest their power.
It is not that they lack power
but rather they will not use their power
to harm the people.
They are not the only ones who have power
and do not use it to harm the people.
The True Person does not harm the people.
Whenever there is no harm done,
that power flows into the common Virtue.

A great country is like the low lands
where all the streams unite.

In all things under heaven
the female overcomes the male by her stillness,
and because she is still she lies below.

Hence, if the great country will take the low place
it will win over the little country.
If the little country will take the low place
it will win over the great country.

Thus, the one gets below and prospers
and the other remains below and prospers.
All that the great country wants is more people.
All that the little country wants is a place
for its people to go and to be employed.
If each is to get what it wants
it is necessary for the great country
to take the low place.

The Tao is to the ten thousand things
what the shrine is in the home.
It is the treasure of the virtuous
and the protection of the wrongdoer.

Good words are appreciated.
Good deeds deeds accepted as gifts.

Even the wrongdoers are not abandoned.

Hence, on the day an Emperor is installed
and appoints the three ducal ministers.
remain where you are and make an offering of the Tao.
It will be preferable to a gift ofjade discs
followed by a team of fonr horses.
Why did the ancients value the Tao?
Was it not because through it
you can find what you seek,
and because of it
you can escape what is hounding you?

Therefore, it is the most valuable thing under heaven.

Act without striving.
Work without interfering.
Find the flavor in what is flavorless.

Enlarge the small, increase the few.
Heal injury with goodness.

Handle the difficult while it is still easy.
Cultivate the great while it is still small.

All difficult things begin as easy things.
All great things begin as small things.

Therefore, the True Person never attempts anything great,
and accomplishes great things.

Lightly made promises inspire little faith.
Trying to make things easy results in great difficulties.

Therefore, the True Person regards everything as difficult,
and is never overcome by difficulties.

Peace is easily maintained while things are still at rest.
Trouble is easily handled before it starts.
What is brittle is easily broken.
What is minute is easily scattered.

Handle a problem before it appears.
Secure order before confusion begins.

A tree as big as a person’s embrace begins as a tiny shoot.
A terrace nine stories high rises from a shovelful of earth.
A journey of a thousand miles begins under your feet.

A person who interferes does harm,
and those who grasp lose their hold.
Therefore, the True Person acts without striving and does no
harm,
avoids grabbing and never loses hold.

People often ruin their ventures
when they are on the verge of success.
So, be as careful at the end as at the beginning,
and your work will not be ruined.

Therefore, the True Person seeks freedom from desire,
does not value things that are hard to come by,
learns without scholarship,
brings people back to what they have passed by,
and assists the ten thousand things to find their own
natures;
all without daring to interfere.

The ancients who practiced the Tao
did not use it to enlighten the people,
but rather to assist them in gaining simplicity.
The reason people are difficult to govern
is because they are too clever.

Hence, a person who attempts
to govern a country by cleverness
will injure it.
Those who govern without cleverness
will be a blessing to the land.
These are the two models.
Knowing these models is called the Mystic Virtue.
The Mystic Virtue is deep and so far-reaching
that it can lead all things back
toward great harmony.

How did the sea
gain kingship of a hundred streams?
Because it takes the lower position.
Hence, it is king of a hundred streams.

Therefore, when True Persons are over the people
they put themselves below the people by their speech.
When they lead the people
they stand behind the people.

When True Persons are given places above the people
they do not crush the people with their weight.
When they take their place ahead of the people
they do not obstruct the people’s progress.
That is why everything under heaven supports them gladly
and does not tire of them.

Because they strive with no one,
no one can ever strive with them.

Everyone under heaven says my Tao is great
and resembles nothing else.
It is because it is great that it seems different.
If it were like anything on earth
it would have been small from the beginning.

I have three treasures that I cherish and hald fast.
The first is gentleness,
the second is simplicity,
the third is daring not to be first
among all things under heaven.
Because of gentleness I am able to be courageous.
Because of simplicity I am able to be generous.
Because of daring not to be first
I am able to lead.

If people forsake gentleness and attempt to be courageous,
forsake simplicity and attempt to be generous,
forsake the last place and attempt to get the first place,
this is certain death.

Gentleness conquers in battle and protects in defense.
What heaven guards, it arms with the gift of gentleness.

A skilled warrior does not rush ahead of others
A skilled fighter does not make a show of anger.
A skilled victor does not seek revenge.
A skilled employer does not acr superior.

This is known as the virtue of not competing.
This is known as making use of the abilities of others.
This is known as being united with heaven
as it was in ancient times.

The master soldiers have a saying:
I dare not be the host but prefer to be the guest.
I dare not advance an inch
but prefer to retreat a foot.

This is called marching without Inoving,
rolling up a sleeve without baring an arm,
capturing a foe without a battlefront,
arming yourself without weapons.

There is no disaster greater than attacking
and finding no enemy.
Doing so will cost you your treasure.
Thus it is that when opposing forces meet,
victory will go to those
who take no delight in the situation.

My words are easy to understand
and easy to put into practice.
Yet no one under heaven understands them
or puts them into practice.

My words have an ancestor. My actions are governed.

Because people do not understand this
they do not understand me.
Those who understand me are few.
Those who follow me should be respected.

Therefore, the True Person wears homespun clothes
and carries jade in the heart.

lt is well to know that you do not know.
To think you know when you do not is sickness.

When you are sick of sickness you will no longer be sick.
True Persons are not sick because they are sick of sickness;
this is the way to health.

When the people lack a sense of awe
disaster will descend upon them.

Do not constrict their living space.
Do not harass them in their work.
If you do not oppress them, they will not weary of you.

Therefore, True Persons know themselves
but make no show of themselves.
They know their value
but do not exalt themselves.
They prefer this within to that without.

A person whose courage lies in daring will meet death.
A person whose courage lies in not daring
will encounter life.
Of the two courses, either may be beneficial or harmful.

Heaven dislikes what it dislikes.
Who knows the reason why?
Even the True Person has difficulty with such a question.

The Tao of Heaven
does not strive and yet it overcomes,
does not speak and yet it gets responses,
does not beckon and yet it attracts,
is at ease and yet it follows a plan.

The net of heaven is cast wide.
Though the mesh is coarse, nothing ever slips through.

When the people do not fear death,
of what use is it to threaten them with death?
If the people were always afraid of death
and if those who did wrong
would always be arrested and put to death,
who would do wrong?

There is always a Lord of Execution
whose duty it is to kill.
If you try to fill that function
it is like trying to hew wood
in place of a master carpenter. You will probably injure your own hands.

Why are the people starving?
Because their leaders eat up too much of the tax-grain;
that is why the people are starving.
Why are thc people difficult to govern?
Because their leaders interfere;
that is why the people are difficult to govern.
Why do the people treat death lightly.
Because their leaders are so grossly absorbed
in the pursuit of living;
that is why the people treat death lightly.

Indeed, it is wiser to ignore life altogether
than to place too high a value on it.

At birth you are supple and soft.
At death you are stiff and hard.
Grass and trees are pliant and tender when living,
but they are dry and brittle when dead.
Therefore, the stiff and hard are attendants of death,
the supple and soft are attendants of life.

Thus, the hard weapon will be broken.
The mighty tree will invite the axe.

Therefore, the hard and mighty belong below;
the yielding and gentle belong above.

The way of heaven is like the bending of a bow.
The high end is pulled down and the low end is raised up.
The excessive is dirninished
and the deficient is supplemented.

It is the way of heaven to take where there is too much
in order to give where there is not enough.
The way of people is otherwise.
They take where there is not enough
in order to increase where there is already too much.
Who will take from their own excesses
and give to all under heaven?
Only those who hold to the Tao.

Therefore, the True Person benefits yet expects no reward,
does the work and moves on.
There is no desire to be considered better than others.

Nothing under heaven is
softer or more yielding than water.
Yet it has no equal for attacking things
that are hard and stiff.
Nothing can withstand it.

Everyone knows that the yielding overcomes the stiff,
and the soft overcomes the hard.
Yet no one applies this knowledge.

Therefore, an Old One said:
Only a person who has accept,ed the country’s dirt
is a leader worthy to offer sacrifice
at its shrines of earth and grain.
Only a person who takes llp the country’s burdens
deserves to be a leader
among those who dwell under heaven.

Straightforward words seem crooked.

Even though a truce is made between great enemies,
some enmity is bound to remain.
How can this be beneficial?

Therefore, the True Person
undertakes the obligations of the agreerment
but makes no claim upon others.
The person who has Virtue shares with others.
The person who lacks Virtue takes fron others.

The way of heaven has no favorites;
it always remains with what is good.

In a small country with few people:
Though there are machines that would increase
production ten to a hundred miles
they are not used.
The people take death seriously and do not
travel about.

Though they have boats and carriages no one uses them.
Though they have armor and weapons,
there is no occasion to display them.

The people give up writing
and return to the knotting of cords.
They are satisfied with their food.
They are pleased with their clothes.
They are content with their homes.
They are happy in their simple ways.

Even though they live within sight of another country
and can hear dogs barking and cocks crowing in it,
still the people grow old and die
without ever coming into conflict.

Sincere words are not elegant;
elegant words are not sincere.
The good person does not argue;
the person who argues is not good.
The wise do not have great learning;
those with great learning are not wise.

True Persons do not hoard.
Using all they have for others, they still have more.
Giving all they have to others, they are richer than before.

The way of heaven is to benefit and not to harm.
The way of the True Reason is to assist without striving
in the unfolding of the story of the earth.

Even the finest teaching is not the Tao itself. Even the finest name is insufficient to define it. Without words, the Tao can be experienced, and without a name, it can be known. To conduct one’s life according to the Tao, is to conduct one’s life without regrets; to realize that potential within oneself which is of benefit to all. Though words or names are not required to live one’s life this way, to describe it, words and names are used, that we might better clarify the way of which we speak, without confusing it with other ways in which an individual might choose to live. Through knowledge, intellectual thought and words, the manifestations of the Tao are known, but without such intellectual intent we might experience the Tao itself. Both knowledge and experience are real, but reality has many forms, which seem to cause complexity. By using the means appropriate, we extend ourselves beyond the barriers of such complexity, and so experience the Tao.

We cannot know the Tao itself, nor see its qualities direct, but only see by differentiation, that which it manifests. Thus, that which is seen as beautiful is beautiful compared with that which is seen as lacking beauty; an action considered skilled is so considered in comparison with another, which seems unskilled. That which a person knows he has is known to him by that which he does not have, and that which he considers difficult seems so because of that which he can do with ease. One thing seems long by comparison with that which is, comparatively, short. One thing is high because another thing is low; only when sound ceases is quietness known, and that which leads is seen to lead only by being followed. In comparison, the sage, in harmony with the Tao, needs no comparisons, and when he makes them, knows that comparisons are judgements, and just as relative to he who makes them, and to the situation, as they are to that on which the judgement has been made. Through his experience, the sage becomes aware that all things change, and that he who seems to lead, might also, in another situation, follow. So he does nothing; he neither leads nor follows. That which he does is neither big nor small; without intent, it is neither difficult, nor done with ease. His task completed, he then lets go of it; seeking no credit, he cannot be discredited. Thus, his teaching lasts for ever, and he is held in high esteem.

By retaining his humility, the talented person who is also wise, reduces rivalry. The person who possesses many things, but does not boast of his possessions, reduces temptation, and reduces stealing. Those who are jealous of the skills or things possessed by others, most easily themselves become possessed by envy. Satisfied with his possessions, the sage eliminates the need to steal; at one with the Tao, he remains free of envy, and has no need of titles. By being supple, he retains his energy. He minimizes his desires, and does not train himself in guile, nor subtle words of praise. By not contriving, he retains the harmony of his inner world, and so remains at peace within himself. It is for reasons such as these, that an administration which is concerned with the welfare of those it serves, does not encourage status and titles to be sought, nor encourage rivalry. Ensuring a sufficiency for all, helps in reducing discontent. Administrators who are wise do not seek honours for themselves, nor act with guile towards the ones they serve.

It is the nature of the Tao, that even though used continuously, it is replenished naturally, never being emptied, and never being over-filled, as is a goblet which spills its contents upon the ground. The Tao therefore cannot be said to waste its charge, but constantly remains a source of nourishment for those who are not so full of self as to be unable to partake of it. When tempered beyond its natural state, the finest blade will lose its edge. Even the hardest tempered sword, against water, is of no avail, and will shatter if struck against a rock. When untangled by a cutting edge, the cord in little pieces lies, and is of little use. Just as the finest swordsmith tempers the finest blade with his experience, so the sage, with wisdom, tempers intellect. With patience, tangled cord may be undone, and problems which seem insoluble, resolved. With wise administrators, all can exist in unity, each with the other, because no man need feel that he exists, only as the shadow of his brilliant brother. Through conduct not contrived for gain, awareness of the Tao may be maintained. This is how its mysteries may be found.

Nature acts without intent, so cannot be described as acting with benevolence, nor malevolence to any thing. In this respect, the Tao is just the same, though in reality it should be said that nature follows the rule of Tao. Therefore, even when he seems to act in manner kind or benevolent, the sage is not acting with such intent, for in conscious matters such as these, he is amoral and indifferent. The sage retains tranquility, and is not by speech or thought disturbed, and even less by action which is contrived. His actions are spontaneous, as are his deeds towards his fellow men. By this means he is empty of desire, and his energy is not drained from him.

Like the sheltered, fertile valley, the meditative mind is still, yet retains its energy. Since both energy and stillness, of themselves, do not have form, it is not through the senses that they may be found, nor understood by intellect alone, although, in nature, both abound. In the meditative state, the mind ceases to differentiate between existences, and that which may or may not be. It leaves them well alone, for they exist, not differentiated, but as one, within the meditative mind.

When living by the Tao, awareness of self is not required, for in this way of life, the self exists, and is also non-existent, being conceived of, not as an existentiality, nor as non-existent. The sage does not contrive to find his self, for he knows that all which may be found of it, is that which it manifests to sense and thought, which side by side with self itself, is nought. It is by sheathing intellect’s bright light that the sage remains at one with his own self, ceasing to be aware of it, by placing it behind. Detached, he is unified with his external world, by being selfless he is fulfilled; thus his selfhood is assured.

Great good is said to be like water, sustaining life with no conscious striving, flowing naturally, providing nourishment, found even in places which desiring man rejects. In this way it is like the Tao itself. Like water, the sage abides in a humble place; in meditation, without desire; in thoughtfulness, he is profound, and in his dealings, kind. In speech, sincerity guides the man of Tao, and as a leader, he is just. In management, competence is his aim, and he ensures the pacing is correct. Because he does not act for his own ends, nor cause unnecessary conflict, he is held to be correct in his actions towards his fellow man.

The cup is easier to hold when not filled to overflowing. The blade is more effective if not tempered beyond its mettle. Gold and jade are easier to protect if possessed in moderation. He who seeks titles, invites his own downfall. The sage works quietly, seeking neither praise nor fame; completing what he does with natural ease, and then retiring. This is the way and nature of Tao.

Maintaining unity is virtuous, for the inner world of thought is one with the external world of action and of things. The sage avoids their separation, by breathing as the sleeping babe, and thus maintaining harmony. He cleans the dark mirror of his mind, so that it reflects without intent. He conducts himself without contriving, loving the people, and not interfering. He cultivates without possessing, thus providing nourishment, he remains receptive to changing needs, and creates without desire. By leading from behind, attending to that which must be done, he is said to have attained the mystic state.

Though thirty spokes may form the wheel, it is the hole within the hub which gives the wheel utility. It is not the clay the potter throws, which gives the pot its usefulness, but the space within the shape, from which the pot is made. Without a door, the room cannot be entered, and without windows it is dark. Such is the utility of non-existence.

Through sight, the colours may be seen, but too much colour blinds us. Apprehending the tones of sound, too much sound might make us deaf, and too much flavour deadens taste. When hunting for sport, and chasing for pleasure, the mind easily becomes perplexed. He who collects treasures for himself more easily becomes anxious. The wise person fulfills his needs, rather than sensory temptations.

The ordinary man seeks honour, not dishonour, cherishing success and abominating failure, loving life, whilst fearing death. The sage does not recognise these things, so lives his life quite simply. The ordinary man seeks to make himself the centre of his universe; the universe of the sage is at his centre. He loves the world, and thus remains unmoved by things with which others are concerned. He acts with humility, is neither moved nor moving, and can therefore be trusted in caring for all things.

The Tao is abstract, and therefore has no form, it is neither bright in rising, nor dark in sinking, cannot be grasped, and makes no sound. Without form or image, without existence, the form of the formless, is beyond defining, cannot be described, and is beyond our understanding. It cannot be called by any name. Standing before it, it has no beginning; even when followed, it has no end. In the now, it exists; to the present apply it, follow it well, and reach its beginning.

The sage of old was profound and wise; like a man at a ford, he took great care, alert, perceptive and aware. Desiring nothing for himself, and having no desire for change for its own sake, his actions were difficult to understand. Being watchful, he had no fear of danger; being responsive, he had no need of fear. He was courteous like a visiting guest, and as yielding as the springtime ice. Having no desires, he was untouched by craving. Receptive and mysterious, his knowledge was unfathomable, causing others to think him hesitant. Pure in heart, like uncut jade, he cleared the muddy water by leaving it alone. By remaining calm and active, the need for renewing is reduced.

It is only by means of being that non-being may be found. When society changes from its natural state of flux, to that which seems like chaos, the inner world of the superior man remains uncluttered and at peace. By remaining still, his self detatched, he aids society in its return to the way of nature and of peace. The value of his insight may be clearly seen when chaos ceases. Being one with the Tao is to be at peace, and to be in conflict with it, leads to chaos and dysfunction. When the consistency of the Tao is known, the mind is receptive to its states of change. It is by being at one with the Tao, that the sage holds no prejudice against his fellow man. If accepted as a leader of men, he is held in high esteem. Throughout his life, both being and non-being, the Tao protects him.

Man cannot comprehend the infinite; only knowing that the best exists, the second best is seen and praised, and the next, despised and feared. The sage does not expect that others use his criteria as their own. The existence of the leader who is wise is barely known to those he leads. He acts without unnecessary speech, so that the people say, „It happened of its own accord”.

When the way of the Tao is forgotten, kindness and ethics need to be taught; men learn to pretend to be wise and good. All too often in the lives of men, filial piety and devotion arise only after conflict and strife, just as loyal ministers all too often appear, when the people are suppressed.

It is better merely to live one’s life, realizing one’s potential, rather than wishing for sanctification. He who lives in filial piety and love has no need of ethical teaching. When cunning and profit are renounced, stealing and fraud will disappear. But ethics and kindness, and even wisdom, are insufficient in themselves. Better by far to see the simplicity of raw silk’s beauty and the uncarved block; to be one with onself, and with one’s brother. It is better by far to be one with the Tao, developing selflessness, tempering desire, removing the wish, but being compassionate.

The sage is often envied because others do not know that although he is nourished by the Tao, like them, he too is mortal. He who seeks wisdom is well advised to give up academic ways, and put an end to striving. Then he will learn that yes and no are distinguished only by distinction. It is to the advantage of the sage that he does not fear what others fear, but it is to the advantage of others that they can enjoy the feast, or go walking, free of hindrance, through the terraced park in spring. The sage drifts like a cloud, having no specific place. Like a newborn babe before it smiles, he does not seek to communicate. In the eyes of those who have more than they need, the sage has nothing, and is a fool, prizing only that which of the Tao is born. The sage may seem to be perplexed, being neither bright nor clear, and to himself, sometimes he seems both dull and weak, confused and shy. Like the ocean at night, he is serene and quiet, but as penetrating as the winter wind.

The greatest virtue is to follow the Tao; how it achieves ! without contriving. The essence of Tao is dark and mysterious, having, itself, no image or form. Yet through its non-being, are found image and form. The essence of Tao is deep and unfathomable, yet it may be known by not trying to know.

Yield, and maintain integrity. To bend is to be upright; to be empty is to be full. Those who have little have much to gain, but those who have much may be confused by possessions. The wise man embraces the all encompassing; he is unaware of himself, and so has brilliance; not defending himself, he gains distinction; not seeking fame, he receives recognition; not making false claims, he does not falter; and not being quarrelsome, is in conflict with no one. This is why it was said by the sages of old, „Yield, and maintain integrity; be whole, and all things come to you”.

Nature’s way is to say but little; high winds are made still with the turn of the tide, and rarely last all morning, nor heavy rain, all day. Therefore, when talking, remember also to be silent and still. He who follows the natural way is always one with the Tao. He who is virtuous may experience virtue, whilst he who loses the natural way is easily lost himself. He who is at one with the Tao is at one with nature, and virtue always exists for he who has virtue. To accept the irrevocable is to let go of desire. He who does not have trust in others should not himself be trusted.

He who stretches beyond his natural reach, does not stand firmly upon the ground; just as he who travels at a speed beyond his means, cannot maintain his pace. He who boasts is not enlightened, and he who is self-righteous does not gain respect from those who are meritous; thus, he gains nothing, and will fall into disrepute. Since striving, boasting and self-righteousness, are all unnecessary traits, the sage considers them excesses, and has no need of them.

The creative principle unifies the inner and external worlds. It does not depend on time or space, is ever still and yet in motion; thereby it creates all things, and is therefore called ‘the creative and the absolute’; its ebb and its flow extend to infinity. We describe the Tao as being great; we describe the universe as great; nature too, we describe as great, and man himself is great. Man’s laws should follow natural laws, just as nature gives rise to physical laws, whilst following from universal law, which follows the Tao.

The natural way is the way of the sage, serving as his dwelling, providing his centre deep within, whether in his home or journeying. Even when he travels far, he is not separate from his own true nature. Maintaining awareness of natural beauty, he still does not forget his purpose. Although he may dwell in a grand estate, simplicity remains his guide, for he is full aware, that losing it, his roots as well would disappear. So he is not restless, lest he loses the natural way. Similarly, the people’s leader is not flippant in his role, nor restless, for these could cause the loss of the roots of leadership.

The sage follows the natural way, doing what is required of him. Like an experienced tracker, he leaves no tracks; like a good speaker, his speech is fluent; He makes no error, so needs no tally; like a good door, which needs no lock, he is open when it is required of him, and closed at other times; like a good binding, he is secure, without the need of borders. Knowing that virtue may grow from example, this is the way in which the sage teaches, abandoning no one who stops to listen. Thus, from experience of the sage, all might learn, and so might gain. There is mutual respect twixt teacher and pupil, for, without respect, there would be confusion.

Whilst developing creativity, also cultivate receptivity. Retain the mind like that of a child, which flows like running water. When considering any thing, do not lose its opposite. When thinking of the finite, do not forget infinity. Act with honour, but retain humility. By acting according to the way of the Tao, set others an example. By retaining the integrity of the inner and external worlds, true selfhood is maintained, and the inner world made fertile.

The external world is fragile, and he who meddles with its natural way, risks causing damage to himself. He who tries to grasp it, thereby loses it. It is natural for things to change, sometimes being ahead, sometimes behind. There are times when even breathing may be difficult, whereas its natural state is easy. Sometimes one is strong, and sometimes weak, sometimes healthy, and sometimes sick, sometimes is first, and at other times behind. The sage does not try to change the world by force, for he knows that force results in force. He avoids extremes and excesses, and does not become complacent.

When leading by the way of the Tao, abominate the use of force, for it causes resistance, and loss of strength, showing the Tao has not been followed well. Achieve results but not through violence, for it is against the natural way, and damages both others’ and one’s own true self. The harvest is destroyed in the wake of a great war, and weeds grow in the fields in the wake of the army. The wise leader achieves results, but does not glory in them; is not proud of his victories, and does not boast of them. He knows that boasting is not the natural way, and that he who goes against that way, will fail in his endeavours.

Weapons of war are instruments of fear, and are abhorred by those who follow the Tao. The leader who follows the natural way does not abide them. The warrior king leans to his right, from whence there comes his generals’ advice, but the peaceful king looks to his left, where sits his counsellor of peace. When he looks to his left, it is a time of peace, and when to the right, a time for sorrow. Weapons of war are instruments of fear, and are not favoured by the wise, who use them only when there is no choice, for peace and stillness are dear to their hearts, and victory causes them no rejoicing. To rejoice in victory is to delight in killing; to delight in killing is to have no self-being. The conduct of war is that of a funeral; when people are killed, it is a time of mourning. This is why even victorious battle should be observed without rejoicing.

The Tao is eternal, but does not have fame; like the uncarved block, its worth seems small, though its value to man is beyond all measure. Were it definable, it could then be used to obviate conflict, and the need to teach the way of the Tao; all men would abide in the peace of the Tao; sweet dew would descend to nourish the earth. When the Tao is divided, there is a need for names, for, like the block which is carved, its parts then are seen. By stopping in time from torment and conflict, strife is defeated, and danger averted. The people then seek the wisdom of Tao, just as all rivers flow to the great sea.

Knowledge frequently results from knowing others, but the man who is awakened, has seen the uncarved block. Others might be mastered by force, but to master one’s self requires the Tao. He who has many material things, may be described as rich, but he who knows he has enough, and is at one with the Tao, might have enough of material things, and have self-being as well. Will-power may bring perseverance; but to have tranquility is to endure, being protected for all his days. He whose ideas remain in the world, is present for all time.

All things may act, without exclusion, according to the natural way, which fulfills its purpose silently, and with no claim. Being an aspect of natural order, it is not the ruler of any thing, but remains the source of their nourishment. It cannot be seen; it has no intention, but all natural things rely on its presence. When all things return to it, it does not enslave them, so unmanifested, its greatness prevails. Modelling himself upon the Tao, he who is wise, does not contrive, but is content with what he achieves.

The wise man acts at one with the Tao, for he knows it is here that peace is found. It is for this reason that he is sought. Whilst guests enjoy good music and food, as these are supplied by a benevolent host, a description of Tao seems without form, for it cannot be heard and cannot be seen. But when the music and food are all ended, the taste of the Tao still remains.

It is the way of the Tao, that things which expand might also shrink; that he who is strong, will at some time be weak, that he who is raised will then be cast down, and that all men have a need to give, and also have a need to receive. The biggest fish stay deep in the pond, and a country’s best weapons should be kept locked away. That which is soft and supple, may overcome the hard and strong.

The way of nature is not contrived, yet nothing which is required is left undone. Observing nature, the wise leader knows this, and replaces desire with dispassion, thus saving that energy, otherwise spent, which has not been wasted away. The wise leader knows his actions must be without the use of forced energy. He knows that more is still required, for he also knows that he must act without deliberate intent, of having no intention. To act without contrived intent is to act without contriving, and is the way of nature, and so is the way of the Tao.

A truly good man is unaware of the good deeds he performs. Conversely, a foolish man must try continuously to be good. A good man seems to do little or nought, yet he leaves nothing undone. A foolish man must always strive, whilst leaving much undone. The man who is truly wise and kind leaves nothing to be done, but he who only acts according to his nation’s law leaves many things undone. A disciplinarian wanting something done rolls up his sleeves, enforcing it with violence. It may be that goodness still remains, even when the natural way is lost, and that kindness still exists when goodness is forgotten. It may be that justice still remains when the people are no longer kind, and when this is lost, that ritual still remains. However, ritual may be performed only as an act of faith, and may be the beginning of confusion, for even divination and the such are but the flowery trappings of the Tao, and are the beginning of great folly. He who is truly great does not upon the surface dwell, but on what lies beneath. It is said that the fruit is his concern, rather than the flower. Each must decide what it might be he seeks, the flowery trapping, which comes to summer fullness first, or the fruit which is beneath.

From the principle which is called the Tao, the sky, the earth, and creativity are one, the sky is clear, the earth is firm, and the spirit of the inner world is full. When the ruler of the land is whole, the nation too is strong, alive and well, and the people have sufficient to meet their earthly needs. When the daytime sky is dark and overcast like night, the nation and its people will surely suffer much. The firmness of the dew filled earth gives it its life; the energy of the inner world prevents its becoming drained of strength; its fullness prevents it running dry. The growth of all things prevents their dying. The work of the leader should ensure the prosperity of the populace. So it is said, „humility is the root of great nobility; the low forms a foundation for the great; and princes consider themselves to be of little worth”. Each depends on humility therefore; it is of no advantage to have too much success, so do not sound loudly like jade bells, nor clatter like stone chimes.

The motion of nature is cyclic and returning. Its way is to yield, for to yield is to become. All things are born of being; being is born of non-being.

On hearing of the Tao, the wise student’s practice is with diligence; the average student attends to his practice when his memory reminds him so to do; and the foolish student laughs. But we do well to remember that with no sudden laughter, there would be no natural way. Thus it is said, „There are times when even brightness seems dim; when progress seems like regression; when the easy seems most difficult, and virtue seems empty, inadequate and frail; times when purity seems sullied; when even reality seems unreal, and when a square seems to have corners; when even great talent is of no avail, and the highest note cannot be heard; when the formed seems formless, and when the way of nature is out of sight”. Even in such times as these, the natural way still nourishes, that all things may be fulfilled.

The Tao existed before its name, and from its name, the opposites evolved, giving rise to three divisions, and then to names abundant. These things embrace receptively, achieving inner harmony, and by their unity create the inner world of man. No man wishes to be seen as worthless in another’s eyes, but the wise leader describes himself this way, for he knows that one may gain by losing, and lose by gaining, and that a violent man will not die a natural death.

Only the soft overcomes the hard, by yielding, bringing it to peace. Even where there is no space, that which has no substance enters in. Through these things is shown the value of the natural way. The wise man understands full well, that wordless teaching can take place, and that actions should occur without the wish for self-advancement.

A contented man knows himself to be more precious even than fame, and so, obscure, remains. He who is more attached to wealth than to himself, suffers more heavily from loss. He who knows when to stop, might lose, but in safety stays.

In retrospect, even those accomplishments which seemed perfect when accomplished, may seem imperfect and ill formed, but this does not mean that such accomplishments have outlived their usefulness. That which once seemed full, may later empty seem, yet still be unexhausted. That which once seemed straight may seem twisted when seen once more; intelligence can seem stupid, and eloquence seem awkward; movement may overcome the cold, and stillness, heat, but stillness in movement is the way of the Tao.

When the way of nature is observed, all things serve their function; horses drawing carts, and pulling at the plough. But when the natural way is not observed, horses are bred for battle and for war. Desire and wanting cause discontent, whilst he who knows sufficiency more easily has what he requires.

The Tao may be known and observed without the need of travel; the way of the heavens might be well seen without looking through a window. The further one travels, the less one knows. So, without looking, the sage sees all, and by working without self-advancing thought, he discovers the wholeness of the Tao.

When pursuing knowledge, something new is acquired each day. But when pursuing the way of the Tao, something is subtracted; less striving occurs, until there is no striving. When effort is uncontrived, nothing is left undone; the way of nature rules by allowing things to take their course, not by contriving to change.

The sage is not mindful for himself, but is receptive to others’ needs. Knowing that virtue requires great faith, he has that faith, and is good to all; irrespective of others’ deeds, he treats them according to their needs. He has humility and is shy, thus confusing other men. They see him as they might a child, and sometimes listen to his words.

In looking at the people, we might see that in the space twixt birth and death, one third follow life, and one third death, and those who merely pass from birth to death, are also one third of those we see. He who lives by the way of the Tao, travels without fear of ferocious beasts, and will not be pierced in an affray, for he offers no resistance. The universe is the centre of his world, so in the inner world of he who lives within the Tao, there is no place where death can enter in.

All physical things arise from the principle which is absolute; the principle which is the natural way. All living things are formed by being, and shaped by their environment, growing if nourished well by virtue; the being from non-being. All natural things respect the Tao, giving honour to its virtue, although the Tao does not expect, nor look for honour or respect. The virtue of the natural way is that all things are born of it; it nourishes and comforts them; develops, shelters and cares for them, protecting them from harm. The Tao creates, not claiming credit, and guides without interfering.

The virtue of Tao governs its natural way. Thus, he who is at one with it, is one with everything which lives, having freedom from the fear of death. Boasting, and hurrying hither and thither, destroy the enjoyment of a peace filled life. Life is more fulfilled by far, for he who does not have desire, for he does not have desire, has no need of boasting. Learn to see the insignificant and small, grow in wisdom and develop insight, that which is irrevocable, do not try to fight, and so be saved from harm.

When temptation arises to leave the Tao, banish temptation, stay with the Tao. When the court has adornments in profusion, the fields are full of weeds, and the granaries are bare. It is not the way of nature to carry a sword, nor to over-adorn oneself, nor to have more than a sufficiency of fine food and drink. He who has more possessions than he can use, deprives someone who could use them well.

That which is firmly rooted, is not easily torn from the ground; just as that which is firmly grasped, does not slip easily from the hand. The virtue of the Tao is real, if cultivated in oneself; when loved in the family, it abounds; when throughout the village, it will grow; and in the nation, be abundant. When it is real universally, virtue is in all people. All things are microcosms of the Tao; the world a microcosmic universe, the nation a microcosm of the world, the village a microcosmic nation; the family a village in microcosmic view, and the body a microcosm of one’s own family; from single cell to galaxy.

He who has virtue is like a newborn child, free from attack by those who dwell in the way of nature, the way of the Tao. The bones of the newborn child are soft, his muscles supple, but his grip is firm; he is whole, though not knowing he was born of the creative and receptive way. The way of nature is in the child, so even when he shouts all day, his throat does not grow hoarse or dry. From constancy, there develops harmony, and from harmony, enlightenment. It is unwise to rush from here to there. To hold one’s breath causes the body strain; exhaustion follows when too much energy is used, for this is not the natural way. He who is in opposition to the Tao does not live his natural years.

Those who know the natural way have no need of boasting, whilst those who know but little, may be heard most frequently; thus, the sage says little, if anything at all. Not demanding stimuli, he tempers his sharpness well, reduces the complex to simplicity, hiding his brilliance, seemingly dull; he settles the dust, whilst in union with all natural things. He who has attained enlightenment (without contriving so to do) is not concerned with making friends, nor with making enemies; with good or harm, with praise or blame. Such detatchment is the highest state of man.

With natural justice, people must be ruled, and if war be waged, strategy and tactics used. To master one’s self, one must act without cunning. The greater the number of laws and restrictions, the poorer the people who inhabit the land. The sharper the weapons of battle and war, the greater the troubles besetting the land. The greater the cunning with which people are ruled, the stranger the things which occur in the land. The harder the rules and regulations, the greater the number of those who will steal. The sage therefore does not contrive, in order to bring about reform, but teaches the people peace of mind, in order that they might enjoy their lives. Having no desires, all he does is natural. Since he teaches self-sufficiency, the people who follow him return to a good, uncomplicated life.

When the hand of the ruler is light, the people do not contrive, but when the country is severely ruled, the people grow in cunning. The actions of the sage are sharp, but they are never cutting, they are pointed, though never piercing, they are straightforward, not contrived, and not without restraint, brilliant but not blinding. This is the action of the sage, because he is aware that where happiness exists, there is also misery and strife; that where honesty may be found, there is occasion for dishonesty, and that men may be beguiled. The sage knows that no-one can foretell just what the future holds.

By acting with no thought of self-advancement, but with self-restraint, it is possible to lead, and genuinely care for others. This happens by acting virtuously, and leaving nothing to be done. A foundation virtuous and firm, rooted in receptivity, is a prerequisite of good leadership, and for a life both long and strong. He whose virtue knows no limit, is most fitting to lead. His roots are deep, and his life protected by his meditative practice, as the bark protects the tree.

To rule a country, one must act with care, as when frying the smallest fish. If actions are approached, and carried out in the natural way, the power of evil is reduced, and so the ruler and the ruled are equally protected. They will not contrive to harm each other, for the virtue of one refreshes the other.

A great country remains receptive and still, as does a rich and fertile land. The gentle overcomes the strong with stillness and receptivity. By giving way to the other, one country may conquer another; a small country may submit to a large, and conquer it, though having no arms. Those who conquer must be willing to yield; to yield may be to overcome. A fertile nation may require a greater population, to use its resources to the full, whilst the country without such natural wealth may require them to meet its people’s needs. By acting in unity, each may achieve that which it requires.

The source of all things is in the Tao. It is a treasure for the good, and a refuge for all in need. Whilst praise can buy titles, good deeds gain respect. No man should be abandoned because he has not found the Tao. On auspicious occasions, when gifts are sent, rather than sending horses or jade, send the teaching of Tao. When we first discover the natural way, we are happy to know that our misdeeds are in the past, where they belong, and so are happy to realize that we have found a treasure.

Act without contriving; work naturally, and taste the tasteless; magnify the small; increase the few, and reward bitterness with care. Seek the simple in the complex, and achieve greatness in small things. It is the way of nature that even difficult things are done with ease, and great acts made up of smaller deeds. The sage achieves greatness by small deeds multiplied. Promises easily made are most easily broken, and acting with insufficient care causes subsequent trouble. The sage confronts problems as they arise, so that they do not trouble him.

If problems are accepted, and dealt with before they arise, they might even be prevented before confusion begins, In this way peace may be maintained. The brittle is easily shattered, and the small is easily scattered. Great trees grow from the smallest shoots; a terraced garden, from a pile of earth, and a journey of a thousand miles begins by taking the initial step. He who contrives, defeats his purpose; and he who is grasping, loses. The sage does not contrive to win, and therefore is not defeated; he is not grasping, so does not lose. It is easy to fail when nearing completion, therefore, take care right to the end, not only in the beginning. The sage seeks freedom from desire, not grasping at ideas. He brings men back when they are lost, and helps them find the Tao.

Knowing it is against the Tao to try to enforce learning, the early sages did not contrive to teach the way of the Tao. There are two ways of government. One is to be cunning, to act with guile, and to contrive to cheat the people. When this way is used to rule, the people grow in cunning, and contrive to cheat the ruler. The second way to govern the land, is to do so without contriving. People so governed are truly blessed, for they are governed with virtue, and virtuous government is fair to all, thus leading to unity.

The sea is the ruler of river and stream, because it rules from well beneath. The teacher guides his students best, by allowing them to lead. When the ruler is a sage, the people do not feel oppressed; they support the one who rules them well, and never tire of him. He who is non-competitive invites no competition.

Those who follow the natural way are different from others in three respects. They have great mercy and economy, and the courage not to compete. From mercy there comes courage; from economy, generosity; and from humility, willingness to lead from behind. It is the way of sickness to shun the merciful, and to acclaim only heroic deeds, to abandon economy, and to be selfish. They are sick, who are not humble, but try always to be first. Only he who is compassionate can show true bravery, and in defending, show great strength. Compassion is the means by which mankind may be guarded and saved, for heaven arms with compassion, those whom it would not see destroyed.

An effective warrior acts not from nihilistic anger, nor from desire to kill. He who wins should not be vengeful. An employer should have humility. If we wish for peace and unity, our dealings with our fellow man must be without desire for self-advantage, and carried out without contention.

Arguments may be won by waiting, rather than making an aggresive move; by withdrawing rather than advancing. By moving without appearing to move, by not making a show of strength, but by conserving it well; by capturing without attacking, by being armed, but with no weapons, great battles may be won. Do not underestimate those you enjoin in battle, for this can result in losing what is of greatest value. When a battle is enjoined, by remembering this, the weaker may still win.

Though the words of the sage are simple, and his actions easily performed, they are few among many, who can speak or act as a sage. For the ordinary man it is difficult to know the way of a sage, perhaps because his words are from the distant past, and his actions naturally disposed. Those who know the way of the sage are few and far between, but those who treat him with honesty, will be honoured by him and the Tao. He knows he makes no fine display, and wears rough clothes, not finery. It is not in his expectancy of men that they should understand his ways, for he carries his jade within his heart.

To acknowledge one’s ignorance shows strength of personality, but to ignore wisdom is a sign of weakness. To be sick of sickness is a sign of good health, therefore the wise man grows sick of sickness, and sick of being sick of sickness, ’til he is sick no more.

The sage retains a sense of awe, and of propriety. He does not intrude into others’ homes; does not harass them, nor interfere without request, unless they damage others. So it is that they return to him. Though the sage knows himself he makes no show of it; he has self-respect, but is not arrogant, for he develops the ability to let go of that which he no longer needs.

A brave man who is passionate will either kill or be killed, but a man who is both brave and still might preserve his own and others’ lives. No one can say with certainty, why it is better to preserve a life. The virtuous way is a way to act without contriving effort, yet, without contriving it overcomes. It seldom speaks, and never asks, but is answered without a question. It is supplied with all its needs and is constantly at ease because it follows its own plan which cannot be understood by man. It casts its net both deep and wide, and though coarse meshed, it misses nothing in the tide.

If the people are not afraid of death, they have no fear of threats of death. If early death is common in the land, and if death is meted out as punishment, the people do not fear to break the law. To be the executioner in such a land as this, is to be as an unskilled carpenter who cuts his hand when trying to cut wood.

When taxes are too heavy, hunger lays the people low. When those who govern interfere too much, the people become rebellious. When those who govern demand too much of people’s lives, death is taken lightly. When the people are starving in the land, life is of little value, and so is more easily sacrificed by them in overthrowing government.

Man is born gentle and supple. At death, his body is brittle and hard. Living plants are tender, and filled with life-giving sap, but at their death they are withered and dry. The stiff, the hard, and brittle are harbingers of death, and gentleness and yielding are the signs of that which lives. The warrior who is inflexible condemns himself to death, and the tree is easily broken, which ever refuses to yield. Thus the hard and brittle will surely fall, and the soft and supple will overcome.

The Tao is as supple as a bow; the high made lower, and the lowly raised. It shortens the string which has been stretched, and lengthens that which has become too short. It is the way of the Tao to take from those who have a surplus to what they need, providing for those without enough. The way of the ordinary person, is not the way of the Tao, for such people take from those who are poor and give to those who are rich. The sage knows that his possessions are none, therefore he gives to the world; without recognition, doing his work. In this way he accomplishes that which is required of him; without dwelling upon it in any way, he gives of his wisdom without display.

There is nothing more yielding than water, yet when acting on the solid and strong, its gentleness and fluidity have no equal in any thing. The weak can overcome the strong, and the supple overcome the hard. Although this is known far and wide, few put it into practice in their lives. Although seemingly paradoxical, the person who takes upon himself, the people’s humiliation, is fit to rule; and he is fit to lead, who takes the country’s disasters upon himself.

When covenants and bonds are drawn between the people of the land, that they might know their obligations, it is commonplace for many to fail to meet their dues. The sage ensures his dues are met, though not expecting others to do the same; in this way he is virtuous. He is without virtue of his own, who asks of others that they fulfil his obligations on his behalf. The way of nature does not impose on matters such as these but stays with the good for ever, and acts as their reward.

A small country may have many machines, but the people will have no use for them; they will have boats and carriages which they do not use; their armour and weapons are not displayed, for they are serious when regarding death. They do not travel far from home, and make knots in ropes, rather than do much writing. The food they eat is plain and good, and their clothes are simple; their homes are secure, without the need of bolts and bars, and they are happy in their ways. Though the cockerels and dogs of their neighbours can be heard not far away, the people of the villages grow old and die in peace.

The truth is not always beautiful, nor beautiful words the truth. Those who have virtue, have no need of argument for its own sake, for they know that argument is of no avail. Those who have knowledge of the natural way do not train themselves in cunning, whilst those who use cunning to rule their lives, and the lives of others, are not knowledgeable of the Tao, nor of natural happiness. The sage seeks not to have a store of things or knowledge, for he knows, the less of these he has, the more he has, and that the more he gives, the greater his abundance. The way of the sage is pointed but does not harm. The way of the sage is to work without cunning.

PREFACE

A number of problems arise when translating any work from a written language, such as early Chinese, into twentieth century English. One such problem is the difference between the written forms of the two languages, another is the difference between the two cultures, and a third is the time which elapsed between the writing of the original work, in this instance, some time between six hundred and three hundred years before the Christian era, and the compilation of the textual arrangement by Wang Bih, dating from the third century A.D., used today.

There are however, other problems for any translator/interpreter of this work. The first is the number of changes in the form of written Chinese characters since the original work was written. At least one such change occurred prior to the arrangement of the text by Wang Bih, and at least another three have been implemented since his time.

The source of another problem has been described by Dr. L. Wieger (please see bibliography/reference section below) as, „… the ignorance of scribes who continually brought to light faulty forms which were … reproduced by posterity …”.

Another problem related to those mentioned immediately above is the change in writing instruments used by Chinese scribes. With the invention of the paint brush, the efficient ‘fibre tipped pen’ (made from vegetable fibre soaked in ink, and held in a hollow bamboo tube) fell into disuse. The resultant change in writing style was due to the fact that the writer had less control over the stroke of a brush than of an instrument with a fine, firm tip. Despite this handicap, the brush could be used to paint on silk, and was considered to produce a more ‘artistic’ form of calligraphy than the earlier instrument. Furthermore, it became almost a ‘hallmark of a gentleman’ to write in a free, flowing and virtually illegible style. There can be no doubt that this was the cause of many errors which were made and subsequently compounded.

A further problem is the possibility of confusion, caused in part by the multiple meanings of some of the limited number of characters said to have been used in the original text, this being attributed to the cryptic style of Lao Tzu. It is also in part a result of the nature of early Chinese grammatical structure itself. Even if a literal translation were desirable, it would make little sense to the reader schooled only in Western grammar, who would therefore be unfairly presented with the problem of ‘guessing the missing words’, which, it may be said, is a primary function of the translator of any work such as this.

Having discussed the problems which exist for the translator of such a work as the Tao Te Ching, it is only reasonable to mention briefly the problem which exists for the reader, concerning the significance of various influences upon a translator.

There are already at least forty-two English translations of this work (listed by Clark Melling of the University of New Mexico), each, I am sure, carried out as ably and honestly as was possible. However, it is difficult, if not impossible, for any person not to be influenced by the philosophy, beliefs, culture and politics of their own society, historical period and education system.

Even a brief glance at various translations of the work of Lao Tzu will illustrate how such a ‘hidden curriculum’ surreptitiously imposes itself upon even the most honest of men, thus creating a major problem for the reader. This is the case even for the reader who merely hopes to see an accurate English rendering of the work, but the reader’s problems are compounded if he or she seeks a translation which presents a reasonably accurate description of Taoism (Tao Chia), the ‘system’ of which the Tao Te Ching is a major work. It must be said of the existing English translations, that most treat the Tao Te Ching as a literary or poetic work, whilst many others treat it as a work of mysticism, rather than a work of classical scholarship, which I believe it to be, describing the key concepts of Taoist philosophy (tao chia) expressed in a poetic manner. My intention here has been to provide a translation suitable for those readers wishing to discover something of that philosophy, as described in one of its major works.

On the matter of ‘translation’, I should state that I consider the term to be a misnomer when applied to an English rendering of this classical Chinese work. For the reasons mentioned above, I believe that any such work is at least as much, and probably more a matter of interpretation than of literal translation. This problem is admirably expressed by Arthur Hummel, former Head of the Division of Orientalia at the Library of Congress when he writes in his foreword to Dr. C.H. Wu’s translation (referenced), „Any translation is an interpretation … for the language of one tradition does not provide exact verbal equivalents for all the creative ideas of another tradition.”

Whilst I have tried to ensure the accuracy of my own sources, this does not of course guarantee the accuracy of the result. Furthermore, since I have not attempted to be literally accurate in my interpretation, and because this rendering is not intended to compete with such translations, I have listed below some titles, including ten translations of the Tao Te Ching, which have been of value in this undertaking. They are listed in order to acknowledge the work of the translators, as well as to provide alternative sources for those readers wishing to conduct their own research and comparisons. The other titles are those of books on the Chinese language, and these are listed for the benefit of those readers wishing to undertake their own translations.

BIBLIOGRAPHY AND REFERENCES

‘Tao Te Ching’, translated by Gia-Fu Feng and Jane English, is published by Wildwood House. It concerns itself with the ‘spiritual level of being’, and contains Chinese characters written in a cursive form which although not always easy to read, are certainly aesthetically pleasing. However, the photographs which illustrate this edition are also pleasing to the eye, and it is as much for the illustrations as for the translation that this edition is recommended.

‘Lao Tzu Tao Te Ching’ is translated by D.C. Lau, and published by Penguin Books in their ‘Penguin Classics’ series. It is currently in its seventeenth printing, the first edition dating from nineteen sixty-three. Although this translation is written in a style which I find rather too literal for my own taste, it carries a very lucid introduction, as well as footnotes, a glossary and a reference section, all of which recommend it to the reader who wishes to check reference sources.

‘Truth and Nature’, by Cheng Lin, published in Hong Kong, does not claim to be a translation, but interprets the Tao Te Ching in a very interesting manner. Two arrangements of the Chinese text are included, one according to the arrangement of Wang Bih. The reader wishing to use the original language as a source will find the Chinese text in this edition of value. It must be emphasized however, that there are a number of Chinese texts available. Whilst these usually conform to Wang Bih’s arrangment of the text, they do vary in detail.

‘The Simple Way of Lao Tsze’ (sic) is a very pleasant analysis of the Tao Te Ching first published by ‘The Shrine of Wisdom’ in London some sixty years ago. It contains many footnotes, and is an interpretation rather than a direct translation, attempting to describe the ‘spirit’ of Taoism, and doing so without pretence. However, some readers may find the nomenclature somewhat esoteric (although it is only reasonable to expect that the same criticism might be levelled at my own interpretation).

‘Lao-Tzu: „My Words are very easy to understand”’ by Man-jan Cheng, translated by Tam C.Gibbs, and published by North Atlantic Books, is a Confucionist (rather than Taoist) rendering. It therefore contains material of value to the student who wishes to ‘see both sides of the coin’. This edition consists of a series of lectures by Man-jan Cheng, and includes the Chinese texts of both the Tao Te Ching and the lectures. The printing of the Chinese characters is large and clearly printed, which commends it to the student requiring a text in the ‘original’ language, although it must be emphasized that there are a number of differences between the Chinese text in this edition and that of Dr. Wu, mentioned immediately below.

The translation by Dr. J.C.H. Wu is in its eighteenth printing, a fact which will not surprise any reader of this delightful little edition. Small in size, and containing an excellently drafted Chinese text, this translation is likely to appeal to the reader who is of the Catholic faith.

‘The Way and Its Power’ is the title of the translation by Arthur Waley, published as ‘A Mandala Book’ by Unwin Paperbacks. As the translator himself says, it „represents a compromise…”, but even so it is possibly the most widely read translation in the U.K. It is for this reason that it is included it as a reference work worthy of reading. The use of the word ‘power’ in the title of this translation provides a clue to the style of the translator, who employs very strong academic (but non-Taoist) arguments, which are made in his copious introduction.

The translation entitled ‘Tao Te Ching by Lao Tzu’, translated by A.J. Bahm, and published by Frederick Ungar is well supported by notes in an ‘afterword’. The translation itself is written in a very pleasant and easy-to-read style, which is (unfortunately) unusual for the work of a professor of philosophy.

‘Tao: A New Way of Thinking’ by Chang Chung-yuan, published by Harper and Row, is a translation which contains excellent commentaries and footnotes. The translator undoubtedly has expert historical and philosophical knowledge which he puts to good use in this excellent edition, in which he compares various aspects of Taoist philosophy with that of European philosophers.

The tenth translation used for my own researches is ‘The Tao Te Ching of Lao Tzu’ translated by James Legge as one of a two volume set of ‘The Texts of Taoism’, published by Dover Publications. Although written in eighteen-ninety, this translation withstands the test of time extremely well. The translator was very knowledegable in his subject, as well as of Chinese philosophy, literature and religions, and does not hesitate to state his opinions, arguing a strong case where these differ from those of other translators from the Chinese.

Because of the changes in calligraphic style mentioned earlier, any student wishing to conduct their own research into the Chinese text of the Tao Te Ching will need to be at least familiar with the relationship between modern and classical Chinese characters.

An outstanding book covering the ‘middle period’ is the ‘Ch’ien Tzu Wen’ (Thousand Character Classic) of Chou Hsing-szu, written some time between 507 and 521 A.D., an excellent English language edition being that edited by F. W. Paar, with calligraphy by Fong-Chih Lui, and published by Frederick Ungar in 1963. This edition also carries translations in French, German and Latin. Although it is not a rendering of the Tao Te Ching, it contains many passages from that work.

‘Chinese Characters’ by L. Wieger, translated from the French by L. Davrout (mentioned previously) is a lexicon with etymological lessons, but also contains both a phonetic dictionary and a dictionary of characters arranged by ‘radicals’ (the means by which it is possible to ‘find’ a character written in ‘Kanji’, the root form of both Chinese and Japanese writing in a dictionary). This book also contains a number of examples of ‘early period’ characters which will be of value to those readers interested in the calligraphy and other graphic communication.

In similar vein, ‘Analysis of Chinese Characters’, by G.D. Wilder and J.H. Ingram, published by Dover Publications, complements the work of Wieger, listing one thousand and two characters, together with derivations and modern alternatives.

Chang Hsuan’s work on ‘The Etymologies of 3000 Chinese Characters in Common Usage’, published by Hong Kong University Press, also shows the derivations of many Chinese characters, from the ‘small seal’ script. Unfortunately however, this book contains virtually no English and is therefore intended primarily for the student who is already proficient in the Chinese language.

The earliest form of Chinese writing predates even the Tao Te Ching, and possibly originates from the same period as the original I Ching of Fu Hsi. This writing consists of characters inscribed on bone, shell and antler horn, the collection being known as ‘The Couling-Chalfant Collection of Inscribed Oracle Bones’. The collection has long been dissipated, some pieces being in the Royal Scottish Museum (Edinburgh), some in the Carnegie Museum (Pittsburg), other pieces in the British Museum (London), and the remainder in the Field Museum of Natural History (Chicago). Fortunately though, an excellent catalogue exists, drawn by F.H. Chalfant, edited by R.S. Britton, and published by the Commercial Press, Shanghai, in 1935. This book illustrates each of the pieces, showing the characters inscribed on the original material. It is a particularly valuable work for those interested in tracing the origins of many of the Chinese characters in use to this day. Translations are not provided.

The philosopher Chuang Tzu, a follower of Lao Tzu, did much to clarify the somewhat criptic style of his teacher. The book ‘Chuang Tzu’ translated by H.A. Giles, published by Unwin Paperbacks, renders the sayings of the later master into English in a clear and fine literary style. This book, said to have been originally written by Chuang Tzu himself sometime between the fourth and third centuries before the Christian era, contains a number of references to the Tao Te Ching. For this reason it is a valuable book, but its value is increased by the humour and depth inherent in Chuang Tzu’s writing.

It may be of interest to some readers that the dictionaries I have used are Lin Yutang’s ‘Chinese English Dictionary of Modern Usage’, published by the Chinese University of Hong Kong, and Andrew Nelson’s ‘The Modern Reader’s Japanese-English Character Dictionary’, published by Charles E. Tuttle.

Since it may seem strange that I have used a Japanese dictionary to translate a Chinese work, it is perhaps worth mentioning that many Japanese characters are Chinese in origin, and that the characters in Andrew Nelson’s dictionary are listed in a sequence, and according to a system different from the same characters in the dictionary by Lin Yutang. Although the spoken Chinese and Japanese languages differ considerably, the written Japanese language has its roots in the Chinese. I therefore use the Japanese dictionary as a ‘cross-reference’ for finding the meaning of characters which I have difficulty in locating by Lin-Yutang’s arrangement.

ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS

The fact that I have not listed more of the forty-two English translations of the Tao Te Ching is not meant to reflect in any way on their quality, but simply means that I have not used them on this occasion; all of them, of course, have something of value to offer.

Since I have acknowledged the work of other translators and interpreters, it would be remiss of me not to acknowledge the help I received from my own teachers, each of whom attempted to aid my understanding and development in his own unique manner. The reason why I refrain from mentioning them by name in print is not due to disrespect, but rather out of respect for the Taoist belief that,

„To boast of one’s teachers is to try to give credence to one’s own words.”

Fortunately it is not considered boastful to mention in print, one’s own students. It is therefore with pleasure and gratitude that I acknowledge the help I have received from those who consider me their teacher, and through whose questions I have gained so much. On this occassion my special thanks go to Ian (and his wife, Jeanette) for their company, the help they provided without being asked, and for their patience; to Michael, who did most of the proof-reading; to Jackie who transcribed my notes to the ‘word processor’ (which does not know that its ‘sixty-four bit binary system’ is an outcome of Taoist ‘yin-yang’ philosophy) and who tried to ensure that what I had written made sense; and to Judith, particularly for providing me with a copy of her B.A. dissertation ‘A Comparison of Plotinus and Chuang Tzu’, which was of great help in explaining some of the more obscure phrases in other translated texts.

Finally, I take this opportunity (on behalf of Judith and all other members of the English speaking Zen Taoist community) to thank Professor Cavendish, former Professor of Philosophy at Saint David’s University College, Lampeter, who personally supervised her dissertation, which is of value to us all.

INTRODUCTION: THE TAO TE CHING, LAO TZU, TAOISM AND ZEN

There is frequently some confusion between three practices, each of which is generically termed ‘Taoism’. Since this confusion exists, it is important that the prospective student of Taoism can distinguish between them. The three activities, or practices of Taoism are Philosohical or speculative Taoism, Religious or esoteric Taoism, and Alchemical or ‘debased’ Taoism.

The earliest of these is Philosophical Taoism (Tao-chia), which is believed to have developed between the sixth to the second century before the Christian era, from the earlier ‘Yin-Yang’ school of philosophy, whose teachings it inherited and integrated into its own ‘philosophical system’ through the ‘I Ching’, now (unfortunately) most widely known as a work of ‘divination’.

Philosophical Taoism is generally thought to have been based on the ‘Tao Te Ching’ of the possibly legendary Lao Tzu, and the work of his follower, Chuang Tzu, which is known through the book which bears his name, and is otherwise without title.

The major development and establishment of Religious Taoism (Tao-chiao) took place during the two Han dynasties (from 206 B.C. to 220 A.D.), and considered the Tao Te Ching as divine teaching, using specific interpretations of Lao Tzu’s work as one of its own primary scriptures. The Religious Taoists deified Lao Tzu, describing him as the ‘T’ai Shang Lao-chun’. In later centuries, Religious Taoism was to become a very powerful movement throughout China, where it was widely practiced, at least until the middle of the twentieth century.

The earliest known reference to Alchemy (in Eastern and Western Literature) is in the ‘Shi-chi’, written about eighty-five B.C., but the ‘Chou’-i ts’an t’ung ch’i’ of Wei Poyang (c.200 A.D.) was probably the first major alchemical text to use a Taoist work to this end, some auhorities believeing the treatise to be a derivation of the I Ching. This form of alchemy was referred to by the Philosophical Taoists as ‘debased Taoism’.

Of these three ‘forms’ of Taoism (or practices which called themselves Taoist), Religious and Alchemical Taoism are not mentioned in the text of this work, other than where they, and similar practices, were referred to, usually indirectly, in the Chinese text (and then usually in a derisory manner).

Readers of both the I Ching and the Tao Te Ching will readily apppreciate from many of Lao Tzu’s statements, that he was certainly well versed in the concepts explained in the earlier work, and accepted its major precept, that all things are always in a state (or process) of change (‘I Ching’ means ‘Book of Changes’). However, even allowing for the age of the I Ching, and the certainty that its concepts were well known in China at the time of Lao Tzu, it would seem, from historical records, that the Tao Te Ching was considered to be a perplexing book, even in the period in which it was written. Although not mentioning either Lao Tzu or the Tao Te Ching (nor the I Ching) by name, many of Chuang Tzu’s stories (which are probably apocryphal) serve to illustrate and explain points from the Tao Te Ching. If there were no confusion or doubt, presumably such explanatory material would not have been required.

In its original form, the Tao Te Ching (as it is now known) is believed to have consisted of eighty-one short chapters, these being arranged in two sections, known as the ‘Tao Ching’ and the ‘Te Ching’. The first of these was comprised of thirty-seven chapters, and the second of forty-four chapters. The length of the original work is said to have been approximately five-thousand characters, and it is probable that these were written on bamboo strips or slats, which would then have been bound together to form two scrolls, each appearing somewhat like a venitian blind with vertical slats. These were a common form of ‘record’ in the period of Lao Tzu, this being known as ‘The Period of the Warring States’.

Since it is not known with absolute certainty that a person named ‘Lao Tzu’ actually lived during the period of the warring states, to catagorically describe the Tao Te Ching as the work of Lao Tzu would be without sufficiently valid historical foundation. Even the ‘biography of Lao Tzu’ which may be found in the ‘Historical Records’ (Shih-chi) of Ssu-ma Ch’ien (second century B.C.) is not without its inconsistencies. This record describes Lao Tzu as having been an archivist of the Court of Chou, and further states that he is said to have personally instructed Kung Fu Tzu (Confucius).

It is in this last statement that one inconsistency may be found, for other chronicles state the date of the death of Lao Tzu to precede that of the birth of Kung Fu Tzu by nearly half a century. Even the author of the ‘Historical Records’ states his doubts as to the authenticity of the information available regarding Lao Tzu, and some scholars maintain that the Tao Te Ching does not present a distinctive or single point of view. They argue that it is probably a compilation or anthology of sayings from various writers and schools of thought, reaching its present form in the third century B.C.

Conversly, according to legend, it is said that on his retirement from public office, Lao Tzu headed west, and that the guardian of the pass to the state of Ch’in requested that he write a treatise on the Tao before departing. It is then that Lao Tzu is supposed to have sat for two days, in which time he wrote the Tao Te Ching, after which he left, some writers stating that he was never heard of again, others describing his ascent to heaven in the form of a magnificent dragon.

Whichever story we believe concerning the existence of Lao Tzu, we may reasonably conclude (at least) that there is much contradictory evidence. Although I cannot offer conclusive proof that he did exist, I do not believe that the contradictions prove that such a person did not exist, and neither do I believe they prove the Tao Te Ching to have been written by more than one person. As I have stated, the reasons for my beliefs are admittedly without sufficient ‘hard evidence’ to withstand strong philosophical questioning, but they are offered here for those who might wish to know of an argument contrary to current academic opinion.

Since one meaning of the words ‘Lao Tzu’ is ‘Old Man’, it is very unlikely that they were used as an ordinary (or ‘proper’) name, but could well have been a ‘nickname’. Some authorities claim that this was so in the case of the person in question, the nickname possibly being derived from the fact (?) that he was born with white hair, like that of an old man. This theory seems to borne out by the fact that the second character, can also be used to mean ‘child’. However, in the context of teaching and learning, it also means ‘master’ or ‘scholar’ (compared with ‘pupil’ or ‘student’). Furthermore, and for the purpose of this discussion, more importantly, the same two characters which form the Chinese ‘Lao Tzu’ form the words ‘old scholar’, pronounced as ‘roshi’ in Japanese, a title usually reserved in that language for a master of Zen teaching.

This means that ‘Lao Tzu’ is the Chinese equivalent to the Japanese ‘Roshi’. For this reason I believe there probably was a person called Lao Tzu, but that Lao Tzu was his title, rather than his name. It may of course be that there were many ‘old scholars’, all known by that title, but the existence of many has never been considered proof of the non-existence of one.

At this juncture it is perhaps necessary to mention briefly the historical and philosophical relationship between Taoism, Ch’an and Zen. The word ‘Zen’ is the Japanese pronunciation of the Chinese ‘Ch’an’, the system attributed to the ‘Bodhidharma’ (in Japanese ‘Daruma’), described by followers of Zen Buddhism as the twenty-eighth Buddhist Patriarch, who is said to have arrived in China in 526 A.D. Although well known to followers of Zen, it is not always known to others that the Bodhidharma then spent nine years in the earliest Chinese Buddhist temple, which had by that time been in existence for over four hundred years. Furthermore, during that period, the original Buddhism of India had undergone many changes in China, much of its teaching having been adapted (Tibetan Buddhists might claim, ‘adulterated’) by its proximity to Taoism.

Today, in the West at least, the most widely known sects of Zen are Buddhist. However, even before its acceptance by Buddhists, Ch’an (or ‘Zen’) was accepted by the Chinese followers of Philosophical Taoism (Tao Chia) as an adjunct to their own philosophy and practices. So it was that the ‘non-religious’ aspects of Zen and Taoism became integrated into the system known in China as ‘Ch’an Tao-chia’.

It is probable that we will never know all the reasons for this two-way integration which occurred between Tao-chia and Ch’an, but some of the reasons become apparent when we learn something of the similarities between the philosophies underlying the two systems. It will hopefully suffice to mention that the practitioners of each group probably felt an affinity with the ‘fluidity’ of thought and action of the practitioners of the other, recognizing this as stemming from the same philosophical source as their own. Similarly, it is very likely that the members of both groups appreciated the ‘ethics’ of the other, since both philosophies emphasize the development of the individual as a prerequisite to the development of society.

Notwithstanding any inaccuracies in my own interpretation of events, of even greater historical significance is the fact that from about six hundred A.D., the survival of Philosophical Taoism was made possible only through its adoption by Ch’an. Had it not been for this fact, the antagonistic attitude of the Religious Taoists, combined with their growing governmental power, might easily have resulted in the forceful demise of Taoist Philosophy as it is known today.

As to the continued integration and co-existence of Taoism and Zen, we fortunately need look no further than the words of the great Zen scholar, Professor D.T. Suzuki, who said,

„To ask a question about Zen is to ask a question about the Tao.”

All this is of course intended to illustrate the links between the two practices which use the same written characters as a teaching name or honorary title, and that this title may have been used by the author of the Tao Te Ching wishing to retain his anonymity.

If this was the case, it could have been either for reasons of personal safety on the part of the author, or out of deference to his own teachers. Any reader who has knowledge of the history of China during the peiod of the warring states will readily appreciate, and hopefully sympathise with the first of these reasons, but the second reason perhaps requires some explanation. This is now offered.

Carrying out one’s work in an unostentatious manner is an important aspect of Taoist teaching, as is respect for one’s teachers. In some instances these two principles were adhered to so rigorously that a writer or painter might either not sign his work at all, or use a pseudonym compiled (possibly as an anagram) from the names of his most revered teachers. It is therefore possible that the author of the Tao Te Ching used the pseudonym ‘Lao Tzu’ as an acknowledgement of his own teacher, using the title ‘old scholar’ to refer to that teacher as he might have been known and referred to by his own students.

It is quite likely that the title ‘Roshi’, used in Zen (Japanese Ch’an) developed as an ‘official title’ from its earlier Chinese usage. In Zen, it is thought to be rank bad manners to use the real name of one’s own teacher in a published work, at least in the context of he or she being one’s own teacher (for reasons which I have attempted to explain in the ‘Acknowledgements’ section), but it is quite acceptable to refer to him (or her) by an honorary title. Combine any of these possibilties with the fact that one’s own teacher may have been given or have chosen a ‘teaching name’ (a pseudonym under which a teacher may work) and it becomes easier to understand why it is impossible to be definitive regarding the ‘real name’ of the author or authors of the Tao Te Ching. For the purposes of this discussion however, I wish to continue from the assumption that the Tao Te Ching did have an author, and that we may, without too much ‘licence’, refer to him as Lao Tzu.

The second factor which causes me to believe that we should not completely disregard the legend of the writing of the Tao Te Ching concerns its cryptic style. The basis of my belief is twofold. In the first instance, if, as legend tells us, Lao Tzu completed his writing in two days, it is not surprising that it was cryptic, since this would have required him to write at a rate of two and one half thousand words each day. It may therefore be that he wrote as succinctly as possible in order to complete his task as quickly as possible, so that he could continue on his journey into retirement.

Those who know the Tao Te Ching will also know that Lao Tzu did not teach that a task should be rushed; rather, he taught that all things should occur in their natural time. This leads to my second point regarding the cryptic style of the original work.

We know that the keeper of the pass, who made the request for a written copy of Lao Tzu’s thoughts, was a well known Taoist of the period named Yin Hsi, also referred to as ‘Kwan Yin’. As a Taoist, he would certainly have been familiar with the teachings of Lao Tzu, even though, as he himself is supposed to have told the old philosopher, because of the nature of his work, he had not been able to avail himself of personal tuition from the master. It could be that the ‘vagueness’ (or seemingly esoteric nature of the first chapter) is due to the fact that Lao Tzu would have had no reason to explain the Tao to someone who was already versed in Tao-chia.

I believe we can assume that, although possibly not nationally famous, Lao Tzu would certainly have been well known in his own province. This would certainly seem to be the case, since Yin Hsi either recognised the figure of Lao Tzu, or his name, otherwise he would not have made his request to that particular traveller.

Assuming the keeper of the pass to know something of the teaching of Lao Tzu, his request could have been made in the form of a list of questions, to which Lao Tzu might have written the answers in the form of brief (or cryptic) notes, as an ‘aide memoire’. This might of course also account for the apparent discontinuity of the completed work. If the text were written in answer to a number of questions, the sequence of the text would conform to that of the questions, which might easily have been prepared by Yin Hsi over a period of time, in the hope that the occasion might arise when he would meet with a scholar such as Lao Tzu, with whom he could then discuss his questions. This could account for the apparent repetitions in the text, for two questions both phrased in a similar manner, would presumably be answered in a similar manner.

This concludes the summary of my own beliefs regarding the legend of Lao Tzu and the Tao Te Ching, other than to add the rider used frequently even by those who disagree totally with my own interpretation of the legend. This is that, irrespective of the authenticity of the legend and the problem of identifying its authorship, the majority of scholars date the origin of the text of the Tao Te Ching no later than 400 B.C. Furthermore, there is virtually no dissent among scholars as to its great value as a philosophical, literary and historical work.

NOTES ON THE INTERPRETATION

The text of the Tao Te Ching follows immediately after these notes, the arrangement following the convention set by Wan Bih in the third century A.D. Each of the eightyone sections is shown in English, the text being as brief as English grammar will permit, whilst still retaining sensibility. The differences between my own rendering of the text and those of other translators will seem to some readers to be minor; to others they may seem radical. In either case, the reader is of course free to compare the texts by referring to those editions cited earlier in these notes.

The Chinese characters employed as chapter headings are written in a style approximating to the period in which the original text was written. The style is commonly known as ‘small seal script’. Readers wishing to use modern Chinese characters for their own researches may of course refer to any or each of the Chinese texts mentioned earlier, and there are of course many others.

‘Small seal script’ is by no means the earliest written form of Chinese, but it is certainly one of the most aesthetically pleasing and easiest to read. Being more pictographic than later forms, the symbolism of the images contained within the small seal characters is easier to understand than it is in later forms. Modern Chinese script is virtually always more stylized, and (if hand written) frequently more ‘freehand’, and therefore sometimes difficult for the inexperienced reader to decipher.

Each small seal script chapter heading provides an approximate rendering of either the English title beneath or beside which it appears, or of the key concept or concepts embodied in the text of that chapter. As with the Chinese text itself, there are a number of different ‘authentic’ chapter headings. In most instances I have used a ‘traditional’ heading, but where even the traditional meaning is unclear I have used the heading I believe to be most appropriate to the contents of the chapter. Following the usual conventions, horizontally presented script should be read from left to right, and vertically presented script should be read from top to bottom, the right hand column first.

As I have stated earlier, because of the cryptic nature of the original text, and also because of the difference between the structure of English and Chinese grammar, a completely literal translation of the Chinese text would make little if any sense to the reader not versed in both the written Chinese language and the concepts of Taoism. This means that virtually any intelligible English rendering of the Tao Te Ching is bound to be longer than the original Chinese text. The variation in the length of many English (and Chinese) texts of the Tao Te Ching will be readily apparent to the reader of those translations listed in the reference section.

There are many valid arguments for and against the inclusion of commentaries on the text in any edition of the Tao Te Ching, but in this instance I hope that the English rendering will ‘speak for itself’, thus serving the purpose for which it is intended. It is for this reason that no separate commentaries are included.

The text in this edition is somewhat longer than that found in most other translations. There are two reasons for this, the first being that it includes certain expansions resulting from points raised in discussion by my own students. In those instances where there was apparent lack of clarity in my original drafts, additions have been made to clarify the concepts involved. (Where additions have been made to the most commonly available Chinese and English editions, the addition and the reason for its inclusion are annotated in the appendix at the end of the book.) The second reason is the form of interpretation employed, the rationale of which is now briefly described.

I do not believe it is by accident that the Tao Te Ching can be interpreted at many different levels without contradiction. The actual interpretation placed upon the text by any translator will depend on many factors, as has already been discussed. However, there is no doubt that Tao-chia and Ch’an are both very much concerned with individual development, maintaining that this is essential to a healthy society.

It is from this particular viewpoint that the rationale for this interpretation has developed. Although other translators have certainly raised this issue, to the best of my knowledge this is the first rendering to give priority to this aspect of the Tao Te Ching. It was because my own students requested such an interpretation in English, and because we were unable to find such an interpretation that I undertook the translation and interpretation presented here.

Stanley Rosenthal
(Shi-tien Roshi)
British School of Zen Taoism
Cardiff, September 1984

THE TAO AND ITS NAME

Naming things enables us to differentiate between them, but names are words, and words easily give rise to confusion. They do not replace the thing or direct experience of the thing which they name, but only represent or describe it.

Consider a thing such as a strawberry. If we wish to find the word ‘strawberry’, we look in a dictionary; if we wish to find a description of a strawberry, we look in an encyclopaedia. But if we are hungry, we do not go to the library, but to the field where fine strawberries may be found. If we do not know where there is such a field, we might seek guidance as to where fine strawberries may be found. A book on the Tao is like such a guide.

It can point us in the direction of the strawberry patch, but cannot provide the fruit itself. It can give an idea of the taste of Tao, but of itself, has no taste to compare with direct experience of the Tao.

Consider now three things: There is the universal principle which enables all things to be, and to flourish naturally; there is the name ‘Tao’, by which that universal principle is known; and there are words which describe the manifestations of the Tao.

Even the name ‘Tao’ is only a convenience, and should not be confused with the universal principle which bears that name, for such a principle embraces all things, so cannot be accurately named nor adequately described. This means that Tao cannot be understood, for it is infinite, whereas the mind of man is finite, and that which is finite cannot encompass that which is infinite.

Although we cannot understand Tao, we are not prevented from having knowledge of it, for understanding stems from one of the two forms of knowledge.

It stems from that which is called cognitive knowledge, the knowledge born of words and numbers, and other similar devices. The other form of knowledge, conative knowledge, needs no words or other such devices, for it is the form of knowledge born of direct personal experience. So it is that conative knowledge is also known as experiential knowledge. Cognitive and experiential knowledge both have their roots in reality, but reality is complex, and complexity is more of a barrier to cognitive knowledge than it is to experiential knowledge, for when we seek cognitive knowledge of a thing, that is, understanding of it, the knowledge we gain of that thing is understanding only of its manifestations, which is not knowledge of the thing itself.

We may seek to understand a thing, rather than to experience it, because, in a world beset with man made dangers, it is frequently safer to understand than to experience. Tao is not man made, and there is nothing in it to fear. So it is that we may experience Tao without fear. When we cease to seek cognitive knowledge, that is, cease to seek understanding of a thing, we can gain experiential knowledge of that thing. This is why it is said that understanding Tao is not the same as knowing Tao; that understanding Tao is only to know that which it manifests, and that knowing Tao is to be one with the universal principal which is Tao. This is to say that knowledge of Tao is not the same as understanding Tao. To know Tao is to experience both Tao and the manifestations of that universal principle. As human beings, we are born as manifestations of Tao.

If this seems complex, the reason is because Tao is both simple and complex. It is complex when we try to understand it, and simple when we allow ourselves to experience it. Trying to understand Tao is like closing the shutters of a window before looking for a shadow. We might close the shutters to prevent anyone from discovering our treasure, but the same shutters prevent the moonlight from entering the room. All there is in the room is darkness, and in total darkness we cannot find the shadow, no matter how hard or diligently we seek.

We call one thing a shadow, and another darkness, but the shadow is darkness, and the darkness shadow, for in reality, both darkness and shadow are absence of light, yet we call one shadow and the other darkness. The shadow is darkness in the midst of light, but within total darkenss, the shadow seems to disappear, for darkness is a shadow within shadows. We may think that the shadow has been destroyed when all light is removed, but it has not been wiped away; in reality it has grown, but we need light even to see that form of darkenss which we call a shadow.

Such is the pursuit of the universal priciple called Tao, that if we seek to understand it, we prevent the very means by which it may be found, for the only way in which we might find Tao is through the experience of Tao. We find Tao when we do not seek it, and when we seek it, it leaves us, just as the silver moonlight leaves the room when we close the shutters. We find and know Tao when we allow ourselves to find and know it, just as the moonlight returns when we allow it to return.

We do not need to seek Tao as we seek physical treasures such as jade or gold. We do not need to seek Tao as we seek such treasures as fame or titles. We do not need to seek the treasure of Tao, for although the greatest of treasures, it is also the most common. Perhaps it is bacause it is so common that so few men find it; they seek it only in mysterious and secret places, in chasms and caves, and in the workplace of the alchemist. The Tao is not hidden in these places, and is hidden only from those who frequent and inhabit them, secretively, and with the shutters closed.

Just as darkness may be known as the absence of light, so to may light be known as the absence of darkness. When we experience darkness and light as having the same source, we are close to the Tao, for Tao is the source of both darkness and light, just as it is also the source of all other natural things. When we experience ourselves as part of Tao, as a shadow or reflection of the universal principle, we have found it, for it is said that „Experience of Tao is Tao”.

1. Knowledge of ‘the Tao’, and experience of the Tao

There is a way in which we may conduct our lives without regrets, and in such a manner as assists in developing and realizing our individual potential, without harming others, or inhibiting the realization of their potential, and which is beneficial to a healthy society.

Such a way of life may of course be conducted without a name, and without description, but in order that others may know of it, and so as to distinguish it from other ways in which life may be conducted, we give it a name, and use words to describe it.

When discussing or describing this way in which life may be conducted, rather than refer to it in full, for convenience, we refer to it as ‘the way’, meaning simply that the discussion is concerned with this particular way, not that it is the only way of conducting one’s life. In order that we might distinguish it more easily from other ways, we refer to it also by its original name, which is ‘Tao’.

By intellectual intent, that is, through thought and words, and by considering ourselves as non-participating observers of this way of life, we may gain knowledge of its manifestations; but it is only through participation that we can actually experience such a way of life for ourselves.

Knowledge of anything is not the same as the thing of which we have that knowledge. When we have knowledge of a thing but do not have experience of it, in trying to describe that thing, all we can describe is our knowledge, not the thing itself. Equally, even when we have experience of a thing, all we can convey is knowledge of that experience, not the experience itself.

Knowledge and experience are both real, but they are different realities, and their relationship is frequently made complex by what distinguishes them, one from the other. When they are used according to that which is appropriate to the situation, we may develop that way of life which enables us to pass through the barrier of such complexities. We may have knowledge of „Tao”, but Tao itself can only be experienced.

2. Letting go of opposites

It is the nature of the ordinary person, the person who is not yet at one with the Tao, to compare the manifestations of the natural qualities possessed by things. Such a person tries to learn of such qualities by distinguishing between their manifestations, and so learns only of their comparative manifestations.

So it is that the ordinary person might consider one thing beautiful when compared with another which he considers to be ugly; one thing skillfully made compared with another which he considers badly made. He knows of what he has as a result of knowing what he does not have, and of that which he considers easy through that which he considers difficult. He considers one thing long by comparing it with another thing which he considers short; one thing high and another low. He knows of noise through silence and of silence through noise, and learns of that which leads through that which follows.

When such comparisons are made by a sage, that is a person who is in harmony with the Tao, that person is aware of making a judgement, and that judgements are relative to the person who makes them, and to the situation in which they are made, as much as they are relative to that which is judged.

Through the experience and knowledge through which he has gained his wisdom, the sage is aware that all things change, and that a judgement which is right in one situation might easily be wrong in another situation. He is therefore aware that he who seems to lead does not always lead, and that he who seems to follow does not always follow.

Because of this awareness, the sage frequently seems neither to lead nor follow, and often seems to do nothing, for that which he does is done without guile; it is done naturally, being neither easy nor difficult, not big or small. Because he accomplishes his task and then lets go of it without seeking credit, he cannot be discredited. Thus, his teaching lasts for ever, and he is held in high esteem.

3. Without seeking acclaim

The talented person who is also wise, retains humility, and so does not create rivalry. The person who possesses material things, and who does not boast of his possessions, does much to prevent stealing. Those who are jealous of talents, skills or possessions of others, easily become possessed themselves by envy.

The sage is satisfied with a sufficiency; he is not jealous, and so is free of envy. He does not seek fame and titles, but maintains his energy and keeps himself supple. He minimizes his desires, and does not train himself in guile. He thus remains pure at heart. By acting in an uncontrived manner, the harmony of the inner world of his thoughts and the external world of his environment is maintained. He remains at peace with himself.

For these reasons, an administration which is concerned with the welfare of those whom it serves, does not encourage the seeking of status and titles; it does not create jealousy and rivalry amongst the people, but ensures that they are able to have a sufficiency, without causing them to become discontent, therefore the members of such an administration do not seek honours for themselves, nor act with guile towards the people.

4. The unfathomable Tao

The mind should not be filled with desires. The individual who is at one with the Tao is aware of the distinction between that which is needed as a sufficiency, and that which is a desire, or merely wanted rather than needed.

It is the manner of the Tao that even though continuously used, it is naturally replenished, never being emptied, and never being as full as a goblet which is filled to the brim and therefore spills its fine spring water upon the ground. The Tao therefore does not waste that with which it is charged, yet always remains a source of nourishment for those who are not already so full that they cannot partake of it.

Even the finest blade will lose its sharpeness if tempered beyond its mettle. Even the most finely tempered sword is of no avail against water, and will shatter if struck against a rock. A tangled cord is of little use after it has been untangled by cutting it.

Just as a fine sword should be used only by an experienced swordsman, intellect should be tempered with experience. By this means, tangled cord may be untangled, and seemingly insoluable problems resolved; colours and hues may be harmonized to create fine paintings, and people enabled to exist in unity with each other because they no longer feel that they exist only in the shadow of the brilliance of others.

To conduct oneself without guile is to conduct oneself in a natural manner, and to do this is to be in contact with nature. By maintaining awareness of the way of nature, the wise person becomes aware of the Tao, and so becomes aware that this is how its seemingly unfathomable mysteries may be experienced.

5. Tranquil but unceasing

Those things which are in opposition with each other are not benevolent towards each other, and may even treat each other with contempt or malevolence.

Although the creatures which are born of nature may be in opposition with each other, nature itself is in opposition to nothing for there is nothing for it to oppose. It acts without conscious intention, and it is therefore neither deliberately benevolent, contemptuous nor malevolent. In this respect the way of the Tao is the same as the way of nature. Therefore, even when acting in a benevolent manner, the sage does not act from any conscious desire to be benevolent.

Through his manner of breathing like a babe, he remains free of conscious desire, and so retains his tranquility. By this means he is empty of desire, and his energy is not drained from him.

6. The manifestation of Tao through complimentary opposites

All physical things possess certain natural qualities, such as size, shape and colour. Since the universal principle encompasses all things, so it encompasses their natural qualities.

Being possessed by all things, natural qualities are general to all things, but in order to relate to a quality, we think of it as it exists relative to a particular thing, and to ourselves. We therefore think of and describe a quality according to how it is manifested through one particular thing compared with another. Thus, we judge one thing to be big, compared with another thing, which we think of as small; one person young, and another old; one sound noisy, and another quiet. Equally, we judge and compare by thinking of the aesthetic quality in terms of its manifestations, ‘beautiful’ or ‘ugly’; morality in terms of good or bad; possession in terms of having or not having; ability in terms of ease or difficulty; length in terms of long or short; height in terms of high or low; sound in terms of noisy or quiet; light in terms of brightness or darkness.

Although many of the manifestations which we compare are judged by us to be opposites, one to the other, they are not in opposition, but are complimentary, for even extremes are nothing other than aspects or specific examples of the quality which encompasses them. Both big and small are manifestations or examples of size, young and old are examples of age, noise and quietness are aspects of sound, and brightness and darkness are extremes of light.

It is the nature of the ordinary man to compare and judge the manifestations of the naturally occurring qualities inherent in things and in situations. It is not wrong to do this, but we should not delude ourselves into believing that we thereby describe the quality rather than a manifestation of the quality.

Whilst all judgements are comparative, a judgement is frequently, if not always, relative to the individual who makes that judgement, and also to the time at which it is made. To the young child, the father may be old, but when the son reaches that age, it is unlikely that he will consider himself old. To the child, the garden fence is high, but when the child grows bigger, the same fence is low. The adult in his physical prime knows that to run ten miles, which is easy at that time, will become more difficult as he becomes older, but that that the patience required to walk will become easier.

The sage knows that qualitative judgements, such as old and young, big and small, easy and difficult, or leading and following, relate as much to the person who makes that judgement, as they relate to the thing or action described. Consider a sage and an ordinary man sitting on a hill in the late evening, looking down on the road below. When darkness has fallen, they both see the light of two lanterns approaching, one yellow, the other red, bobbing gently as their bearers pass by. From the positions of the two lights, the ordinary man knows that the bearer of the yellow lantern leads the bearer of the red. As he watches, he sees the red lantern draw level with the yellow, and as they pass beneath him, the red lantern preceding the yellow.

The ordinary man wonders why the two lantern bearers do not walk side by side. The sage, who has seen what his companion has seen, thinks it right that the two travellers should do as they have done, to walk side by side through the night, neither leading and neither following the other. The sage is aware that he who seems to lead does not always lead, and that he who seems to follow does not always follow. Because of this, the sage frequently seems neither to lead nor follow, and often seems to do nothing, for that which he does is natural, being neither easy nor difficult, not big or small.

Those changes which occur naturally in life, the sage accepts as natural, accepting them as an opportunity for learning, whilst realizing that knowledge is not his possession. Because he knows that the credit for learning is due to the willingness of the student, he teaches without teaching, but by allowing his students to observe the virtue of observing natural qualities, rather than only comparing and judging their manifestations. He does this without seeking credit, and continues without contriving to be given credit. Because of this, his teaching lasts for ever, and he is held in high esteem.

The gifted person retains humility and thus prevents jealousy. The person who does not boast of his possessions prevents stealing. Only those who have greed are perplexed by envy. The wise person is therefore satisfied with a sufficiency, and is free of envy. He does not seek fame and titles, but keeps himself strong and supple. He minimizes his desires, and does not train himself in guile. He thus remains pure at heart. By acting in an uncontrived manner he maintains his inner harmony.

That which can be perceived is not the timeless That.
That which can be named is not the nameless One.

The source of heaven and earth is without form or substance.
Naming creates the ten thousand things.

When desire is absent, the mystery is obvious.
When desire occurs, creation unfolds.

Mystery and creation arise from the same source.
The source is emptiness.
Void within void.
The realm of Tao.

Judging beauty creates ugliness.
Defining good creates evil.
All and void arise together.

Hard and soft,
long and short,
high and low,
sound and silence,
now and then.
Opposites exist because of each other.

Therefore the sage acts by not-doing and teaches no-thought.
The ten thousand things arise and vanish without him.

He works without motive,
indifferent to outcome.
Because there is no doer,
his actions are timeless.

Bestowing honor breeds ambitions.
Hoarding treasure invites thieves.
Displaying objects of desire sows the seeds of discontent.

Therefore the sage governs
by emptying minds and filling bellies,
by weakening wills and strengthening bones.

He extols the virtue of desireless unknowing
and keeps intellects off balance.

When not-doing is accomplished,
nothing remains undone.

Tao is hollow emptiness.

The substance of All,
it is absent of substance.
Dimensionless Void,
it is the source of the ten thousand things.

It blunts sharpness,
unravels entanglements,
diffuses brightness,
merges with dust.

Dark, invisible, it only seems to be.
It is the child of no-thing
and the father of God.

The realm of heaven and earth is indifferent to the myriad creatures.
They appear as straw dogs.
The sage is indifferent to the multitudes of men.
They appear as straw dogs.

The realm of heaven and earth is like a bellows,
both empty and full.
Moving, it brings forth, endlessly.

More words, less understanding.
Hold fast to the core.

The urge of creation is ceaseless.
It is called the Dark Mother.

The womb of the Dark Mother
is the ground of heaven and earth.

Timeless, imperceptible,
it continues ever-present.

Endless use does not touch it.

The realm of heaven and earth is everlasting.

Why is it everlasting?
Because it is not conscious of itself.
Having no thought of being, it never is not.

Like this, the sage forgets himself
so is always present.

Without self-concern,
the self is eternal.
When self-interest subsides,
fulfillment happens.

Supreme virtue is like water.
It nourishes the ten thousand things without effort
and flows in places men shun.
It is like Tao.

Stand on solid ground.
Go deep into the heart.
Speak only what is true.

In friendship, be kind.
In governing, be just.
In enterprise, be able.
In action, watch the timing.

Do not contend with nature and nothing will go wrong.

An over-filled cup is difficult to carry.
An over-sharp point is easily broken.

Fill your house with gold and jade
and it cannot be protected.
Become puffed with pride
and disaster will follow.

Do only what needs doing then forget it.
This is the way of heaven.

While maintaining a body
can you become One?
While breathing the force of life
can you be innocent as a babe?
While polishing the dark mirror
can you be without dust?

While loving and ruling the people
can you refrain from action?
While coming and going from heaven
can you be passive as a woman?
Understanding all things
can you abide in unknowing?

Give birth and nurture.
Create without claim.
Lead without taking command.

This is supreme virtue.

Thirty spokes of the wheel converge
to define a hole.
Clay is molded into pots
to shape emptiness.
Walls are hammered into rooms
to enclosed space.
Windows are cut into walls
to frame absence.

Though things may have value,
without no-thing they are useless.

The five colors confuse the eye.
The five tones deaden the ear.
The five flavors dull the palette.

Racing and hunting madden the mind.
Valuable goods hinder movement.

Therefore the sage is guided by his gut, not his senses.
He attends to one and ignores the other.

Receive honor with dismay.
Accept misfortune gratefully.

Why receive honor with dismay?
Honor and dishonor cause the same disturbance.
With honor comes the fear of disgrace.
With disgrace comes anxiety and dread.

Why accept misfortune gratefully?
Misfortune weakens the bond to body and self.
Without a separate self, what misfortune is possible?
See misfortune as a condition of separation,
and you will become whole.

See the world as your body, and all will be delivered unto you.

Searching, we cannot see it.
We call it ephemeral.
Straining, we cannot hear it.
We call it ethereal.
Reaching, we cannot grasp it.
We call it intangible.

These three are often confused
because they are the same.

The One is not bright above and dark below.
Transparent, it moves in and out of nothing.

Its form has no shape.
Its image has no substance.
It is indistinct, elusive.
Nothing to face, nothing to follow.

Hold to the timeless Tao.
Abide in the present.
Now is the ancient beginning.

The old masters were deep, unfathomable,
profound beyond understanding.
Because they were unfathomable
we can only describe their demeanor.

Cautious, as if crossing an icy stream.
Alert, as if sensing danger.
Respectful, like visiting guests.
Yielding, like melting ice.
Simple, like uncarved wood.
Open, like beckoning valleys.
Mysterious, like opaque pools.

Still the mind and the mud settles.
Do nothing and action comes of itself.

One who embraces Tao has no desire for fulfillment.
Not desiring fulfillment, he is finished with birth and death.

Be completely empty.
Be completely still.

Witness the ten thousand things
appear and vanish in one motion.
Watch as they arise, linger,
and return to the source—stillness.

This is the way it is.
It is called everlasting life.
To witness the everlasting is to be awake.

Not seeing the everlasting, one engages in blind action.
Blind action leads to misfortune.

Seeing the everlasting, one encompasses all.
Encompassing all, one is impartial.
Being impartial, one acts nobly.
Acting nobly, one enters heaven.

Entering heaven is to be one with Tao.
Being one with Tao is to be everlasting.

Though the body dies, nothing is disturbed.

When a sage governs, people barely notice.

Lesser rulers are praised and loved.
Lesser still are feared and obeyed.
The least are ridiculed and despised.
Trust is earned by trusting.

The sage uses words sparingly.
His work is done without fanfare.
People say: “It happened by itself.”

When Tao is forgotten,
charity and righteousness are born.

When intelligence and knowledge are valued,
duplicity and pretense soon follow.

When the family is discordant,
love and duty are preached.

When the country is in chaos,
loyal patriots appear.

Abandon holiness, renounce wisdom.
It will be a hundred times better for everyone.

Eliminate morality and benevolence.
Love and empathy will naturally return.

Give up cleverness and profit.
Thieves and bandits will disappear.

But those are outward lessons, not the core.
Be simple.
Be true.
Cast off selfhood and desire.

Between yes and no, is there really much difference?
Good and bad, are they so far apart?
Must I think as others think?
Alas, there would be no end to fear.

The multitudes are busy with feasts and celebrations.
In spring they climb towers and enjoy the view.
I alone am unmoved, like an infant too young to smile.

Others have more than enough.
I alone have nothing.
My mind is that of a fool—empty.

Others are clear and bright.
I alone am nebulous and dim.
Others are alert and clever.
I alone am withdrawn,
adrift in the ocean,
directionless as swirling wind.

Everyone else has purpose.
I alone am stubborn and untamed.
I am different.
I am nourished by the Dark Mother.

Supreme virtue is to abide in Tao alone.

Tao is elusive and empty—
oh yes, utterly empty and elusive—
yet within it dreamlike images arise.

Oh yes, it is indistinct and nebulous,
but within it shadows take form.

Oh yes, it is mysterious and dark,
but within it appearances originate.

The origin of creation is the real.
Its manifestations are unceasing.
This can be witnessed.

How do I witness the origin of creation?
By looking!

Surrender and become whole.
Bend low and be straightened.
Become empty and be filled.
Burn out and be renewed.

Having nothing, beauty is revealed.
Having much, the way is hidden.

The sage abides in One
and thus is master of heaven and earth.
Not being self-absorbed, his vision is clear.
Not asserting himself, his light shines forth.
Not showing off, his merit is obvious.
Not praising himself, praise is showered upon him.
Not contending, nothing under heaven stands in his way.

This ancient saying, “Surrender and become whole,”
is it empty words?
Being whole means all things have returned to you.

To speak a short time is the way of nature.
High winds blow out before morning.
Hard rain subsides in a day.

What issues these?
The realm of heaven and earth.
If the realm of heaven and earth cannot maintain duration,
what chance has man?
This is why one embraces Tao.

He who aligns with Tao becomes one with Tao.
He who aligns with virtue attains supreme virtue.
He who fails to align with Tao is lost.

He who aligns with Tao is received by Tao.
He who aligns with virtue finds only virtue.
He who has become lost is close to home.

Faith comes to the faithful.

He who stands on tiptoe is unsteady.
He who strides too hard cannot go far.

He who shines a light on himself is not enlightened.
He who asserts himself is not distinguished.
He who praises himself has no merit.
He who brags of his success will not last long.

Observers of Tao see these as spoiled food and pointless action—
shunned even by the myriad creatures.
One who knows Tao does not abide them.

Formless no-thing.
Precedent of heaven and earth.
Timeless, unchanging, solitary, silent.
It is the mother of the ten thousand things.

I do not know its name.
I call it Tao.
If forced to describe it,
I call it great.

Great implies vast reaches.
Vast reaches implies far away.
Far away implies return.
Tao is great.
Heaven is great.
Earth is great.
Man, too, is great.
In the realm there are four greats,
and a noble man is one.
Man follows the way of earth.
Earth follows the way of heaven.
Heaven follows the way of Tao.
Tao is the great Way.

Gravity is the ground of lightness.
Stillness is the master of unrest.

The sage can travel all day,
yet never wander far from the baggage wagon.
Though splendor and spectacle may beckon,
he remains unmoved, indifferent.

Why should the lord of ten thousand chariots act lightly?
One who acts lightly is not grounded.
One who is restless is not his own master.

A good walker leaves no tracks.
A good speaker does not slip up.
A good accountant needs no counter.

A good doorsmith uses no bolts or locks
yet none can open what he closes.
A good binder uses no knots
yet what he binds cannot be unraveled.

The sage is good at saving souls and rejects no one.
He takes care of all things and abandons nothing.
This is called “the way of awareness.”

The good man is the ignorant man’s teacher.
The ignorant man is the good man’s lesson.
To not honor the teacher and value the lesson—
no matter how much wisdom one acquires—
is to miss the mark.
This is an essential secret.

Know the strength of the male, but keep to the role of the female.
Be the river of the world.
Being the river of the world, supreme virtue flows without end.
Flowing without end, you are the timeless infant.

Know the purity of light but maintain darkness.
Be the model of the world.
Being the model of the world, supreme virtue is constant.
Maintaining constant virtue, you are the boundless realm.

Be worthy of high honors, but keep to the role of the lowly.
Be the valley of the world.
Being the valley of the world, supreme virtue is fulfilled.
Being fulfilled, you are the uncarved block.

The uncarved block appears as separate things.
The sage sees things as they are and rules the world.
Great power does not divide.

There are those who want to control the realm
and make it more to their liking.
They will never succeed.
The realm of heaven and earth is perfect, a sacred vessel.
It cannot be improved.
He who tries to change it, destroys it for himself.
He who tries to hold it, loses all contact.

It is natural for beings to sometimes lead, sometimes follow,
sometimes breathe hot, sometimes blow cold,
sometimes expand, sometimes decay,
sometimes overcome, sometimes collapse.

The sage therefore abandons pleasure, judgment and pride.

When counseling rulers, observers of Tao do not advise force.
This is certain to bring consequences.
Where great armies have passed, thorn bushes thrive.
Famine follows in the wake of war.
A good ruler does only what is necessary to achieve results.
He does not abuse position.

Achieve results, but do not glory in them.
Achieve results, but do not boast.
Achieve results, but be not proud.
Achieve results because there is no choice.
Achieve results but do not overpower.

Doing more than necessary brings exhaustion.
This is not in harmony with Tao.
What is not in harmony with Tao soon perishes.

Even the finest weapons are instruments of ill omen,
hated and feared by all creatures.
Observers of Tao have no use for them.

At home, a man of virtue gives precedence to the left.
At war, he gives precedence to the right.

Weapons are not the tools of a man of virtue.
Weapons are instruments of ill omen,
to be employed as a last resort.
Do not relish their use
or admire their excellence.
To see weapons as excellent is to relish killing.
If you relish killing you will never find the way.

On joyful occasions, precedence is given to the left.
On sad occasions, precedence is given to the right.

When an army is arrayed, the lieutenant is placed on the left.
The commander is placed on the right.
Thus, war is conducted as a funeral rite.
When multitudes are being killed,
hold in your heart only sorrow.
When victory is achieved,
mark it with mourning.

Tao is the uncarved block.
Timeless, undefined, infinitesimally subtle.
None is its master.

If lords and princes observed it,
the ten thousand things would arrive as guests to the table.
Heaven and earth would rejoice
and sweet nectar would fall,
though none under heaven had decreed it.

When the whole is divided the parts are named.
There are already too many names.
It is time to stop.
Knowing when to stop avoids exhaustion.

Tao in the world is like
stream flowing to river flowing to sea.

One who knows others is wise.
One who knows self is enlightened.
One who masters others is strong.
One who masters self is powerful.

Knowing you have enough is fulfillment.
Exerting strong effort brings exhaustion.

He who abides where he is lasts long.
He who dies without ceasing is timelessly present.

Great Tao flows everywhere,
left and right, all directions.

The ten thousand things depend on it
and it does not turn away.
Its purpose is fulfilled but it lays no claim.

It clothes and nourishes the ten thousand things
but is not their lord.
It desires nothing.
It is smaller than small.

The ten thousand things return to it
but it is not their master.
It is indeed great.
Because it knows nothing of greatness,
it is greater than great.

Extol the great illusion
and the men of the world will gather.
Talk of success, security and happiness
and the multitudes will flock.
Offer music and tasty food and travelers will stop in.

Talk of Tao has no flavor.
Look for it—there is nothing to see.
Listen for it—there is nothing to hear.

Merge with it—there is no boundary or end.

If you want it to contract, let it expand.
If you want it to weaken, let it gain strength.
To bring a thing down, let it be raised high.
To bring a thing to you, let go.

This is called “perceiving the subtle workings.”

Soft and weak overcome hard and strong.
A fish should not leave deep water.
A country should not show off its power.

Tao does nothing yet nothing remains undone.

When a noble man observes this
the ten thousand things are transformed.
When the desire to act re-emerges,
it is stilled by the nameless no-thing.

Without things there is no desire.
Without desire there is stillness.
In stillness, the realm of heaven and earth is perfect.

The man of high virtue is not aware of himself
and thus attains supreme virtue.
The man of low virtue self-consciously strives
and thus is without virtue.

The wise man does nothing
yet leaves nothing undone.
The ignorant man is consumed by doing
yet little is accomplished.

The compassionate man acts without motive.
The righteous man acts to gain merit.
The moral man acts to impose order.
If no one responds,
he bares his arms and becomes an enforcer.

When Tao is lost there is virtue.
When virtue is lost there is goodness.
When goodness is lost there is morality.
When morality is lost, rules of conduct are imposed.

Rules are the remnants of trust and faith,
and the beginning of chaos.
Knowledge is an ornamental blossom of Tao
and the beginning of misunderstanding.

The sage dwells in the depths, not the surface,
in the root not the flower.
He abides in one and lets go of the other.

Before time, these ancestors arise from One:

Heaven arises from One and becomes clear.
Earth arises from One and becomes firm.
Spirit arises from One and becomes divine.
Emptiness arises from One and becomes creation.

The ten thousand things arise from One
and become manifest.
Kings and princes arise from One
and become exalted.
One is the source of All.

Separated from the Source:
the clearness of heaven would vanish,
the firmament of earth would dissolve,
the divinity of spirit would dissipate,
creation would become desolation.
The ten thousand things would perish,
and kingdoms would disappear.

Humility is the root of honor.
Lowliness is the foundation of esteem.

Thus, a noble man considers himself
orphaned, bereft, unworthy.
This is knowing the humble source—is it not?

To seek praise is not praiseworthy.
Do not jangle like jewelry.
Be still as stone.

Tao moves by returning and acts by yielding.
Thus, the ten thousand things arise into being.

Being arises from non-being.
Things arise from no-thing.

When the wise student hears of Tao
he practices diligently.
When the average student hears of Tao
he practices off and on.
When the foolish student hears of Tao
he laughs out loud.
If the foolish do not laugh, it is not Tao.

Thus it is said:
The path of light is through darkness.
The road ahead leads back.
The easy way is most difficult.
The highest fulfillment is emptiness.

True purity seems sullied.
True abundance seems bereft.
True power seems weak.
True substance seems hollow.

The greatest region has no boundaries.
The best tools are fashioned slowly.
The highest sounds are hard to hear.
The perfect form has no shape.

Tao is unseen, undefined.
Yet Tao alone nourishes
and brings all things to fulfillment.

From Tao, One arises.
From One, two.
From two, three.
Three becomes the ten thousand things.

The ten thousand things carry yin on their backs
and hold yang in their arms.
Existence depends on the two.

Men hate to be orphaned, bereft, unworthy,
yet this is how the noble man describes himself.
Loss is gain, gain is loss.

I teach what has always been taught:
“A fervent man is surprised by death.”
I see this as the foundation of my teaching.

Under heaven, the soft and yielding
overcomes the hard and strong.
That without substance permeates the impenetrable.

Thus, I embrace non-action.
Teach without words.
Work without doing.

Few under heaven understand this.

Name or person, which is more dear?
Person or possessions, which is more precious?
Gain or loss, which is more harmful?

Excessive desire incurs great expense.
One who hoards treasure suffers loss.
One who knows enough is enough
will always have enough.
One who knows when to stop avoids exhaustion.
Thus, he will endure.

Perfection appears imperfect but has no flaw.
Fulfillment appears as emptiness but has no limit.

Great truth is a paradox.
Great wisdom is self-evident.
Great eloquence is unpracticed.

Movement overcomes cold.
Stillness overcomes heat.
Stillness and simplicity put all things right under heaven.

When Tao is embraced in the realm,
race horses haul their own manure.
When Tao is unknown in the realm,
war horses are bred at the borders.

There is no greater curse than desire,
no greater misfortune than greed.
He who knows enough is enough
will always have enough.

Without leaving home one can know the whole world.
Without looking outside one can see heaven.
Looking afar does not find what is near.

Thus, the sage knows without learning,
sees without seeking,
acts without doing.

For students of knowledge,
every day something is acquired.
For observers of Tao,
every day something falls away.

Less and less is done
until not-doing is achieved.
When there is no doer,
nothing remains to be done.

The realm of heaven and earth
is ruled by timeless principles.
He who tries to interfere is not ready to receive it.

The sage has no heart or mind of his own.
Thus, he knows the heart and mind of all.

I am good to the good
and good to the not-so-good.
This is the goodness of Virtue.

I trust the trustworthy
and have faith in those who should not be trusted.
This is the faith of Virtue.

The sage is in harmony
with the realm of heaven and earth.
His mind is merged with the world.
People turn to him and listen.
He treats them as his children.

In the passage from womb to grave
one in three are disciples of living.
One in three are disciples of death.
One in three are just passing through.

All believe they have life.

He who knows the truth of existence
does not fear wild bulls or tigers.
He wears no armor in battle.

Bulls have no place to thrust their horns.
Tigers have no place to sink their claws.
Weapons have no place to enter.

Why is this?
Because death is for the living.

Tao gives them life.
Virtue gives them nourishment.
The manifest world gives them form.
The tendencies of each make them what they are.

Therefore the ten thousand things honor Tao and esteem Virtue.
This honor and esteem are not commanded.
It is just the nature of things.

And so, all things arise from Tao.
By Virtue they are nourished, developed, clothed,
sheltered, soothed, aged and buried.

To create without possessing,
to act without making claims,
to lead without taking command—
this is timeless Virtue.

Where the realm of heaven and earth begins
could be called the mother of creation.

Knowing the mother, become the child.
Being the child, stay close to the mother.
Death will not bother you.

Stay quiet, keep inside,
and you will never want for anything.
Open your mouth, meddle in affairs,
and you are beyond rescue.

Perceiving the subtle is insight.
To yield requires strength.
Use the light of creation to become illuminated
and thus be saved.

This is called “entering the Absolute.”

If I have the least bit of knowledge
I will follow the great Way alone
and fear nothing but being sidetracked.
The great Way is simple
but people delight in complexity.

The government is corrupt.
The fields are overgrown.
The granaries are empty.
Yet some wear fine clothes,
carry sharp swords,
gorge on food and drink,
and are surrounded by luxury.
They are thieves.

This is certainly not the great Way.

What is deeply rooted will not topple.
What is firmly grasped will not slip away.

It will be honored through generations of ancestors.

Cultivated in the self, Virtue is manifest.
Cultivated in the family, Virtue grows.
Cultivated in the village, Virtue flourishes.
Cultivated in the nation, Virtue abounds.
Cultivated in the universe, Virtue is everything.

As the self, observe the self.
As the family, observe the family.
As the village, observe the village.
As the nation, observe the nation.
As the universe, observe the universe.

How do I know the universe?
Like this.

A man of Virtue can be compared to a newborn child.

Snakes and scorpions do not strike him.
Fierce beasts do not prey upon him.
Birds of prey do not attack him.

Though his bones are soft and his muscles weak,
his grip is firm.
Without knowing the union of man and woman,
his organ stands erect.

His vital force is strong.
He can scream all day without becoming hoarse.
His harmony is perfect.

To know harmony is to know the everlasting.
To know the everlasting is enlightenment.

To interfere with life is ill-fated.
To control the breath causes strain.
If you exert yourself you will become exhausted.
This is not in harmony with Tao.

What is not in harmony with Tao does not long endure.

One who knows does not talk about it.
One who talks about it does not know.

Stay quiet.
Keep inside.
Blunt sharpness.
Unravel entanglements.
Diffuse brightness.
Merge with dust.

This is called “discovering original nature.”

One who knows original nature is
indifferent to intimacy and estrangement,
unconcerned with benefit and harm,
immune to honor and disgrace.

He is embraced by heaven.

Rule the country with sincerity.
Wage war with cunning.
Master the universe with indifference.

How do I know this is the way it is?

Because of this:
The more taboos, the poorer the people’s spirit.
The sharper men’s weapons, the more trouble in the land.
The greater the ingenuity, the more clutter in the world.
The more abundant the laws, the more abundant the thieves.

Therefore the sage says:
I take no action and the people naturally reform.
I remain at peace and the people become content.
I do not meddle and the people become prosperous.
I desire nothing and the people return to original nature.

When government does not interfere, the people are genuine.
When government intrudes, the people are cunning.

Happiness is founded on misery.
Misery lurks within happiness.
Is there an end to it?
Nothing stays the same.
Honesty moves with deceit.
Good flows with evil.
But people’s delusion persists.

Thus, the sage is sharp but not divisive,
straightforward but not hurtful,
principled but not severe,
illumined but not blinding.

In leading people and serving heaven,
nothing surpasses humility.
Humility is having no preferences.
Humility accumulates virtue.

Where virtue accumulates, nothing is impossible.
When nothing is impossible, there are no limits.
A man without limits is fit to rule the realm.
The mother of the realm is everlasting.

This is called being deeply rooted.
Timeless awareness of Tao.

Governing a country is like cooking a delicate fish.

Rule in observance of Tao
and the forces of adversity become harmless.
They do not lose their power,
only their power to harm.

The sage, too, does no harm
and so he is not harmed.
Virtue flows unimpeded.

A country becomes great by lying low,
like the delta of a great river.
The confluence of the realm.
The mother of the world.

The female conquers the male by stillness.
Being still, she takes the lower position.

A great country conquers a small country
by taking the lower position.
A small country conquers a great country
by merging with it.

Thus, the great country conquers by yielding,
the small country conquers by being absorbed.

The great country needs more people.
The small country needs greater purpose.
Each gets what it needs.

It is proper for greatness to yield.

Tao is the ground of the ten thousand things.
It is the refuge of the good man
and the guardian of the bad.

Fine speech can buy high rank.
Good deeds can earn respect.
Should one without them be abandoned?

Therefore, on the day the son is crowned
and the three ministers named,
do not send gifts of jade and teams of horses.
Remain still and offer Tao.

Why has Tao been honored since ancient times?
“Seek and you will find; transgress and you will be forgiven.”
Is this not the reason?

Above all else, observe Tao.

Perform not-doing.
Work without motive.
Savor what has no flavor.

Regard the small as great, the few as many.
Repay injury with compassion.

See simplicity in the complex.
See greatness in small gestures.
Confront the difficult while easy.
Do great things in small increments.

The sage does nothing great,
but great things are accomplished.

Easy promises are easily broken.
Things taken lightly become difficult.
The sage regards nothing lightly,
therefore nothing is difficult.

That which is still is easy to contain.
What has not yet begun is easy to prevent.
The fragile is easily broken.
The minute is easily dispelled.

See things before they emerge.
Attend to them before they grow out of control.

A tree trunk that fills a man’s arms
begins as a tiny shoot.
A terrace nine stories high
begins with a basket of dirt.
A journey of a thousand miles
begins underfoot.

Those who strive meet defeat.
Those who grasp lose their grip.
The sage does nothing and never fails.
He has nothing and never loses.

Failure often comes on the verge of success.
Be as careful in the end as the beginning
and there will be no failure.

The sage desires no-desire.
He does not value wealth.
He learns by not thinking.
He restores to others what has been lost.
He helps the ten thousand things return to original nature
but does not interfere.

The ancient observers of Tao did not teach it to others.
They let them remain simple and unknowing.
People are difficult to deal with when they think they know.

Leaders who think they know are a curse to those they lead.
Leaders with a simple heart are a blessing to all.

Both are manifestations of the same truth.
Knowing the truth is Virtue.
Virtue is mysterious, profound, far reaching.
Reaching far, it returns to itself and is complete.

Rivers rule valleys and seas rule rivers
because they take the lower position.

The sage is elevated by placing himself below others.
He leads by leaving himself behind.
When he assumes high position, the people do not feel his weight.
When he rules they do not feel threatened.
The realm rejoices and never tires of his presence.
Because he does not contend, nothing stands against him.

Everyone agrees the Tao I teach is great, yet unlike anything else.
Indeed, if it were not singular it would not endure.

I hold three treasures close:
The first is unconditional regard for all.
The second is being content with little.
The third is not placing myself before others.

From compassion comes courage.
From contentment comes an open heart.
From humility comes the capacity to lead.

Daring without mercy,
giving without generosity,
ruling without modesty,
this is the way of death.

Attacking with compassion, you are victorious.
Defending with compassion, you are impregnable.
What heaven favors it infuses with compassion.

A good general is not aggressive.
A good warrior is not wrathful.

A skillful conqueror does not instigate battle.
A skillful employer serves those under him.

This is the virtue of not contending.
This is mastering the strength of others.
This is being in accord with the principles of heaven.

Skillful warriors have a saying:
“Do not move first, play the guest.
Do not move forward an inch, retreat a foot.”

This is called advancing without moving.
Reaching without showing one’s arms.
Capturing without attacking.
Doing battle without weapons.

There is no greater mistake than underestimating the enemy.
Underestimating the enemy, I risk losing everything of value.

Thus, when equal opponents are matched,
the one aware of sorrow will prevail.

What I teach is easy to understand and practice,
yet no one understands it or puts it to practice.

My words are from the source.
My actions are those of the ancestor.
People do not understand this.
Therefore, they do not understand me.

Those who see me as I am are rare.
Those who seek to follow my teachings are few.

The sage wears coarse clothing
but carries jade in his pockets.

To know that you do not know is clarity.
To think that you know is sickness.

Being sick of sickness, one attains clarity.
The sage is sick of sickness.
Therefore, he is clear.

When people do not respect power,
disaster is on the horizon.

Do not limit their space.
Do not disrupt their lives.
Do not oppress them
and they will not tire of you.

The sage knows himself, but does not claim knowledge.
He loves himself, but does not feel important.
He lets go of that and chooses this.

A courageous and reckless man will kill or be killed.
A courageous and careful man preserves life.
Of the two, which is beneficial and which brings harm?
Who knows what heaven favors.
Even the sage is unsure.

The way of heaven does not contend, yet overcomes.
Does not speak, yet converses.
Without being summoned it comes of its own,
unhurried, and according to plan.

The net of heaven is vast.
Though the mesh is wide, nothing slips through.

If people are not afraid of death,
why threaten them with death?

If people are in constant fear of death,
and if being unruly means you will be killed,
who would dare be unruly?
Who would dare kill him?

There is always a lord of death.
Trying to do his job is like
taking the place of an artisan.
He who tries to carve like a master carpenter
rarely avoids being cut.

Why are the people starving?
The government takes their grain for taxes.
Therefore they are starving.

Why are the people rebellious?
The government interferes in their lives.
Therefore they are rebellious.

Why do people ignore the gravity of death?
They are consumed by the intensity of life.
Therefore they ignore the gravity of death.

One who is not consumed by life
is better off than one who values it.

A man is born supple and soft.
At death he is rigid and hard.
The ten thousand things, the grass, the trees,
while living are tender and pliant.
In death they are dry and withered.

The hard and unbending are companions of death.
The soft and yielding are companions of life.

Thus, an inflexible army is easily defeated.
An unbending tree is easily broken.

The hard and strong are laid low.
The soft and yielding are raised up.

The way of heaven, is it not like the stringing of a bow?
The high end is lowered, the low is raised up.
If the string is too long it is shortened.
If the string is too short it is lengthened.

The way of heaven takes from the excessive
and gives to the insufficient.
The way of man is different.
Those with too much take from those who have little.

Who keeps just enough and gives the rest to the world?
Only observers of Tao.

The sage works without expectation.
Achieves without taking credit.
He does not desire to seem worthy.

In all the world nothing is softer and weaker than water.
Yet for overcoming the hard and strong it is unequaled.

The pliant overcomes the unbending.
The submissive overcomes the unyielding.
Everyone knows this but no one puts it into practice.

Therefore the sage says:
He who takes on the suffering of the world is fit to rule it.
One who accepts the evils of the world as his own
is a king under heaven.

Truth is often a paradox.

When bitter quarrels are settled,
enmity is sure to remain.
What can be done?

A man of virtue pays his debts
but does not exact his due.
He fulfills his obligations
but makes no demands.

The Tao of heaven plays no favorites.
It flows with Virtue.

Let the state be small.
Let the people be few.
Though they have equipment to arm ten battalions
they do not do it.
They take death seriously and do not venture far.

They have ships and carts
but there is no place they want to go.
They have armor and weapons
but they are not displayed.

Men return to knotting rope.
They enjoy their meals and are comfortable in their clothes.
They are content in their homes and happy with their lives.

Though the neighboring state is so close
you can hear the cocks and dogs,
they leave each other in peace as they grow old and die.

Truth is not eloquent.
Eloquence is not truth.
Wise men do not try to persuade.
Whoever tries to persuade is not wise.

One who knows, claims unknowing.
One who claims knowledge, does not know.

The sage does not acquire.
He bestows what he has on others
and always has more.
The more he gives, the greater his abundance.

The way of heaven is to give without harm.
The way of the sage is to serve without striving.

Cokolwiek by o Nim nie mówić, istoty Tao nie da się opisać. Można nadać Mu nazwę, ale to nie będzie właściwa nazwa. Nicość to początek Nieba i Ziemi. Byt zaś jest Matką wszystkiego stworzenia. Poprzez Nicości można poznać jak subtelne jest Tao. Dzięki Bytowi można ujrzeć Jego bezmiar. Oba jednocześnie się wyłoniły, a potem odrębne przyjęły nazwy. Pozostały jednak równie tajemnicze. Tajemnicze a jeszcze bardziej tajemniczym się staje. Z nich się rodzi ogrom i subtelność.

Każdy wie, że to, co jest piękne, to jest piękne. Dzięki temu wiadomo, co jest brzydkie. Każdy też wie, że dobre jest to, co jest dobre. Stąd wiadomo, co nie jest dobre. W ten sposób jednocześnie się zrodziły Byt i Nicość. Powstało tak to, co trudne i to, co łatwe; długie i krótkie przedmioty nawzajem się określają, a wysokie i niskie są dla siebie nawzajem miarą. Tak samo też postępują mędrcy, którzy działają nie robiąc nic i nauczają nie używając słów. Wszystkie rzeczy w Nim istnieją, ono jednak nie ingeruje. Tworzy, lecz nie posiada. Nie polega na tym, co uczyni. Nie pyszni się tym i dlatego, co uczyni, wiecznie trwa.

Jeśli nie będzie się szanować ludzi wybitnych, to lud nie będzie zawistny. Jeśli nie będzie się cenić rzadkich dóbr, to lud nie będzie kraść. Jeśli nie będzie się wystawiać na widok publiczny drogocenności, to lud nie będzie się burzył. Mędrcy kierują się takimi oto zasadami: – opróżnić umysły a napełnić brzuchy, – osłabić ducha a wzmocnić ciało. Dzięki temu lud o niczym nie będzie wiedział i niczego nie będzie pragnął. Ci zaś, którzy już wiedzą, nie będą w stanie niczego zdziałać. Postępować należy tak, aby niczego nie robić, a wtedy panował będzie ład.

Tao jest puste, ale zastosowań ma bez liku. Ono jest jak otchłań morska. Wydaje się być przodkiem wszystkiego stworzenia. Przytępia to, co w nim ostre, a to, co zawiłe, rozsupłuje. Blask swój przyćmiewa i łączy swój pył. Niedostrzegalne, a jednak wiecznie trwa. Nie wiem skąd się wzięło, ale wydaje mi się, że istniało wcześniej niźli Stwórca.

Niebo i Ziemia nie są miłosierne: nie martwią się o los tego, co istnieje. Święci mędrcy również nie są miłosierni: los ludzkości ich nie obchodzi. Przestrzeń między Niebem i Ziemią zda się być niczym miech: pusta a jednak niewyczerpana, z której za każdym poruszeniem coraz więcej i więcej się rodzi. Słowami nic się nie da wskórać: już lepiej nie mówić nic.

Tao jest jak doliny i bóstwa, które nigdy nie przeminą. Nazywam Je „tajemniczą żeńskością”, a bramę, która wiedzie do „tajemniczej żeńskości” nazywam fundamentem Nieba i Ziemi. Ono jest jak pajęczyna: ledwo co istnieje; a jednak nie ma końca.

Niebo i Ziemia istnieją od dawna. Tak długowieczne są dlatego, że same siebie nie tworzą: oto sekret ich żywotności. Mędrcy postępują tak samo: nie stawiają siebie na pierwszym miejscu, a mimo to są na czele; nie dbają o siebie, a jednak mają za co żyć. Czyż zabiegają oni wciąż o swoje? Nie. Dlatego też zawsze dopną swego.

Najznakomitsi ludzie są jak woda, woda bowiem znakomicie zaspokaja potrzeby wszystkiego stworzenia: nie siłuje się z nimi; przebywa w miejscach, którymi człowiek gardzi, dlatego też jest blisko Tao. Znakomicie potrafią oni wybrać sobie miejsce zamieszkania, opróżnić serca z pragnień i obdarowywać z czystej dobroci. Potrafią też doskonale mówić, łatwo więc uwierzyć w ich słowa. Umieją sprawnie rządzić i załatwiać różne sprawy, dlatego wiele mogą. Bezbłędnie wybierają porę na swój ruch. Z niczym się nie siłują i dlatego nie popełniają błędu, i nie mają czego żałować.

Co za dużo to nie zdrowo, lepiej przerwać póki czas. Ostrze często szlifowane nie będzie ci długo służyć. Jeśli swój dom wypełnisz po brzegi nefrytem i złotem, nie będzie komu go strzec. Jeśli zgromadzisz majątek i zbierzesz zaszczyty, sam na siebie tym nieszczęście ściągniesz. Kiedy już zrobisz, co do ciebie należy, wycofaj się; taka jest bowiem naturalna kolej rzeczy.

Dusza ogarnia Wielką Jedność. Czyż może więc się od niej odłączyć? Czy, złagodniawszy dzięki nieingerowaniu w naturę życia, można stać się niemowlęciem; a obmywszy się z tajemniczego światopoglądu, czy można zostać bez skazy? Kochając kraj i rządząc ludem, czy można niczego nie czynić? Kiedy się otwierają i zamykają Niebiosa, czy można być płochym jak kura? Kiedy wszyscy są pojętni wokoło, czy można o niczym nie wiedzieć? Tworzyć i pielęgnować. Tworzyć, ale nie posiadać. Nie polegać na tym co się czyni. Przewodzić, ale nie rządzić. Oto co nazywam tajemniczym Te.

Trzynaście szprych w jedno się łączy koło; dzięki pustej przestrzeni między nimi powóz się toczy. Naczynie powstaje z połączenia gliny; dzięki pustej przestrzeni wewnątrz ma zastosowanie. Budując dom, wykuwa się okna i drzwi, dzięki pustej przestrzeni można go używać. Chociaż z Bytu płyną korzyści, to dzięki Nicości można ich doświadczyć.

Od nadmiaru barw traci się wzrok. Od nadmiaru brzmień traci się słuch. Od nadmiaru smaków, traci się czucie w podniebieniu. Od jazdy konnej i polowań łatwo oszaleć. Przedmioty trudne do zdobycia wyrządzają krzywdę. Mędrcy więc dbają o swój brzuch a nie oko; Odsuwają od siebie tamto, a biorą to.

„Zaszczyt i hańba taka samą napełniają trwogą. Nieszczęście należy cenić jak siebie samego” Co to znaczy, że „zaszczyt i hańba taka samą napełniają trwogą”? Otóż: Zaszczyt jest jak zdobycie szczytu hańba jest jak upadek. Strach go więc zarówno osiągnąć jak i stracić. Dlatego też mówimy, że „zaszczyt i hańba taka samą napełniają trwogą”. Co to znaczy, że „nieszczęście należy cenić jak siebie samego”? Otóż: Winą tego, że spotykają mnie nieszczęścia, jest moje istnienie. Gdyby mnie nie było, jakież by mnie mogły spotkać nieszczęścia? Dlatego też temu, który ceni sobie poświęcenie dla świata, można świat powierzyć. Temu, kto z ochotą poświęca się światu, można świat przekazać.

Nie da się Go zobaczyć, toteż nazywa się spokojnym; nie da się Go usłyszeć, toteż nazywa się niknącym; nie da się Go pochwycić, toteż nazywa się drobniutkim. Tych trzech aspektów nie sposób zbadać dogłębnie, wszystkie się mieszają w jedną całość. W najwyższym punkcie nie jest jasne, w najniższym nie jest mroczne. Ciągnie się tajemniczo jak nić bezimienne i wraca do Nicości. Oto co nazywam bezpostaciową formą, bezprzedmiotowym obrazem. Nazywam Je nienamacalnym i nieokreślonym Gdy się Je spotyka, nie widzi się Jego twarzy, kiedy się za Nim idzie nie widzi się Jego pleców. Kiedy pojmie się Tao przeszłości, wiedza ta pozwoli zapanować nad tym, co dziś istnieje. Znajomość pradawnego początku, uważam za regułę Tao.

Starożytni mistrzowie Tao byli subtelni i posiadali tajemniczą logikę. Ich głębi pojąc się nie da. Tak, trudno było poznać ich głębię, ale i nie łatwo opisać jacy byli na co dzień: ostrożni jak ktoś zimą przekraczający rzekę; przezorni jak ktoś kto się boi swych sąsiadów; uprzejmi jak gość; podatni jak topniejący lód; szczerzy jak nieociosany kloc; przepastni jak dolina, niezorganizowani jak zmącona woda. Któż mógłby się w wodach zmąconych uspokoić i z wolna zajaśnieć? Któż mógłby w ciszy się poruszyć i z wolna ożyć? Ci, którzy to pojmują, nie pragną sytości; a ponieważ nie pragną sytości, nie muszą się ujawniać ani tworzyć niczego nowego.

Trzeba osiągnąć zupełną pustkę i zachować niczym nie zmącony spokój; ujrzymy wtedy jak powraca wszystko, co się narodziło. Mnóstwo jest bytów, a wszystkie powracają do swojego źródła. Powrót do źródła nazywam uspokojeniem. To właśnie nazywam powrotem do natury rzeczy. Powrót do natury rzeczy zaś, to nieustanność zmian. Poznanie tej nieustanności nazywam zrozumieniem. Niewiedza o niej zaś sprawia, że bezmyślnie powodujemy nieszczęścia. Poznanie nieustanności zmian prowadzi do ogarnięcia wszystkiego. Ogarnięcie wszystkiego prowadzi do równości. Równość prowadzi do powszechności. Powszechność prowadzi do boskości. Boskość to Tao, a Tao to trwałość. Żadne wtedy za życia nie czyha niebezpieczeństwo.

Doskonały władca to taki, o którego istnieniu nikt nie wie. Nieco gorszym od niego jest taki, który się cieszy dobrą sławą. Jeszcze gorszy jest taki, którego należy się bać. A jeszcze gorszy jest ten, którym się gardzi. Jeśli ktoś jest nieszczery, nikt mu nie zaufa. Władcy, który jest oszczędny w słowach, łatwo odnieść sukces i załatwić wiele spraw. Lud mówi wtedy: „Zawsze tak było to naturalny stan rzeczy”.

Kiedy zignorujemy wielkie Tao, pojawi się sztuczna uprzejmość i kierowana zwyczajem sprawiedliwość. Kiedy pojawia się mądrość, powstają wielkie oszustwa. Kiedy brak zgody w rodzinie, wymyśla się przykazania miłości. Kiedy w państwie panuje chaos, pojawiają się lojalni urzędnicy.

Porzućcie mądrość i wiedzę, a lud zyska na tym po stokroć. Porzućcie dobroduszność i etykę a ludzie znów będą się kochać. Porzućcie spryt i chęć zysku, a nie będzie więcej złodziei. Nie wystarczy jednak tylko to przeczytać, trzeba w zgodzie z tym postępować. Ukażcie swą prostotę, bądźcie jak nieociosany kloc. Mniej zabiegajcie o swoje; skromniejsze miejcie pragnienia.

Przestańcie się uczyć, a nie będziecie mieć zmartwień. Czym się różni aplauz od gwizdów pogardy; a czym dobro jest inne od zła? Czy muszę się bać tego, czego się wszyscy boją? Takich pytań mógłbym jeszcze podać wiele. Wszyscy się cieszą, jak na pieczeniu barana albo wiosennej majówce. Tylko ja siedzę cicho w kącie i nie daję znać o sobie, jak niemowlę, co się jeszcze nie uśmiecha. Umęczony, nie mam dokąd wrócić. Wszyscy mają w brud wszystkiego, tylko mnie na nic nigdy nie starcza. Jestem głupi i o niczym nie wiem. Wszyscy błyszczą, tylko ja jestem ciemny. Wszyscy pałają zapałem, tylko ja jestem markotny. Obojętny na wszystko jak ocean, wieczny pędziwiatr. Każdy ma jakieś możliwości, tylko ja nic nie potrafię. Tylko ja jestem inny, bo mnie żywi matka-natura.

Przejawy wielkiego Te są niczym innym jak tylko miernym odzwierciedleniem Tao. Tao tak właściwie to jest nieokreślone i nienamacalne. Nieokreślone! Nienamacalne! A jednak zawiera w sobie obrazy. Nieokreślone! Nienamacalne! A jednak zawiera w sobie byty. Niezgłębione i mroczne! A jednak zawiera w sobie istotę życia; prawdziwą istotę życia. Można Mu zaufać. Od prawieków Jego imię wiecznie trwa, nieustannie dając początek bytom. Skąd wiem jaki był początek świata? Stąd.

Co się złamie, to się zrośnie. Co się pognie, to się wyprostuje. Co jest głębokie, to się napełni. Co się zniszczy to się odnowi. Kto mało posiada, wiele osiągnie. Kto wiele posiada, to się mu pomiesza w głowie. Dlatego też mędrzec ogarnia Wielką Jedność, i przez jej pryzmat ocenia świat. Nie robi z siebie widowiska dlatego daje się poznać. Nie mówi: „Patrzcie, to ja!” dlatego jest sławny. Nie chwali się swymi osiągnięciami dlatego odnosi sukces. Nie wynosi się nad innych, dlatego nie zginie. Nie wdaje się w rywalizację, dlatego nikt z nim nie rywalizuje. Skądże by więc to stare powiedzenie: „Co się złamie, to się zrośnie” miało być czczą gadaniną. Prawda jest taka, że się zrośnie.

Małomówność jest czymś naturalnym. Wichura nie trwa przecież cały dzień, Ulewny deszcz nie pada całą dobę. Kto jest tego sprawcą? Niebo i Ziemia. Nawet Niebo i Ziemia nie mogą tak bez końca, a co dopiero człowiek. Dlatego też kto postępuje, tak aby osiągnąć Tao, jednoczy się z Tao; kto postępuje, tak aby osiągnąć Te, jednoczy się z Te; kto postępuje, tak aby stracić, jednoczy się ze zgubą. Tego, który się zjednoczy z Tao, Tao wita równie radośnie; Tego, który się zjednoczy z Te, Te wita równie radośnie; Tego, który straci, Zguba wita równie radośnie. Jeśli ktoś jest nieszczery, nikt mu nie zaufa.

Kto się wspina na palce, nie wystoi; a kto postawi zbyt duży krok, nie dojdzie. Kto sam siebie promuje, nie zabłyśnie; Kto się uważa za pewniaka, nic nie znaczy; Kto się przechwala, niczego nie osiągnie; Kto się unosi ponad innych, długo nie zabawi. Wszystko to za sprawą Tao. To się nazywa: obżarstwo i pracoholizm. Wszyscy tym gardzą; dlatego ten, kto poznał Tao, nie przejmuje się tym.

Jest takie Coś, co powstało w niewyjaśnionych okolicznościach, zanim jeszcze Niebo i Ziemia powstały. Samotne i puste. Niezależne i niezmienne. Wszędzie coś robi i się nie obija. Można by powiedzieć, że to Matka Świata. Nie wiem, jak się nazywa. Ja nazywam Je Tao. Z braku lepszego słowa nazywam Je Wielkim. O Wielkim mówię, że odchodzi; o Odchodzącym mówię, że jest daleko; o Dalekim mówię, że wraca. Tao więc jest wielkie. Niebo jest wielkie. Ziemia jest wielka. Człowiek również jest wielki. W naszym wymiarze istnieją cztery wielkie elementy Człowiek jest jednym z nich. Człowiek przestrzega zasad Ziemi; Ziemia przestrzega zasad Nieba, Niebo przestrzega zasad Tao. Tao przestrzega samo Siebie.

Ciężar jest źródłem lekkości, Spokój włada zamieszaniem. Dlatego też mędrcy trwają przy swym wozie; choćby się piękne wkoło roztaczały widoki, nic ich nie rozproszy. Czyżby więc władca olbrzymiego imperium, mógłby lekceważyć sobie świat. Lekceważąc, odetnie się od źródeł; Wprowadzając zamieszanie, utraci władzę.

Kto umie chodzić, nie zostawia po sobie śladów; kto umie mówić, nie popełnia błędów; kto umie liczyć, nie używa liczydeł; kto umie zamykać nie korzysta z kluczy i zasuw, a jednak nikt po nim nie otworzy; kto umie wiązać, nie posługuje się sznurem i liną; a jednak nikt po nim nie rozwiąże. Tak też mędrcy mogą zawsze zbawić lud, dlatego nikt nie zostanie odtrącony; zawsze mogą uratować dobytek, dlatego nic się nie zmarnuje. To się nazywa dziedzictwem jasności. Dlatego też ten, który umie, jest nauczycielem tego, który nie umie; a ten, który nie umie, jest uczniem tego, który umie. Jeśli nie cenimy swego nauczyciela, czy też nie szanujemy swego ucznia, choćby się nam to wydawało czymś słusznym, błądzimy potwornie. To się nazywa istotnym i subtelnym.

Kto, wiedząc, co znaczy męstwo, zachowuje się jak kura, jest strumykiem świata. Kto jest strumykiem świata tego Te nie opuszcza, ktoś taki na powrót się staje niemowlakiem. Kto, wiedząc co to jasność, trzyma się ciemności, świeci przykładem dla świata. Kto świeci przykładem dla świata temu Te nie ciąży, ktoś taki wraca do nieskończoności. Kto, wiedząc, co znaczy uwielbienie, woli raczej żyć w pogardzie, jest doliną dla świata. Kto jest doliną dla świata, ten ma Te pod dostatkiem, taki ktoś odzyskuje swą pierwotna naturę: znów jest jak nieociosany pieniek. Z pnia tego, gdy go rozłupać, powstają naczynia, których używają mędrcy, dlatego przewodzą oni urzędnikom. Kto bowiem dobrze rządzi, nie stosuje cięć.

Wywieraniem nacisku, trudno cokolwiek osiągnąć, sam byłem świadkiem nieudanych prób. Świat jest boskim naczyniem, na które nie można wpłynąć. Nie sposób go opanować. Ci, którzy mają na niego wpływ, psują go. Ci, którzy go opanują – tracą. Stworzenia się przecież dzielą na te, które idą samodzielnie, oraz na te, które podążają za tymi pierwszymi; na te, które oddychają nosem, oraz na te, które oddychają ustami; na te, które są silne, oraz na te, które są słabe; na te, które są spokojne, oraz na te, które są niebezpieczne. Mędrcy odrzucają więc nadmiar, zbytek i przesadę.

Ten, kto władcy służy dobrą radą, radą zgodną z Tao, nie ucieka się do przemocy. Przemoc często przemoc rodzi. Cierniste tylko krzaki wyrosną, tam gdzie stały wojska. Po wielkiej wojnie, chude nastają lata. Znawca osiąga swój cel i na tym poprzestaje; nie śmie dalej rosnąć w siłę. Osiąga swój cel, ale się nim nie pyszni; osiąga swój cel, ale nie idzie po trupach, osiąga swój cel, ale obca mu duma. Osiąga swój cel, bo nic nie może na to poradzić; osiąga swój cel bez wysiłku. Kto ma mocną pozycję, znaczy, że jest stary; a to się kłóci z Tao. Co się zaś kłóci z Tao, tego koniec bliski.

Wspaniała broń nie wróży nic dobrego, nikt jej nie cierpi; dlatego nie stosuje jej ten, kto pojął Tao. W czas pokoju człowiek szlachetny ceni sobie lewą stronę, w czas wojny zaś ceni stronę prawą. Broń nie wróży nic dobrego, to nie jest narzędzie godne szlachetnej osoby. Szlachetny używa jej tylko wtedy, gdy naprawdę musi, uważając jednak spokój za rzecz najważniejszą. Zwycięstwo nie jest dla niego powodem do chwały miałby się cieszyć, że zabijał ludzi? Taki co się cieszy, że zabija ludzi, nie może władać światem. W szczęściu lewa strona się liczy, w niedoli zaś prawa. Młodszy rangą generał stoi po lewej stronie, głównodowodzący zaś po prawej; to tak samo jak na pogrzebie. Kiedy się zabija miliony, trzeba nad tym płakać; dlatego kiedy się zwycięża na wojnie, postępuje się według zasad pogrzebu.

Tao jest niezmienne i nie sposób Go nazwać, jest jak nieociosany kloc; chociaż małe, nikt się nim nie wysługuje. Jeśliby Je pojęli możni i królowie, wszyscy byliby Mu posłuszni. Kiedy Niebo i Ziemia są w zgodzie, spuszczają słodką rosę; a lud, który jej nie ma, dzieli się nią po równo. Kiedy powstały byty, pojawiły się też nazwy; należy jednak znać umiar, kto zna umiar, unika niebezpieczeństw. Jeśliby porównać Tao do świata ludzi: ma się ono do niego, jak górskie potoki do rzek, a rzeki do mórz.

Kto zna innych, jest mądry; a kto zna siebie jest bystry. Kto wygrywa z innymi, jest silny, a kto wygrywa sam z sobą ma Moc. Kto wie ile mu potrzeba, jest bogaty. Kto dzielnie trwa w swym zamiarze, ma siłę woli. Kto zna swoje miejsce, będzie długo żył, a kto umrze lecz nie wszystek, będzie żył na wieki.

Tao rozpływa się wszędzie, na prawo płynie i na lewo. Wszystko dzięki Niemu się rodzi, Ono się jednak nie interesuje tym, co stwarza, nie posiada tego, czego dokona Ubiera i karmi wszystko, lecz nie jest mu władcą. Nigdy niczego nie pragnie, można by Je więc nazwać Małym. Wszystko wraca do Niego, lecz Ono nie jest mu władcą, można by Je więc nazwać Wielkim. Ponieważ nie jest wielkie, może wielkim się stać.

Kiedy ktoś trzyma Wielki Obraz, cały świat lgnie do niego. Lgnie, ale się nie wdziera; panuje bowiem spokój i porządek. Kusząca muzyka przykuwa uwagę przechodnia. Tao, kiedy powstaje, jest nijakie i bez smaku: Patrzysz i Go nie widzisz, Słuchasz i Go nie słyszysz, Czerpiesz z Niego, a Ono się nie wyczerpuje.

Jeśli coś ma się skurczyć, to musi być długie. Jeśli coś ma osłabnąć, to musi być mocne. Jeśli coś ma być wyrzucone, to musi być wpierw przyjęte. Jeśli coś ma zostać zabrane, musi wpierw być podarowane. To właśnie nazywam Subtelna Jasnością. To co słabe i miękkie wygrywa z tym co twarde i silne. Ryby nie mogą opuścić głębin, a tajników rządzenia krajem, nie można wyjawić ludowi.

Tao nieustannie trwa; niczego nie robi, a wszystko samo się dzieje. Gdyby Je pojęli możni i królowie, wszystko by się rozwijało w naturalny sposób. A gdyby się rozwinęło na tyle, że zapragnęłoby działać, powstrzymałbym je za pomocą Pu, dla którego nie znajduję nazwy. Za Jego sprawą ustąpiłyby wszystkie pragnienia. Kiedy ustąpią pragnienia zapanuje spokój, i ład się sam zaprowadzi na świecie.

Najwyższa Moc (czyli Te) nie obnosi się swą Mocą, stąd wiadomo że Ją ma. Mała Moc pragnie Mocy, stąd wiadomo, że Jej nie posiada. Najwyższa Moc nic nie robi i nie szuka sobie korzyści. Mała Moc nic nie robi, ale ma w tym swój interes. Dobroduszność robi coś, ale bezinteresownie. Etyka też coś robi, ale ma w tym swój interes. Obyczajowość robi coś, a, gdy się nie spotyka z odzewem, zakasując rękawy, siłą się bierze do dzieła. Jeśli więc stracimy Tao, pozostanie nam Moc; jeśli stracimy Moc, pozostanie nam Dobroduszność; jeśli stracimy Dobroduszność, pozostanie nam Etyka; jeśli stracimy Etykę, pozostanie nam Obyczajowość. A Obyczajowość to przecież rozrzedzenie wiary i zaufania oraz początek chaosu. Wiedza prorocza to tylko złuda, prowadząca do ogłupienia. Wielkiemu mężowi zależy więc na tym, co gęste, a nie na tym, co rzadkie; zależy mu na tym, co prawdziwe, a nie na tym, co złudne. Odrzuca więc tamto, a bierze to.

Dawno temu osiągnęły Jedność: Niebo osiągnęło Jedność i stało się czyste; Ziemia osiągnęła Jedność i uspokoiła się; Bóstwa osiągnęły Jedność i stały się nadprzyrodzone; Potoki osiągnęły Jedność i zapełniły się; Stworzenia osiągnęły Jedność i narodziły się, Możni i królowie osiągnęli Jedność i rządzą światem. A wszystko to dzięki Niej. Jeśliby Niebo nie stało się czyste, rozpadłoby się; jeśliby się Ziemia nie uspokoiła, nic by z niej nie zostało; jeśliby się Bóstwa nie stały nadprzyrodzone, przepadłyby z kretesem; jeśliby się Potoki nie zapełniły, wyczerpałyby się; jeśliby się Stworzenia nie rodziły, zginęłyby; jeśliby możni i królowie nie byli poważani, straciliby swe stanowiska. Poważanie przecież zaczyna się od pogardy, a na szczyt od dołu się wchodzi. To dlatego możni i królowie mówią o sobie: „Sierota”, „Liliput”, „Niezdara”. Czyż nie jest to zaczynanie od pogardy? No a co? Sława, kiedy się już ją osiągnie, nie jest sławą. Nie pragnij błyszczeć jak nefryt, bądź matowy jak pospolity kamyk.

Ruchem Tao jest ciągłe powracanie, narzędziem Tao jest słabość. Wszystko na świecie ma swój początek w Bycie, Byt zaś bierze się z Nicości.

Geniusz, kiedy usłyszy o Tao, czym prędzej za nim podąży. Przeciętniak, kiedy usłyszy o Tao, pomyśli sobie: „może jest a może Go nie ma”. Niedojda, kiedy usłyszy o Tao, wybuchnie śmiechem; Gdyby taki się nie śmiał, jakież by z Niego było Tao. Przodkowie powiadali: jasna Droga jest ciemna, bliska Droga jest odległa, równa Droga jest wyboista, najwyższa Moc jest jak przepaść, czysta biel nie jest bez skazy, posiąść wielką Moc to nie wszystko, ugruntowana Moc kryje w sobie lenistwo, najmocniejsi zmieniają zdanie, największy kwadrat nie ma rogów, największe naczynie nie ma określonej formy, najgłośniejszy dźwięk jest niesłyszalny, największy Obraz jest bezkształtny, Tao jest ukryte i bezimienne. Dlatego też Tao wspomaga i tworzy.

Tao rodzi Jedność, Jedność rodzi dwojakość, dwojakość rodzi trojakość, a trojakość rodzi całą resztę. Wszystkie stworzenia dźwigają ying i obejmują yang, z ich połączenia czerpią siłę. Ludzie nie cierpią być: Sierotą, Liliputem i Niezdarą; a przecież królowie sami siebie tak nazywają: Kto więc traci, ten zyskuje; a kto zyskuje, ten traci. Tego, czego nauczał inny, ja również nauczam: kto przemoc stosuje, nie umrze spokojnie. Biorę to za ojca wszelkich nauk.

To co miękkie, więcej ma w sobie sprytu niż to, co twarde; Nicość przenika to, co się między Nicością znajduje. Stąd też wiem, że niedziałanie przynosi korzyści. Jeśli chodzi o naukę bez słów i korzyści płynące z niedziałania, nie wielu jest na świecie takich, którzy je osiągnęli.

Sława czy zdrowie bardziej nam bliskie? Zdrowie czy bogactwa bardziej cenimy? Zysk czy strata, co bardziej boli? Dlatego też kto pożąda, ten drogo zapłaci; a kto wielkie posiada bogactwa, wielkie poniesie straty. Kto zna umiar, ten się wstydził nie będzie, Kto wie kiedy przestać, uniknie zguby i żył będzie długo.

To co w doskonałym jest stanie, wydaje się uszkodzone, nigdy się jednak nie zużyje. To co pełne, wydaje się puste, nigdy się jednak nie opróżni. To co proste, wydaje się pokrętne. To co sprytne, wydaje się głupawe. Kto pięknie mówi, ten jakby się jąka. Cisza zwycięża zamęt, Mróz zwycięża upał. Spokój rządzi światem.

Kiedy świat przestrzega Tao, panuje umiar, a konie orają ziemię. Kiedy świat nie przestrzega Tao na obrzeżach miasta hoduje się konie bojowe. Nie ma większego nieszczęścia niż brak umiaru. Nie ma większej winy niż żądza. Tylko ci, którzy znają umiar, zawsze są syci.

Nie wychodząc z domu, można poznać świat. Nie wyglądając przez okno, można zobaczyć, jak wielkie jest Tao. Im bardziej się oddalamy, tym mniej wiemy. Dlatego też mędrcy nie podróżują, a wszystko wiedzą. Nie widzą, a wszystko jest dla nich jasne. Nie robią nic, a wszystko samo się dzieje.

Codziennie zbieramy plony, tego czegośmy się nauczyli; dzięki Tao zaś, codziennie się kurczymy. Kurczymy się i kurczymy, aż nic z nas nie zostaje. Nie robimy nic, a wszystko samo się robi. Jeśli ktoś chce rządzić światem, niczego nie powinien robić. Jeśli bowiem cokolwiek uczyni, nie wystarczy to, aby rządzić światem.

Mędrcy nie mają własnych zmartwień, zmartwieniami innych się przejmują. Jeśli ktoś jest dobry, uważam go za dobrego; jeśli ktoś nie jest dobry, to też uważam go za dobrego i osiągam dobroć. Jeśli ktoś jest wierny, wierzę mu, Jeśli ktoś nie jest wierny, to też mu wierzę i osiągam wierność. Mędrcy dają się zassać światu, mogą nim rządzić, bo prosty jest ich umysł. Wszyscy naokoło wpatrują się i pilnie słuchają, wszyscy mędrcy są dziećmi.

Wychodzimy do życia a wchodzimy do śmierci. Trzech z dziesięciu żyje długo. Trzech z dziesięciu żyje krótko. Tych, którzy się rodzą i niechybnie kroczą ku śmierci, to również trzy osoby na dziesięć. Czemu tak jest? Dlatego że prowadzą zbyt intensywne życie. Słyszałem, że ci, którzy wiedzą jak dbać o życie, nie napotykają na swej drodze nosorożców czy tygrysów. Jeśli wstąpią do armii, żadna broń nie zada im rany. Nosorożec nie ma w co wepchnąć swego rogu, tygrys nie ma w czym zatopić swych pazurów, broń nie ma na czym zahaczyć swego ostrza. Czemu tak jest? Dlatego, że oni kroczą po drodze nieśmiertelnych.

Tao rodzi, Te chowa, świat kształtuje, okoliczności budują. Dlatego nie ma wśród bytów takiego, któryby nie szanował Tao i nie cenił Te. Szacunek dla Tao i docenianie Te, nie wynikają z czyjegoś rozkazu, są czymś zupełnie naturalnym. Dlatego Tao rodzi, Te chowa, przewodzi, uczy, umacnia, opiekuje się, karmi oraz chroni. Rodzi ale nie posiada, nie polega na tym, co uczyni, przewodzi i nie zarzyna. Oto co się nazywa tajemnym Te.

Jest Początek na świecie, który to jest Matką świata. Jeśli dotrzemy do matki, poznamy jej dzieci; jeśli poznamy jej dzieci i będziemy trzymać się matki, nie czeka nas żadne niebezpieczeństwo. Zatkajmy usta, oczy, uszy i nos, zamknijmy drzwi, a nie będziemy musieli się trudzić do końca życia. Kiedy zaś otworzymy usta, oczy, uszy i nos, zaczną nam się mnożyć sprawy i nie zaznamy spokoju. Kto widzi małe, ten jest oświecony. Kto trwa w miękkości, ten jest mocny. Kto korzysta z blasku, powraca do stanu oświecenia i nic mu nie grozi. Oto co nazywam życiem w zgodzie z Wiekuistym.

Jeślibym nagle posiadł wiedzę, szedłbym tam gdzie mnie Tao prowadzi, bałbym się jedynie zejścia na złą drogę. Szlak, którym Tao wiedzie, jest prosty, ludzie jednak wolą ścieżki pokrętne. Na pańskim dworze ład i porządek, kiedy pola chwastem porastają a spichlerze świecą pustkami. Oni jednak noszą się w kolorowych jedwabiach, ostre miecze mają przy boku, jedzą i piją bez miary, wszystkiego mają w bród, przywódcy zbójców. Gdzież tam miejsce dla Tao.

Jak się coś dobrze zasadzi, to się wyrwać nie da; jak się coś dobrze obejmie, to się już nie wymknie, potomkowie będą nas za to wielbić bez końca. Traktuj tak siebie samego, a osiągniesz prawdziwą Moc. Traktuj tak rodzinę, a Mocy będzie miała w nadmiarze. Traktuj tak okolicę, a Moc osiągnie na długo. Traktuj tak swój kraj, a Moc jego będzie obfita. Traktuj tak cały świat, a Moc się jego rozrośnie. W taki sposób siebie postrzegasz przez siebie samego, rodzinę postrzegasz przez rodzinę, okolicę postrzegasz przez okolicę, kraj postrzegasz przez kraj, a świat postrzegasz przez świat. Skąd wiem, że tak się na świecie dzieje? Stąd.

Ten kto pojął dobrze Te, jest jak niemowlę. Nie pogryzą go jadowite owady, Dzikie zwierzęta nie rozszarpią, ptaki drapieżne nie porwą. Kości jego są miękkie a ścięgna wiotkie, jeśli jednak coś chwyci, to trzyma mocno. Nie poznał jeszcze związku kobiety z mężczyzną, jego narządy rozrodcze są jednak uniesione, gdyż siły witalne osiągnęły w nim pełnię. Cały dzień krzyczy a mimo to nie ochrypnie, gdyż osiągnął pełną harmonię. Jeśli ktoś pojął harmonię, można powiedzieć, że poznał Wiekuiste. Jeśli ktoś pojął Wiekuiste, można powiedzieć, że doznał oświecenia. Jeśli ktoś ceni swe życie, można powiedzieć, że jest w tarapatach. Jeśli ktoś okazuje złość, można powiedzieć, że się bije sam z sobą. Kiedy osiągnie się dojrzałość, przychodzi starość. To nie jest Tao. Kto nie pojął Tao, tego koniec bliski.

Ci, którzy wiedzą, mówią niewiele; ten, kto dużo gada, ten mało wie. Przytępiaj to, co w tobie ostre, a to, co zawiłe, rozsupłuj. Blask swój przyćmiewaj i łącz swój pył. Oto co się nazywa mistyczną harmonią. Ten kto Ją osiągnie nie może być jej bliskim ani dalekim; nie może na tym zyskać ani stracić; nie przyda mu to zaszczytów, ani nie okryje go hańbą. Dlatego też taki człowiek to skarb.

Aby rządzić krajem, trzeba wiedzieć co słuszne; aby władać bronią, trzeba sprytu; lecz tylko poprzez nieingerownie można posiąść świat. Skąd wiem, że tak właśnie jest? Stąd. Im więcej tabu, tym lud uboższy; im więcej ostrej broni na dworach, tym większy w kraju zamęt; im więcej kto potrafi, tym więcej czyni podłości; im bardziej istotne się stają prawa i nakazy, tym więcej wszędzie złodziei i bandytów. Dlatego też mędrzec powiada tak: nie robię nic, a lud się sam rozwija; siedzę cicho, a lud sam wie, co słuszne; nie ingeruję, a lud się sam bogaci; nie mam żądań, a lud sam staje się nieskażony.

Kiedy rządzącym brak werwy, lud żyje w prostocie; kiedy rządzący są pełni zapału, lud żyje w niedostatku. Niedola jest podporą szczęścia, szczęście jest kryjówką niedoli. Któż zna tego kres? Nie ma tu słuszności. Słuszność zmienia się w zawiść, Dobroć zmienia się w zło. Dziwią się temu ludzie od dawna. Dlatego też mędrcy są szczerzy, ale nie do bólu; ostrzy, ale nie ranią; prości, ale bez przesady; świecą, ale nie oślepiają.

Rządząc ludem i służąc Stwórcy, należy być oszczędnym. Kto jest oszczędny, ten jest zawczasu posłuszny; kto jest zawczasu posłuszny, ten nagromadzi sobie Mocy pod dostatkiem; kto nagromadzi sobie Mocy pod dostatkiem, ten wszystko pokona; kto wszystko pokona, ten nie zna szczytu swych możliwości, kto nie zna szczytu swych możliwości, ten może posiąść państwo; kto posiądzie podstawy państwa, ten przetrwa długo. Oto co nazywam Tao, które zapuszcza głęboko korzenie, wiecznie trwa i patrzy wciąż.

Rządzić wielkim państwem, to jak gotować małą rybkę. Jeśli władca na świat spogląda zgodnie z zasadami Tao, duchy nie będą straszyć; nie tylko nie będą straszyć, ale nie będą też krzywdzić ludzi; nie tylko nie będą krzywdzić ludzi, ale też władcy nie będę krzywdzić ludu. Przecież, kiedy nikt nie będzie nikogo krzywdził, Moc pokieruje wszystkich z powrotem ku Niemu.

Wielkie państwo leży nisko jak ocean do niego spływa cały świat. Samica świata, samica zwykle zwycięża samca spokojem, spokojem się przed nim uniża. Wielkie państwo uniża się więc przed małym krajem, i tak go zdobywa. Mały kraj uniża się przed wielkim państwem i tak je zdobywa. Jedno zdobywa dzięki uniżeniu, drugie dzięki uniżeniu również zdobywa. Wielkiemu państwu zależy na tym, aby sobie wszystkich wychować; małemu krajowi chodzi o to, aby się do czegoś przydać. Oba więc osiągają to czego chcą. Wielkość wymaga uniżenia.

Tao jest schronieniem wszystkiego stworzenia. Jest skarbem ludzi zacnych i podporą dla słabych na duchu. Dobrym słowem, można sobie kupić poważanie; Właściwym postępowaniem można podnieść swój status. Jeśli ktoś jest słaby na duchu, czy należy go odtrącać? Dlatego też gdy się kogoś mianuje Synem Niebios, ustanawia ministrów daje im się wpierw nefryt a potem czterokonny zaprzęg; wszystko to jednak nie dorównuje darowi jakim jest Tao. Dlaczego więc dawniej tak ceniono Tao? Czyż nie dlatego, że ten kto szuka, ten dzięki niemu znajduje, a kto czyni źle, ten dzięki niemu unika kary? Dlatego świat je tak ceni.

Czyń wszystko, nie robiąc niczego, staraj się bez wysiłku, znajduj smak w tym, co nie ma smaku. To co wielkie jest małe, a to co małe – wielkie. Krzywdę odwzajemniaj dobrym wychowaniem. Zaplanuj to co trudne, kiedy jeszcze jest łatwe; zajmij się wielką sprawą, kiedy jest jeszcze mała. To co na świecie trudne, jest najpierw łatwe, a to co wielkie, jest najpierw małe. Dlatego też mędrzec nie uważa się za wielkiego, a jednak osiąga wielkość. Przecież mało kto uwierzy komuś, kto bez wahania składa obietnice. To co bardzo proste, jest bardzo trudne. Dlatego też mędrzec utrudnia sobie i dlatego ostatecznie nic nie jest dla niego trudne.

Łatwo zapanować nad czymś, co jest spokojne; łatwo rozważać nad czymś, czego jeszcze nie ma; łatwo stłuc coś, co jest kruche; łatwo rozsypać coś, co jest drobne. Tworzy się coś, zanim to coś zainstnieje; panuje się nad czymś, zanim zapanuje nad tym bałagan. Drzewo tak grube, że jedna osoba nie może go objąć, rodzi się z patyczka cienkiego jak włos; budowę pagody, co ma dziewięć pięter, rozpoczyna się od pustaka; podróż tysiąca mil, zaczyna się od kroku. Kto się za coś bierze, ten przegrywa; kto chce coś utrzymać – traci. Dlatego też mędrzec niczego nie robi, wiec nie przegrywa; niczego nie chce utrzymać, dlatego nic nie traci. Ludzie zazwyczaj coś robią i ciągle przegrywają na finiszu. Przezorni traktują koniec jako początek, a więc nie przegrywają. Dlatego mędrzec pragnie nie pragnąć, nie ceni sobie rzadkich przedmiotów; Uczy się nie uczyć i wraca do tego, co inni omijają. Pozwala naturze biec się jej własnym tokiem i nie śmie działać.

Starożytni znawcy Tao, nie oświecali ludu, lecz go ogłupiali. Trud w rządzeniu ludem, wynika z tego, że lud dużo wie. Jeśli rządząc krajem, wykorzystuje się wiedzę, w kraju panuje nędza; jeśli rządzi się nie stosując wiedzy, w kraju panuje szczęście. Kto zna te zasady, pojął najważniejsze. Kto zna je długo, posiadł tajemną Moc. Tajemna Moc głęboka jest i rozległa, do niej wszystko wraca! Aż w końcu osiąga jedność.

Rzeki i morza rządzą strumykami. Dzięki temu, że się znajdują niżej, mogą rządzić strumykami. Tak też i mędrzec, jeśli chce władać ludem, musi spuścić z tonu; jeśli chce przewodniczyć ludowi, musi podążać za nim. Dlatego też, jeśli mędrzec stanie nad ludem, nie będzie mu ciężarem; jeśli będzie szedł na czele, lud nie ucierpi. Dlatego wszyscy będą się cieszyć i go popierać. Jako że z nikim nie rywalizuje, nikt z nim nie będzie rywalizował.

Wszyscy mówią, że moje Tao jest wielkie i z niczym się go nie da porównać. Ale to właśnie dlatego, że jest wielkie, nie da się go z niczym porównać. Jeśliby się dało go z czymś porównać, dawno by się już stało małe. Trzy rzeczy sobie cenię, skarby, których strzegę: miłość, oszczędność i powstrzymanie się od wyprzedzania innych. Dzięki miłości jestem odważny; dzięki oszczędności mogę się rozwijać; dzięki temu, że powstrzymuje się od wyprzedzania innych, mogę się stać władcą wszystkiego. Jeśli ktoś odrzuca miłość i pragnie odwagi, odrzuca oszczędność i pragnie się rozwijać, brnie naprzód porzuciwszy tyły – dąży ku śmierci! Miłość wszelki bój zwycięży przed wszystkim obroni. Kogo Niebo pragnie uratować, tego ogarnie miłością.

Dobry przywódca nie jest agresywny; dobry wojownik nie popada w gniew; kto radzi sobie z przeciwnikiem, nie lubi swarów; kto umie wykorzystać ludzi, uniża się przed nimi. Oto Moc płynąca z braku rywalizacji, siła wykorzystania ludzi, biegun sięgający nieba.

Żołnierze powiadają: „Nie śmiem wstrzynać wojny, wolę już być do niej wciągnięty; nie śmiem postąpić o krok, wolę się cofnąć o dwa.” Oto co się nazywa formowaniem szeregów, gdy się nie ma wojska; zakasywaniem rękawów, gdy się nie ma ramion; chwytanie za broń, gdy się jej nie posiada, rzucanie się na wroga, gdy on nie istnieje. Nie ma większego nieszczęścia niż zlekceważenie siły wroga; jeśli zlekceważę siły wroga, stracę swoje skarby. Dlatego, gdy już dochodzi do walki, wygrywa strona, która tego żałuje.

Łatwo zrozumieć, co mówię, łatwo też wykonać. Nikt jednak nie rozumie i nie potrafi wykonać. Słowa nie pochodzą ode mnie, a nad czynami nie ja władam. Jeśli ktoś o tym nie wie, nigdy mnie nie zrozumie. Nie wielu potrafi mnie zrozumieć; ze świeczką szukać tych, którzy czynią, jak mówię. Dlatego też mędrcy ubierają się w byle płótno, ale noszą przy sobie klejnot.

Wiedzieć, a myśleć, że się nie wie, to największe osiągnięcie. Nie wiedzieć, a myśleć, że się wie, to jakaś choroba. Mędrcy nie są chorzy; uważają tą chorobę za chorobę. I właśnie dlatego, że uważają tą chorobę za chorobę, nie są chorzy.

Kiedy lud się czuje niezagrożony, zbliża się wielkie niebezpieczeństwo. Nie zmniejszaj jego domostw, nie utrudniaj mu życia. Jeśli nie będziesz go uciskał, on nie będzie ci nieprzychylny. Dlatego mędrcy znają się, ale się nie popisują; troszczą się o siebie, ale się nie pysznią. Dlatego odrzucają tamto, a biorą to.

Kto się odważy na śmiałość – zginie; kto się odważy na nieśmiałość – żyć będzie. Z tych dwóch jedno jest korzyścią, a drugie zgubą. Niebo tym gardzi. Któż wie dlaczego? Trudne jest to także dla mędrców. Niebo nie walczy, a wygrywa; nie mówi, a odpowiadają Mu; nikt go nie woła, a Ono przychodzi; pobłaża, a wszystko idzie według planu. Sieci nieba mają wielkie oka: Niebo jest nieroztropne, a jednak niczego nie gubi.

Jeśli się ludzie nie boją śmierci, to na nic się zda grożenie im śmiercią. Jeśli ludzie się boją śmierci i dopuszczają się przestępstw, złapałbym takich i zabił. Któżby się postawił? Od wieków istnieje Mistrz Kat, który zabija. Zastępować kata w zabijaniu, to jak zastępować rzemieślnika w przycinaniu: można się skaleczyć w palec.

Jeśli lud głoduje, to dlatego że ci na górze nakładają zbyt wielkie podatki. Stąd głód. Jeśli ludem trudno rządzić, to dlatego że ci na górze za wiele robią. Stąd trudno jest rządzić. Jeśli lud nie przejmuje się zbytnio śmiercią, to dlatego że ci na górze żyją zbyt intensywnie. Stąd lud nie przejmuje się zbytnio śmiercią. No, przecież! Kto nie zabiega o życie, więcej ma oleju w głowie niż ten, co je sobie ceni.

Człowiek za życia jest słaby i wiotki, kiedy umrze, staje się twardy i mocny. Rośliny za życia są słabe i miękkie, kiedy umrą, usychają i więdną. Dlatego też kto silny, podąża za śmiercią; kto słaby, podąża za życiem. Silnego żołnierza można pokonać, twarde drewno można przeciąć. Siła znaczy niewiele, słabość – to dopiero coś!

Niebo działa tak jak łuk, który się naciąga! To co wysoko, obniża się; to co nisko, to się wznosi; Jeśli cięciwa jest za długa, to się ją skraca; jeśli jest za krótka, dodaje się. Niebo działa tak: zabiera tam, gdzie jest nadmiar, a dodaje tam, gdzie czegoś brak. Ludzie działają zupełnie inaczej: zabierają tym, którym brakuje, aby się przysłużyć tym, którzy mają nadmiar. Któż potrafi zabrać tam, gdzie jest nadmiar, aby się przysłużyć światu? Tylko ktoś z zasadami. Dlatego mędrcy nie polegają na tym, co robią i nie szczycą się swoim sukcesem: nie pragną pokazać, jacy są wspaniali.

Nie ma na świecie nic, co by było słabsze i miększe niż woda; a jednak żadna siła nie jest w stanie jej pokonać. Nic tego nie zmieni. Słabe pokonuje silne, miękkie pokonuje twarde; wszyscy o tym wiedzą, lecz nikt nie stosuje w życiu. Dlatego mędrcy mówią: „Kto się pozwala mieszać z błotem za cały kraj, ten rządzi ołtarzami ziemi; kto bierze na siebie wszystkie nieszczęścia kraju, ten jest jego władcą.” Prawda zdaje się być czymś zupełnie na odwrót.

Rozwiązywanie sporu, jeszcze większy sprowadza spór. Cóż w tym dobrego? Dlatego mędrcy są zawsze słabszą stroną umowy, i nie ponaglają kontrahentów do jej wykonania. Kto jest w porządku, ten dotrzymuje umowy; kto nie jest w porządku, nalicza odsetki. Niebo nie faworyzuje nikogo, zawsze jest po stronie tych, którzy są dobrzy.

Kraj niech będzie mały i słabo zaludniony; niech posiada narzędzia, ale ich nie używa; niech się strzeże śmierci i nie wyrusza daleko w drogę. Chociaż posiada łodzie i wozy, niechaj nie wsiada na nie; chociaż posiada tarcze i włócznie, niechaj ich nie pokazuje. Niech powróci do wiązania supełków na sznurku. Smaczna będzie jego kuchnia, piękne stroje, spokojne domostwa i radosne obyczaje. A sąsiedzi, choć się nawzajem widują, słyszą nawzajem swoje kury i psy, niech się nie kontaktują ze sobą aż do śmierci.

Słowa wiarygodne nie są piękne, piękne słowa nie są wiarygodne. Człowiek porządny nie dyskutuje, kto dyskutuje nie wiele jest wart. Kto posiadł widzę, ten nie jest mądry, kto jest mądry, ten nic nie wie. Mędrcy niczego nie gromadzą, im więcej służą innym, tym więcej mają, im więcej dają innym, tym więcej dostają. Niebo jest ostre ale nie rani. Mędrcy, kiedy coś robią, nie są nadgorliwi.

Nawet najwspanialsza nauka nie jest mądrością Tao, gdyż nie można go ująć żadną definicją. Nawet najdoskonalsze słowo nie jest tu wystarczające. Tao można bowiem doświadczyć bez użycia słów, rozpoznać bez nazw i definicji. Zrozumienie nienazwanego, oznacza zrozumienie istoty źródła wszechrzeczy.

By podążać ścieżką Tao, należy wyrzec się namiętności. Tylko wówczas bowiem życie będzie pozbawione żalu. I choć potencjał Tao można zrealizować wyłącznie w pojedynkę, pożytek z jego działania odczuwają wszyscy.

Mimo, że nie potrzeba tu słów ani definicji, wielu używa ich, by opisać Tao. Myślą, że w ten sposób mogą lepiej wyjaśnić drogę, którą chcą podążać. Używają słów oraz definicji, by nie mylić ścieżki Tao z innymi ścieżkami, które mogą zostać przez człowieka wybrane.

Dzięki zebranej wiedzy, głębokim przemyśleniom i światłym słowom, rozpoznajemy wszelkie przejawy Tao. Jednakże dopiero porzucając swe intelektualne analizy, możemy doświadczać czystego Tao.

Zarówno zdobyta wiedza, jak i zebrane doświadczenia są prawdziwe, lecz rzeczywistość przyjmuje tak wiele form i kształtów, że na zawsze pozostanie tajemnicą.

Poprzez korzystanie z odpowiednich środków, rozprzestrzeniamy się poza bariery wszelkiej złożoności. I tak oto doświadczamy czystego Tao.

Tak naprawdę, nie możemy poznać prawdziwego Tao, ani dojrzeć jego celu. W swym ograniczonym postrzeganiu, możemy jedynie dostrzec zróżnicowanie, poprzez które Tao objawia się we wszechświecie.

Stąd to, co jest postrzegane jako piękne – jest naprawdę piękne, tylko wówczas, gdy porównać je z tym, co brzydkie. Działanie uznane za sprawne jest przyrównywane do działania postrzeganego jako nieudolne. Człowiek uważa się za bogatego, tylko gdy porówna swój majątek z nędzarzem.

Działanie, które wydaje się trudne, jest takie z powodu rzeczy, które przychodzą łatwo. Coś nazwiemy długim dopiero, gdy porównamy z czymś stosunkowo krótkim. Jedna rzecz jest wysoka, ponieważ inna jest niska. Tylko z powodu dźwięku, znamy ciszę, natomiast przywódca wydaje się przewodzić tylko dlatego, ponieważ inni za nim idą.

Dla porównania: mędrzec żyjący w zgodzie z naukami Tao, nie potrzebuje żadnych porównań. Jeśli już je stosuje wie, że porównywanie jest jednoznaczne z wydawaniem osądu. Tak naprawdę jednak, osąd odnosi się tylko do osoby, która go wygłasza.

Poprzez swoje doświadczenia mędrzec staje się świadomy zmienności wszechrzeczy. Ten bowiem, który przewodzi może, równie dobrze, podążać za przewodnikiem. Mędrzec zatem nie robi nic, kieruje swoimi sprawami nie podejmując działań, swoje nauki przekazuje bez użycia słów.

Dlatego też nie jest wielki ani mały. Wbrew pozorom, nie jest to ani trudne ani łatwe – jeśli wyzbyć się pragnienia. Kończąc swoje zadanie mędrzec zapomina o nim natychmiast. Nie czeka na pochwały, nie szuka zaszczytów, przez co inni mogą go wyśmiać, a nawet potępić. Jego nauki trwają jednak wiecznie, trudno go zatem nie darzyć szacunkiem.

Praca zostaje wykonana, lecz jak – tego nikt nie widzi. Oto prawdziwa siła zaniechania.

Pielęgnując w sobie pokorę, jesteśmy w stanie powstrzymać się od rywalizacji, nawet jeżeli jesteśmy bardziej utalentowani od innych. Bogacz, który nie przechwala się swym majątkiem, nie wodzi innych na pokuszenie, nie tworzy okazji dla złodzieja.

Ten, który zazdrości majątku, bądź talentów posiadanych przez innych, łatwo może zostać opętany przez zawiść.

Dlatego mędrzec jest zadowolony ze swojego stanu posiadania, choćby nawet skromnego. Dzięki temu nie odczuwa potrzeby odbierania innym. Żyjąc w jedności z Tao, pozostaje wolny od zawiści i pragnień. Będąc elastycznym, gromadzi energię, minimalizuje pożądanie i nie uczy się podstępnego działania, ani subtelnych słów pochlebstwa. Poprzez niedziałanie, zapewnia harmonię swemu wnętrzu, pozostaje w zgodzie z samym sobą.

Natomiast władcy są zazwyczaj zaniepokojeni dobrobytem poddanych i nie zachęcają ich do zdobywania zaszczytów, nie zachęcają do rywalizacji o pozycję w społeczeństwie. Zapewniają pewien poziom życia, by zmniejszyć niezadowolenie i utrzymać się przy władzy, jednocześnie zapominając, że to oni powinni służyć poddanym.

Mądrzy władcy nie szukają zaszczytów dla siebie, ani nie działają podstępnie wobec poddanych.

Tao jest jak pustka wewnątrz naczynia. Choćby napełnić naczynie, prędzej czy później zostanie ono opróżnione, zawsze odzyskując stan wewnętrznej pustki. Przepełniony kielich nie utrzyma swej zawartości. Dlatego też mocy Tao nie można wyczerpać, nieustannie stanowi ona źródło pokarmu dla wszelkiego istnienia. Tylko ci, którzy potrafią się nim pożywić, zostaną napełnieni.

Nawet najwspanialsze ostrze straci swą przenikliwość, jeśli będzie hartowane wbrew swej naturze. Nawet najdoskonalszy miecz, przeciwstawiony wodzie traci swą wartość, przeciwstawiony skale zostanie jedynie stępiony. Jeśli rozplączemy zasupłany sznur przy pomocy ostrza, będzie leżał w kawałkach i do niczego nam się już nie przyda.

Tak jak najlepszy płatnerz hartuje doskonały miecz swoim doświadczeniem, tak mędrzec, przy pomocy mądrości, hartuje ducha. Dzięki cierpliwości zasupłany sznur może zostać rozplątany, a problemy, które wydają się nierozwiązywalne, mogą zostać przezwyciężone.

Pod mądrymi rządami wszyscy mogą żyć w harmonii, nie zdając sobie nawet z tego sprawy. Wyzbywając się pragnienia nadmiernego zysku, człowiek jest w stanie zachować świadomość Tao. W taki oto sposób tajemnice Tao mogą zostać odkryte.

Natura, zarówno w Niebie jak i na Ziemi, działa pozbawiona jakichkolwiek intencji i zamiaru, zatem nie może być postrzegana jako łaskawa bądź wroga w żadnej sytuacji.

Pod tym względem Tao jest takie samo, choć w rzeczywistości powinniśmy powiedzieć, że to natura działa zgodnie z zasadami Tao. Zatem, nawet jeśli natura wydaje się działać łaskawie, mędrzec nie działa z takim zamiarem, w istotnych sprawach, pozostaje obojętny. Pozostaje poza dobrem i złem.

Mędrzec zachowuje spokój, nie będąc rozpraszanym zbędnymi słowami ani myślami, a jeszcze mniej wymuszonymi czynami. Jego działania są spontaniczne, skierowane ku ludziom.

W tym znaczeniu jest on pozbawiony pragnień i nigdy nie trwoni on swojej mocy.

Niczym ukryta, żyzna dolina, oczyszczony umysł jest spokojny i zachowuje swoją moc.

Skoro, zarówno energia jak i bezruch, same w sobie nie posiadają kształtu, to nie mogą zostać odnalezione drogą zmysłów, ani zrozumiane drogą intelektu, chociaż w naturze obydwie te drogi prowadzą nas do świata zmysłów i intelektu.

W stanie medytacji, umysł przestaje rozróżniać pojęcia istnienia i nieistnienia. Nie wie, czy sam istnieje. A może wcale go nie ma?

Dusze ludzkie pozostają perfekcyjnie samotne w swej egzystencji, nie rozróżnialne niczym jedność w obrębie medytującego umysłu.

Żyjąc w zgodzie z Tao, świadomość siebie nie jest konieczna. Na drodze Tao samoświadomość istnieje, będąc jednocześnie nieświadomością. Człowiek nie jest rozumiany jako istnienie bądź nieistnienie.

Mędrzec nie próbuje odnaleźć samego siebie, ponieważ wie, że wszystko co może znaleźć, to jedynie manifestacja uczuć i myśli, które same w sobie są niczym.

To dzięki ochronnej powłoce jasnego światła mędrzec pozostaje w jedności ze swoim ja. Wiedząc o tym, nie przywiązuje do tego wagi.

Odosobniony, jest jednak zjednoczony z zewnętrznym światem, czuje spełnienie w bezinteresowności i jest pewien swojej istoty.

Podobno wielkie dobro jest jak woda, podtrzymująca życie bez świadomego wysiłku, płynąca naturalnym prądem, zapewniająca pożywienie, odnajdywana nawet w miejscach odrzucanych przez zachłannego człowieka. Tak właśnie wygląda droga Tao.

Niczym woda, mędrzec pozostaje pokorny, jego umysł płynie w medytacji, nie posiada pragnień, jest głęboki w zamyśleniu, w swych czynach delikatny i taktowny. W mowie szczerość prowadzi mędrca, który jako przywódca po prostu jest kim jest. W rządzeniu, kompetencja jest jego celem, co zapewnia poprawność jego kroków.

Ponieważ nie działa dla własnej korzyści, ani nie tworzy zbędnych konfliktów, jest poprawny w swych czynach w stosunku do wszystkich ludzi.

Łatwiej utrzymać filiżankę, kiedy nie jest przepełniona. Ostrze miecza jest bardziej efektywne, jeśli nie hartowano go ponad miarę.

Łatwiej ochraniać swoje złoto i klejnoty, gdy posiada się je w umiarkowanej ilości. Człowiek, który zabiega o zaszczyty i bogactwo, sam jest swoją zgubą.

Mędrzec pracuje w ciszy, nie poszukując pochwał ani sławy. Wypełnia swoje obowiązki z naturalną łatwością, a potem – gdy wypełni zadanie – wycofuje się. Oto droga i natura Tao.

Jeśli zebrać razem oświecone i nieoświecone dusze, można uczynić je jednością, co byłoby zapewne szlachetnym uczynkiem. Gdy wewnętrzny świat myśli pozostaje w harmonijnej jedności z zewnętrznym światem działań i przedmiotów, człowiek może być istotą nieskazitelną.

Toteż mędrzec unika ich rozdzielania. Oddycha jak śpiące niemowlę. W ten sposób zachowuje harmonię. Poleruje mroczne lustro swojego umysłu, dzięki czemu może ono odbijać obrazy z krystaliczną przejrzystością. Działa bez celu, po prostu kochając ludzi i nie wtrącając się do ich spraw. Jego umysł sięga wszystkich stron świata. Jakże zatem może nie być mędrcem?

Tao daje życie wszelkiemu istnieniu i odżywia je. Daje życie, lecz nie traktuje go jak swoją własność. Jest źródłem wszystkiego, lecz nie chwali się tym faktem. Góruje na wszystkim, lecz nie kontroluje niczego. Oto, tak zwana, Tajemna Wartość Tao.

Mimo, że trzydzieści szprych tworzy koło, to jednak pustka między nimi sprawia, że koło jest użyteczne.

To nie glina czyni dzban użytecznym, lecz przestrzeń w obrębie kształtu, który nazywamy dzbanem.

Bez drzwi, nie można wejść do pokoju, a bez okien panuje w nim ciemność. Są one wycięte w ścianie, lecz to ich wewnętrzna pustka czyni je tak ważnymi.

Istnienie przedmiotów ułatwia nam korzystne przystosowanie się do warunków panujących w świecie. Jednakże to rzeczy, które nie istnieją przynoszą faktyczny pożytek. Oto prawdziwa funkcja pustki.

Dzięki oczom dostrzegamy kolory, lecz zbyt wiele kolorów oślepia nas. Pomimo rozumienia tonów, zbyt wiele dźwięków może nas ogłuszyć. Zbyt intensywny smak psuje podniebienie.

Polując dla sportu, goniąc dziko za przyjemnościami, łatwo możemy doprowadzić swoje umysły do szaleństwa. Kto gromadzi skarby tylko dla siebie, poszukuje rzadkich i cennych przedmiotów, staje się często zachłanny.

Mędrzec zatem zaspokaja potrzeby swego ciała, nie ulegając zmysłowym pokusom. Odrzuca skutek na rzecz przyczyny.

Zaszczyty i hańba wydają się jednakowo budzić lęk. Zarówno szczęście, jak i wielkie nieszczęście, są uważane za dwie strony tej samej monety. Sukces i porażka nie są traktowane w jednakowy sposób, lecz w obliczu śmierci stanowią tylko kolejną lekcję życia.

Cóż to znaczy, że zaszczyty i hańba taki sam budzą lęk? Otóż, przeciętny człowiek osiąga zaszczyty ze strachem w sercu, traci je – zostając zhańbionym – również ze strachem w sercu.

Cóż to znaczy, że szczęście i nieszczęście to dwie strony tej samej monety? Ponieważ fizyczne ciało jest źródłem cierpienia dla ducha. Bez ciała jednak, także szczęście nie miałoby dostępu do człowieka.

Zwyczajny człowiek pragnie być środkiem wszechświata; wszechświat mędrca jest w jego wnętrzu. Mędrzec kocha świat, lecz pozostaje niewzruszony wobec rzeczy, którymi inni się niepokoją. Działa z pokorą w sercu, pozostając nieporuszonym. Dlatego też można mu zaufać w każdej sprawie.

Tao jest tajemnicą. Patrzymy na nie, lecz nie widzimy. Jego światło jest zbyt łagodne. Słuchamy go, lecz nie słyszymy. Jest niesłyszalne. Próbujemy je pochwycić, lecz nie możemy utrzymać w ręku. Jest zbyt delikatne. Z tych też powodów nie można go opisać, dlatego zamiast wielu słów używamy tego jednego: Tao.

Nie ma żadnego kształtu, toteż jego wierzchnia część nie jest oświetlona, a dolna część nie jest pogrążona w cieniu. Nieustające w działaniu, jednak nie może zostać określone. Po zakończonej pracy, powraca do swego naturalnego stanu – nicości. Ludzie określają je mianem Bezkształtnego Kształtu, Cieniem Cienia, Nieuchwytną Chwilą.

Jeśli spotkamy Tao, nie zobaczymy jego twarzy. Jeśli za nim podążymy, nie zobaczymy jego pleców. Istnieje jedynie w chwili obecnej, stosując się wyłącznie do teraźniejszości. Podąża przed siebie we właściwy sposób, sięgając początku, nie kresu. Oto klucz do ścieżki Tao.

Manifestacja Tao w człowieku

Utalentowani mistrzowie z dawnych czasów, będący subtelnie, lecz absolutnie przenikliwi, pojmowali tajemnicę Tao, choć umykała ona ludzkiemu pojmowaniu. Ponieważ mędrcy wykraczali poza ludzkie zrozumienie, mogę jedynie próbować ich opisać.

Zwykle skurczeni, niczym człowiek przeprawiający się przez rzekę w zimie, wyglądali na niezdecydowanych, jakby obawiali się wszystkiego dookoła. Byli uprzejmi, jak gość w domu gospodarza, ustępliwi niczym lód na wiosnę, skromni niczym nieukształtowany jeszcze kawałek drewna, puści niczym dolina, nieciekawi niczym mulista woda.

Kto może oczyścić mętną wodę? Wystarczy pozostawić ją w spokoju, a stopniowo sama się oczyści. Kto może zapewnić rozwój duchowy ludzkości? Wystarczy pozwolić, by społeczny harmider trwał nadal, a uduchowienie ludzi będzie stopniowo rosło.

Ci, którzy zachowywali takie właśnie metody Tao, nie pragnęli spełnienia swoich ambicji. To właśnie dzięki temu mogli zachować wewnętrzny spokój i byli piękni niczym nieoszlifowane diamenty.

Stan pustki powinien być podniesiony do najwyższego poziomu, tak by spokój stał na straży zapału. Wszelkie istnienie przechodzi przez okres wzmożonej aktywności, lecz prędzej czy później powraca do swego pierwotnego stanu. Gdy krzew kwitnie, wydaje nasienie i powraca do korzeni. Oto właśnie prawdziwa stałość. Owa stałość może być dowodem na to, że krzew osiągnął swój właściwy koniec.

Świadectwo tego spełnienia jest niezmienną zasadą. Poznając tę zasadę sięgamy po prawdziwą mądrość, choć może to prowadzić do niekonwencjonalnego zachowania z naszej strony. Znajomość tej zasady prowadzi do wielkiej radości i wyrozumiałości. One z kolei prowadzą do jedności z wszelkim istnieniem. Z jedności wypływa szlachetność charakteru. A kto odznacza się szlachetnym charakterem, jest w stanie osiągnąć oświecenie. Wówczas posiądzie Tao. Posiadając Tao, będzie żył długo, a opuszczając fizyczną formę, nie będzie obawiał się potępienia. Tao go bowiem ochrania.

W dawnych czasach ludzie nie wiedzieli, że ktoś nimi rządzi. W wiekach następnych kochali i wychwalali swoich władców. Jeszcze później bali się ich, aż w końcu zaczęli nimi gardzić. Wiara w mądrość władców podupadła, dlatego przeniesiono ją na społeczeństwo. Kto bowiem nie zasługuje na szacunek, nie będzie nim obdarzony.

Jakże mądrzy byli władcy dawnych czasów, którzy działali bez niepotrzebnych słów. Ich powściągliwość w słowach, pozwalała pozostać w cieniu swego narodu. Powodzenie we wszystkich ich przedsięwzięciach sprawiało, że ludzie mogli mówić: „To wydarzyło się samo z siebie, ponieważ sami sobie jesteśmy władcami”.

Kiedy mądrość Tao zostaje zapomniana, modne stają się hasła życzliwości i sprawiedliwości. Ludzie bowiem łatwo uczą się udawać mądrych i zaradnych. Obłudnie twierdzą, że znają Tao, podczas gdy nie mają o nim pojęcia.

Dopiero, gdy harmonia zanika w rodzinie, rodząc konflikty i kłótnie, pojawia się prawdziwe synowskie oddanie. Zwykle po fakcie. Podobnie, gdy kraj popada w nieporządek, pojawiają się lojalni ministrowie. Zazwyczaj również po fakcie.

Po stokroć lepiej byłoby dla nas, gdybyśmy potrafili przestać się wymądrzać, wręcz odrzucić swoją mądrość. Wyrzekając się swej łaskawości i porzucając prawość, moglibyśmy stać się uczciwi i uprzejmi. Wyrzekając się sztuki podstępu i porzucając działania skierowane na zysk, nie byłoby złodziei i przestępstwa.

Wszystkie te rzeczy pojawiają się, gdy ludzie zapominają o ścieżce Tao. Sprawiają, że starożytne mądrości tracą swą siłę i rzeczywiście są warte jedynie zapomnienia. Lecz proste poglądy i oczywiste prawdy zwykle niszczą egoizm i pomagają unikać nadmiernej żądzy.

Kiedy wyrzekamy się mądrości, niewielka pozostaje różnica pomiędzy wyrażeniem przez kogoś gotowości do pomocy i zwykłym pochlebstwem. Jednakże świadomość tej różnicy pozwoli uniknąć otchłani pustego życia.

To, czego obawiają się wszyscy ludzie jest rzeczywiście przerażające. Lecz jak wszechstronny i nieskończony jest to strach, to już kwestia dyskusyjna. Przewagą mędrca jest to, że nie ma w nim żadnego strachu.

Większość ludzi wygląda na zadowolonych i radosnych, jakby uczestniczyli w pięknej uroczystości lub świętowali nadejście wiosny. Jedynie mędrzec wydaje się obojętny i spokojny, niczym płynąca po niebie chmura. Jest niczym nowonarodzone dziecko, które jeszcze nigdy się nie roześmiało. Wydaje się być przygnębiony i opuszczony, jakby nie miał dokąd pójść.

Większość ludzi posiada wystarczająco dóbr, a nawet więcej niż im potrzeba. Jedynie mędrzec wydaje się biedakiem. Jest głupcem pogrążonym w szaleństwie.

Większość ludzi jest inteligentnych i spostrzegawczych. Jedynie mędrzec wydaje się być pogrążony w niewiedzy. Patrzą na niego pełni pogardy, gdyż jest nudny i wiecznie zakłopotany. Jakby dryfował bez celu po morzu, nigdzie nie znajdując wytchnienia.

Większość ludzi dąży do czegoś w swym życiu. Jedynie mędrzec wydaje się niepotrzebny i niezdarny, jak grubiański sąsiad.

Mędrzec jest zatem zupełnie inny niż większość ludzi, on jeden docenia opiekuńczą moc Tao.

Podążanie za Tao jest najwyższą cnotą. Jak to jednak osiągnąć? Ulotne spojrzenie, nieokreślony dotyk. Wszelkie istnienie ukryte w półmroku. Z pozoru nieosiągalne, jednak w rzeczywistości całkowicie naturalne.

Tao jest nieograniczone, jego istota mroczna i tajemnicza. Nie posiadając kształtu, stanowi istotę prawdy. Dzięki temu możemy – mimo wszystko – odnaleźć jego kształt. Tao jest pradawne, lecz imię jego nie przemija wraz z upływem czasu. Kształtuje wszelkie istnienie i nigdy nie przemija. Poznać jego imię można tylko, jeśli nie będzie próbowało się go poznać.

Skąd to wszystko wiem? Właśnie stąd.

To, co podzielone staje się jednością; nagiąć się oznacza pozostać wyprostowanym; pustka napełnia się; to, co zniszczone odnawia się. Ci, którzy pragną niewiele, mogą wiele zyskać, natomiast ci, którzy pożądają ponad miarę, mogą zostać skrępowani przez swoje majątki.

Mędrzec zatem obejmuje sobą tylko jedną rzecz: pokorę – i naucza jej wszystkich ludzi. Jest nieświadomy samego siebie, dzięki czemu świeci niczym gwiazda. Nie mówi wciąż o sobie, dlatego staje się sławny. Nie poszukując sławy, zdobywa uznanie. Nie wywyższa się, jednak zostaje wywyższony. Dzięki temu, że nie walczy z nikim, jest niepokonany.

Czyżby pusta była starożytna mądrość, że to, co podzielone staje się jednością? Tylko będąc jednością z wszelkim istnieniem można ją w pełni zrozumieć. Dlatego rozważmy te słowa dopiero, gdy osiągniemy ową jedność.

Mówić niewiele jest całkowicie zgodne z naturą człowieka. Gwałtowny wiatr rzadko szaleje przez cały poranek, niespodziewany deszcz rzadko trwa przez cały dzień. Dlaczego tak się dzieje? To dzięki Niebu i Ziemi. Pomyśl, skoro Niebo i Ziemia nie są w stanie sprawić, by wiatr i deszcz trwały długo, to o ile mniej jest w stanie zdziałać człowiek.

Dlatego też ten, który postanawia kroczyć ścieżką Tao nie może być od Tao oddzielony. On i Tao są jednością. Człowiek cnotliwy, nie może być postrzegany oddzielnie od cnoty. On jest cnotą. Natomiast człowiek, który odchodzi od Tao i gubi cnotę, błądzi po bezdrożach i ponosi porażkę. Temu faktowi nie można zaprzeczyć.

A zatem, życie w zgodzie z Tao przynosi szczęście samo w sobie, życie cnotliwe również przynosi szczęście samo w sobie, jednakże ci, którzy akceptują porażkę jako element swojego życia także mogą być szczęśliwi. Wszyscy powinni zaakceptować nieodwołalne – swoją rolę w życiu wszechświata. Temu bowiem, któremu brakuje zaufania, nie można zaufać.

Ten, który stoi na palcach, nie stąpa twardo po ziemi. Podobnie jak ten, który wydłuża krok by przyspieszyć, nie zajdzie daleko. Dlatego też człowiek, który szczyci się swoją mądrością, nie jest oświecony, a ten, który uważa swoje poglądy za najważniejsze, nie zyska sławy, a jedynie złą reputację. Ten natomiast, który będzie się przechwalał, nie znajdzie potwierdzenia swych prawdziwych zalet. Kto jest zarozumiały, nie będzie lepszy od innych.

Takie zachowania – z punktu widzenia Tao – są jak resztki na stole albo rak trawiący ciało. Wszyscy gardzą takimi rzeczami. Nic więc dziwnego, że człowiek podążający ścieżką Tao nie akceptuje i nie pozwala sobie na tego typu zachowanie.

Zanim nastały Niebo i Ziemia, powstało coś, czego nie sposób określić. Coś, co jednoczy wewnętrzne i zewnętrzne światy. Niezależne zarówno od czasu, jak i przestrzeni, pozostaje niezmienne i bezkształtne, odseparowane od reszty istnienia i nie pożądające zmian, lecz docierające wszędzie. Przypływa i odpływa, rozprzestrzeniając się po nieskończoności. Niewyczerpane, dlatego nazywane często Matką Wszechrzeczy.

Nie znamy nazwy tego czegoś, dlatego używamy określenia Tao, bądź Droga albo Naturalna Ścieżka. Nadając imię, jednocześnie poświadczamy jego wspaniałości.

Wspaniałość płynie z nurtem strumienia życia. Płynąc oddala się, sięgając bardzo daleko. Kiedy już sięgnie bardzo daleko, powraca. Dlatego też Tao jest wspaniałe, Niebo jest wspaniałe, Ziemia jest wspaniała, podobnie jak mędrzec. On również jest wspaniały. We wszechświecie są cztery wspaniałe rzeczy. I jedną z nich jest mędrzec.

Ludzie wzorują swoje prawa na prawach Ziemi, czyli natury. Ziemia opiera swoje prawa na prawach Nieba, które pozwala zaistnieć prawom fizyki. Źródłem praw Nieba są zasady Tao. Tao jest zatem uniwersalnym prawem, z którego wypływają wszystkie inne prawa.

Ciężar jest źródłem lekkości, stałość rządzi ruchem.

Dlatego też mędrzec maszerując cały dzień, nie oddala się za bardzo od swych bagaży. Nawet w obliczu wspaniałych perspektyw zysku, pokornie nie rusza się z miejsca, pozostając w bezruchu. Obojętny pokusie, nie zapomina o swoim celu.

Podobnie władca królestwa, mimo swego bogactwa, powinien swym przewodnikiem uczynić prostotę. Nie wolno mu przedkładać własnych interesów ponad interesy poddanych. Jeśli bowiem będzie zachowywał się nieodpowiedzialnie, utraci prawo do sprawowania władzy. Działając zbyt pochopnie może stracić tron.

Doświadczony podróżnik nie pozostawia za sobą tropu. Uzdolniony mówca nie mówi niczego, co mogłoby zostać uznane za błędne – jego słowa są bez skazy. Zręczny księgowy nie musi używać żadnych rejestrów. Solidne drzwi nie potrzebują rygla ani krat, mimo to otwarcie ich jest niemożliwe. Dobre spoiwo wiąże nie potrzebując żadnych sznurów i węzłów, mimo to rozdzielenie tego, co owo spoiwo związało jest niemożliwe.

W taki sam sposób mędrzec zręcznie ratuje ludzi i nie odrzuca nawet tego, który przestanie słuchać mądrych rad. Mędrzec jest bardzo dobry w pomaganiu wszelkiemu istnieniu, dlatego z jego doświadczenia wszyscy mogą czerpać korzyści. Oto co oznacza ukrywanie światła w swej własnej światłości.

A zatem ten, który posiada doświadczenie jest uznawany za mistrza przez tego, kto doświadczenia nie posiada. Ten natomiast, kto nie posiada doświadczenia, jako uczeń, zwiększa reputację swojego nauczyciela. Jeśli uczeń nie będzie szanował mistrza, a mistrz nie będzie radować się z posiadania ucznia, nawet mądrzy ludzie będą mogli odnieść mylne wrażenie. Tak oto wygląda najwyższy stopień wtajemniczenia.

Kto zna swą męską siłę, jest w stanie zachować kobiecą miękkość. Nawet kiedy rzeka płynie wieloma korytami w końcu wpada do morza i nie traci z tego powodu niczego ze swej wspaniałości. Zachowując dziecięcy umysł, można być wolnym od grzechu.

Kto wie, jak biel przyciąga, zawsze pozostaje w cieniu czerni. Naucza pokory swymi czynami, a nauczając jej staje się wzorem postępowania. Trwając w niezmiennej doskonałości, nieskończoność powraca do pierwszego kroku wykonanego przez człowieka.

Kto wie, jak wielkim jest człowiekiem, nigdy nie odrzuca hańby i poniżenia. Nie zamyka się na doświadczenia, zarówno dobre jak i złe, gdyż to one kształtują ludzką istotę. Niezmienna doskonałość jest ostatnim krokiem na drodze rozwoju. Sprowadza bowiem do początku.

Nieukształtowany surowiec, rozdzielony i rozdany, staje się naczyniem. Mędrzec będąc zatrudnionym w rządzie, niechybnie stanie na jego czele, a w swych najwspanialszych aktach prawnych zawrze pokojowe rozwiązania.

Jeżeli ktokolwiek zapragnąłby władzy nad królestwem dla własnych korzyści i rzeczywiście próbowałby osiągnąć ten cel, miejmy nadzieję, że nigdy nie odniesie sukcesu. Królestwo jest bowiem zbyt kruche, by zdobywać je siłą. Ten, kto spróbuje przemocą zdobyć władzę, zniszczy królestwo. Ten, kto spróbuje przemocą utrzymać władzę, szybko ją utraci.

Naturalną rzeczą jest zmiana, czasem maszeruje się na przedzie, czasem daleko z tyłu. Co ogrzane, może zamarznąć. Czasami jest się silnym, czasami słabym. Czasami jest się zdrowym, czasami chorym.

Dlatego mędrzec nie próbuje zmieniać świata na siłę. Wie, że przemoc prowadzi jedynie do przemocy. Czerpie radość z istniejącego stanu rzeczy, unikając nadmiaru i wysiłku potrzebnego do zdobycia tego, co nie jest do niczego potrzebne.

Ten, kto wspomaga władcę zgodnie z naukami Tao, nie będzie próbował potwierdzać swoich wpływów w królestwie przy pomocy potęgi armii. Obranie takiego kierunku działania spotkałoby się z odpowiednią reakcją.

Gdziekolwiek kroczy wielka armia, wyrastają kolczaste krzewy i ciernie. W cieniu starć wielkich armii rodzą się ponure dni. Po wojnie zawsze bowiem następują złe lata.

Wytrawny dowódca wyprowadza decydujące uderzenie i zatrzymuje się. Nie odważyłby się, poprzez kontynuowanie akcji, potwierdzać i chełpić się swoim wojennym mistrzostwem. Będzie atakować wroga, jednocześnie wystrzegając się próżności czy gloryfikowania swych czynów, a w szczególności arogancji w działaniach. Atakuje, ponieważ atak jest czynem koniecznym. Atakuje, lecz nie w celu osiągnięcia biegłości w sztuce walki.

Gdy rzeczy osiągają szczyt swoich możliwości, zaczynają się starzeć. W takim wypadku owe rzeczy nie są zgodne z Tao. A wszystko, co nie jest zgodne z Tao, szybko osiąga kres swojego istnienia.

Wielkie armie, jakkolwiek piękne same w sobie, są jedynie narzędziami nieszczęścia. Są znienawidzone przez wszystkie istoty żyjące. Dlatego też ten, kto poznał ścieżkę Tao, stara się trzymać od nich z daleka.

Człowiek oświecony za zaszczytne zwykle uważa miejsce po swojej lewej stronie, lecz w czasach wojny skłania się ku prawicy. Jednakże ostry miecz jest narzędziem cierpienia, nie jest narzędziem oświeconego człowieka. Używa go tylko w ostateczności. To, co ceni najbardziej to spokój i cisza. Uważa, że zwycięstwo przy użyciu przemocy jest wysoce niepożądane. Człowiek, który uważa inaczej – że przemoc nie jest niepożądana – zwykle znajduje radość w zabijaniu. Ten, z kolei, kto znajduje radość w zabijaniu nie powinien mieć najmniejszego nawet wpływu na losy innych ludzi.

Gdy władca spogląda na lewo, to czas pokoju i okazja do świętowania, gdy natomiast patrzy na prawo, oto nadchodzi czas smutku. Po lewej stronie władcy stoi jego następca i doradca. Po prawicy natomiast zasiadają generałowie. Podsycanie wojny jest jak pogrzeb, gdy bowiem ginie wielu ludzi nastaje czas żałoby. Oto dlaczego nawet zwycięska bitwa powinna być opłakiwana żałobnym lamentem.

Tao jest wieczne i zawsze bezimienne. Chociaż w swej pierwotnej prostocie, niczym nie wyrzeźbiony jeszcze kamień, może wydawać się małe, jego wartość dla każdego człowieka wykracza ponad wszelką miarę. Gdyby feudalny książę lub król mógł strzec je i rozporządzać nim, wszelkie istnienie w naturalny sposób oddałoby mu panowanie nad światem.

Niebo i Ziemia, pod przewodnictwem Tao, jednoczą się i posyłają w dół słodkie krople rosy, które bez udziału człowieka, docierają wszędzie w równym stopniu.

Kiedy Tao zaczyna działać w świecie, można określić je konkretnym imieniem. Kiedy już jednak zostanie nazwane, człowiek wie, kiedy powinien się zatrzymać. Gdy człowiek wie, kiedy się zatrzymać w swoich działaniach, będzie wolny od wszelkiego ryzyka porażki i od podejmowania błędnych decyzji.

Stosunek Tao do całego świata jest podobny do stosunku między wielkimi rzekami i oceanami, a strumieniami w dolinach.

Kto poznaje ludzi jest wnikliwy. Kto poznaje siebie zdobywa prawdziwą mądrość. Kto potrafi pokonać innych jest silny. Kto potrafi pokonać siebie zdobywa prawdziwą potęgę. Kto jest zadowolony ze swojego stanu posiadania jest bogaty. Kto potrafi działać ze zdecydowaniem posiada silną wolę.

Kto nie zawiedzie pokładanych w nim nadziei, długo będzie piastował swoje stanowisko. Kto umrze, lecz nie zostanie zapomniany, osiągnie długowieczność.

Wspaniałe Tao jest wszechobecne! Można je odnaleźć zarówno w lewej ręce, jak i w prawej.

Wszystko w swym rozwoju jest uzależnione od Tao, któremu nic nie jest w stanie się sprzeciwić. Tao działa, zawsze kończąc co zacznie, zawsze zaczynając coś nowego, gdy skończy stare. Tao dba o wszystkie istoty, lecz nie usiłuje nimi zawładnąć. Można je znaleźć w najmniejszych rzeczach. Wszelkie istnienie zatacza krąg, powraca do początku i znika, nie zdając sobie nawet sprawy z tego, że Tao nim kieruje. Można je znaleźć w najwspanialszych rzeczach.

Mędrzec jest zatem zdolny do wypełnienia swych najwspanialszych osiągnięć dokładnie w taki sam sposób. Osiąga wielkość nie starając się jej zdobywać.

Temu, kto trzyma w swych dłoniach Wielki Obraz niewidzialnego Tao, cały świat odwdzięcza się ciągłym odradzaniem się. Ludzie szukają u niego schronienia i nie grozi im doznanie krzywdy. Znajdują u niego odpoczynek, spokój i ulgę w cierpieniu.

Jeśli gospodarz zaoferuje dobrą muzykę i jedzenie, ludzie zatrzymają się u niego na chwilę. Lecz jeśli gospodarz zaoferuje swym gościom mądrość Tao – mimo, że wyda się ona nudna i bez smaku – zatrzyma ich na dłużej, chociaż nie dostrzegą i nie usłyszą Tao. Co więcej, gdy muzyka i jedzenie skończą się, Tao pozostanie. Jest ono bowiem niewyczerpane.

By wziąć głęboki wdech, wpierw należy zrobić wydech. By osłabić cokolwiek, wpierw należy je wzmocnić. By kogoś obalić, wpierw należy go wynieść na piedestał. By kogoś okraść, wpierw należy obdarować go. Oto ścieżka zwana Ukrytym Światłem Działania.

Tak bowiem jest w świecie, że delikatne pokonuje twarde, a słabe zwycięża silne.

Ryby powinny zostać w głębinach stawu, a miecze powinny zostać w swych pochwach.

Tao w naturalny sposób nie podejmuje działania, a mimo to nic, co jest konieczne nie pozostanie niewykonane.

Gdyby ludzie byli w stanie zrozumieć i stosować w życiu mądrość Tao, cały świat mógłby rozwijać się w harmonii z samym sobą.

Gdyby jednak harmonijny rozwój świata stałby się dla mnie obiektem pożądania, poskromiłbym owo pożądanie dzięki niemej prostocie.

Niema prostota jest wolna od narzuconej celowości, dzięki czemu można wyzbyć się pożądania. Wówczas, w ciszy i spokoju, cały świat rozwija się w harmonii z samym sobą.

Ten, kto pielęgnuje w swym wnętrzu cnotę Tao, nie stara się jej pokazać innym. Dlatego właśnie jest mędrcem. Kto wiedziony jest niższymi pobudkami, nieustannie próbuje dowieść swoją wartość. Dlatego właśnie mędrcem nie jest.

Toteż mędrzec nie dokonał niczego i nie odczuwa potrzeby dokonywania czegokolwiek. Ten, kto mędrcem nie jest zawsze podejmuje działanie, gdyż nieustannie odczuwa taką potrzebę.

Mędrzec kieruje się w swej naturze życzliwością, nie pozostawia niczego własnemu losowi. Ten natomiast, kto podstawą swych działań czyni ludzką sprawiedliwość, pozostawia wiele niedokończonych spraw.

Człowiek dobrze wychowany zawsze stara się pokazać swoją przyzwoitość, lecz nie znajdując odpowiedzi na nią u innych, zrobi wszystko, by wymusić uznanie siłą.

W duszy człowieka pozostaje cnota, nawet jeśli zagubi w sobie Tao. Dobro nadal wypełnia duszę, nawet jeśli cnota zostanie zapomniana. Jeśli dobro także gdzieś przepadnie, pozostanie jeszcze sprawiedliwość. W ostateczności, nawet jeśli nie będziemy znali sprawiedliwości, instynktownie kierować się będziemy właściwym szlakiem.

Wiedz jednak, że życie właściwe jest osłabioną formą wesołości i lojalnej wiary. Jest również początkiem nieporządku. Umiejętność szybkiego przewidywania i rozumienia jest kwiatem Tao, jak również początkiem głupoty.

Dlatego też prawdziwy mędrzec trwa w swej stałości i wystrzega się tego, co kruche. Skupia się na owocu, a nie na kwiecie, z którego owoc powstaje. Odrzuca, co pojawia się pierwsze, by móc czerpać z tego, co następuje jako drugie.

W dawnych czasach wszystko było nierozerwalną jednością. Dzięki tej jedności niebo jest jasne i czyste. Dzięki tej jedności ziemia stała się mocna i pewna. Dzięki tej jedności duchy zyskały więcej sił. Dzięki tej jedności doliny kwitły obficie. Dzięki tej jedności wszystkie stworzenia zaczęły żyć. Dzięki tej jedności władcy wszystkich krain świecili przykładem dla swych poddanych.

To wszystko jest skutkiem działania Tao.

Gdyby niebo nie było tak czyste, zostałoby rozdarte. Gdyby ziemia nie była tak pewna, szybko popękałaby i ugięła pod własnym ciężarem. Gdyby duchy nie posiadły mocy, wkrótce przestałyby istnieć. Gdyby doliny nie były tak obfite, zamieniłyby się w pustynie. Gdyby żadne stworzenie nie zaczęłoby żyć, świat byłby pusty. Gdyby władcy nie potrafili rządzić mądrze, mimo całej swej wspaniałości, wszyscy by upadli.

Jak widać szlachetność wyrasta z pospolitości, duma natomiast opiera się na skromności, która jest jej prawdziwym źródłem. Dlatego też władcy nazywają siebie samotnymi, słabymi i nieprzydatnymi. Czyż nie oznacza to, iż wielkość ich nie przysłania im źródeł swej wielkości? Nie w ogólnym obrazie leży bowiem siła, lecz w sprawnym funkcjonowaniu wszystkich elementów całości. Mądrzy władcy nie próbują zatem przyozdabiać się drogocennymi klejnotami. Wystarczy im surowe piękno zwyczajnych kamieni.

Natura jest żywiołem cyklicznym, dokładnie tak jak Tao, koniec staje się początkiem, początek powraca na koniec. Słabość wyznacza kurs potęgi czynów Tao.

Wszystkie rzeczy zrodziły się z bytu; byt z kolei narodzony jest z niebytu.

Światły człowiek, gdy usłyszy o Tao, cierpliwie dąży do jego realizacji poprzez codzienną praktykę. Przeciętny człowiek, usłyszawszy o Tao, zdaje się je rozumieć, lecz nie zawsze potrafi żyć w zgodzie z jego naukami. Głupcy, gdy wysłuchają nauk Tao, kpią z niego i śmieją się do rozpuchu. Jednakże czy Tao byłoby jeszcze sobą, gdyby nie było wyśmiewane?

Dlatego też mędrcy często powtarzają: Tao, choć jest najjaśniejszym światłem, wydaje się być mroczne; człowiek, który czyni postępy w jego praktykowaniu, wydaje się stać w miejscu, a nawet cofać w rozwoju; szlak Tao, choć prosty, wydaje się wyboisty i trudny; najwyższa cnota rodzi się na dnie najgłębszej otchłani; najwspanialsze piękno zdaje się tak odrażające, że rani oczy; najbogatszy człowiek to ten, który zdaje się nie mieć niczego, a nawet największa moc wydaje się niewielka, słaba; niezachwiana mądrość Tao, wydaje się nietrwała, zmienna niczym chorągiew na wietrze; przestrzeń doskonała nie posiada granic; naczynie doskonałe jest wyrabiane bardzo powoli; dźwięk doskonały jest ledwie słyszalny, jest prawie ciszą; doskonałe dzieło sztuki natomiast jest swoim własnym cieniem i nie posiada ukrytego znaczenia.

Tao jest dobrze ukryte i nie posiada imienia, nie można go poznać. Niemniej tylko Tao jest zdolne wspomóc człowieka i doprowadzić go do doskonałości.

Tao istnieje, mimo że się nigdy nie narodziło. Istniejąc dało początek pierwszemu wrażeniu. Pierwsze wrażenie zrodziło wspomnienie, a z niego natomiast powstała pierwsza myśl. Dzięki myślom istnieje cały nieskończony wszechświat. Materia, która narodziła się we wszechświecie, pozostawiła za sobą mrok i skierowała się ku światłu, z którego będzie mogła się na nowo odrodzić w nowej formie. Harmonię przemian zachować można dzięki nicości, która jest jej oddechem.

Nikt nie chce być samotny, nie chce być postrzegany przez innych jako bezwartościowy i niepotrzebny. Jednak mądry przywódca właśnie w taki sposób opisuje siebie, ponieważ wie, że pewne zwycięstwa osiągnąć można tylko przez przegraną, natomiast przegrywa się często przez dążenie do zbyt wielkiego zwycięstwa.

Uczę tylko tego, czego i inni uczą. Gwałtowny i silny człowiek nie umiera zwykle z przyczyn naturalnych. Oto podstawa mego nauczania.

Miękkość wody, gdy uderzy, zwycięży bez trudu twardość kamienia. Niebyt równie łatwo wpełza tam, gdzie nie ma najmniejszych nawet szczelin. Stąd właśnie znam zalety nie podejmowania żadnego działania.

Niewielu potrafi nauczać bez użycia słów, nieliczni potrafią korzystać z zalet niedziałania.

Sława czy życie – które z nich jest wam droższe? Życie czy bogactwo – które z nich wybierzecie? Skup się na życiu i zapomnij o innych rzeczach. Skup się na nich, a stracisz życie. Które z wymienionych wyżej przynosi większy smutek i ból?

Stąd widzimy, że człowiek pragnący sławy odrzuca to, co najwspanialsze. Kto kocha bogactwo odrzuca prawdziwy skarb.

Kto osiągnął spełnienie nie obawia się wstydu. Kto wie, kiedy się zatrzymać nie poniesie klęski. Wolny od niebezpieczeństw, długo będzie żył.

Kto, z perspektywy czasu, uważa swoje największe osiągnięcia za liche, znajdzie wielką siłę w sobie, która starczy mu na bardzo długo. To, co kiedyś wydawało się pełne, może później wydać się puste, jednak nadal będzie niewyczerpane. To, co kiedyś wydawało się proste, może wydać się pokręcone, gdy przyjrzeć się jeszcze raz. Mądrość może sprawiać wrażenie głupoty, a elokwencja niezdarnego bełkotu.

Nieprzerwany ruch może pokonywać chłód, a stałość zwyciężać gorąco. Czystość i stałość są źródłem słusznych praw dla wszelkiego istnienia.

Gdy dostrzegamy naturalną drogę Tao, nagle okazuje się, że wszystkie rzeczy służą swoim celom. Konie, na przykład, ciągną powozy i pługi. Gdy natomiast nie dostrzegamy naturalnej drogi Tao, konie są hodowane do walki na wojnie. Nie ma większego nieszczęścia niż brak ograniczenia niezdrowej ambicji, klęski większej niż rozczarowanie swoimi osiągnięciami, winy większej niż chciwość wypełniająca serce. Dlatego prawdziwa radość powinna być trwała i niezmienna. Tylko wówczas człowiek otrzymuje to, czego potrzebuje.

Nawet bez wychodzenia z domu mędrzec jest w stanie rozumieć świat. Bez wyglądania przez okno może dostrzec drogę Niebios. Im dalej bowiem patrzy, tym większym jest ślepcem.

Dlatego też prawdziwy mędrzec zdobywa wiedzę bez podróżowania, określa istotę wszystkich rzeczy bez patrzenia na nie, bez wysiłku realizuje swoje cele, nie zabiegając zbytnio o ich realizację.

Kto poświęca czas na naukę, każdego dnia coś zyskuje. Kto poświęca czas na Tao, każdego dnia może czynić coraz mniej, aż w końcu nie będzie czynił zupełnie niczego. Gdy dojdzie się do punktu całkowitego niedziałania, nie pozostaje nic co nie zostałoby zrobione.

Prawo natury rządzi poprzez pozwolenie rzeczom obierania ich własnego kursu, nie wymaga od nikogo, by walczył o zdobywanie świata. Pozwala istnieć bez wysiłku, zdobywać bez zdobywania.

Mędrzec nie wypełnia swego umysłu pragnieniami, lecz skupia się na potrzebach innych ludzi. Dla dobrych, jest dobry. Dla niedobrych, również jest dobry. I w ten sposób wszyscy otrzymują dar dobra. Wobec ludzi szczerych, mędrzec jest szczery. Wobec nieszczerych, również jest szczery. I w ten sposób wszyscy mogą poznać czym jest szczerość.

Mędrzec jest często postrzegany przez innych jako osoba niezdecydowana, utrzymująca swój umysł w obojętności. Ludzie kierują swoje oczy i uszy w jego stronę, a on traktuje ich, jakby byli jego dziećmi.

Ludzie umierają, by móc narodzić się ponownie. Pojawiają się na świecie, by umrzeć.

Na przestrzeni lat pomiędzy narodzinami, a śmiercią okazuje się, że na każdych dziesięciu ludzi trzech podąża za życiem, a trzech za śmiercią. Na tę dziesiątkę przypada również trzech, którzy usiłują stać po stronie życia, lecz których działania kierują się ku śmierci. Ich działania cechuje zbyt mocne usiłowanie zatrzymania życia, co prowadzi zwykle do zupełnie odwrotnych rezultatów.

Podobno człowiek, który umiejętnie potrafi kierować swym życiem, może bez obaw wyruszyć w podróż i nie musi wystrzegać się nosorożców ani tygrysów, w obliczu ludzi nie potrzebuje zbroi ani ostrego miecza. Nosorożec nie znajdzie bowiem żadnego miejsca, które mógłby przeszyć swym rogiem, a tygrys nie znajdzie żadnego miejsca, w które mógłby wbić pazury, żaden miecz nie dosięgnie swego celu. To dlatego, ponieważ taki człowiek nie ma w swej duszy miejsca dla śmierci.

Wszystkie istniejące na świecie rzeczy rodzą się z podstawowej reguły Tao i są odżywiane przez jej nieustanne działanie. Wszystkie rzeczy są kształtowane zgodnie ze swoją naturą, ich przeznaczenie dokonuje się poprzez osiągniętą formę. Dlatego też wszystkie rzeczy, bez wyjątku, darzą Tao szacunkiem i błogosławią jego działania.

Szacunek dla Tao oraz jego działań nie jest rezultatem żadnego skoordynowanego aktu wiary, lecz zwyczajnego, spontanicznego hołdu.

Pamiętajmy zatem, że to Tao stwarza wszystkie rzeczy, to Tao odżywia je, kieruje ich rozwojem, opiekuje się nimi, dopełnia je, pozwala im dojrzeć, podtrzymuje je i pomnaża. Tao tworzy wszystkie rzeczy, lecz nie próbuje ich posiadać. Tao prowadzi przez życie, lecz nie chełpi się swoją mocą. Pozwala rozwijać się, lecz nie próbuje kontrolować. Oto czym jest tajemne działanie.

Tao będące źródłem wszelkiego istnienia, jest często nazywane Matką Wszechrzeczy.

Poznając matkę, można również poznać jej dzieci. Kiedy człowiek poznaje źródło swego pochodzenia, strzeże go za wszelką cenę. Wówczas, przez całe życie będzie wolny od niebezpieczeństwa.

Pozwólmy mu milczeć, pozwólmy nawet nie oddychać, a nie będzie musiał trudzić się przez całe swoje życie. Jeśli człowiek będzie mówić bez potrzeby czy tracić dech w pogoni za karierą, nigdy nie uchroni się przed niebezpieczeństwem.

Umiejętność dostrzegania rzeczy małych, to sekret mądrego rozumowania. Obrona tego, co delikatne i miękkie, to sekret prawdziwej siły.

Kto prawidłowo korzysta ze swej mądrości, bez problemu powróci do źródła swej istoty. Uwolni się z nieszczęsnej klatki swego ciała i nigdy nie zazna krzywdy.

Gdybym nagle stał się sławny i został wyniesiony na ważne stanowisko, najważniejszą dla mnie troską byłoby pozostać w zgodzie ze wspaniałym Tao.

Wspaniałe Tao, podobnie jak droga, jest gładkie i proste, lecz ludzie lubią wędrować bocznymi ścieżkami.

Ich budynki i dziedzińce są dobrze utrzymane, lecz pola zarastają chwastami, a spichlerze świecą pustkami. Ubierają się w eleganckie i bogato zdobione szaty, przy pasie nosząc ostre miecze. Pobłażają sobie w jedzeniu i piciu, nie znając umiaru. Ich bogactwo wykracza poza wszelkie marzenia. Książęta tego rodzaju mogą być uważani za złodziei i pyszałków.

Taki sposób życia stoi z pewnością w sprzeczności z Tao.

Roślina, której korzenie są mocne, nie zostanie łatwo wyrwana z ziemi. Podobnie jak człowiek, którego mocno pochwycono, nie wyślizgnie się łatwo. Dlatego też człowiek powinien oddawać cześć swoim przodkom.

Pielęgnując Tao w swym wnętrzu, człowiek osiąga prawdziwą moc. Kierując się zasadami Tao w rodzinie, jej zamożność będzie rosła. Utrzymując Tao w swym mieście, doprowadzi się do jego rozkwitu. Znajdując Tao w narodzie, stworzy się szczęśliwy kraj. Wypełniając mądrością Tao cały świat, doprowadzi się do wypełnienia wszystkich ludzi cnotą. W taki oto sposób efekt działania Tao można dostrzec w pojedynczym człowieku, obserwując go w różnych sytuacjach. Podobnie w rodzinie, w mieście, w narodzie i w świecie. Człowiek jest bowiem miniaturowym odzwierciedleniem rodziny. Rodzina jest miniaturowym odzwierciedleniem miasta. Miasto jest miniaturowym odzwierciedleniem kraju. Kraj jest miniaturowym odzwierciedleniem całego świata.

Skąd wiem, że jest właśnie tak, jak to opisałem? Dzięki obserwacji.

Człowiek, którego duszę wypełnia cnota jest podobny do nowonarodzonego dziecka. Jadowite owady nie będą go żądlić, nie pochwycą go dzikie bestie, nie będą atakowały drapieżne ptaki.

Kości nowonarodzonego dziecka są delikatne, a jego mięśnie miękkie, lecz mimo to chwyt ma mocny. Może i nie pojmuje jeszcze stosunków łączących mężczyzny z kobietą, lecz jego narządy mogą być pobudzone, ukazując doskonałość istoty ludzkiej. Może krzyczeć przez cały dzień, a jego gardło nie chrypnie i nie wysycha – oto naturalna harmonia.

Tym, którzy pielęgnują ową harmonię, objawia się sekret niezmiennego Tao, a z posiadanej wiedzy wyrasta prawdziwa mądrość.

Zbytni pośpiech w życiu jedynie szkodzi, lecz zatrzymanie się całkowite również do niczego nie prowadzi. W obu przypadkach człowiek zyskuje wyłącznie fałszywą siłę, nad którą można jedynie płakać.

Wszystkie istoty osiągają dojrzałość, a następnie starzeją się, co wydaje się być sprzeczne z Tao. Wiadomo bowiem, że co sprzeczne z Tao, szybko umiera.

Ci, którzy znają Tao, nie muszą o nim mówić. Ci, którzy lubią o Tao często opowiadać, zwykle nie mają o nim pojęcia. Mędrzec zatem mówi niewiele, jeśli w ogóle cokolwiek i wycisza zmysły. Zawsze stara się stępić, co ostre, dzięki czemu zamienia złożoność w prostotę. Ukrywając swój geniusz wydaje się być głupcem, dzięki czemu nie wyróżnia się zbytnio wśród ludzkiej ciemnoty. Oto czym jest tajemna jedność.

Taki człowiek, jak opisany powyżej nie może być traktowany ani jako członek rodziny, ani jako zupełnie obcy. Nie zaprząta sobie głowy zyskiem i stratą, ani hojnością czy skąpstwem. On jest bowiem najzacniejszym ze wszystkich ludzi.

Kraj powinien być rządzony przy pomocy sprawiedliwych środków, natomiast wojna powinna być prowadzona z nieuchwytną przebiegłością. Jednak prawdziwą władzę w państwie można zdobyć tylko poprzez zaprzestanie działań i wyzbycie się celowości.

Skąd o tym wiem? Z powodu tych kilku faktów: im więcej w państwie zakazów – tym biedniejsi są ludzie, im więcej środków przynoszących zyski – tym większy panuje chaos, im więcej w ludzkim działaniu znajdziemy podstępu – tym dziwniejsze dzieją się rzeczy, im więcej ogłasza się praw – tym więcej pojawia się złodziei i przestępców.

Dlatego też mędrzec twierdzi, że nic nie będzie robił, a ludzie sami powrócą do swego naturalnego stanu. Twierdzi, że będzie pielęgnował w sobie ciszę, a ludzie sami naprawią swoje błędy. Twierdzi, że nie będzie sprawiał nikomu kłopotów, a ludzie sami staną się bogaci. Twierdzi, że nie będzie przejawiał żadnych ambicji, a ludzie sami osiągną pierwotną prostotę.

Gdy ręka władcy jest lekka, ludzie są uprzejmi i szczerzy, jeżeli jednak kraj jest rządzony zbyt brutalnie, ludzie stają się rozczarowani i niezadowoleni.

Szczęście podąża za cierpieniem, które z kolei czai się w cieniu szczęścia. Któż mógłby wiedzieć, jak potoczą się losy świata? Może nie będzie on miał końca?

Czy powinniśmy zatem poprawiać innych? Próba naprostowania czegoś wiąże się z tego czegoś nagięciem. Rezultatem dobrego uczynku mogą być złe konsekwencje. Dobro zatem może przekształcić się w zło. Tak to już wygląda od bardzo dawna.

Dlatego też mędrzec nie rani nikogo swoimi czynami, choć są one ostre niczym miecz; nikomu nie zadaje bólu, choć jego szczerość trafia zawsze w samo sedno; jest zawsze taktowny, choć bezpośredni w wymowie; oświecony, choć nigdy nie oślepia blaskiem patrzących nań ludzi.

Nic tak nie wspomaga dobrych rządów i właściwej służby bogom, jak skromność. To właśnie dzięki skromności człowiek jest w stanie utrzymać harmonię w swej duszy. Owa harmonia przejawia się w ciągłym powrocie do naturalnych mądrości Tao. Dzięki wciąż powtarzającej się akumulacji cech Tao w człowieku możemy bez trudu pokonywać wszelkie stające nam na drodze przeszkody. Dzięki pokonywaniu przeszkód zyskujemy siłę, by przekraczać wszelkie granice. A gdy będziemy zdolni wykraczać poza swoje ograniczenia, będziemy mogli władać każdym królestwem.

Panując mądrze, władca zdobywa serca swoich poddanych, dzięki czemu jego wpływ będzie długotrwały. Jego korzenie wrosną głęboko w ziemię, a owoce jego działań będą solidne. Oto droga dalekowzroczności i długiego życia.

Rządzenie wielkim królestwem jest jak smażenie małych ryb. Pozwól, by królestwo było rządzone zgodnie z mądrością Tao, a wewnętrzne demony ludzi nie będą miały wstępu na ich terytorium. Oczywiście demony nie znikną całkowicie, nie stracą nawet swej siły, lecz nie będą mogły skrzywdzić żadnego człowieka. Nie tylko zresztą demony nie będą mogły szkodzić ludziom, ale również rządzący nimi mędrzec.

Ponieważ mędrcy i demony nie zadają sobie wzajemnie ran, ich siła może zjednoczyć się i przekształcić w moc Tao.

Gdy królestwo posiądzie wielką siłę i rozległe wpływy, staje się wspaniałe niczym ocean – wszystkie rzeki i strumienie kierują się ku niemu.

Można to zilustrować także w inny sposób. Otóż kobieta, dzięki swej stałości i uległości zawsze zwycięża nad mężczyzną.

Stałość i uległość może być postrzegana jako poddaństwo, lecz w rzeczywistości wielkie królestwo ustępując mniejszym królestwom, zyskuje je dla siebie, podbija bez walki. Natomiast małe królestwo, które ulegnie wielkiemu królestwu stanie się jego częścią, a zatem samo będzie wielkim królestwem. Jedno królestwo uległością zdobywa, drugie pozwala się zdobyć.

Wielkiemu królestwu nie chodzi o nic więcej, jak zjednoczenie ludzi i otoczenie ich właściwą opieką. Małemu królestwu nie chodzi o nic innego, jak o akceptację i uzyskanie właściwej opieki. Oba królestwa dostają to, czego pragną. Wielkie królestwo powinno jednak pamiętać, by się nie wywyższać.

Tao jest osią wszelkiego istnienia. Jest bezcennym skarbem dla dobrych ludzi i schronieniem dla ludzi złych.

Piękne słowa mogą przynieść zaszczyty wypowiadającej je osobie, jednakże dzięki naturalnej dobroci można osiągnąć znacznie więcej.

Dlaczego Tao chroni nawet złych ludzi? Ponieważ nikt nie powinien być porzucony tylko dlatego, że błądzi w ciemności swego umysłu. Oto powód istnienia władców i ich doradców. Najlepszymi bowiem darami nie są klejnoty czy piękne konie, lecz spokój pozwalający sięgnąć mądrość Tao.

Powodem, dla którego starożytni cenili sobie Tao, jest możliwość szybkiego osiągnięcia swoich celów i wyzbycie się wad charakteru. Oto dlaczego znaczenie Tao jest tak wielkie dla całego świata.

Należy działać bez podejmowania działań, praktykować bez odbywania praktyki. Należy umieć wyczuć smak tego, co nie posiada smaku oraz małe rzeczy traktować jakby były wielkimi. Na nienawiść należy odpowiadać dobrocią.

Kontempluj pojawiające się trudności, nawet gdy wszystko przychodzi ci z łatwością. Kieruj wielkimi rzeczami kiedy są jeszcze małe.

Całkowicie naturalnym jest fakt, że nawet najtrudniejsze rzeczy można wykonać z łatwością, jeśli wybierze się odpowiedni czas, a wielkie działania powstają z mniejszych uczynków.

Dlatego też mędrzec unika wielkich rzeczy, dzięki czemu sam osiąga wielkość. Zbyt pochopnie złożone obietnice łatwo można złamać, toteż podkopują one zaufanie.

Przedsięwzięcia, które wydają się łatwe, zwykle sprawiają masę problemów. Z tego też powodu mędrzec każdą rzecz w życiu traktuje jak trudne zadanie. Dzięki temu nie ma żadnych problemów.

Co pozostaje w spoczynku, łatwo utrzymać w ryzach. Łatwo zapobiec temu, co jeszcze się nie pojawiło. To, co słabe, z łatwością może zostać złamane. To, co nieliczne bez problemu można rozproszyć.

Rozważ problem, zanim ten się pojawi. Zarządzaj, zanim brak kierownictwa sprowadzi bałagan. Wielkie drzewo, wyrasta z maleńkiego pędu. Nawet najwyższa wieża została zbudowana przy pomocy maleńkich cegieł. Nawet najdłuższa podróż rozpoczyna się od jednego kroku.

Kto próbuje ulepszać coś na siłę, zwykle to niszczy. Jeśli próbuje siłą pochwycić, traci bezpowrotnie.

Mędrzec zatem nie usiłuje kształtować niczego według własnej woli, dlatego niczego nigdy nie zniszczy. Mędrzec nie próbuje niczego pochwycić, dzięki czemu niczego nigdy nie straci. Natomiast ludzie w swej gonitwie za sukcesem bardzo często ponoszą porażkę tuż przed realizacją swoich zamierzeń.

Człowiek powinien być tak samo ostrożny na końcu, jak był na początku, jeśli chce osiągnąć sukces.

Dlatego też pragnieniem mędrca jest nie pragnąć niczego, nie ceni on rzeczy trudnych do zdobycia.

Uczy się jak być nieukiem, zwraca się w stronę tego, co inni ludzie ignorują. W ten oto sposób pomaga wszystkim napotkanym stworzeniom w ich naturalnym rozwoju, lecz wystrzega się ingerowania w ich decyzje.

W dawnych czasach praktykujący nauki Tao nie starali się oświecać innych. Dbali raczej o to, by ludzie byli prostolinijni.

Cała trudność w rządzeniu ludźmi wynika z tego, że są oni istotami inteligentnymi. Panowanie nad krajem w podstępny sposób przynosi jedynie cierpienie. Błogosławiony kto rządzi krajem przy pomocy skromności i dobroci. Kto pamięta o tych prostych zasadach, będzie idealnym władcą. Świadomość swojej doskonałości to głęboko ukryta cnota.

W odróżnieniu od cnoty zwykłych ludzi, prawdziwa cnota jest zaiste ukryta bardzo głęboko i daleko sięgają jej wpływy. Tylko ten sposób może prowadzić do absolutnej harmonii.

Strumienie i oceany są zwane władcami dolin, a to dlatego, że płyną ich dnem. To rzeka stwarza dolinę siłą swego pędu. Dlatego też mędrzec pragnący wznieść się ponad ludzkość, musi w swych słowach i czynach stawiać się poniżej innych. Musi trzymać się na uboczu.

Mędrzec przewodzi ludziom, jednakże oni nie odczuwają w związku z tym żadnego ciężaru. Gdy bowiem władca jest mędrcem jego poddani nie doznają krzywdy. Dlatego cały świat może z radością wspierać go, nigdy nie będąc wyczerpanym.

Ponieważ mędrzec nigdy z nikim nie walczy, nikt nie może go zwyciężyć.

Wszyscy zgodnie twierdzą, że Tao jest wspaniałe. Według mnie nie ma w nim nic niezwykłego. Twierdzę tak, ponieważ wspaniałość Tao jest czymś całkowicie naturalnym. Jak szybko i jak nisko upadłby człowiek, gdyby próbował na siłę osiągnąć wspaniałość?

Tao zawiera w sobie trzy cenne skarby, których zawsze będzie strzegło. Pierwszy zwany jest współczuciem. Drugi to umiar. Trzecim natomiast jest pokora.

Tylko człowiek, który potrafi współczuć może być prawdziwie odważny. Tylko człowiek, który potrafi zachować umiar, może być prawdziwie szczodry. Tylko człowiek, który potrafi pochylić głowę w pokorze, może być dobrym władcą.

Gdyby człowiek był odważny – lecz nie znałby współczucia, gdyby człowiek był szczodry – lecz nie znałby umiaru, gdyby człowiek był władcą królestwa – lecz nie znałby pokory, jego dni byłyby policzone.

Jeśli natomiast człowiek zna prawdziwe współczucie, zawsze będzie zwyciężał w bitwie, pokonując każdego wroga. Jeśli użyje współczucia w obronie, zawsze odeprze atak. Niebiosa chronią swych wybrańców przy użyciu współczucia.

Kto jest doskonałym wojownikiem, nie jest z natury wojowniczy. Najlepiej walczy ten, kogo nie przepełnia gniew. Najwspanialszy zdobywca nie jest najeźdźcą. Kto chce być dobrym pracodawcą, sam stosuje się do własnych wymagań stawianych pracownikom.

Oto prawdziwa cnota niesprzeciwiania się. Oto sekret pozwalający odkrywać i korzystać z umiejętności innych ludzi. Oto sposób na działanie zgodne z prawami niebios. Już w starożytnych czasach takie postępowanie było uznawane za największą zaletę.

Pewien ekspert w dziedzinie wojskowości powiedział: „Nie ważę się występować naprzód jak gospodarz, wolę zawsze zachowywać się jak gość. Waham się posunąć do przodu choćby o cal, lecz jestem gotów w każdej chwili cofnąć się o stopę”.

Oto dążenie do przodu bez wykonywania jakiegokolwiek ruchu, oto zwyciężanie bitwy bez użycia broni, oto nacieranie na wroga bez wrogości, oto sposób na pochwycenie przeciwnika bez uścisku.

Nie ma większego błędu niż niedocenianie przeciwnika. Jeśli nie będziemy doceniać swoich przeciwników, z pewnością przegramy i stracimy wszystko.

Dlatego też, gdy na przeciw siebie staną dwie armie o podobnej sile, zwycięży ta strona, której przywódca będzie świadomy słabych punktów swojej armii.

Chociaż zrozumienie moich słów nie powinno przysparzać trudności, podobnie zresztą jak praktykowanie zawartej w nich mądrości – nikt na świecie zdaje się mnie nie rozumieć i nie podążać za moim przykładem.

Słowa wypływają z idei, wydarzenia następują jako skutek pewnej konkretnej przyczyny. Mimo tego, często nie są rozumiane. Dlatego też i ja nie jestem rozumiany.

Naprawdę niewielu jest takich, którzy mnie rozumieją. To właśnie dzięki temu widać, jak jestem wybitny. To normalne, że mędrzec przyodziewa się w skromne szaty i ukrywa swoje prawdziwe bogactwo. Swój najcenniejszy klejnot nosi bowiem w sercu.

Prawdziwą siłą ducha jest wiedza nieświadoma, natomiast świadome ignorowanie mądrości jest oznaką słabości.

Jedynie przez zaakceptowanie choroby można wyzdrowieć.

Wówczas słabość zwalcza się siłą.

Mędrzec jest mądry, ponieważ zaakceptował swoją ignorancję, pozwolił zadomowić się jej w umyśle i przeminąć naturalnym biegiem rzeczy.

Kiedy ludzie nie obawiają się rzeczy, których obawiać się powinni, można być pewnym nadejścia tych rzeczy.

Nie pozwól takim ludziom ograniczać własnej swobody, nie gódź się, by wiedli puste życie. Pozostawieni samym sobie nigdy nie zaznają spokoju.

Dlatego też mędrzec szanuje siebie mimo, że nie rozumie swojej istoty. Ceni siebie, lecz nie przecenia. Dlatego odrzuca pochlebstwo, wybierając szczerą pochwałę.

Zuchwała odwaga prowadzi do śmierci. Odwaga zmieszana z ostrożnością prowadzi do życia. Obie te rzeczy, odwaga i ostrożność, są czasem korzystne, a czasami szkodliwe.

Pewne rzeczy są odrzucane przez Niebiosa. Któż może wiedzieć dlaczego? Nawet mędrzec ma czasem problem z odpowiedzią na to pytanie.

Siła Niebios przejawia się w tym, że nie atakuje, ale podbija. Niebiosa nie odpowiadają przy użyciu słów, lecz ich odpowiedzi są zawsze prawidłowe. Niebiosa nie wzywają do siebie, lecz wszystko dąży do nich, ponieważ są cierpliwe i przepełnione mocą.

Niebiosa zarzucają swą sieć głęboko i szeroko. Sieć owa mimo, że składa się z dużych oczek, niczego nie przepuszcza.

Jeśli ludzie nie boją się śmierci, jak można ich przestraszyć groźbą śmierci? Jeśli nauczyć ludzi strachu przed śmiercią, wówczas każdego przestępcę można pochwycić i przeprowadzić na nim egzekucję. Kto w takich warunkach odważy się łamać prawo?

Zawsze musi znaleźć się ktoś, kto wykona egzekucję. Jednakże roli kata nie może odegrać każdy. Kat bowiem jest takim samym rzemieślnikiem jak stolarz. Jego fach wymaga odpowiednich umiejętności. Człowiek nie znający się na rzemiośle, które próbuje wykonywać z całą pewnością sam się zrani.

Zatem nie próbujmy ingerować w naturalny porządek rzeczy.

Gdy podatki są zbyt wysokie, ludzie zaczynają głodować. Władcy bowiem zabierają dla siebie zbyt wiele. Ludźmi nie jest łatwo rządzić, gdy władcy zaczynają zbytnio ingerować w życie swych poddanych. Ludzie nie przykładają zbytniej wagi do śmierci, gdy zaczynają się zbytnio koncentrować na zdobywaniu dostatku.

Tylko ten, kto nie koncentruje się na wartości swojego życia, może je w pełni docenić.

Człowiek rodzi się delikatny i miękki. W chwili śmierci jego ciało jest sztywne i twarde.

Tak samo jest ze wszystkim, z trawą dla przykładu i drzewami, które w okresie wzrostu są wrażliwe i delikatne, a gdy umierają są twarde i suche.

A zatem twardość i sztywność należą do domeny śmierci, podczas gdy delikatność i miękkość towarzyszą życiu. Dlatego wojownik, który chce być niepokonany nigdy nie będzie atakował. Drzewo, które nie chce się złamać musi naginać się stosownie do podmuchów wiatru.

Dlatego w hierarchii bytu to, co twarde i silne stawiamy niżej od tego, co delikatne i słabe.

Tao można by dobrze zobrazować przy pomocy rysunku łuku. Tao jest bowiem jak łuk: wysokie opada, a niskie powstaje ku górze. Odbiera tym, którzy mają dużo, by oddać tym, którzy są w potrzebie.

Oto droga Niebios. Umniejsza, co rozrosło się nadmiernie, powiększa, co jest zbyt małe.

Niestety droga przeciętnego człowieka wygląda inaczej. Ludzie mają zwyczaj zabierania biednym i dawania bogatym. Gdzie znajdziemy człowieka, który dzięki swemu bogactwu, potrafi służyć światu? Zapewne wśród tych, którzy swój majątek noszą w sercu.

Mędrzec nie pragnie nagród za swe czyny, dzięki czemu są one podwójnie wartościowe. Mimo tego mędrzec nie przywiązuje się do swoich dokonań i nie próbuje udowodnić innym jaki jest wspaniały.

Nie ma nic bardziej delikatnego i słabego od wody, jednakże działając przeciw temu co stałe i silne, jej płynna delikatność, czyni ją niezwyciężoną. Nic bowiem nie może zmienić na stałe natury wody.

Powszechnie wiadomo, że delikatność pokonuje twardość, słabość zwycięża siłę. Niestety niewielu jest zdolnych zastosować tę wiedzę w swoim życiu.

Dlatego właśnie mędrzec zawsze powtarza: „Ten, który potrafi przyjąć na swe barki hańbę narodu, idealnie pasuje na władcę. Taki władca, zawsze przyjmie na siebie katastrofy kraju.”

Proste słowa najczęściej wydają się paradoksalne.

Zawierając umowy i podpisując kontrakty, ludzie przyjmują na siebie zobowiązania, które powinni wypełniać. Niestety dla wielu dane komuś słowo znaczy niewiele, toteż często nie dotrzymują obietnic.

Mędrzec, będąc przeciwnym takiemu zachowaniu, zawsze dotrzymuje słowa, chociaż od innych tego nie wymaga. W taki oto sposób objawia się jego cnotliwość.

Nie można nazwać cnotliwym tego, który wykorzystuje innych do wypełniania swoich zobowiązań.

Droga natury nie narzuca niczego w sprawach tego typu, pozwalając każdemu działać wedle własnej woli. Pamiętajmy jednak, że Tao zawsze stoi po stronie dobrego człowieka, będąc dla niego nagrodą samą w sobie.

W niewielkim kraju, zamieszkanym przez niezbyt liczną populację, powinno się utrzymywać grupę ludzi o nieprzeciętnych umiejętnościach bojowych. Należy dbać o to, by ludzie ci nie korzystali ze swoich zdolności bez potrzeby. W takim kraju ludzie nie powinni bać się śmierci, a jednocześnie dalekie krainy nie powinny budzić w nich pożądania. Nawet jeśli posiadaliby okręty i powozy, nie powinni mieć okazji do ich użycia. Nawet jeśli posiadaliby zbroje, nie powinni mieć okazji do ich przyodziania. Nawet jeśli posiadaliby broń, nie powinni mieć okazji do jej zastosowania.

Ludzie powinni żyć w zgodzie z dawnymi obyczajami, zamiast opierać swe działania na prawach spisanych w kodeksach i ustawach. Powinni delektować się pożywieniem, być dumnymi ze swoich szat, zadowolonymi ze swoich domów i radować się swoimi zwyczajami.

Nawet, gdyby sąsiednie kraje były tak blisko, że byłoby słychać szczekanie psów i pianie kogutów, życie w kraju rządzonym jak ten opisany powyżej, sprawiłoby, że jego mieszkańcy nie pragnęliby wyjeżdżać.

Prawda nie zawsze jest piękna, z kolei piękne słowa nie zawsze przedstawiają prawdę. Ci, którzy podążają ścieżką Tao, nie dyskutują o niej, ponieważ wiedzą, że z żadnych argumentów użytych w dyskusji nie będzie trwałego pożytku. Ci, którzy znają naturalną drogę, nie poszerzają nadmiernie swej wiedzy, natomiast ci, którzy używają wiedzy do wypełniania życia swojego i innych, nie są świadomi Tao, ani naturalnego szczęścia.

Dlatego też Mędrzec nie przechowuje niczego dla siebie. Wie, że im mniej posiada, tym więcej ma, a im więcej oddaje innym, tym bardziej obfite jest jego życie.

Choć Droga Niebios jest ostra niczym klinga miecza, nie zadaje ran. Mędrzec kroczy swą ścieżką bez wysiłku, jego działania odznaczają się lekkością.

Kilka słów wstępu do Księgi Drogi i Cnoty

Tao Te Ching (lub Dao De Jing) znany również jako „Laozi wuqian wen”, czyli „Księga 5000 znaków Laozi” jest starożytnym chińskim traktatem filozoficznym, będącym podstawą kanonu filozofii określanej mianem taoizmu. Napisany w VI wieku p.n.e. – czyli ponad 2500 lat temu – jest jednym z najważniejszych (o ile nie najważniejszym) tekstów w długiej historii Chin. Autorstwo „Księgi Drogi i Cnoty” przypisuje się mędrcowi Laozi (imię to oznacza: „Stary Mistrz”), archiwiście biblioteki państwowej z czasów Dynastii Zhou.

Pierwsze wzmianki o Laozi możemy znaleźć w „Zapiskach Historyka” z II wieku p.n.e., których autorem był Sima Qian (Sy-ma Ts‘ien). Według niego Laozi urodził się 14 lipca 604 r. p.n.e. we wsi Kio-Jin (gmina Lai, okręg Kukien, ówczesne państwo Zhou), a nazywał się Li Er (pośmiertnie Li Dan). Przydomek Laozi został mu nadany przez następne pokolenia ze względu na fakt, iż był on pierwszym ze wszystkich wielkich chińskich mędrców.

Istnienie Laozi po dziś dzień nie zostało ostatecznie udowodnione. Nawet jednak, jeśli założymy, że jest on postacią historyczną, możemy znaleźć wiele odmiennych biografii mędrca i nie mniej opowieści o powstaniu Tao Te Ching. Nie sposób dzisiaj określić, które z nich są prawdziwe. Niektórzy zawierzają starożytnym przekazom (np. Sima Qian), inni skłaniają się ku bardziej współczesnym hipotezom. Wiele zaciekłych dyskusji stoczono do tej pory, jakby nie biorąc przy tym pod uwagę nauk Laozi. Czyż takie dyskusje nie są bowiem pozbawione sensu? Wsłuchajcie się w nieśmiertelne słowa Księgi, a poznacie odpowiedź na to pytanie.

By zadość uczynić tradycji, przytoczę jedną z legend powstania Tao Te Ching. Nie twierdzę, że jest ona prawdziwsza od innych, ani że przemawiają za nią jakieś szczególne dowody. Powód jej wyboru jest prosty: podoba mi się najbardziej ze wszystkich znanych mi wersji.

Zgodnie z tą legendą, Laozi pod koniec swego długiego życia, porzucił sprawowany przez siebie urząd i udał się na zachód. Wędrował w poszukiwaniu miejsca odpowiedniego na spędzenie ostatnich chwil życia. W końcu dotarł na przełęcz Xiangu, gdzie znajdowała się strażnica, stanowiąca kraniec państwa. Tam został rozpoznany przez strażnika imieniem Yin Xi. Kiedy ten dowiedział się o celu podróży mistrza, nie chciał go przepuścić. Zbyt wielki żywił podziw i szacunek dla mądrości starego człowieka, by mógł pozwolić na jej rozpłynięcie się w mrokach dziejów. Strażnik błagał Laozi o spisanie kanonu zasad i prawd wszechświata. Niechętny temu pomysłowi, Laozi jednak dał się przekonać i pozostał na pograniczu dopóki nie powstał traktat znany dzisiaj jako Tao Te Ching. Kiedy Yin Xi trzymał w ręku księgę, pozwolił mistrzowi udać się w dalszą drogę. Ten dosiadł wołu i wszelki słuch po nim zaginął.

Nie wiadomo dokąd udał się Laozi, gdzie znalazł miejsce swojego ostatecznego spoczynku. Jedyne, co pozostało to zbiór 81 rozdziałów opisujących w najprostszy możliwy sposób Drogę oraz Cnotę, którymi powinni kierować się ludzie.

Jak zauważyłem wcześniej jest to tylko jedna z wielu legend. Jakkolwiek interesująca, powinna być traktowana wyłącznie jako ciekawostka. Nie zapominajmy o tym, co naprawdę ważne, mianowicie o samym Tao Te Ching. Tak naprawdę bowiem nie jest ważna geneza powstania, lecz treść dzieła. Mądrość jaką przekazuje.

Z tego właśnie powodu nie będę silił się na dodawanie komentarzy do poszczególnych rozdziałów, na interpretacje, które wyjaśnią, co autor miał na myśli. Nie będę również, wzorem innych tłumaczy i redaktorów, rozpisywał się na temat taoizmu. Przemilczę zarówno jego historię, jak i zasady. Co więcej, nie napiszę nawet słowa na temat moich własnych przemyśleń wywołanych lekturą księgi. To nie ma przecież większego znaczenia. Jeśli chcesz przeczytać „Tao Te Ching”, musisz to zrobić samodzielnie. Nie będę w tym pomagał więcej niż już pomogłem tłumacząc cały tekst. Nie szukaj u mnie duchowego wsparcia, nie udzielę go. Nie szukaj u mnie mądrości, którą podzielić się nie jestem w stanie. Nie próbuj przekonać mnie, bym rzekł choć jedno słowo o mądrości. Potrafię jedynie milczeć. Resztę pracy pozostawiam tobie, Czytelniku. Wszak w tym celu właśnie powstała ta wspaniała księga. Abyś mógł podążyć dalej ścieżką prawdziwej ludzkiej mocy.

Tao[1], które można wyrazić słowami, nie jest (prawdziwym)[2] niezmiennym tao.
Nazwa, którą można je określić, nie jest (prawdziwą) niezmienną nazwą.
Bezimienne (stało się) prapoczątkiem nieba i ziemi.
Nazwane (stało się) rodzicielką dziesięciu tysięcy rzeczy.
Przeto (ten, kto) trwale pozbawiony jest pragnień wszelakich, (potrafi) dojrzeć subtelną istotę tao, (ten zaś, kto) niezmiennie tkwi w pętach swych pragnień, (może) tylko ujrzeć zewnętrzną pozorność rzeczy.
Te dwie (strony tao) wywodzą się ze wspólnego źródła, lecz noszą odmienne nazwy.
To, co jest w nich wspólne, nazywamy wielką tajemnicą, tajemnicą nad tajemnicami, bramą (wiodącą do poznania) wszelakich cudowności.

Gdy cały świat uznał piękno za piękno, wtedy (pojawiła się) szpetota.
Gdy wszyscy uznali dobro za dobro, wtedy (powstało) zło.
W ten sam sposób:
Byt i Niebyt wzajemnie się rodzą.
Trudne i łatwe wzajemnie się dopełniają.
Długie i krótkie są sobie wzajemnie miarą.
Wysokie i niskie są względem siebie zależne,
Dźwięki i tony wzajemnie tworzą harmonię,
A wcześniejsze i późniejsze nawzajem po sobie następują.
Dlatego mędrzec dokonuje czynów nie działając, i prowadzi nauczanie bez uciekania się do słów.
(Wtedy) tysiące rzeczy oddziałuje na niego, a on się przed tym nie wzbrania.
Stwarza (wiele rzeczy), ale ich sobie nie przywłaszcza,
Przyczynia się (do ich rozwoju), ale się od nich nie uzależnia.
Osiąga sukcesy, ale się nimi nie szczyci.
I właśnie dlatego, że się nimi nie szczyci, (żadnej z tych rzeczy) nie jest pozbawiony.

Jeśli nie będziecie uznaniem umiejętności i wiedzy otaczać, sprawicie, że wśród ludu zwad i kłótni nie będzie.
Jeśli cenić nie będziecie przedmiotów drogocennych, trudnych do zdobycia, doprowadzicie do tego, że wśród ludu nie będzie złodziei.
Jeśli nie będziecie ukazywać przedmiotów godnych pożądania, sprawicie, że serca ludu nie będą wzburzone.
Dlatego, gdy rządy mędrzec w kraju sprawuje, opróżnia serca ludzi a napełnia ich żołądki, osłabia ich dążenia (i ambicje), a wzmacnia ich kości (i mięśnie). Nieustannie prowadzi do tego, by lud nie miał wiedzy ani pragnień. Prowadzi również do tego, by ci, którzy wiedzę posiedli, nie mieli odwagi (z niej robić użytku) i działać.
(Mędrzec) działa (opierając się na zasadzie) niedziałania i dlatego nie ma niczego, co by nie (podlegało) jego władzy.

Tao jest jako puste (naczynie) i mimo iż ciągle jest w użyciu, jak gdyby nigdy się nie przepełniało. Jest ono jak otchłań bezdenne: Jak gdyby było praojcem wszechrzeczy.
Przytępia ono swoją ostrość,
Porządkuje (wypełniający je) chaos,
Łagodzi swój blask,
Utożsamia się z pyłem (ziemi).
Jest tak nieograniczone, jak gdyby trwało wiecznie.
Nie wiem, czyim jest ono dzieckiem:
(Istniało) zanim (na ziemi i na niebie pojawiły się różne) zjawiska i najwyższe bóstwo.

Niebo i ziemia nie przejawiają (cnoty) ludzkości[3] i traktują dziesiątki tysięcy istot jak (ofiarne) psy ze słomy[4].
Mędrzec nie przejawia (cnoty) humanitarności i traktuje (wszystkich ludzi) stu rodów jak (ofiarne) psy ze słomy. Czyż przestrzeń między niebem i ziemią nie wydaje się jako miech kowalski albo flet. Jest pusta (w środku), ale nie można jej wyczerpać. Znajduje się (w ciągłym) ruchu i coraz więcej wydaje (na świat rzeczy).
Wielosłowie (gadatliwość) wróży niepowodzenie, dlatego lepiej jest zachować umiar.

(Tao, które jest jak) duch doliny, nigdy nie ginie.
To nazywamy je tajemnicą pierwiastka żeńskiego, bramą wiodącą do tajemnicy pierwiastka żeńskiego.
To nazywamy je korzeniem nieba i ziemi.
(Tao) ciągnie się jak nić nieprzerwanie, jak gdyby istniało (wiecznie), a jego działalność nigdy nie ustaje.

Niebo jest długowieczne, a ziemia jest długotrwała.
Niebo i ziemia mogą być długowieczne i długotrwałe dzięki temu, że same siebie (nawzajem) nie rodzą. Właśnie dlatego mogą być długowieczne.
Dlatego Mędrzec stawia siebie za innymi ludźmi i przez to znajduje się przed nimi, nie dba o swoje ciało a przez to je zachowuje.
Czyż nie jest tak, że właśnie dzięki temu, że nie zabiega o urzeczywistnienie swoich osobistych (pragnień), jego osobiste (cele) mogą się spełnić?

Najwyższa dobroć[5] podobna jest wodzie. Dobroć wody (polega na tym, że) przynosi ona korzyści dziesiątkom tysięcy rzeczy, mimo iż z nikim nie walczy. Pozostaje (ona w najniższym położeniu), w którym żaden człowiek nie chciałby się znajdować. Dlatego zbliża się ona w swym podobieństwie do tao.
(Jeśli chodzi o miejsce, w którym człowiek) przebywa, najbardziej ceni się jego (niskie) położenie.
(Jeśli chodzi o) serce (i wypełniające je uczucia), najbardziej ceni się ich głębię.
(Jeśli chodzi o) stosunki (między ludźmi), najbardziej ceni się w nich ludzkość[6]
(Jeśli chodzi o) słów (wypowiadanie), najbardziej ceni się w nich szczerość i wiarygodność.
(Jeśli chodzi o) rządów (w kraju sprawowanie), najbardziej ceni się w nich ład i spokój.
(Jeśli chodzi o) służenie (panu i władcy), najbardziej ceni się umiejętności i sprawność.
(Jeśli chodzi o) działalność (wszelaką), najbardziej się ceni (prowadzenie jej) we właściwym czasie.
Zaiste, właśnie dlatego, że się z nikim nie walczy (dla osiągnięcia tych wartości), nie (rodzi się) opór i przeciwdziałanie.

Jeśli masz trzymać naczynie, aż się przepełni, lepiej tego zaniechaj.
Jeśli (swój miecz) doprowadzisz do niezwykłej ostrości, nie będziesz w stanie długo jej zachować.
Jeśli dom swój wypełnisz złotem i nefrytem, nie zdołasz ustrzec go (przed grabieżą).
Jeśli bogactwa i zaszczyty wbiją cię w pychę, nieszczęścia same przybędą ich śladem.
Gdy dzieło zakończysz, spełnisz swe zadania, wycofaj się z życia i (schroń gdzieś na odludziu).
Takie jest bowiem Tao nieba, (prawa natury).

Duch i ciało stanowią jedność i mogą (tak trwać) nie rozdzielając się.
Koncentrując się na regulacji oddechu i harmonijnym osłabieniu swych sił, można (osiągnąć) stan (pozbawionego pragnień) niemowlęcia.
Usuwając (przygodne myśli) i (poświęcając się) tajemnej obserwacji (otaczającego świata), możesz (pozostać czysty) bez skazy.
W miłowaniu ludu i rządzeniu krajem możesz wtedy nie (uciekać się do) wiedzy[7].
Bramy niebios otwierają się i zamykają, (powodując liczne przemiany), (a wtedy) można zachowywać się (wobec nich biernie) jak kura.
Blask (mądrości rozchodzi się) we wszystkie strony, a więc można (działać) nie działając.
(Należy tak jak tao) rodzić i żywić to, (co się zrodziło).
(Należy) rodzić, ale nie poczytywać (przez siebie zrodzonego), za swoją własność.
(Należy) stwarzać, ale (tego, co się stworzyło) nie wykorzystywać dla własnych celów.
(Należy) przewodzić (innym), ale nie należy okazywać im swojej wyższości.
To właśnie nazywamy tajemniczą (cnotą) te (przyjęcia zasad tao).

Trzydzieści szprych w piaście (tworzy koło). Dzięki pustce między nimi istnieje pożytek z koła.
Z gliny formuje się naczynie i garnki. Dzięki pustce w ich wnętrzu istnieje pożytek z naczyń.
W ścianach domów wycina się drzwi i okna. Dzięki pustce w ich wnętrzu istnieje pożytek z domów.
Na tym właśnie polega korzyść z pełnego i pożytek z pustego.

Pięć barw czyni ludzi ślepymi[8].
Pięć dźwięków czyni ludzi głuchymi.
Pięć smaków sprawia, że podniebienie ludziom drętwieje.
Cwałowanie na koniach i polowanie wśród pól wprawia serca ludzi w szał.
Przedmioty drogocenne, trudne do zdobycia, popychają ludzi do zbrodni.
Dlatego właśnie Mędrzec troszczy się o (to, co jest godne jego) wnętrza, a nie o (to, co jedynie mami jego) wzrok. Odżegnuje się od tamtego, a czerpie z tego.

Łaska i niełaska (jednako) napawają cię strachem.
Zaszczyty sprowadzają na ciebie wielkie nieszczęścia.
Dlaczego mówimy, że łaska i niełaska (jednako) napawają cię strachem? Gdy łaska na ciebie spływa, boisz się przyjąć ją i boisz się ją utracić. Właśnie dlatego mówimy, że łaska i niełaska (jednako) napawają cię strachem.
To, że posiadam ciało, jest (główną) przyczyną, że spadają na mnie wielkie nieszczęścia.
Gdy tylko nie będę miał ciała, jakież cierpienia mogłyby mnie dosięgnąć?
Dlatego ceniąc cały świat tak jak swoje ciało, godzien będziesz, by ci ten świat przekazać (we władanie): miłując cały świat tak jak swoje ciało, godzien będziesz, by ci ten świat powierzyć.

Patrzymy nań, lecz nie dostrzegamy. Przeto zwiemy je niewidzialnym.
Nasłuchujemy je, lecz nie słyszymy. Przeto zwiemy je niesłyszalnym.
(Pragniemy) je ująć w dłonie, ale nie możemy go dosięgnąć. Przeto zwiemy je nieuchwytnym.
Tych trzech (właściwości tao) nie można dokładniej zbadać. Łączą się ze sobą tworząc jedność.
Jego wierzch nie jest spowity jasnością.
Jego spód nie jest pogrążony w ciemności.
Jest ono ciągłe, jak nić nieprzerwane.
I bezimienne.
W końcu znów się przemienia w nicość. Dlatego nazywamy je nadawaniem kształtu bezkształtnemu, tworzeniem obrazów z niematerialnego. Dlatego mówimy, że jest to coś bardzo niejasnego i nieokreślonego.
Idąc mu naprzeciw, nie dostrzegamy jego twarzy.
Postępując w ślad za nim, nie widzimy jego pleców.
Kto pojmie tao starożytności, ten zdoła pokierować rzeczywistością dnia dzisiejszego i będzie mógł poznać najdawniejszy początek. Nazywamy go (ciągnącym się w nieskończoność jak nić) tao.

Ci, którzy w dawnych czasach zasłynęli jako znawcy zasad tao, byli cudownie subtelni i tajemniczo niezgłębieni.
(Ich wiedza była tak) głęboka, że zwykły człowiek nie potrafił ich zrozumieć.
Chociaż nie mógł ich zrozumieć, starał się jednak, przynajmniej bardzo powierzchownie poznać ich oblicze.
Jakże byli przezorni, jak człowiek przechodzący zimą przez rzekę.
Jakże byli ostrożni, jak ktoś, kto się boi sąsiadów ze wszystkich (czterech) stron.
Jakże byli powściągliwi, jak ktoś, kto się znajduje w roli gościa.
Jakże byli niezbadani, jak kawałek topniejącego lodu.
Jakże byli niezłomni, jak nieociosany pal drzewa.
Jakże byli rozlegli (w swej wiedzy), jak (szeroka) dolina.
Jakże byli nieprzeniknieni, jak zmącone wody powodzi.
Co można zrobić, żeby zmącenie ustąpiło?
Należy zachować spokój (i bezruch), a (woda) stopniowo stanie się czysta.
Co można zrobić, żeby spokój zachować na wieki?
Poprzez ruch (i zmiany) stopniowo spokój się zrodzi.
Ci, którzy przestrzegali tej zasady tao, nigdy nie dążyli do wypełnienia swoich pragnień do końca.
Właśnie dlatego, że ich pragnienia nie były do końca spełnione, potrafili (w spokoju doczekać) wyczerpania (swoich sił), nie (starając się) ich na nowo przywrócić.

Osiągam pełnię (wewnętrznej) pustki, zachowuję w sercu całkowity spokój.
Tysiące rzeczy rodzi się i rozwija, a ja przyglądam się, jak powracają (do swego źródła).
Każda rzecz rodzi się i osiąga pełny rozkwit, (a wówczas) każda z nich wraca do swego źródła.
Powrót do źródła oznacza pełny spokój. Nazywamy to spełnieniem swego przeznaczenia.
Spełnienie własnego przeznaczenia nazywamy niezmienną (zasadą).
Poznanie owej niezmiennej (zasady) zwiemy oświeceniem.
Ci, co nie posiedli poznania niezmiennej (zasady), w swej szaleńczej głupocie dopuszczają się wielu zbrodni.
Ci, co niezmienną (zasadę) poznali, stają się wszechogarniającymi.
Będąc wszechogarniającymi, są oni bezstronni i (wszystko traktują jednako).
Będąc bezstronnymi, zdobywają dostojeństwo królewskie.
W swym królewskim dostojeństwie naśladują oni niebo.
Niebo bierze przykład z tao.
Tao oznacza nieskończone (trwanie).
Utrata ciała nie stanowi więc dla Mędrca niebezpiecznego zagrożenia.

W zamierzchłej przeszłości ledwie zdawano sobie sprawę z tego, że istnieli (jacyś władcy).
Później miłowano ich i sławiono.
Później odczuwano przed nimi strach.
Później pogardzano nimi i żywiono do nich nienawiść.
Dlatego ci, których słowa się nie spełniły (czyli nie dotrzymali obietnic), nie cieszyli się zaufaniem (ludu).
(Prześwietni władcy starożytności) zatopieni byli w myślach i (zawsze) cenili swoje słowa, (nie nadużywając ich). (A mimo to) powstawały wielkie osiągnięcia, a wszystkie dzieła wieńczyło pomyślne zakończenie.
Wszyscy (ludzie) ze stu rodów mówili: My (postępowaliśmy) tak sami (z siebie).

Gdy odrzucono zasady Wielkiego Tao, wówczas powstały (konfucjańskie cnoty) ludzkość i sprawiedliwość[9].
Gdy (na świecie) pojawiły się mądrość i wiedza, wówczas powstała „wielka sztuczność”.
Gdy między krewnymi sześciu stopni zapanowała niezgoda, wówczas powstały (konfucjańskie cnoty) „synowskiej powinności” i „ojcowskiej miłości”.
Gdy w państwie zaczął się szerzyć wielki zamęt, wówczas to pojawili się wierni słudzy (i lojalni ministrowie).

Odrzućcie wiedzę, usuńcie mądrość, a naród skorzysta na tym stokrotnie.
Odrzućcie ludzkość, usuńcie sprawiedliwość[10], a u ludzi ponownie (pojawią się wrodzone) uczucia ojcowskie i synowskie.
Odrzućcie przemyślność, usuńcie (chęć zdobycia) korzyści, a znikną zbójcy i złodzieje.
Tych trzech (zleceń) nie wystarczy traktować jako (piękną) maksymę. Dlatego powinny (wam one służyć jako zasady), których będziecie się trzymać w codziennym działaniu).
Zachowujcie więc naturalną prostotę, unikajcie sztuczności, mniej zabiegajcie o własne (korzyści), a pragnienia wasze niechaj będą skromne.

Połóżcie kres nauce (o nakazach moralności), a nie będzie więcej kłopotów i zmartwień.
Jakaż bowiem różnica dzieli (synowskie) „słucham” od „czekam pokornie na polecenia”, (wypowiadane przez córkę w odpowiedzi na wezwanie rodziców)?[11]
Jak bardzo oddalone są od siebie dobro i zło?
Czy koniecznie trzeba odczuwać trwogę przed tym, czego inni ludzie się boją?
Rozległa zaiste jest (nauka nakazów moralnych) i nigdy nie ma jej końca.
Wszyscy ludzie cieszą się i radują, jak gdyby świętowali Dzień Wielkiej Ofiary albo wspinali się po tarasach (strojnych) wiosennym (kwieciem), (tylko ja jeden) jestem cichy i spokojny i nie widać u mnie żadnych, oznak (radości). Jestem jak niemowlę, które jeszcze nie poczuło się dzieckiem (na tym świecie). Samotny i zagubiony, Jak gdybym nie miał dokąd pójść.
Wszyscy ludzie pełni są pragnień, dążeń, i tylko ja jeden, jak gdyby pozostawiony jestem (sobie samemu).
Zaiste, w piersi mej kryje się serce człowieka głupiego — otępiałe, pogrążone w chaosie.
Niechaj jednak inni błyszczą blaskiem swego umysłu, a ja sam wolę się pogrążyć w mrokach (niewiedzy).
Niechaj inni ludzie szczycą się przenikliwością, jasnością (swego umysłu), a ja sam wolę jak w odrętwieniu, w bezdennej zadumie się zatopić.
Jestem obojętny na wszystko jak morze, (co bezustannie swe wody przelewa); los rzuca mnie we wszystkie strony, jak gdybym nie mógł się nigdzie zatrzymać.
Niechaj wszyscy ludzie mają jakieś cele i pragnienia, ja tylko jeden wolę pozostać otępiałym nędzarzem.
Tylko ja jeden różnię się od innych ludzi i cenię sobie czerpanie pokarmu z matki (natury).

Zewnętrzne przejawy Wielkiej Cnoty (te) wywodzą się wyłącznie z tao.
Tao jest czymś, co jest zupełnie nieuchwytne i nieokreślone.
Chociaż jest nieokreślone i nieuchwytne, zawarte są w nim wyobrażenia.
Chociaż jest nieuchwytne i nieokreślone, zawarte są w nim rzeczy.
Chociaż jest nieprzeniknione i wypełnione ciemnością, zawarte jest w nim nasienie.
Nasienie to jest najwyższą prawdą i zawiera w sobie to, co się musi stać (to jest przeznaczenie).
Dlatego od czasów najdawniejszych aż do dnia dzisiejszego nazwa jego (to jest tao) nie ginie. Służy ona jako określenie wspólnego praźródła wszystkich rzeczy.
A skąd ja wiem o istnieniu wspólnego praźródła wszystkich rzeczy?
Właśnie dzięki niemu.

Złamane staje się całym.
Krzywe staje się prostym.
Puste staje się pełnym.
Zmurszałe staje się nowym.
Nieliczne staje się licznym.
Liczne sprowadza oszołomienie.
Dlatego Mędrzec obejmuje Jedność i czyni ją miarą dla wszystkiego pod niebem.
Nie ukazuje się (publicznie) i dlatego świeci (swoją osobowością).
Nie twierdzi nigdy, że ma rację, i dlatego (to, co mówi) jest oczywiste.
Nie domaga się uznania, i dlatego ma wielkie osiągnięcia.
Nie stara się nad innymi wywyższać, i dlatego (wszystkim) przewodzi.
Zaiste, ponieważ o nic nie zabiega, dlatego nie ma na (całym świecie) pod niebem nikogo, kto mógłby z nim rywalizować.
W dawnych czasach mówiono, że złamane stają się całym. Czyż to nie były tylko czcze słowa?
Naprawdę, (złamane) staje się całym i wraca (do swego pierwotnego kształtu).

Oszczędność w słowach (jest zgodna) z naturą.
Bowiem i gwałtowny wicher nie dmie przez cały ranek.
Ani ulewny deszcz nie pada przez dzień cały.
Kto sprawia, że tak się dzieje?
Niebo i ziemia.
A skoro nawet niebo i ziemia nie mogą (sprawić, by wiatr i deszcze zawładnęły światem) na dłużej, to cóż dopiero człowiek (może tu poradzić)?
Dlatego (człowiek powinien) postępować zgodnie z zasadami tao.
Postępując zgodnie z tao, utożsami się z nim.
Jeśli mu się wiedzie, utożsamia się z powodzeniem.
Jeśli mu się nie wiedzie, utożsamia się z niepowodzeniem.
Jeżeli utożsami się z tao, to raduje się, osiągając je.
Jeżeli utożsami się ze swoim powodzeniem, to podobnie raduje się, osiągając je.
Jeżeli utożsami się ze swoim niepowodzeniem, to tak samo raduje się ze swojego niepowodzenia.
Jeżeli niezupełnie będziecie w to wierzyć, doprowadzi to do (całkowitej) utraty wiary (w zasady tao).

Kto wspina się na palce, nie stoi (mocno na ziemi).
Kto dwa kroki chce zrobić jednocześnie, nie idzie (szybko).
Kto ukazuje się (publicznie), nie świeci (swoją osobowością).
Kto twierdzi, że ma (zawsze) rację, to (to, co mówi), nie jest (dla wszystkich) oczywiste.
Kto domaga się uznania, nie ma żadnych osiągnięć.
Kto stara się nad innych wywyższyć, nikomu nie przewodzi.
Wszystko to zawarte jest w (zasadach) tao.
(O tego rodzaju zachowaniach) powiadają: „Są to zbyteczne pragnienia i niepotrzebne starania (dosłownie: nadmiar pożywienia, zbyteczny wysiłek). Wszystkie istoty żywią do tego nienawiść”.

Dlatego ci, co posiedli tao, nie zajmują się tymi (staraniami).
Istnieje coś[12], powstałe z chaosu, zanim się jeszcze niebo i ziemia zrodziły.
Jakże ciche jest ono. Jakże puste i bezkresne!
Stoi samotnie i nie ulega żadnym przemianom.
Oddziałuje na wszystko dokoła i nie (odczuwa) zmęczenia.
Można je uważać za matkę (całego świata) pod niebem.
Nie znam jego (prawdziwej) nazwy.
Nadają mu miano: tao, czyli Droga.
A gdy usilnie się staram znaleźć dla niego właściwą nazwę, mówię o nim Wielkie[13].
O Wielkim mówię, że przemija.
O przeminionym mówię, że się oddala.
O oddalonym mówię, że powraca.
Dlatego właśnie tao jest wielkie, niebo jest wielkie, ziemia jest wielka i człowiek, (który poznał ich tajemnice) jest wielki.
Na świecie są cztery rzeczy wielkie i człowiek jest jedną z nich.
Człowiek wzoruje się na ziemi, ziemia bierze za wzór niebo, niebo obiera sobie za wzór tao, a tao czerpie wzory z (praw rządzących) przyrodą.

Ciężkość (i powaga) leżą u podstaw lekkości.
(Bezruch) i spokój sprawują władzę nad poruszeniem.
Dlatego Mędrzec, mimo iż przez cały dzień podróżuje, nie opuszcza powagi powozu (zasłoniętego firankami). I chociaż dokoła roztaczają się wspaniałe widoki, siedzi spokojnie (panując nad swoim wzruszeniem).
A cóż dopiero mówić o władcy (imperium), mogącego wystawić dziesięć tysięcy wozów bojowych, który zajęty sobą, lekko traktuje (cały świat) pod niebem.
Jeśli się będzie zachowywał lekko, (bez należytej powagi), wówczas utraci podstawę (swego panowania).
Jeśli (pozwoli sobie na) wzruszenie, wówczas utraci władzę (nad swoim imperium).

Doświadczony wędrowiec nie (potrzebuje) kolein (wozów) i śladów, (by dojść do celu).
Wytrawny mówca nie (potrzebuje) wad i błędów (innych ludzi), (by wygłosić wspaniałe przemówienie).
Biegły rachmistrz nie (potrzebuje) bambusowych bierek dla liczenia i sztonów, (by wykonać najtrudniejsze zadanie).
Doskonały majster od zamknięć nie (potrzebuje) antab i rygli, (by zamknąć coś tak), żeby nie można było tego otworzyć.
Wyborny mistrz od wiązania nie (potrzebuje) węzłów i słupów, (by związać coś tak), żeby nie można było tego rozwiązać.
Tak samo mędrzec (wyznający zasady tao) zawsze potrafi dobrze pomóc ludziom (w poznaniu istoty życia), ponieważ nikogo nie odtrąca. Zawsze potrafi dobrze pomóc (innym) istotom, ponieważ żadnej z nich nie odtrąca.
Nazywamy to przyswojeniem jasności (zaobserwowanej w prawach rządzących przemianami w przyrodzie).
Dlatego człowiek biegle znający (naturę) ludzi jest mistrzem tych, którzy nie znają biegle (natury) ludzi, a ci którzy nie znają biegle (natury) ludzi, są substancją, na którą oddziałuje człowiek znający biegle (naturę) ludzi.
Ci, co nie czczą swego mistrza i nie troszczą się o swoją substancję, mimo że (uważają się) za mądrych, (w rzeczywistości) błądzą w wielkich (ciemnościach niewiedzy).
To właśnie nazywamy największą i najsubtelniejszą (tajemnicą istnienia).

Znając (możliwość życia aktywnego) po męsku, przestrzegając (jednak zasad życia biernego, właściwych) dla rodzaju żeńskiego, staję się niczym (najgłębszy) jar (dla całego świata) pod niebem. Kiedy jestem jak (najgłębszy) jar (dla całego świata) pod niebem, (siła mojej) niezmiennej Cnoty (te) ze mnie nie wycieka i ponownie wracam do (stanu) niemowlęctwa.
Znając (naturę tego, co jest) białe, (a więc jasne, aktywne, męskie), trzymając się (jednak tego, co jest) czarne, (a więc ciemne, bierne żeńskie), staję się miarą (dla całego świata) pod niebem. Kiedy jestem miarą (dla całego świata) pod niebem, (siła mojej) niezmiennej Cnoty (te) nie jest w nadmiarze i ponownie wracam (do stanu, w którym) nie ma krańcowości.
Wiedząc, (co to jest) chwała, a jednak wybierając (życie) w hańbie i (poniżeniu), jestem jako parów (dla całego świata) pod niebem. Będąc jako parów (dla całego świata) pod niebem, (sprawiam, że siła mojej) niezmiennej Cnoty (te) jest w dostatecznej (ilości, nie za małej i nie za dużej), i ponownie wracam do (stanu pierwotnej) prostoty (podobnej nieociosanemu pniu drzewa).
Gdy (pierwotna) prostota (nieociosanego pnia drzewa) się rozprasza, powstaje z niego (drewniane) naczynie.
Mędrzec (wyznający tao) wykorzystuje ją (pierwotną prostotę) i staje się wyższy ponad godność i urzędy.
Bowiem utrzymywanie powszechnego ładu nie polega na obciosywaniu (pnia drzewa i niszczeniu jego pierwotnej natury).

(Byli tacy, co) zamierzali opanować świat, uciekając się w tym celu do działania. Widziałem, że jednak nie osiągnęli swojego zamiaru.
Świat jest naczyniem (pełnym) cudownych tajemnic i nie można (go zdobyć za pomocą) działania.
Kto działa, ten doznaje porażki.
Kto go (posiadł) i trzyma mocno, ten go straci.
Bowiem jedne rzeczy idą (przodem), inne podążają (w tyle) za nimi.
Jedne oddychają delikatnie (nosem), inne dyszą gwałtownie (ustami).
Jedne z nich są silne, inne zaś słabowite.
Jedne z nich niszczą i łamią, inne zaś ulegają rozkładowi.
Dlatego Mędrzec (wyznający tao) unika zbytku, unika przepychu, unika bogactwa.

Kto służy władcy ludzi zgodnie z (zasadami) tao, nie będzie orężem ujarzmiał świata. Tego rodzaju postępki lubią wracać (i mścić się). Gdzie wojsko się zatrzymuje, tam wokół jeno kolczaste ciernie rosną. Po wielkich wyprawach wojennych zawsze następują lata wielkiego głodu.
Wytrawny (dowódca) osiąga swój cel i na tym poprzestaje. Nie ośmiela się silą czegokolwiek zagarniać. Osiąga swój cel, ale się tym nie chełpi.
Osiąga swój cel, ale (przeciwko nikomu) się z wojskiem nie wyprawia.
Osiąga swój cel, ale się tym nie szczyci.
Osiąga swój cel, ale nie może czynić inaczej. (z pewnością jako znawca zasad tao nie chciałby osiągnąć tego celu, ale jako wódz nie ma innego wyjścia).
Osiąga swój cel, ale nie stosuje przy tym siły.
(Wszystko), gdy tylko osiągnie dojrzałość, (zaczyna) się starzeć.
Mówi się o tym (osiągnięciu celu), że nie jest zgodne z zasadami) tao.
A jeśli coś nie jest (zgodne z zasadami) tao, wcześnie nadejdzie jego kres.

Zaiste, wspaniały oręż jest narzędziem sprowadzającym nieszczęścia i wszystkie istoty nienawidzą go.
Dlatego ten, kto (postępuje zgodnie z zasadami) tao, nie zajmuje się nim.
Człowiek szlachetny przebywając (w swym domostwie w czasach pokoju), ceni lewą stronę (jako miejsce honorowe), gdy zaś chwyta oręż do ręki (w czas wojny), ceni prawą stronę (jako miejsce honorowe).
Oręż jest narzędziem sprowadzającym nieszczęścia, a nie jest narzędziem (odpowiednim) dla człowieka szlachetnego.
Posługuje się nim tylko wtedy, kiedy już nie może uczynić inaczej. Zawsze jednak pokój i łagodność ceni sobie najwyżej.
Nawet gdy odnosi zwycięstwo, nie widzi w tym nic pięknego. A gdyby dostrzegał w tym jakiś urok, to tak jak gdyby radowało go zabijanie ludzi.
Ci, którym radość sprawia zabijanie ludzi, nigdy nie będą w stanie osiągnąć swego celu (na świecie) pod niebem.
Przy radosnych uroczystościach lewą stronę ceni się (jako miejsce honorowe).
W czasie smutnych uroczystości honoruje się prawą stronę.
Zastępca głównodowodzącego wojsk zajmuje zawsze miejsce po lewej stronie, zaś najwyższy wódz obiera sobie miejsce po prawej stronie.
(Można) powiedzieć, że stanęli oni zgodnie z rytuałem żałobnym. Rzeź masy. (niewinnych) ludzi jest opłakiwana z wielką żałością.
(Dlatego nawet) gdy w czasie wojny osiągną zwycięstwo, ustawiają się według rytuału żałobnego.

Tao jest niezmienne i bezimienne.
Chociaż w swojej (nieskażonej) prostocie jest ono maleńkie, (na świecie) pod niebem nie ma nic, co mogłoby je uczynić swoim sługą.
Jeśli książęta i władcy zdołają zachować je (i postępować zgodnie z jego zasadami), wówczas dziesiątki tysięcy istot i rzeczy samorzutnie poddawać się będą ich woli.
Wtedy także niebo i ziemia, łącząc się ze sobą, sprowadzą (na ziemię) słodką rosę (dostatku i pomyślności). Lud zaś bez (specjalnych) nakazów sam się równomiernie (będzie dzielił owocami swej pracy).
Gdy po raz pierwszy (wprowadzono pośród istniejących rzeczy sztuczny) porządek, pojawiły się nazwy (dla konkretnych pojęć).
Skoro więc były już nazwy, człowiek (działający zgodnie z tao) powinien wiedzieć, kiedy się zatrzymać (w swoim działaniu). Bowiem wiedząc, kiedy się zatrzymać, można uniknąć utraty (swojego jestestwa).
(Gdybyśmy chcieli zrobić) porównanie, to tao (na świecie) pod niebem podobne jest (rwącym) potokom, (głębokimi) wąwozami biegnącymi ku (spokojnym wodom) rzek i mórz.

Ten, kto zna (innych) ludzi, posiada (tylko) wiedzę.
Ten, kto zna siebie samego, jest (człowiekiem) oświeconym.
Ten, kto zwycięża (innych) ludzi, jest (tylko) silny.
Ten, kto zwycięstwa nad sobą samym odnosi, jest (człowiekiem) potężnym. Ten, kto zna umiar (i cieszy się tym, co ma), jest bogaty.
Ten, kto przemocą, wprowadza w życie (swoje plany), posiada (tylko) silną wolę.

[Brak rozdziału]

[Sens: Tao ubiera i żywi wszystkie rzeczy, lecz nimi nie rządzi i nie szuka poklasku.]

[Brak rozdziału]

[Sens: Tao nie ma zapachu; nie jest wystarczająco solidne, by być widzialnym, ani na tyle głośne, by być słyszalnym. Jednak trwa wiecznie.]

[Brak rozdziału]

[Sens: Miękkie i delikatne podbija twarde i mocne.]

Tao nigdy nie działa, a jednak nie ma niczego, co by nie było (przezeń) zrobione,
Gdyby książęta lenni i królowie potrafili przestrzegać tej zasady, dziesiątki tysięcy (istot) rzeczy uległoby samoistnym przemianom.
Gdyby w trakcie tych przemian pojawiło się pragnienie czynu, potrafię stłumić je za pomocą (naturalnej) prostoty bezimiennego (tao).
Jeżeli stłumię (ich pragnienia) za pomocą bezimiennego (tao), wyzbędą się oni swych pragnień.
Nie mając żadnych pragnień, (pogrąża się w błogim) spokoju a wówczas (w całym świecie) pod niebem samoistnie nastanie ład i porządek.

(Człowiek, który posiadł cnotę) te w najwyższym stopniu, nie (daje po sobie poznać, że posiadł) cnotę i właśnie dlatego cnotę (te) w najwyższym stopniu posiada.
(Człowiek, który posiadł cnotę) te w miernym stopniu, (usilnie daje po sobie poznać), że nie stracił (okazji w życiu, żeby zdobyć) cnotę, i właśnie dlatego nie posiada cnoty (te)
(Człowiek, który posiadł cnotę) te w najwyższym stopniu, nie czyni (niczego, co by było wbrew jego naturze) i nie posiada (celów i pragnień), dla których urzeczywistnienia by cokolwiek uczynił.
(Człowiek, który posiadł cnotę) te w miernym stopniu (czyli w rzeczywistości wcale jej nie posiada), działa (wbrew własnej naturze), a także ma (cele i pragnienia), dla których realizacji wszystko to czyni.
(Człowiek), który cnotę ludzkości[14] w najwyższym stopniu posiada, działa, a jednak nie posiada (innych celów i pragnień), dla których realizacji podejmowałby te działania.
(Człowiek), który cnotą najwyższej sprawiedliwości się szczyci, również działa, lecz dla określonego celu swe działania podejmuje.
(Człowiek), który w najwyższym stopniu zasady etykiety opanował, podejmuje działania, a gdy się nie spotka z wzajemnością, wówczas zakasuje rękawy i okłada (pięściami człowieka, który nie odpowiedział na jego ceremonialny gest).
Dlatego, gdy zanika tao, pozostaje te; gdy ginie cnota te pozostaje ludzkość[15]; gdy ludzkość zanika, pozostaje sprawiedliwość: gdy ginie sprawiedliwość, pozostaje już tylko (powierzchowna) etykieta.
Etykieta (i przestrzeganie jej zasad) jest zaledwie drobną resztką lojalności i szczerości. Jest ona początkiem (i źródłem) wielkiego chaosu.

Już w zamierzchłych czasach osiągano jedność (z tao), (zgodność z jego prawami, prawami natury):
Niebo osiągnęło jedność (z tao) dzięki temu jest czyste.
Ziemia osiągnęła jedność (z tao) i dzięki temu jest nieruchoma.
Duchy osiągnęły jedność (z tao) i dzięki temu posiadły cudowną moc.
Dolina osiągnęła jedność (z tao) dzięki temu wypełnia się po brzegi.
Dziesięć tysięcy istot i rzeczy osiągnęło jedność (z tao) i dzięki temu się zrodziło.
Władcy osiągnęli jedność (z tao) i dzięki temu (mogli) prawidłowo (rządzić całym światem) pod niebem.
Są to najwyższe (osiągnięcia dokonane dzięki jedności z tao).
Powiedzmy,
że niebo nie stałoby się dzięki temu jasne; wówczas zachodziłaby obawa, że się rozleci,
że ziemia nie stałaby się dzięki temu nieruchoma; wówczas zachodziłaby obawa, że się rozstąpi,
że duchy nie posiadłyby dzięki temu cudownej mocy; wówczas zachodziłaby obawa, że rozpłyną się w nicość,
że dolina by się dzięki temu nie wypełniła po brzegi; wówczas zachodziłaby obawa, że całkowicie wyschnie, (stając się nieurodzajną, bezpłodną rozpadliną),
że dziesięć tysięcy (istot) i rzeczy dzięki temu by się nie zrodziło; wówczas zachodziłaby obawa, że całkowicie by wyginęły,
że władcy feudalni nie zyskaliby dzięki temu szlachectwa i wysokiej (pozycji); wówczas zachodziłaby obawa, że zostaną obaleni.
Dlatego szlachectwo miernotę ma za podstawę, a wysoka (pozycja) w niskiej (pozycji) ma fundament.
Toteż feudalni władcy mówią o sobie „sierota”, „osamotniony”, „niezaradny”.
Jest to braniem miernoty za podstawę. Czyż nie jest tak?
Przecież posiadanie kilku powozów (ma swoją podstawę, punkt wyjścia) w nieposiadaniu żadnego wozu.
Nie należy więc dążyć do tego, by być cenionym jak (rzeźbiony) nefryt, lecz do tego, by być prostym (i niezawodnym) jak (rozrzucone na ziemi) kamienie.

Dążenie ku swemu przeciwieństwu jest (przejawem) ruchu (wynikającego z zasad) tao.
Słabość jest (główną cechą, na której opiera się) wykorzystanie (zasad) tao.
Dziesięć tysięcy istot (i rzeczy na świecie) pod niebem zrodziło się z bytu.
A byt powstał z niebytu.

Uczeni o (głębokiej), wyższej (wiedzy), usłyszawszy o (zasadach) tao, czynią natychmiast starania, by je stosować (w życiu).
Uczeni o przeciętnej (wiedzy), usłyszawszy o (zasadach) tao, (odnoszą się do nich czasami tak), jakby one istniały, (a czasami tak), jakby ich nie było.
Uczeni o małej (miernej wiedzy), usłyszawszy o (zasadach) tao, śmieją się z tych zasad na cały głos, a nawet ci z nich, którzy się nie śmieją, nie (uważają ich za) dostatecznie (dobre), by przyjąć je jako zasadę (swego postępowania).
Dlatego wśród dawnych porzekadeł znajdziemy takie oto:
„Jasne (wyraźne zasady) tao wydają się jak gdyby mroczną (niewyraźną ciemnością)”.
„Tao postępowania do przodu wydaje się jak gdyby cofaniem”.
„(Tao), droga płaska i równa wydaje się jak gdyby najeżona niebotycznymi wierzchołkami gór”.
„Najwyższe (przejawy) cnoty wydają się głęboką doliną (prostoty)”.
„Wielka chwała wydaje się poniżeniem”.
„Największa cnota wydaje się niepełna”.
„Cnota zdecydowania wydaje się lenistwem”.
„Prostota i naturalność wydają się czymś wymuszonym”.
„To co najbardziej kwadratowe, jest jak gdyby bez rogów”.
„Najwspanialsze naczynia rytualne zostały wytworzone «najpóźniej»”.
„Najpotężniejszy dźwięk (z daleka dobiega naszych uszu jako) lekki szum”.
„Największy wizerunek, (gdy się nań z bliska popatrzeć) nie zawiera kształtów”.
(Zasady) tao ukryte są (przed nami) i są bezimienne. I tylko tao potrafi (ustalić) początek i kres (wszelkiego istnienia).

Tao dało początek (materialnej)[16] jedności (świata):
Jedność (podzieliła się), dając początek dwóm (przeciwstawnym siłom in i jang).
Dwie (siły) zrodziły trzecią.
A trzecia dała początek dziesięciu tysiącom (istot) i rzeczy.
Dziesięć tysięcy (istot i) rzeczy zawiera w sobie (siłę) in i spowite jest (siłą) jang.
(Obie siły) wdzierając się w (otaczający je) fluid, doznają harmonijnego (połączenia).
Ludzie bardzo nie chcą, by ich w życiu spotkały trzy nieszczęścia: sieroctwo, wdowieństwo i nieudolność.
A jednak królowie i książęta nadają sobie takie właśnie określenia[17],
Dlatego (wszystkie istoty i) rzeczy, jeśli ktoś chce je zmniejszyć, na odwrót — coraz bardziej się rozrastają, jeśli ktoś chce się przyczynić do ich wzrostu, one — na odwrót — stają się coraz mniejsze.
Ludzie wzajemnie się pouczają.
Ja również ich o tym pouczam.
Ludzie, którzy siłę stosują, nie osiągną (lekkiej) śmierci. Pragnę przyjąć to (stwierdzenie) za ojca (podstawę) mych nauk.

Najbardziej miękkie rzeczy pod niebem potrafią przeniknąć przez najtwardsze rzeczy pod niebem, (tak jak woda przez skały).
Niebyt potrafi przejść na wylot przez substancję (bez) najdrobniejszych szczelin.
Dzięki temu właśnie poznałem korzyści płynące z niedziałania.
Nauczać bez słów.
Czerpać korzyści z niedziałania.
Bardzo niewielu (ludzi na świecie) pod niebem osiągnęło tę (umiejętność).

Sława czy ciało, cóż jest nam bliższe?
Ciało czy bogactwa, cóż bardziej cenimy?
Zysk czy strata, cóż nam większą szkodę wyrządza?
Przesadne umiłowanie czegoś nieuchronnie wielkich nieszczęść (cierpień) staje się przyczyną.
Nadmierne bogactwo z pewnością wielkich strat (jest zapowiedzią).
Kto wie, na czym poprzestać, ten się nie znajdzie nad przepaścią (zagłady).
Lecz żyć będzie długo w spokoju (wolny od wszelkich niebezpieczeństw).

Najpełniejszy okrąg jest jak gdyby wyszczerbiony, a jednak jego zastosowanie przez to nic nie traci.
Największe wypełnienie wydaje się puste, ale jego użycie przez to nie zanika.
To, co bardzo proste, wydaje się wygięte.
To, co najbardziej zręczne, wydaje się nieporadne.
To, co najbardziej krasomówcze, wydaje się pozbawione logiki.
Szybkim marszem można pokonać dokuczliwy ziąb.
Spokojem i bezruchem można pokonać upalny żar.
Zachowując całkowity spokój, można zaprowadzić ład (na świecie) pod niebem.

Gdy (na świecie) pod niebem zapanuje tao, koni bojowych do uprawiania pól używać się będzie.
Gdy (na świecie) pod niebem zaginie tao, kobyły na polach bitewnych rodzić będą źrebięta.
Nie maszże większego nieszczęścia nad brak umiaru.
Nie maszże większego występku nad nieokiełznaną chciwość:
Dlatego dosyt oparty na znajomości umiaru jest trwałym dosytem.

Nie wychodząc za drzwi domu, można poznać (cały) świat.
Nie wyglądając przez okno, można poznać tao (prawa) nieba.
Im dalszą odbywasz wędrówkę, tym wiedza twoja staje się mniejsza.
Dlatego Mędrzec (przestrzegający zasad tao)
Nie odbywa wędrówek, a wie (wszystko).
Nie ogląda (wszystkiego na własne oczy), a (wszystko) jest dla niego jasne.
Nie (podejmuje żadnych) działań, a (wszystko) jest dokonane.

Gdy oddajecie się nauce, (wasza wiedza) z każdym dniem się powiększa.
Gdy oddajecie się (wcielaniu zasad) tao, (wasze pragnienie zdobycia wiedzy) z każdym dniem się zmniejsza.
Zmniejsza się i znów się zmniejsza, aż w końcu osiągacie stan niedziałania.
Nie działacie, a mimo to nie ma niczego, co by nie było zdziałane.
Kierowanie światem niezmiennie polega na nieczynieniu czegokolwiek, (co by naruszało istniejący naturalny porządek rzeczy).
Jeżeli będziecie naruszać ten porządek, wtedy nie będziecie zdolni utrzymać panowania nad (światem) pod niebem.

Mędrzec (wyznający tao) nie ma (własnych) niezmiennych przekonań.
Przekonania (ludu) stu rodów czyni (własnymi) przekonaniami.
Tym, co mi życzą dobrze — (powiada) — ja też życzę dobrze.
Tym, co mi dobrze nie życzą — (powiada) — ja mimo wszystko również życzę dobrze.
(I w ten sposób) osiągam dobroć.
Tym, co darzą mnie zaufaniem — (rzecze) — ja też ufam.
Tym, co mnie zaufaniem nie darzą — (rzecze) — ja mimo wszystko również ufam.
(I w ten sposób) osiągam (ich) ufność.
Mędrzec (wyznający tao, sprawując rządy na świecie) pod niebem, stapia się z nim, (sprawiając, że wszystko) pod niebem (garnie się ku pierwotnej prostocie), wyzbywa się wszelkich pragnień.
Lud cały kieruje ku niemu swój wzrok i słuch.
A Mędrzec sprawia, że (lud) staje się jak niemowlę, (nie posiadając żadnej wiedzy ni pragnień).

Uchodząc z życia (człowiek) wkracza w (krainę) śmierci.
Odcinek drogi przeznaczonej na życie wynosi trzy części z dziesięciu.
Odcinek drogi objętej przez śmierć wynosi trzy części z dziesięciu.
Odcinek życia, w którym człowiek nieustannie znajduje się w polu śmierci, (jak gdyby jedną nogą w grobie), również wynosi trzy spośród dziesięciu części. (Są to okresy niemowlęctwa i starości, kiedy człowiek bez pomocy innych, znajdowałby się nad przepaścią śmierci).
Dlaczego tak się dzieje?
Ponieważ żyje on życiem, które uważa za wielki skarb.
Słyszałem, że ci, co potrafią dobrze chronić swe życie,
Wędrując przez góry, (nie chodzą tam, gdzie mogliby) napotkać dzikie bawoły i drapieżne tygrysy.
Przystępując do walki, nie zabierają ze sobą zbroi ani oręża.
Dziki bawół nie ma więc w kogo wbić swych rogów,
Drapieżny tygrys nie ma w kogo wczepić swoich pazurów.
Przeciwnik nie ma z kim skrzyżować swej broni.
Dlaczego tak jest?
Ponieważ (dzięki swojej postawie życiowej) nie znajduje się on w polu śmierci.

Tao sprawia, że (wszystkie rzeczy) się rodzą.
(Cnota) te sprawia, że się rozwijają i mnożą.
(Inne) rzeczy użyczają im określonych kształtów,
(A przenikające je przeciwstawne) siły sprawiają, że osiągają one pełnię rozwoju.
Dlatego pośród dziesiątków tysięcy (istot i) rzeczy nie ma takiej, która by nie czciła tao i nie ceniła nade wszystko (cnoty) te.
(Bezgraniczna) cześć, jaką otaczane jest tao,
(Niewyobrażalna) wartość, jaką wiąże się z (cnotą) te,
Nie wynikają z (czyichkolwiek) nakazów, lecz (odwiecznie) niezmiennie same przez się są takie.
Dlatego, że
Tao je rodzi,
(Cnota) te rozwija i rozmnaża,
Sprawia, że rosną, że wydają potomstwo,
Że zawiązują owoce, że dojrzewają.
Karmi je i osłania je.
Zrodzić (tysiące rzeczy), lecz nie uważać ich za swoją własność,
Sprawiać (że tysiące rzeczy się rozwijają) i nie (uważać), że się dokonało olbrzymiego wysiłku,
Przewodzić (tysiącom rzeczy), lecz nie sprawować nad nimi władzy,
Oto jest to, co nazywamy najgłębszym i najbardziej tajemniczym przejawem (cnoty) te.

(Wszystko, co istnieje na ziemi) pod niebem, ma swój początek.
Uważa się go za matkę (wszystkich rzeczy) pod niebem.
Dopiero posiadłszy (wiedzę) o matce, można poznać jej dzieci.
Jeśli poznawszy jej dzieci, (człowiek) nadal trzyma się (powszechnych praw przyrody, zgromadzonych w ich) matce, do końca życia swego nie znajdzie się w niebezpieczeństwie.
Zatkajcie wszystkie otwory ciała swego, zamknijcie wszystkie wejścia do niego, a do końca (istnienia) ciała waszego (z sił) nie opadniecie.
Otwórzcie wszystkie otwory ciała waszego, działajcie dla spełniania waszych pragnień, a do końca (istnienia) ciała waszego, nie znajdziecie dla siebie ratunku.
Zdolność dostrzegania rzeczy drobnych nazywamy jasnym (doskonałym) wzrokiem.
Zdolność zachowania w sobie słabości nazywamy (prawdziwą) silą.
Wykorzystanie blasku (wiedzy) pozwala wrócić (do świata rzeczy) jasnych i (słabych).
A wtedy (człowiek) nie wystawi swego ciała na żadne niebezpieczeństwo.
Oto, co nazywamy ćwiczeniem się (w dostosowywaniu) do niezmiennych (praw natury).

Gdybym naprawdę posiadł wiedzę (o tao), zawsze bym kroczył wielką droga (jej zasad), i tylko (możliwość) zboczenia z niej byłaby jedynym źródłem moich obaw.
Wielka droga (tao) jest (szeroka) i równa, ale lud lubi chodzić (bocznymi) ścieżkami.
Dwór książęcy świeci czystością i porządkiem,
A pola chłopskie chwasty i zielsko porasta.
Spichrze zaś ciemną pustką zieją.
Władcy wdzieli szaty barwne i wzorzyste.
Ostre miecze przytroczyli u pasa.
Obżarstwu ich i pijaństwu nie ma granic.
(W pałacach) zgromadzili niezliczone skarby z kamieni i złota.
My to nazywamy grabieżą i przepychem.
Niewątpliwie jest to sprzeczne z zasadami tao.

Nie można wyrwać tego, co jest dobrze osadzone.
Nie można oderwać tego, co mocno ramionami objęte.
(Dlatego dobrze na tych zasadach wychowani) synowie i wnukowie nigdy nie zaprzestają składania ofiar na ołtarzach przodków.
Jeśli tę zasadę człowiek będzie kultywował w sobie samym, wówczas jego cnotą będzie „prawdziwość”.
Jeśli będzie ją kultywował we własnej rodzinie, wówczas jego cnota przejawi się w postaci obfitości,
Jeśli będzie ją kultywował we własnym siole, wówczas jego cnota przejawi się jako trwałość,
Jeśli będzie ją kultywował we własnym kraju, wówczas jego cnota przejawi się jako dobrobyt,
Jeśli będzie ją kultywował (w całym świecie) pod niebem, wówczas cnota jego przejawi się jako powszechność.
Dlatego
Człowiek patrzy na innych z punktu widzenia własnej osoby,
Patrzy na inne rodziny z punktu widzenia własnej rodziny,
Patrzy na inne sioła z punktu widzenia własnego sioła,
Patrzy na inne kraje z punktu widzenia własnego kraju,
Patrzy na świat z punktu widzenia całego świata.
Skąd wiem, że tak właśnie jest (na świecie) pod niebem?
Właśnie na podstawie tego (rozumowania).

(Człowieka) posiadającego nagromadzoną cnotę (te) w znacznej ilości (można) przyrównać do niemowlęcia, (które nie posiada) jeszcze wiedzy i pragnień).
A przecież jadowite owady i gady go nie pokąsają, straszliwe bestie go nie rozszarpią, ani drapieżne ptactwo go w szpony nie porwie.
Kości ma słabe, mięśnie wiotkie, a mimo to mocno trzyma w dłoniach (to, co uchwycił).
Chociaż nic jeszcze nie wie o połączeniu męskiego i żeńskiego, jego członek często jest wzniesiony. A to dlatego, że cudowna esencja życia osiąga w nim najwyższy (poziom).
Może on przez cały dzień krzyczeć, a mimo to nie ochrypnie. Jest tak dlatego, ponieważ naturalna harmonia (pierwotnych sił w nim osiąga w tym czasie) doskonałość.
Poznając zasadę harmonii (sił in i jang) potrafimy zrozumieć niezmienne (prawo tao).
Potrafiąc zrozumieć niezmienne (prawo tao), zdobywamy jasność wiedzy.
Zabiegając o upiększenie i przedłużenie naszego życia, ściągamy na siebie nieszczęście.
Pragnieniami wpływając na (zachwianie) równowagi (naszych sil witalnych), zadajemy (swojej naturze) gwałt.
Wszystkie istoty, gdy osiągną dojrzałość, zaczynają się starzeć. (A więc powyższe zabiegi) nazywamy sprzecznymi z (prawami) tao.
A to co jest sprzeczne z (prawami) tao, wcześniej osiągnie kres (swego istnienia).

Ci, którzy znają (zasady tao), nie rozpowiadają (o nich na wszystkie strony).
Ci, którzy rozpowiadają (o zasadach tao na wszystkie strony), (na pewno ich) nie znają.
(Ten, co poznał zasady tao), zatyka wszystkie otwory swego ciała, zamyka wszystkie wejścia do niego, stępia ostrość (swego umysłu), rozplątuje i odrzuca (krępujące go) więzy (pragnień), dostosowuje odpowiednio blask (swego umysłu), utożsamia się z nic nie znaczącym pyłem (drogi, po której wszyscy stąpają).
To wszystko nazywamy (osiągnięciem) cudownego utożsamienia się (z naturą).
Dlatego
Me można osiągnąć tego, żeby stał się on człowiekiem (nam) bliskim.
Nie można osiągnąć tego, żeby stał się człowiekiem dalekim (pogardzanym, takim, którego los nas nie obchodzi).
Nie można osiągnąć tego, żeby zdobył on jakieś korzyści.
Nie można osiągnąć tego, żeby doznawał cierpień.
Nie można osiągnąć tego, żeby czuł się szanowany i czczony.
Nie można osiągnąć tego, żeby czul się zhańbiony i poniżony.
Właśnie dlatego uznawany jest on za najczcigodniejszego (człowieka na świecie) pod niebem.

W państwie można ład utrzymać za pomocą prawa.
Wojska (ku zwycięstwu) można prowadzić za pomocą niezwykłych (strategii).
Ale (świat) pod niebem można zdobyć tylko przez niedziałanie.
Skąd mi wiadomo, że tak właśnie jest?
A to dlatego, że:
Im więcej na świecie będzie zakazów, w tym głębszej nędzy ludzie żyć będą.
Im więcej użytecznych narzędzi lud posiadać będzie, w tym większym chaosie kraj się pogrąży.
Im więcej będzie zręcznych rzemieślników, tym częściej wymyślne (niezgodne z naturą człowieka) przedmioty pojawiać się będą.
Im więcej praw i nakazów się ukaże, tym więcej będzie rabusiów i złodziei.
Dlatego święty Mędrzec rzecze:
Jeśli nie będę podejmował żadnego działania, lud sam (zgodnie ze swoją naturą) będzie się rozwijał.
Jeśli umiłuję spokój, lud sam (zgodnie ze swoją naturą) będzie żył statecznie.
Jeśli nic czynić nie będę, lud sam (zgodnie ze swoja, naturą) poczuje się bogatym.
Jeśli nie będę miał żadnych pragnień, lud sam (zgodnie ze swoją naturą) zachowa wrodzoną, (niczym nie skażoną prostotę).

Jeśli rządy (w kraju) polegać będą na przyzwalającym niedziałaniu,
Wówczas lud będzie żył w prostocie i lojalności.
Jeżeli rządy (w kraju) sprowadzać się będą do działania (ustalającego normy i zakazy),
Wówczas lud będzie się uciekał do sprytu i podstępu.
O, nieszczęście! Jesteś szczęścia opoką.
O, szczęście! Jesteś nieszczęścia kryjówką.
Któż zna krańce waszej (istoty)?
Czy rzeczywiście nie istnieją (niezmienne) zasady,
I to, co zwykłe, przemienia się w niezwykłe, a dobro w zło?
Lud z tego powodu błądzi (w niewiedzy) od niezliczonych dni.
Dlatego święty Mędrzec jest otwarty i szczery, ale nie jest w tym nienaturalny.
Jest ostry i kanciasty, ale nie rani przez to (innych ludzi).
Jest prostolinijny i uczciwy, ale nie popada w tym w przesadę.
Błyszczy blaskiem (swej wiedzy o tao), ale nie razi (w oczy innych ludzi).

W rządzeniu ludźmi i służeniu niebu (tu: własnym naturalnym skłonnościom) nie ma nic ważniejszego nad powściągliwość.
Powściągliwość oznacza wczesne podporządkowanie się (zasadom tao).
Wczesne podporządkowanie się (zasadom tao) oznacza wielokrotne nagromadzenie (cnoty) te.
Jeśli człowiek wielokrotnie nagromadzi (cnotę) te, wówczas nie będzie niczego, czego by nie mógł pokonać.
Jeśli nie będzie niczego, czego by nie mógł pokonać, nikt nie będzie znał granic jego (możliwości).
Jeśli nikt nie będzie znał granic jego (możliwości), wówczas będzie on mógł mieć państwo (w swoim władaniu).
(Poznawszy) matkę (podstawową zasadę) posiadania państwa, można (nim władać) bardzo długo.
Nazywamy to głębokim korzeniem i mocną podstawą, (główną) drogą wiodącą do długiego życia i trwania przez wieki.

Rządzenie wielkim państwem podobne jest smażeniu małych ryb, (których nie należy zbyt często poruszać i przewracać, żeby się nie rozleciały).
Jeśli (władca) rządzi (państwem) pod niebem zgodnie z (zasadami) tao, wówczas (złe) duchy (zmarłych) się nie pojawiają.
(Złe) duchy (zmarłych) nie tylko się nie pojawiają, ale nawet swym pojawieniem nie mogłyby zaszkodzić ludziom.
Nie tylko (złe) duchy (zmarłych) nie szkodzą ludziom, ale święty Mędrzec (tao wyznający) również ludziom nie wyrządza krzywdy.
Jedni i drudzy (duchy i ludzie oraz mędrzec i ludzie) wzajemnie sobie nie szkodzą i dlatego ich (cnota) te, łącząc się, prowadzi ich ku wspólnemu celowi.

Jeśli wielkie państwo płynie z prądem ustępstw, staje się miejscem spotkania całego świata.
(Jest jak gdyby uosobieniem) żeńskiej (bierności całego świata) pod niebem.
A samica zawsze swoją biernością (uległością) zwycięża samca. Z bierności i spokoju bierze się uległość.
Dlatego wielkie państwa stosują, (zasadę) uległości w stosunku do małych państw i w ten sposób pozyskują małe państwa.
Małe państwa stosują (zasadę) uległości w stosunku do wielkich państw i dlatego pozyskują wielkie państwa.
W ten sposób jedne państwa pozyskują inne przez to, że stają się (w stosunku do nich ulegle), a inne pozyskują je przez to, że są uległe.
Wielkie państwa pragną tylko ludzi jednoczyć i karmić.
Małe państwa pragną tylko oddać się pod władanie (opiekę) innych i im służyć.
Aby i jedne, i drugie (wielkie i małe państwa) osiągnęły cel swoich pragnień, wielkie (państwa) powinny ulegać (małym państwom).

Tao jest ukrytym (celem, ku któremu zmierza) dziesięć tysięcy istot, jest klejnotem ludzi dobrych i schronieniem ludzi niedobrych.
Pięknymi słowy można kupić (u ludzi szacunek).
Wspaniałym zachowaniem można się wywyższyć ponad innych.
Są ludzie niedobrzy (w przestrzeganiu norm postępowania, narzuconych im przez społeczeństwo), ale dlaczego (wszyscy) się od nich odsuwają? Natomiast obierają sobie (władcę, tak zwanego) syna nieba i ustanawiają mu do pomocy trzech Wielkich ministrów.
Chociaż w dłoniach trzymają berła oraz jeżdżą na przedzie w czterokonnych (zaprzęgach), czyż nie lepiej by dla nich było, żeby (w spokoju) usiedli i wkroczyli w (krainę tajemnic) tao?
Czyż nie powiedziano, że ten, co za pomocą tao pragnie coś zdobyć, osiąga to, a ten, co zbrodnię popełni; dzięki niemu (to jest dzięki tao) unika kary?
Właśnie dlatego tao jest tak (wysoko) cenione (w całym świecie) pod niebem.

Czyń poprzez nieczynienie niczego.
Działaj nie uciekając się do działania.
Znajduj smak w rzeczach bez smaku.
(Uważaj rzeczy) małe za wielkie.
A liczebne za nieliczne.
Odpłacaj nienawiść (dobrocią) twej cnoty.
Staraj się pokonywać trudności wtedy, gdy są łatwe do pokonania.
Czyniąc rzeczy wielkie, zaczynaj od rzeczy drobnych. (Bowiem).
Żeby dokonać rzeczy najtrudniejszych na świecie, należy zaczynać od rzeczy najłatwiejszych.
Żeby dokonać największych rzeczy na świecie, należy rozpocząć od rzeczy drobnych.
Dlatego święty (Mędrzec) przez cale życie nie czyni nic wielkiego, i właśnie dlatego zdolny jest stać się wielkim.
Ten, co z łatwością ze wszystkim się zgadza, z pewnością niewielkim zaufaniem cieszyć się będzie u ludzi.
Ten, dla którego wszystko wydaje się łatwe, z pewnością napotka wiele trudności w życiu.
Dlatego święty (Mędrzec) nawet rzeczy łatwe traktując jakby były trudne, do końca (życia) nie napotyka żadnych trudności.

Łatwo sobie poradzić z czymś, co spoczywa w spokoju.
Łatwo spiskować przeciwko czemuś, co się jeszcze nie ujawniło.
Łatwo złamać to, co jest kruche.
Łatwo rozproszyć to, co jest wątłe.
Trzeba działać, zanim coś zaistnieje.
A wydawać zarządzenia przed powstaniem zamieszek.
Grube drzewo (które ledwo można objąć ramionami), wyrasta z cienkiego jak włos pędu.
Dziewięciostopniowy taras wyrasta z nieznacznego wzniesienia.
Tysiącmilowa podróż rozpoczyna się z pierwszego kroku.
Ci, którzy działają, ponoszą porażkę.
Ci, którzy (coś mocno) trzymają, tracą to.
Dlatego
Ponieważ święty (mędrzec) nie oddaje się działaniu, więc nie doznaje porażek.
Ponieważ (niczego mocno) nie trzyma, więc niczego nie traci.
Ludzie, którzy zajmują się jakimiś sprawami, często przez dążenie do ich szybkiego i pomyślnego zakończenia doznają niepowodzenia.
Jeśli do tego, co robią, przywiązują taką samą uwagę na końcu jak na początku, wówczas w sprawach którymi się zajmują, nie ucierpią niepowodzenia.
Dlatego
Święty (mędrzec) nie posiada żadnych pragnień i nie ceni rzeczy, które trudno jest zdobyć.
Uczy się (obywania się) bez przyswajania sobie wiedzy i zwraca się ku rzeczom, które wszyscy (inni ludzie) omijają (nie zwracają na nie uwagi).
Dzięki temu dostosowuje się on do naturalnych (właściwości) dziesięciu tysięcy istot, lecz sam nie odważa się na (sprzeczne z jego naturą) działanie.

W starożytności wszyscy, którzy potrafili (w życiu) stosować zasady tao, nie wykorzystywali swojej (tajemnej wiedzy), by oświecać lud, lecz raczej, by go trzymać w niewiedzy.
Ludem wtedy jest trudno rządzić, gdy mu się daje zbyt dużą wiedzę.
Dlatego
Ten, kto krajem rządzi za pomocą wiedzy, jest jako złoczyńca dla kraju.
Ten, kto nie rządzi krajem za pomocą wiedzy, jest dobroczyńcą dla kraju.
Znajomość tych dwóch (rzeczy, rządzenia za pomocą wiedzy i bez niej) jest ważną zasadą (postępowania zgodnego z tao).
Pamiętanie we wszystkich okolicznościach o tej zasadzie nazywamy Tajemniczą Cnotą (te).
Jest ona przeciwieństwem wszystkich (konkretnych) istot i rzeczy.
Dopiero później osiąga ona wielką zgodność z nimi.

Wielkie rzeki i morza mogą się stać władcami stu dolin dzięki temu, że potrafią się znajdować poniżej nich.
Właśnie dlatego mogą się stać władcami stu dolin.
Dlatego
Jeśli święty (mędrzec) pragnie zgodnie (z tą zasadą) znaleźć się nad ludem, powinien przynajmniej w słowach znaleźć się pod nim.
Jeśli pragnie się znaleźć na czele ludu, powinien siebie samego umieścić z tyłu (za ludem).
Dlatego
Święty (mędrzec) znajduje się ponad (ludem), ale lud nie (odczuwa) jego ciężaru.
Święty (mędrzec) znajduje się na przedzie, ale lud nie czuje się przez to urażony.
Dlatego
(Wszyscy na ziemi) pod niebem z radością będą go popychać, (wysuwać) do przodu i nigdy nie będą mieli go dość.
Ponieważ
Święty (mędrzec) sam o nic nie zabiega, a więc (na świecie) pod niebem nie znajdzie się nikt, kto by mógł z nim rywalizować.

(Wszyscy na świecie) pod niebem mówią o moim tao, że jest wielkie, a przy tym, jak gdyby niepodobne (do wszystkich innych napotykanych na co dzień zjawisk).
Właśnie dlatego, że jest wielkie, jest jak gdyby niepodobne (do rzeczy codziennie napotykanych).
Gdyby było podobne (do zwykłych, codziennych zjawisk), dawno już by się stało drobne, niewielkie.
Mam trzy klejnoty. Strzegę ich i osłaniam.
Pierwszy to miłosierdzie.
Drugi to umiarkowanie.
Trzeci polega na tym, że nie ośmielam się wyjść przed (innych ludzi na świecie) pod niebem.
Jestem miłosierny, a więc (dzięki temu) potrafię być mężny.
Zachowuję umiar, a więc (dzięki temu) potrafię być hojny.
Nie ośmielam się wychodzić przed (innych ludzi na świecie) pod niebem, a więc (dzięki temu) mogę zostać przywódcą wszystkich naczyń (dostojników państwowych).
Jeżeli dzisiaj
Odrzuca się miłosierdzie a okazuje tylko męstwo,
Odrzuca się umiarkowanie a okazuje się tylko hojność,
Odrzuca się możliwość pozostania w tyle, a dąży się tylko do tego, by się znaleźć na przedzie,
Prowadzi to do śmierci.
O, miłosierdzie,
Kto z twoją pomocą walczy, ten zwycięża.
Kto z twoją pomocą się broni, ten pozostaje nienaruszony.
Kogo niebo chce uratować, tego osłania za pomocą miłosierdzia.

Doskonały rycerz nie bywa wojowniczy,
Dobry wojownik nie popada w gniew,
Ten, kto potrafi zwyciężać przeciwników, sam ich nie zaczepia.
Ten, kto potrafi kierować ludźmi, stawia siebie niżej od nich.
Można to wszystko nazwać cnotą niezabiegania o nic.
Jest to także moc wynikająca z umiejętności kierowania ludźmi. Możemy to nazwać najwyższym dostosowaniem się do (praw) nieba (natury) oraz do najstarszego (prapoczątku).[18]

Starożytni dowódcy często mawiali:
Lepiej się bronić niż atakować.
Lepiej cofnąć się o stopę aniżeli na cal pójść naprzód.
Oto jest to, co nazywamy:
Pochodem (wojennym) bez maszerowania,
Zawijaniem rękawów (do walki), chociaż się nie ma ramion.
Atakowaniem, chociaż nie widać przeciwnika,
Wydobywaniem z pochwy miecza, mimo że się go nie posiada.
Nie ma większego nieszczęścia nad lekceważenie przeciwnika.
Lekceważąc przeciwnika, ryzykuję utratę moich (trzech) klejnotów.
Dlatego:
Gdy broń przeciwników się skrzyżuje.
Zwycięży ten z nich, który (niechętnie) z bólem w sercu (do walki staje).

Moje słowa można z wielką łatwością zrozumieć i z wielką łatwością zgodnie z nimi postępować.
Ale (na całym świecie) pod niebem nie ma nikogo, kto by potrafił je zrozumieć i kto by potrafił zgodnie z nimi postępować.
Moje słowa są (podporządkowane) jednemu panu (systemowi).
Moje czyny są (podporządkowane) jednemu przodkowi (głównej zasadzie).
Zaiste, właśnie dlatego, (że ludzie tej prawdy) nie rozumieją, nie potrafią także mnie zrozumieć.
Niewielu jest takich, co potrafią mnie pojąć.
Ci, którzy obierają mnie sobie za wzór (do naśladowania), są w wielkiej cenie.
Tak więc święty (mędrzec) odziewa się w zgrzebne płótno, ale w piersiach kryje drogocenny nefryt.

Wiedzieć, że się (nic) nie wie, to jest szczyt (wiedzy).
A niewiedzę uznawać za wiedzę, to jest choroba.
Zaiste.
Tylko wtedy, gdy człowiek traktuje chorobę jako chorobę, przestaje być chory.
Święty (mędrzec) nie jest chory, ponieważ zdaje sobie sprawę, że jego choroba jest chorobą.
Właśnie dlatego nie jest on chory.

Jeśli lud nie boi się przemocy, wtedy nadchodzi czas, że wielka przemoc na niego spada.
Nie niszczcie jednak jego siedlisk.
Nie pogardzajcie jego życiem.
Zaiste.
Kto nie będzie pogardzał ludem,
Ten przez to nie znajdzie się w pogardzie u ludu.
Dlatego święty (mędrzec) zna siebie, ale nie daje się widzieć (nie demonstruje wszędzie swojej wielkości).
Troszczy się o siebie, ale siebie nie ceni.
Dlatego odrzuca on to (drugie), a wybiera tamto (pierwsze).

Kto się odważa na śmiałość, ginie.
Kto się odważa na nieśmiałość, żyje.
Spośród tych dwóch (rodzajów odwagi), jeden przynosi korzyść, a drugi przynosi szkodę.
Niebo (pewnych rzeczy) nienawidzi. Kto jednak może znać przyczynę (tej nienawiści)?
Również dla świętego (mędrca) jak gdyby przedstawia to trudność.
Tao (główna zasada) nieba (polega na tym), że
Nie walczy, a jednak odnosi zwycięstwo,
Nie wypowiada słów, a jednak udziela odpowiedzi,
Nie wzywa, a jednak (sprawia, że rzeczy) same przychodzą.
Jest powolne, a jednak potrafi kierować (wszystkim).
Sieć nieba jest rzadka i chociaż oka jej są (duże) i oddalone od siebie, nic jej nie umyka.

Jeśli lud nie boi się śmierci, po co straszyć go śmiercią.
Gdyby ktoś chciał doprowadzić do tego, by ludzie bali się śmierci i (ze strachu przed śmiercią) dokonywali czynów nienaturalnych (sprzecznych z ich naturą), chwyciłbym kogoś takiego i zabił.
Kto jednak by się na to odważył?
Zawsze kat jest tym, co zadaje śmierć.
Jeśli ktoś, zastępując kata, zadaje śmierć, to można o nim powiedzieć, że zastępując wielkiego drwala (tu: prawa tao), rąbie (toporem).
A jeśli ktoś, wyręczając wielkiego drwala, rąbie (toporem), do rzadkości (zaliczyć trzeba będzie wypadki), kiedy taki nie porani sobie rąk.

Jeżeli lud głoduje, to dlatego, że możni ściągają z niego zbyt wielkie podatki.
Dlatego właśnie (lud) głoduje.
Jeżeli ludem trudno jest rządzić, to dlatego, że możni dopuszczają się różnych (form) działania (krępując naturę ludu zakazami i nakazami).
Dlatego właśnie (ludem) trudno jest rządzić.
Jeżeli lud lekko traktuje śmierć, to dlatego, że stara się jak najwięcej (radości) zaczerpnąć z życia (i nie mącić tej radości obawami przed śmiercią i zabiegami o przedłużenie życia).
Dlatego właśnie (lud) lekko traktuje śmierć.
Zaiste.
Ten, co nie podejmuje żadnych działań, aby (przedłużyć swoje) życie, jest mądrzejszy od tych, co cenią (swoje) życie (i dokonują różnych czynów, żeby je przedłużyć).

Człowiek rodzi się miękki i słaby,
A umiera twardy i mocny.
Dziesiątki tysięcy (istot i) rzeczy, trawy i drzewa rodzą się miękkie i kruche.
A gdy umierają, stają się suche i sztywne.
Dlatego,
To, co jest twarde i mocne, dąży ku śmierci.
To, co jest miękkie i słabe, kroczy ku życiu.
Dlatego,
Jeżeli oręż jest zbyt sztywny, to ulega zniszczeniu.
Jeżeli drzewo jest zbyt sztywne, to zostaje złamane.
To, co twarde i mocne, stawiamy niżej.
To, co miękkie i słabe, stawiamy wyżej.

Czyż tao niebios nie jest podobne do naciągania łuku (z wycelowaną strzałą)?
Jeżeli wysoko (w górę mierzymy), wówczas cięciwę w dół odciągamy.
Jeżeli nisko (w dół celujemy), wówczas cięciwę w górę przyciągamy.
Jeżeli nadmiernie (ją naciągnęliśmy), zmniejszamy trochę (naciągnięcia).
Jeśli niedostatecznie (naciągnęliśmy), zwiększamy trochę (naciągnięcie).
Jeśli niedostatecznie (naciągnęliśmy), uzupełniamy trochę (zwiększamy) trochę (naciągnięcie).
Tao niebios (jest właśnie takie).
Samo zmniejsza nadmiar (naciągnięcia) i uzupełnia niedostatek.
Tao ludzi natomiast nie jest takie.
Zmniejszają jeszcze bardziej tam, gdzie jest niedostatek, aby zwiększyć tam, gdzie jest nadmiar.
Kto potrafi nadmiar tego, co posiada, zaofiarować (całemu światu) pod niebem?
Potrafią tego dokonać tylko ci, co posiedli tao.
Dlatego święty (mędrzec) działa, ale nie przypisuje sobie (żadnych) zasług.
Nie pragnie, by dostrzegano jego mądrość.

Nie ma na świecie nic bardziej słabego i miękkiego od wody, a jednak w pokonywaniu twardego i mocnego nic nie może jej dorównać.
Nie istnieje też nic takiego, co by mogło ją zastąpić.
To, co słabe, zwycięża to, co mocne.
To, co miękkie, pokonuje twarde.
(Na świecie) pod niebem nie ma nikogo, kto by o tym nie wiedział.
A jednak, nikt nie potrafi stosować (tego prawa natury w życiu).
Dlatego święci (mędrcy) powiadają:
Ten, co nosi na sobie hańbę i wstyd całego kraju, uważany jest za prawdziwego pana tego kraju.
Ten, co bierze na siebie wszystkie klęski i nieszczęścia całego kraju, uważany jest za prawdziwego władcę tego kraju.
(Tak więc)
Oczywiste słowa (prawdy) wydają się paradoksalne.

Chociaż wielki żal można ukoić, jednakże na pewno resztki tego żalu pozostaną.
A więc co należałoby zrobić, żeby było dobrze?
Dlatego
Święty (mędrzec) chociaż ma w ręku dowód (należności, pożyczki), nie zmusza ludzi do jej (natychmiastowego) zwrotu.
Ludzie, którzy posiedli (cnotę) te, są wyrozumiali jak człowiek posiadający dowód (pożyczki).
Ludzie, którzy nie posiadają (cnoty) te, są bezwzględni jak ten, co sprawuje nadzór nad ściąganiem podatków i grzywien.
Tao nieba (traktuje wszystkich ludzi jednakowo) i nie ma wśród ludzi osób bliskich i krewnych.
Zawsze wspiera ludzi dobrych (podporządkowujących się zasadom tao).

Państwa powinny być niewielkie a ludzi w nich mało.
Nawet gdyby istniały różnorakie narzędzia, nie należy z nich korzystać.
Trzeba sprawiać, by lud z całą powagą traktował śmierć i nie oddalał się bardzo od swoich siedzib.
Chociaż byłyby łodzie i wozy, należy sprawić, by nie było niczego, co by można nimi przewozić.
Chociaż byłyby zbroje i oręż (ostry), (należy sprawić) by nie było możliwości zrobienia z nich użytku.
Należy doprowadzić do takiego stanu, by ludzie znów zawiązywali supły na sznurach (jako rodzaj pierwotnego pisma) i stosowali je, delektowali się przygotowanym przez siebie pożywieniem, zachwycali się uszytymi przez siebie strojami, by w spokoju żyli w swoich domostwach, znajdowali przyjemność w kultywowaniu swoich pradawnych obrzędów.
Należy doprowadzić do takiego stanu, że nawet gdyby sąsiedni kraj znajdował się w zasięgu wzroku, gdyby szczekanie psów i pianie kogutów (z sąsiedniego kraju) dobiegało codziennie ich uszu, to ludzie ci, aż do swojej śmierci nigdy by tam ze swoich siedzib się nie wyprawili.

Słowa prawdy nie są piękne, a słowa piękne nie są słowami prawdy.
Ludzie dobrzy nie uczestniczą w (zawiłych, lecz powierzchownych) dysputach.
Ci, którzy uczestniczą w dysputach, nie są dobrzy.
Ci, którzy posiadają wiedzę, nie popisują się nią.
Ci, którzy się swoją wiedzą popisują, nie posiadają jej.
Święty (mędrzec) niczego nie gromadzi.
Jeśli ze wszystkich sił ludziom pomaga, sam przez to ma jeszcze więcej.
Tao niebios przynosi korzyść (dziesięciu tysiącom istot i rzeczy) i nie wyrządza im szkody.
Tao świętego (mędrca) (polega na tym), że we wszystkim co robi z nikim nie walczy.

Prawie wszystko o Tao

Tao jest jednym z najstarszych pojęć wśród chińskich poglądów na istnienie świata i życia. Chociaż tylko jedna szkoła myślenia – taoizm – wzięła od niego swą nazwę, pojęcie to znane było w Chinach co najmniej kilka wieków wcześniej, a następnie wykorzystywane też w odrębnych znaczeniach przez wiele innych szkół filozoficznych, jakie w połowie pierwszego tysiąclecia przed naszą erą pojawiły się w Chinach.

Najstarsze zaświadczenie znaku tao odnajdujemy w napisach na kościach wróżebnych oraz w inskrypcjach na naczyniach z brązu z końca XI wieku p.n.e. Chińscy paleografowie stwierdzają, iż znak ten przedstawiał człowieka z narzuconym na głowę krajem szaty, starającego się ukryć przed wzrokiem innych ludzi. Znak ten miał pierwotnie oznaczać zbója, czyhającego przy drodze na przejeżdżających kupców.

Objaśnienie to jednak, jak się wydaje, należy bardziej do sfery domysłów opartych na dawnej strukturze tego znaku, ponieważ nie zostało zilustrowane konkretnymi przykładami, chociaż jak wiadomo, nie wszystkie fragmenty wspomnianych wyżej inskrypcji udało się do dziś odczytać. Znane są jednak użycia znaku tao już w dość wczesnych tekstach Księgi Dokumentów i Księgi Pieśni, pochodzących z pierwszej połowy I-go tysiąclecia p.n.e. Znak ten w tych tekstach przybrał już formę, która z niewielkimi modyfikacjami wynikającymi ze zmiany przyborów do pisania, stosowana jest do dzisiaj i przedstawia element „głowy” połączony z elementem graficznym, oznaczającym „iść”, „przechodzić”. Znaczenie tego ideogramu zostało objaśnione w najstarszym słowniku chińskim (około 100 rok n.e.) jako „droga, po której się chodzi”, natomiast najobszerniejszy słownik znaków pisma chińskiego z początków naszego stulecia wymienia ponad pięćdziesiąt różnych znaczeń tego słowa.

Oczywiście, nie będziemy tu analizować wszystkich znaczeń, w jakich ten znak występował. Sądzimy jednak, że warto zaprezentować najważniejsze z nich, jakie spotykamy w tekstach z czasów, kiedy przypuszczalnie powstawała podstawowa księga kanonu taoistycznego, Tao-te-king, zwana też Lao-tsy od imienia jej prawdopodobnego twórcy.

Stosunkowo najwcześniej, bo we wspomnianej Księdze Pieśni wyraz tao występuje w znaczeniach „droga”, „ścieżka” oraz „metoda”, „sposób”. Około VI-V wieku p.n.e. w Dialogach konfucjańskich, przypisywanych Konfucjuszowi (551-479 rok p.n.e.) pojawia się to słowo w znaczeniu „zasada”, „zbiór zasad moralnych”. Mniej więcej w tym samym czasie używane jest one również w znaczeniu „prowadzić”, „pokazywać drogę”, a na początku III wieku p.n.e. występuje ono jeszcze w dwóch nowych znaczeniach. W księdze Etykiety jako „wyjaśniać”, „objaśniać”, a u kontynuatora myśli konfucjańskiej, Mencjusza (372-289 rok p.n.e.) jako „mówić”, „wyrażać w słowach”.

To wyliczenie najwcześniejszych znaczeń słowa tao zostało tu zamieszczone co najmniej z dwóch powodów. Z jednej strony, przy dodatkowym założeniu, iż w klasycznym języku chińskim praktycznie prawie każde słowo, a więc i tao, mogło występować w funkcji dowolnej części mowy, a więc jako czasownik, rzeczownik, przymiotnik, przysłówek czy nawet grupa składniowa, chcieliśmy pokazać, z jakimi trudnościami boryka się tłumacz wczesnochińskiego tekstu. Z drugiej zaś strony pragnęliśmy zwrócić uwagę na fakt, iż niekiedy użycie w tekście określonego słowa w określonym znaczeniu pozwala na przybliżone datowanie danego tekstu.

Ta druga uwaga dotyczy również kwestii datowania Tao-te-kingu. Zwyczajowo bowiem uważano, że jego autor, Lao-tsy był starszym współcześnikiem Konfucjusza i żył w VI wieku p.n.e. Tymczasem już pierwsze zdanie Tao-te-kingu zawiera słowo tao, tradycyjnie interpretowane jako „mówić, wyrażać słowami”, co jako że w tym znaczeniu pojawiło się ono dopiero w III wieku p.n.e., stanowi jeden z argumentów na rzecz późniejszego datowania tego dzieła i przeciwko autorstwu Lao-tsy’ego.

Dla zilustrowania, jak prosty i zwięzły, a jednocześnie jak skomplikowany i dopuszczający różne interpretacje jest tekst Tao-te-kingu, przeanalizujemy jego pierwsze zdanie. Składa się ono z sześciu zgłosek-wyrazów: Tao k’o tao jei cz’ang tao.

W klasycznych, tradycyjnie wydawanych tekstach chińskich nie stosowano żadnych znaków interpunkcyjnych, a podział tekstu na mniejsze jednostki wprowadzony był przez późniejszych badaczy i komentatorów, przy czym nie zawsze byli oni zgodni, co dodatkowo pozwalało na różne interpretacje dzieła. Najważniejsze znaczenia tao wymieniliśmy powyżej. K’o znaczy „móc”, jei – „nie”, cz’ang – „stały, niezmienny”. Tłumaczenie drugiej części zdania jako „nie jest niezmiennym tao” w zasadzie u nikogo nie budzi większych zastrzeżeń, chociaż wyraz cz’ang przez niektórych tłumaczy oddawany był jako „wieczny, odwieczny”, a zwrot cz’ang-tao we współczesnej chińszczyźnie może też oznaczać „zwykły bieg wypadków”, natomiast interpretacja pierwszych trzech wyrazów, a zwłaszcza trzeciego była przedmiotem pewnych kontrowersji. Przetłumaczyliśmy je jako „Tao, które można wyrazić słowami”, tak jak oddaje się je w większości interpretacji uczonych chińskich i europejskich, chociaż możliwe jest również tłumaczenie „Tao (droga), którą można używać jako drogę nie jest owym niezmiennym tao”. Przy drugiej wersji tłumaczenia nie powstałaby wątpliwość co do pochodzenia danego tekstu z VI wieku p.n.e.

Jak wspomnieliśmy wyżej, termin tao pojawia się niemal we wszystkich systemach filozoficznych starożytnych Chin. Spotykamy go również w systemie konfucjańskim. W tekstach przedkonfucjańskich wyraz ten znaczy „droga, ścieżka”, bądź „prowadzić, kierować”. Natomiast w Dialogach konfucjańskich przybiera jeszcze nowe znaczenie – „sposób działania”, „zasada postępowania”. Spotykamy go na określenie postępowania słusznego, sprawiedliwego, zgodnego z konfucjańskimi normami etycznymi. Po raz pierwszy, również u Konfucjusza, wyraz ten został użyty na oznaczenie jakiegoś powszechnego prawa, wyznaczającego zasady postępowania. Tao jest więc jakąś powszechną, ogólną zasadą, według której wszyscy, zarówno jednostki, państwa jak i cały świat powinni postępować. Gdy kraj jest rządzony zgodnie z tao, to przestrzega się tam zasad moralnych. Konfucjusz nigdy nie zdefiniował pojęcia tao. Z jego wypowiedzi jednak wynika, że rozumiał przez pojęcie tao pewne zasady moralne, zasady postępowania odpowiednie do pozycji zajmowanej w hierarchii społecznej, a w sumie dające wizję świata współpracującego, pozbawionego konfliktów, walk i wojen. Tao było wspólne dla całego świata, a jednocześnie istniały odrębne tao (to jest zbiory zasad) dla określonych warstw społecznych.

Istniało „tao nieba”, to znaczy, pewne zasady, regularności występowania zjawisk atmosferycznych, istniało „tao władcy”, składające na jego barki pewne rytualne czynności, mające w magiczny sposób zapewnić prawidłowość jego rządów, istniało też „tao człowieka szlachetnego (kun-tsy)”, który zdobył odpowiednią wiedzę w sprawach etykiety, pozwalającą mu właściwie postępować i zachowywać się zgodnie z zajmowaną pozycją społeczną.

Nauka Konfucjusza na przestrzeni wieków ulegała dalszemu rozwojowi. Również termin tao przyjmował coraz to nowe znaczenie. Oznaczano przezeń: nauki mistrza, porządek moralny, prawdę, zasady etyczne; Mencjusz (371-289 p.n.e.), kontynuator myśli konfucjańskiej, głosił, iż tao oznacza „wypełnienie praw naszej ludzkiej natury”, jest „ścieżką moralnego życia człowieka”. Znany konfucjanista i literat, Han Ju (767-824) stwierdzał, iż „postępowanie zgodne z (konfucjańskimi) zasadami humanitarności i sprawiedliwości nazywamy tao”.

Na przełomie XI i XII wieku konfucjanizm ewoluował w doktrynę określaną mianem neokonfucjanizmu. Neokonfucjaniści Cz’eng I (1033-1107) i Cz’eng Hao (1032-1085) uważali, że każda rzecz ma swoją „zasadę” (li), czyli swoje prawo (istnienia). Wszystkie te prawa są pod pewnymi względami jednolite i sprowadzają się do głównego prawa. Ponadto prawa te są wieczne i podczas gdy wszelkie rzeczy pojawiają się i giną, ich prawa, czyli zasady trwają niezmienione. Są one oderwane od rzeczy i niezależne. Twierdzili oni ponadto, że wszelkie zasady rzeczy łączą się w jedną podstawową zasadę i że tao jest właśnie tą podstawową zasadą. Według nich tao było też podstawą i źródłem dwóch sił in i jang (biernej i aktywnej), których wzajemne i przemienne oddziaływanie prowadziło do powstania wszystkich rzeczy.

Zdaniem Czang Tsai’ego (1020-1077) tao to wielki proces przemian materii. Identyfikował on też tao z Wielką Harmonią natury. Było ono dla niego niezmienną zasadą istnienia świata oraz ogólną sumą substancji i funkcji poszczególnych rzeczy.

Najwybitniejszym neokonfucjanistą był Czu Hi (1130-1200), który twierdził, iż tao jest „zasadą” (przyczyną), „dzięki której wszystkie rzeczy są tym, czym są”. Podczas gdy dla wcześniejszych neokonfucjanistów tao przejawiające się w działaniu in i jang było zbiorem idealnych wzorców rzeczy.

Wreszcie dla XVIII-wiecznego myśliciela konfucjańskiego, Tai Czena (1723-1777) tao przejawiało się w nieustannym przeobrażaniu wszechświata i ciągłych przemianach rzeczy w świecie przyrody, ich nieprzerwanej produkcji i reprodukcji.

Kultura chińska wraz z doktryną konfucjańską przenikała stopniowo do krajów sąsiednich. Również termin tao został dość szybko przyswojony w kulturach innych krajów Dalekiego Wschodu. Przytoczę tu tylko kilka powszechne u nas znanych wyrazów z języka japońskiego, zawierających jako morfem termin tao, który po japońsku wymawia się jako do bądź to, (kreska nad literą „o” oznacza wydłużenie tej samogłoski). Są to wyrazy:

1. judo, czyli po polsku dżudo, co dosłownie oznacza „tao miękkości”, czyli metodę, sposób, zasadę (walki) opierającą się na miękkości, w przeciwieństwie do innego rodzaju walk, opartych na twardości, czyli na sile fizycznej.

2. kendo, znane w Polsce pod tą samą nazwą jako rodzaj sportowej walki na japońskie miecze. W dosłownym tłumaczeniu termin ten znaczy „tao miecza”, czyli „zasada walki na miecze”.

Morfem-do w obydwu tych wyrazach mógł pierwotnie zawierać również znaczenie właściwej postawy moralnej, ponieważ istniało przeświadczenie, iż tylko człowiek doskonały pod względem etycznym był w stanie opanować tajniki walki dżudo lub kendo. W dawnych czasach mistrzowie „miękkiej walki” lub „walki na miecze”, nawet wtedy gdy niepohamowana i usprawiedliwiona nienawiść popychała ich przeciwko rywalowi, zawsze przed przystępowaniem do walki zachowywali odpowiedni ceremoniał i nigdy nie napadali na przeciwnika od tyłu bez uprzedzenia. Dzisiejsze walki sportowe również poprzedzane są odpowiednimi ceremonialnymi pokłonami.

3. shinto, w odróżnieniu od różnych napływowych odmian buddyzmu, jest główną tradycyjną religią japońską. W dosłownym tłumaczeniu nazwa ta oznacza „tao duchów”, czyli „drogę duchów” (bóstw), a więc „zasady moralne ustanowione przez bóstwa”.

4. bushido do kodeks rycerski samurajów, zbiór zasad samurajskiej etyki. W dosłownym tłumaczeniu ten termin oznacza „tao rycerzy” (bushi), a więc „zasady postępowania japońskiej warstwy samurajskiej”.

Termin tao był w Chinach w tak powszechnym użyciu, że znalazł również zastosowanie w terminologii buddyzmu, który przywędrował tu z Indii w pierwszych wiekach naszej ery. Oddawano za jego pomocą buddyjski termin mar ga, który poza pierwotnymi chińskimi znaczeniami – „droga, ścieżka, prawidłowa droga, zasada, Prawda, Rozum, Logos, energia kosmiczna” – przyjął nowe odcienie znaczeniowe, związane z filozofią i religią buddyzmu. Najważniejsze z nich to „droga wędrówki dusz”, którą człowiek przedostaje się na świat, by prowadzić dobrą, pozbawioną trosk i zgryzot bądź złą, wypełnioną; cierpieniami egzystencją. Tao jest też każdą z sześciu gati, czyli ścieżek przeznaczenia. Terminem tym określano także „drogę oświecenia”, wiodącą ku nirwanie poprzez kolejne stadia ruchowej doskonałości. Oznaczał on również właściwy stan nirwany, w którym panuje wolność, uwolnienie od nienawiści, pożądania, namiętności, cierpień, pozwalające bezustannie działać dla dóbr wszystkich żyjących.

W końcu należy kilka słów powiedzieć o znaczeniu pojęcia tao w taoizmie głównym chińskim systemie filozoficznym, który od słowa tao utworzył swoją nazwę. Taoizm również przechodził kilka etapów rozwoju, wśród których! wyróżniamy taoizm filozoficzny w czasach do schyłku III wieku p.n.e., taoizn magiczny, rozwijający się w pierwszych wiekach naszej ery, oraz taoizm religijny, którego pozostałości trwają niemal po dzień dzisiejszy.

Najważniejszą z odmian taoizmu, jak się wydaje, jest forma najwcześniejszą, której podstawowym tekstem jest zamieszczona w tłumaczeniu

Księgi Drogi i Cnoty

(

Tao-te-king

). Właściwie dla wyjaśnienia znaczenia tao w Tao-te-kingu moglibyśmy poprzestać na przytoczeniu dwóch cytatów z tej księgi „Tao, które można wyrazić słowami, nie jest (prawdziwym), niezmiennym tao” (rozdz. I) oraz „Ci, którzy znają (zasady tao), nie rozpowiadają (o nich no wszystkie strony) a ci, którzy rozpowiadają o zasadach tao na wszystkie strony (na pewno ich) nie znają” (rozdz. LVI).

Nie zostawimy jednakże czytelnika, by samodzielnie dokonywał dedukcji co do znaczenia słowa tao na podstawie załączonego tłumaczenia. Księga Lao-tsy mimo swej trudności należy do najczęściej tłumaczonych tekstów klasycznej filozofii chińskiej. Przy tym poszczególne tłumaczenia tak bardzo się miedzy sobą różnią, że nawet w kwestii interpretacji znaczenia podstawowego pojęcia, jakim jest tao, występują dosyć istotne rozbieżności. Podstawowa dywergencja dotyczy materialności względnie niematerialności tao. Istnieją na ten temat rozmaite stanowiska, a zdarza się też, iż ten sam uczony w różnych okresach swych badań przyjmuje w tej kwestii diametralnie odmienne stanowiska. Przykładem tego jest jeden z najwybitniejszych obecnie w Chinach znawców filozofii chińskiej Zen Ki-ju (?), który w posłowiu do wydanego w 1956 roku tłumaczenia księgi Lao-tsy na współczesny język chiński utrzymywał iż, „tao jest substancją materialną” (s. 75), natomiast we wstępie do wydanego dwadzieścia dwa lata później nowego tłumaczenia Lao-tsy stwierdził, iż „tao jest jądrem systemu idealistycznego” (s. 10) oraz że „tao nie jest substancją materialną” (s. 11).

Czy możliwe są i w jaki sposób są możliwe tak rozbieżne interpretacji jednego tekstu? Okazuje się, że są one w zupełności możliwe i zależą zarówno od interpretacji dość wieloznacznego tekstu jak i od dalszych dedukcji z tego tekstu wyprowadzonych. Dla przykładu przytoczymy pierwsze zdanie rozdziału XXXII Brzmi ono: „tao cz’an wu ming” (dosłownie „tao niezmienne nie mieć nazwa”). Przetłumaczyliśmy to zdanie jako „Tao jest niezmienne i bezimienne”. Tymczasem w książce chińskiego uczonego Czanga Tai-niena,

Mała historia chińskiej myśli materialistycznej

wydanej w 1960 roku, owe zdanie zostało zinterpretowane jako „tao jest to najprostsza materia bez nazwy” (s 27).

Argumenty w kwestii materialności względnie niematerialności tao opierają się głównie na dedukcji. Jedynym rzeczywistym przykładem, stwierdzającym materialność tao jest zdanie na początku rozdziału XXI: „tao jest czymś, co jest zupełnie nieuchwytne i nieokreślone”. Owe „coś” w tekście chińskim zostało wyrażone słowem wu, które z reguły tłumaczymy jako „rzecz, przedmiot”, a więc substancja materialna. Również początek rozdziału XXV, mówiący, że istnieje coś, „powstałe z chaosu, zanim się jeszcze niebo i ziemia zrodziły”, jakkolwiek nie ma wyraźnego odniesienia do tao, pozwala z dalszego ciągu tekstu wnioskować, iż owe materialne „coś” (wu) jest tao istniejącym jeszcze przed powstaniem nieba i ziemi, a nawet „zanim pojawiło się najwyższe bóstwo” (rozdz. IV)

Na czym opierają swoje twierdzenia zwolennicy niematerialnej, duchowej istoty tao? Dowody są tylko pośrednie, oparte na dedukcji. Za przesłanki służą im takie sformułowania w Tao-te-kingu jak „(Tao) stało się prapoczątkiem nieba i ziemi, rodzicielką dziesięciu tysięcy istot” (rozdz. I) lub „Nie wiem, czyim jest ono dzieckiem. (Istniało ono) zanim (na ziemi i na niebie pojawiły się rożne) zjawiska i najwyższe bóstwo” (rozdz. IV), „Dziesięć tysięcy istot (i rzeczy na świecie) pod niebem zrodziło się z bytu. A byt powstał z niebytu” (rozdz. XI), utożsamiające tao z niebytem, a więc czymś przeciwnym do materialnego bytu, czyli czynnikiem niematerialnym. Na korzyść zwolenników teorii materialności tao można z kolei przytoczyć początkowy fragment rozdziału II, z którego dowiadujemy się, że „gdy cały świat uznał piękno za piękno, wtedy (pojawiła się) szpetota”. W ten sam sposób: „Byt i Niebyt wzajemnie się rodzą”. Wynika z tego, iż ludzie dopiero wtedy, gdy uświadomili sobie, iż to, co ich otacza, jest Bytem, doszli do wniosku, że wobec tego musiało przedtem też istnieć coś przeciwnego do Bytu, a wiec Niebyt.

Przy okazji pragniemy podkreślić, że prezentowany w załączeniu przekład Tao-te-kingu jest tylko jedną z możliwych interpretacji tego dzieła i nie pretenduje do absolutnej poprawności Jesteśmy jednak przekonani, iż w jakimś stopniu pomoże on czytelnikom wyrobić sobie własne zdanie na temat zawartych w nim myśli o życiu i świecie.

Czymże więc jest tao u Lao-tsy’ego? Sądzimy, iż prawda leży pośrodku. Nie jest ono substancją materialną, taką jaką można by dostrzec za pomocą zmysłów ponieważ wielokrotnie podkreśla się w Tao-te-kingu, iż jest ono „niewidzialne, niesłyszalne, nieuchwytne„ (rozdz XIV), „nieuchwytne, nieokreślone” (rozdz XXI) i tak dalej. Nie jest też substancją duchową, przynajmniej taką, która by mogła działać celowo, przejawiać swoją wolę. Tao nawet, istniało już, zanim „pojawiło się najwyższe bóstwo” (rozdz. IV).

Wydaje się, że tao rozumiane było przez Lao-tsy’ego jako zbiór praw rządzących przyrodą w najszerszym tego słowa znaczeniu, a więc także praw (fizycznych) rządzących w przestrzeni kosmicznej, które doprowadziły do powstania (nieba i) ziemi, oraz praw (biologicznych), prowadzących do tego, że wszystko po osiągnięciu dojrzałości podąża ku śmierci. „Tao jest niezmienne i bezimienne” (rozdz. XXXII), oznacza, że prawa przyrody działają z niezmienną (w zasadzie) regularnością, tak jak po nocy przychodzi dzień, po zimie wiosna, tak jak po osiągnięciu starości człowiek umiera. Tao jest w zasadzie nazwą zastępczą, nie oddającą istoty tego pojęcia, ponieważ sensu tao nie można wyrazić słowami, nie można w słowach ująć wszystkich jego cech i właściwości. Tao można poznać jedynie intuicyjnie poprzez obserwację przejawów jego działania w otaczającym nas świecie, a nawet jeszcze lepiej poprzez kontemplację w zamkniętym pomieszczeniu.

Wśród wielu określeń tao niechybnie najważniejszym jest cz’ang, tłumaczone jako „stały, niezmienny”. Chociaż poszczególne rzeczy są zawsze zmienne i zmieniają się, rodzą się i giną lub umierają, to prawa, które rządzą zmianami tych rzeczy, same nie są zmienne. Stąd w Lao-tsy wyraz cz’ang stosowany jest jako określenie czegoś, co jest niezmiennym prawem przyrody.

Pośród praw, które rządzą przemianami rzeczy, najbardziej podstawowym jest to, które głosi, że „gdy rzecz osiągnie swój kraniec, przemienia się w swoje przeciwieństwo.” Nie są to konkretne słowa zaczerpnięte z Lao-tsy’ego, lecz potoczne chińskie powiedzenie, którego źródło niewątpliwie znajduje się u Lao-tsy’ego. Lao-tsy wypowiedział tę myśl w następujących słowach: „Dążenie ku swemu przeciwieństwu jest (przejawem) ruchu (wynikającego z zasad) tao” (rozdz. XL). W innym zaś miejscu czytamy: „O oddalonym mówi się że powraca” (rozdz. XXV). Lao-tsy uważał, że jeżeli coś równie w sobie zawiera pewne, krańcowe jakości, wówczas niezmiennie odwrócą się one w swoje przeciwieństwa.

Takie jest prawo natury. Dlatego nieszczęście jest szczęścia opoką, a szczęście nieszczęścia kryjówką (rozdz. LVIII), dlatego też nieliczne staje się licznym, a liczne sprowadza oszołomienie (rozdz. XXII). Dowiadujemy się też, iż gwałtowny wicher nie dmie prze cały ranek ani ulewny deszcz nie pada przez dzień cały (rozdz. XXIII), a gdy ktoś chce jakieś rzeczy zmniejszyć, na odwrót – coraz bardziej się rozrastają, jeśli ktoś chce się przyczynić do ich wzrostu, one – na odwrót – stają się coraz mniejsze (rozdz. XLII). Wszystkie te aforyzmy przestają być paradoksalne, gdy się zrozumie podstawowe prawa natury, które mają również zastosowanie do pomyślności w życiu ludzkim.

Wychodząc od stwierdzenia, że każda rzecz osiągając swoją krańcowość, następnie przemienia się w swoje przeciwieństwo, można by zapytać, co rozumiemy przez pojęcie „krańcowość”, czy istnieje jakaś absolutna granica dla rozwoju każdej rzeczy, której osiągnięcie lub przekroczenie oznaczałoby dojście do krańcowości? W Tao-te-kingu nikt nie zadaje takiego pytania, a więc też nie znajdziemy na nie bezpośredniej odpowiedzi. Gdyby jednak takie pytanie postawiono, odpowiedź prawdopodobnie by brzmiała, że nie da się oznaczyć jakiejś jednej, absolutnej granicy dla wszystkich rzeczy we wszelkich okolicznościach. Gdy chodzi o działalność ludzką, granica do jakiej człowiek może się posunąć, pozostaje zależna od jego subiektywnego odczucia oraz obiektywnych okoliczności.

Na przykład, gdy jakiś wybitny fizyk lub hydrobiolog miał uczucie, że w porównaniu z całym wszechświatem jego wiedza o nim nie jest większa niż wiedza o morzu; jaką posiada mały chłopczyk bawiący się na piasku na brzegu morskim, wówczas mimo olbrzymich osiągnięć w swojej dziedzinie, znajdowałby się nadal daleko od osiągnięcia granicy (krańcowości) rozwoju swojej wiedzy. Natomiast gdyby jakiś student, przeczytawszy zaledwie podręcznik fizyki, doszedł do wniosku, że już wie wszystko, co jest do poznania w tej dziedzinie wiedzy, z pewnością nie uczyniłby już żadnego postępu w nauce i tylko by „zawracał, cofał się”. Lao-tsy powiedział: „Jeśli bogactwo i zaszczyty wbiją cię w pychę, nieszczęścia same przybędą ich śladem” (rozdz. IX). Tak więc pycha i arogancja są pierwsza oznaką, ze człowiek w swym rozwoju osiągnął kraniec. Jest to pierwsza i najważniejsza rzecz, której człowiek winien unikać.

Granica rozwoju dla danej działalności jest również zależna od obiektywnych warunków. Człowiek cierpi, gdy je za dużo. Przy przejedzeniu, to co jest normalnie dobre dla ciała ludzkiego, staje się szkodliwe. Człowiek winien więc spożywać tylko właściwe ilości pożywienia. Jednakże ta właściwa ilość zależy od wieku człowieka, jego zdrowia oraz jakości jedzenia, jakie spożywa.

Takie są prawa rządzące przemianami rzeczy, Lao-tsy nazywa je niezmiennymi. Mówi o nich: „Poznanie owych niezmiennych zasad zwiemy oświeceniem” (rozdz. XVI) i jednocześnie przestrzega, że ci, co nie posiedli poznania tych niezmiennych zasad, „w swej szaleńczej głupocie dopuszczają się wielu, zbrodni” (rozdz. XVI). Człowiek winien znać tao, czyli prawa natury i kierować swoją działalnością zgodnie z nimi. Jest to określone jako praktykowanie oświecenia. Podstawowa zasada dla człowieka praktykującego oświecenie jest to, że jeśli chce cokolwiek osiągnąć, zaczyna od jego przeciwieństwa, a jeśli chce cokolwiek utrzymać, doszukuje się w tym czegoś przeciwnego. Jeśli chce być silny, misi zacząć od uczucia, że jest słaby.

Co należy robić, aby nie osiągnąć tej krańcowości? Człowiek powinien być łagodny, skromny i ławo zadowalać się tym. co ma. Łagodność jest metodą zachowania sił i w ten sposób wzrastania w siłę. Skromność jest bezpośrednim przeciwieństwem pychy. Tak więc, jeśli wyniosłość jest oznaką, że rozwój człowieka osiągnął krańcowy szczyt, skromność jest przeciwną oznaką i świadczy, że jeszcze wiele zostało do tej granicy. Zadowolenie z tego, co się ma, strzeże człowieka przed posunięciem się zbyt daleko w swych dążeniach a więc nie dopuszcza do osiągnięcia krańcowej granicy. Lao-tsy powiada: „Kto zna umiar, tego wstyd i hańba nie dosięgnie. Kto wie, na czym poprzestać, ten się nie znajdzie nad przepaścią (zagłady)” (rozdz. 44).

Lao-tsy jest też przeciwnikiem nadmiernej aktywności, zaleca tak zwane „niedziałanie”, które oznacza w rzeczywistości nieczynienie niczego w nadmiarze, nieczynienie niczego, co jest sztuczne i sprzeczne z ludzką naturą.

Sztuczność i samowolność są przeciwieństwem naturalności i spontaniczności. Według Lao-tsy’ego tao jest tym, dzięki czemu powstają wszystkie rzeczy. W tym procesie powstawania każda indywidualna rzecz uzyskuje coś z tego wszechświata, a owe coś określane jest mianem te (cnoty). Te jakiejś rzeczy jest tym, czym ona z natury jest.

Za najwybitniejszego kontynuatora myśli Lao-tsy’ego Uznawany jest Czu-ang-tsy (IV wiek p.n.e.). Jego dzieło, zatytułowane również Czuang-tsy, ukazało się w przekładzie polskim w 1953 roku, Czuang-tsy w następujący sposób objaśniał tao: „Tao jest stanem i rzeczywistością, ale nie może być wzięte. Można je osiągnąć, ale nie można go zobaczyć. Kiedy nie było ani nieba, ani ziemi, od dawna już istniało. Stanowi siłę nadprzyrodzoną duchów i władzy nieba. Spłodziło niebo i zrodziło ziemię” (s. 98). Możemy stąd wnioskować, że według Czuang-tsy’ego jakkolwiek także poprzedziło powstanie nieba i ziemi, jednakże w odróżnieniu od wielkiego poprzednika, znajdujemy związek tao z „nadprzyrodzoną siłą duchów i władzą nieba”.

Z innego fragmentu Czuang-tsy’ego dowiadujemy się jednakże, iż tao znajduje się praktycznie wszędzie, w każdej rzeczy i w każdej istocie. „Tung Kuo-tsy zapytał Czuang-tsy: – Gdzie się znajduje to, co nazywamy tao? – Nie ma miejsca, gdzie by go nie było. Tung Kuo-tsy dalej pytał: – Lepiej będzie, jeśli mi to określisz dokładniej. Czuang-tsy na to: – W tej mrówce. – A gdzieś niżej? – W źdźble trawy. – A jeszcze niżej? – W tej cegle – A najniżej? – W tym kale i moczu.” (s. 237). Oznacza to, że tao jest jednolitym elementem przenikającym wszystkie rzeczy. Każda rzecz, według Czuang-tsy’ego, jest specyficzną formą przejawiania się tao.

W taoizmie magicznym i religijnym pojęcie tao przyjmowało nowe znaczenia, o których nie będziemy już mówić, jako że w naszej prezentacji znaczeń słowa tao zgadzamy się z tezą Lao-tsy’ego, głoszącą, iż „Nie masz większego nieszczęścia nad brak umiaru” (rozdz. XLVI).

Przypisy

1 W przekładzie i w towarzyszącym artykule zastosowano polską transkrypcję z tego względu, iż większość terminów, jak chociażby tao, Lao-tsy… utrwaliły się już w tej pisowni. Według nowych zasad wprowadzanych w ChRL, nazwy powyższe brzmiałyby odpowiednio: dao, Lao-zi. Lao-tsy (dosł. stary mistrz) to przydomek założyciela chińskiej szkoły filozoficznej – taoizmu. Istnieją rozbieżności co do rzeczywistego jego nazwiska i imienia. Zdaniem historyka Sy-ma Ts’iena (145-86 r p.n.e.) nazywał się Lao Tan, natomiast w opinii innych wczesnych autorów nazwisko jego brzmiało Liu, a imię Er. Pochodził z księstwa Cz’u, znajdującego się na południowej rubieży terenów objętych przez cywilizację chińską. Daty jego życia nie są znane. Wiadomo tylko, że był starszym współcześnikiem Konfucjusza (551-479 p.n.e.), a więc żył w VI w p.n.e. Tradycja przypisuje mu autorstwo Tao-te-kingu (dosł. Księga Drogi i Cnoty), zbioru wypowiedzi o charakterze aforystycznym podzielonym na osiemdziesiąt jeden rozdziałów. Tekst składa się z około pięciu tysięcy znaków, stąd, znany jest również pod nazwą Lao-tsy wu ts’ien-wen, czyli Tekst pięciu tysięcy znaków Lao-tsy’ego. Tekst księgi jest w znacznej mierze heterogeniczny. Zarówno dawniejsze, jak i nowsze badania wskazują, iż nie wyszedł on spod jednej ręki, a niektóre partie tekstu nie mogły powstać wcześniej niż u schyłku IV w. p.n.e. W tekście Tao te-kingu znajdziemy też liczne powtórzenia, a także fragmenty (może tylko pozornie) sprzeczne te sobą. Zbiór ten jest w wysokim stopniu enigmatyczny i w wielu miejscach dopuszczający różne, nawet przeciwstawne interpretacje. Tekst Księgi w ciągu wieków ulegał licznym deformacjom. W 1973 r odkryto dwa najwcześniejsze egzemplarze tej klasycznej księgi taoistycznej pochodzące z okresów 208-195 r p.n.e. i 194-180 r p.n.e. Zostały one uwzględnione w niniejszym przekładzie. Dowiadujemy się z nich również, że w dawnych czasach tekst Tao-te-kingu rozpoczynał się od rozdziału XXXVII w obecnym układzie, a kolejne rozdziały od I-go następowały po rozdziale LXXXI.

2 W nawiasach ujęto dodano od tłumacza, uzupełniające słowa i wyrażenia, których nie ma w tekście oryginału. Pozwoli to czytelnikowi stwierdzić, co jest częścią tekstu chińskiego, podlegającą również różnym interpretacjom, a co niezbędnym dla zrozumienia tekstu, ale tylko dodatkiem od tłumacza.

3 „Ludzkość” – to polski odpowiednik konfucjańskiego terminu żen. Termin ten pisany jest do chińsku znakiem składającym się z dwóch elementów: człowieka i dwójki, i oznaczał stosunek jaki powinien cechować jednego człowieka względem drugiego. Należy jednak pamiętać, że o ile w kulturze europejskiej oznaczał właściwie odnoszenie się do innych ludzi, niezależnie od ich pozycji społecznej i majątkowej, konfucjańska cnota humanitarności stosunki między ludźmi widziała przez pryzmat miejsca zajmowanego przez tych ludzi w hierarchii społecznej, tzn. stosunek ten był inny w wypadku relacji ojca i syna, władcy i poddanego, starszego i młodszego brata, męża i żony.

4 Psy ze słomy. W starożytnych Chinach składano psy w ofierze bóstwom. Później zastąpiono je imitacjami zrobionymi ze słomy. Po uroczystościach obrzędowych porzucano je. Stosunek do nich był obojętny. Przed obrzędem nie otaczano ich szczególnym szacunkiem czy miłością a i po obrzędzie nie budziły nienawiści ani pogardy.

5 Niektórzy komentatorzy rozumieją termin „dobroć” jako „biegłość”, „umiejętność” postępowania zgodnego z zasadami tao.

6 Określenie „ludzkość” w tym fragmencie, wydaje się, nie zostało użyte w znaczeniu konfucjańskim, lecz w sensie dosłownym, stosunku, jaki winien cechować dwoje ludzi, niezależnie od ich pozycji społecznej.

7 Termin „wiedza” rozumiany jest tutaj w sensie konfucjańskim, jako znajomość etykiety historycznych precedensów, jej zastosowania, oraz zakazów i nakazów normujących zachowania członków społeczeństwa w zależności od zajmowanej pozycji społecznej.

8 Aluzją do doktryny konfucjańskiej w której barwy, dźwięki, smaki, strony świata, określone szczeble drabiny społecznej były między sobą skorelowane.

9 „Sprawiedliwość” – to jedna z głównych cnót konfucjańskich. Znak pisma na oznaczenie tego pojęcia, wymawiany „i”, składa się z dwóch elementów; barana i ręki trzymającej topór. Znak ten był używany jeszcze kilka wieków przed Konfucjuszem. Początkowo jednak oznaczał rytualne zabijanie owiec w ofierze oraz atmosferę dostojeństwa związaną z majestatem władcy składającego ofiarę. W doktrynie Konfucjusza sprawiedliwość była rozumiana jako czyn stosowny dla określonej relacji między członkami zhierarchizowanego społeczeństwa (często opierający się na historycznych precedensach).

10 Ludzkość i sprawiedliwość w rozumieniu konfucjańskim, por. przypis 3 i 9.

11 Według konfucjanistów różnica wynika z odmiennego typu zależności społecznej w rodzinie chińskiej, między synem i córką a rodzicami. Według Lao-tsy’ego, który nie uznaje, a nawet zwalcza te zależności, różnicy nie ma żadnej i córka powinna mieć prawo dowolnie zwracać się do rodziców.

12 „Coś” – dosłownie „rzecz”, „substancja materialna”. Sformułowanie to przeczy przeważającej wśród badaczy Tao-te-kingu opinii o idealistycznym charakterze filozofii Lao-ts’ego.

13 Nie wiadomo dokładnie dlaczego właśnie określenie „wielkie” uznał Lao-tsy za właściwą nazwę tao. Warto natomiast zwrócić uwagę na pewne pokrewieństwo znaków pisma chińskiego dla słów: „człowiek”, „wielki” i „niebo”. Znak żen oznaczający człowieka jest uproszczonym rysunkiem postaci ludzkiej na dwóch nogach. Znak ta – „wielki”, jest rysunkiem człowieka z kreską poziomą na wysokości ramion. Znak tien oznaczający „niebo” zawiera jeszcze dodatkową kreskę ponad „głową wielkiego człowieka”. Z powyższego może wynikać, że trzy pojęcia, jeszcze w czasach zamierzchłych, kiedy powstało pismo chińskie, były w umysłowości Chińczyków ze sobą kojarzone.

14 Ludzkość w rozumieniu taoistycznym.

15 Ludzkość w rozumieniu konfucjańskim.

16 To, że tao dało początek jedności świata, wcale nie wskazuje na jego duchowy, względnie materialny charakter.

17 W dawnych Chinach istniał zwyczaj, iż władcy mówiąc o sobie, zamiast zaimka osobowego używali samoponiżających określeń w rodzaju: sierota, wdowa itp. Zwyczaj ten miał prawdopodobnie na celu zmylenie złych duchów, które nie widząc w danej osobie godnej ofiary, odstępowały od napastowania ich.

18 Ten i następny rozdział posłużyły niektórym badaczom chińskim ostatniego piętnastolecia jako argument dla uznania Tao-te-king za traktat strategiczno-wojenny, dostarczający zwłaszcza sposobów zachowania się słabszego kraju wobec potężniejszego przeciwnika.

Na szlaku wielu wędrówek
Istota Drogi nie jest określona,
Istnieją nazwy, lecz natura słów
Pozostaje nieuchwytna.

Bezimienne jest źródło tworzenia
Chociaż rzeczy wszystkie
Wspólną mają macierz,
A ona ma imię.

Skryta jest ulga serca
I przystań wszelkich dążeń,
Gdy czyjeś oczy zaćmione
Niespokojnym pragnieniem
Tylko zewnętrznym sycą się kształtem.

Tam w głębi zawsze pozostają razem,
Chociaż dzielą ich nazwy.
Pod powierzchnią zjawisk
Zobacz ich związek tajny,
Furtkę do korzeni świata.

Ponieważ pięknym nazywa się piękno
Również brzydota przynosi korzyść.
Ponieważ dobro uznaje się za dobre
Również nikczemność świat ogarnia.

To, co jest i czego nie ma
Podąża wspólnie,
Mocne równoważy słabe,
Krótkie równoważy długie,
Przedtem i potem łączą całość,
Dźwięk i fala tworzą harmonię.

Prawdziwą służbą Mędrca
Jest pracować w milczeniu,
Bo nie racje lecz spełnienia
Są nauką tego, który wszystkim
Jednakowo służy.

Każdemu użycza, nie zatrzymując nikogo,
A co zostawia przechodząc,
Nie zależy od tego, co jest dalej.

Chociaż wiele ma zasług,
Nie przyjmuje wyróżnień,
Dlatego zawsze jest wyróżniony.

Skoro uczciwi i prawi
Nie dostępują zaszczytów
Nikt nie powinien zabiegać o awans.
Czyż wszyscy muszą się stać
Rabusiami i bandytami, kiedy
Bezinteresowne dobro przestało być celem?
Gdy rzeczy przez ogół pożądane
Trzymane są w ukryciu,
Czy powinno to podburzać tłumy?

Polityka Mędrca harmonijnie opróżnia
Ludzkie serca i umysły,
A napełnia ich żołądki,
Osłabia ambicje, by w zamian budować
Mocne ramy stałości,
Zawsze zdolne podtrzymać tego, który wie,
Nie podejmując walki.

Bądź nieustannie aktywny
I miej pełną kontrolę
Nad wszystkim.

Droga jest pusta,
Niewypełniona,
Choć. nieustannie czynna.
Tam w głębi wciąż widać
Początek wszystkiego:
Stępione ostrze,
Rozwiązane węzły,
Stłumioną światłość.
Ujarzmiony wigor.
Tej głębi nie wyczerpiesz.
Kto się w niej narodzi?
Jeden Bóg wie.

Czyż niedelikatny jest ten świat?
Czy żyjące istoty nie są dla niego
Zwierzyną ofiarną?
Czy nieuprzejmy jest Mędrzec
Wobec ludzkiego drobiazgu?

Przestrzeń miedzy ziemią a niebem
Jest jak miech,
Pusty, choć niewyczerpany,
Kiedy się porusza
Dary jego są szczodre.

Przemawiaj podobnie!

Uległy duch nizin to wieczna żeńskość,
Której furtka – jak twierdzą –
Jest fundamentem
Ziemi i Nieba.

Używaj jej nie zaznając trudu.

Niebo jest wieczne
I ziemia Jest równie stara,
Ponieważ świat istnieje
Nie dla siebie
Wciąż może trwać.

Człowiek mądry wybiera miejsce ostatnie,
Dlatego jest przed wszystkimi.
Gubi siebie i przez to jest zbawiony.
Czyż nie odnajdzie swego celu
Gdziekolwiek się uda?

Dobro najwyższe jest jak woda,
Wszystkim jednakowo sprzyja
I bez szmeru podąża w miejsca
Przez człowieka wzgardzone.

Kiedy wiąże się dobro domu
Z dobrem całego kraju,
Kiedy spokój umysłu
Pochodzi z głębi wiedzy,
Kiedy miłość jest darem porozumienia,
Kiedy uczciwość błogosławi mowie,
Kiedy sens działania
Leży w prawdziwej potrzebie,
Wtedy spokój jest celem Drogi.

Nie jest dobrze brać
Cokolwiek zapragniesz.
Lepiej się powstrzymać.
Działaj, bądź energiczny i zaradny,
Ale niezbyt długo.
Nie będziesz panem swojego domu,
Jeśli zbyt wiele w nim zgromadzisz.
Bogactwo, siłę i godność
Powierz wyrokom losu.
Kiedy sukces i sława przyjdą do ciebie
Ukryj się w cieniu.

Takie jest prawo Drogi.

Czy możesz zwierzęcość swą ujarzmić i wejść w niezmąconą jedność?
Czy możesz oddech swój tak stłumić by był lekki jak oddech dziecka?
Czy możesz oczyścić myśli i niczym ich nie plamić?
Czy ludzi kochać potrafisz i całą ziemią władać nie będąc nikomu znany?
Czy możesz być jak uległa kobieta co otwiera i zamyka furtkę nieba?
Czy w jasności umysłu potrafisz ogarnąć cztery strony świata?

Ożywiaj je i zasilaj,
Ożywiaj i nie zagarniaj,
Działaj, lecz bądź daleki,
Rządź, lecz nie bądź władcą.
Oto rejestr wiecznych zasług.

Trzydzieści szprych zbiega się
W piaście koła,
Lecz użyteczność wozu
Jest w pustym środku piasty.

Wypalona skorupa tworzy
Kształt glinianej misy.
Ale jej użyteczność
Jest w miejscu pustym.

By wznieść dom, budujesz ściany
Wstawiasz w nie drzwi i okna,
Choć użyteczność domu
Jest w pustej przestrzeni.

Dlatego korzyść wynika
Z wszystkiego, co istnieje,
Lecz użyteczność – z tego,
Czego nie ma.

Pięć kolorów naraz zaciemnia widzenie,
Pięć jednoczesnych dźwięków stępia ucho,
Pięć smaków nuży podniebienie,
Ściganie pięciu zwierząt na polu
Uczyni człowieka szalonym.

Dobre jest to, co trudne do zdobycia;
Nie kuleje wolno idący.

Człowiek mądry czyni
Tak, jak mu żołądek dyktuje,
A nie zachwyt oczu,
Dlatego wybiera to lub tamto.

Łaska równa jest niełasce.
Wysoka godność i własna osobowość
Jednakowo przysparzają cierpień.

Jeśli wielkie zaszczyty spotykają
Kogoś na niskim stanowisku,
Nie uniknie on przykrych przeżyć;
Jeśli nie zostanie wyróżniony
Również będzie cierpiał.
Tak więc łaska równa jest niełasce.

Cierpisz z własnego powodu.
Gdybyś był pozbawiony „ja”,
Dolegliwości istnienia
Nie znalazłyby obiektu.
Tak więc zarówno wysoka godność,
Jak i twoja własna osobowość
Mogą być źródłem cierpień.

Władzę świata powierz temu,
Kto traktuje swoją funkcję
Tak, jakby była jego duszą.
A rzeczywista wolność będzie powierzona
Temu, kto kocha wszystkich ludzi,
Jak samego siebie.

Nazwano to nieuchwytnym.
Mówią, że ktoś oglądał,
Lecz nigdy się nie pojawiło.
Podobno naprawdę jest niezwykłe,
Aż ktoś słuchał,
Lecz nie wydało dźwięku.
Subtelnym zwali mówiąc,
Że ktoś złapał, ale nie utrzymał.

Te trzy stanowią sumę jednego tylko,
Które jest poza wszelkim wyliczeniem.
Wschodząc nie oświetla,
Zachodząc ciemności nie ściąga,
Biegnie daleko w bezimienny stan
Sprzed kreacji.

Może być formą bezkształtną,
Bezcielesnym kształtem
Albo nieokreślonością zawiłą:
Spotkasz ją – nie ma przodu,
Pójdziesz za nią – nie ma tyłu.

Jeśli szybkość twoja pozwoli
Trzymać się tej przedwiecznej Drogi,
Wtedy rządzić możesz dniem dzisiejszym.
To będzie poznane, co nazwiesz,
Idąc jej tropem.

Doskonali Mistrzowie przeszłości
Byli zbyt nieprzeniknieni, głębocy i subtelni,
Aby ktoś mógł ich zrozumieć,
Łatwiej więc opisać wygląd
Niż świadomość Mędrca.

Jest on podobny człowiekowi przekraczającemu
Lodowaty strumień ostrożnie i chwiejnie.
Posuwa się jakby w największym był zagrożeniu,
Lecz postawę zachowuje godną,
Jakby go zaszczycała każda okoliczność,
Każdy drobiazg.

Jest jak dolina otwarta dla każdego wędrowca,
Jak pień drzewa nie tkniętego żadnym narzędziem.
Zawsze siebie umniejsza, podobny jest więc
Do topniejącego lodu,
Choć bywa gwałtowny jak poruszona lawina.

Kto biegnie zbrukany a powraca przejrzysty?
Kto będąc nieruchomy innych podrywa ku pełni życia?
Kto pojął Drogę i nie stał się chciwy?
Kto znosi poniewierkę nie szukając ulgi?

W ciszy i spokoju
Nieruchomych ścieżek
Dotknij, nieskończonej pustki.
Tam gdzie wspólne
Jest krążenie rzeczy
Widzę jak się cofają,
Dojrzewają i kwitną,
I znów się cofają
Do swoich korzeni.

Takie jest milczenie:
Powrót soków
W głąb korzeni,
Taka jest trwałość,
Wiedza niezachwiana,
Która jest światłem
Wobec ślepoty rozpadu.

Jeśli posiadasz
To, co wiecznie trwa,
Wtedy jesteś sprawiedliwy,
A sprawiedliwość
To królewska godność,
A królewskość jest święta,
Ostateczna.

I choćbyś umarł
Zawsze będziesz.

Władcę ludzie traktują
Każdy na swój sposób.
Jedni chwalą i schlebiają,
Inni unikają z lękiem,
Jeszcze inni pogardzają i lżą.
Jeśli nie ufasz dostatecznie ludziom
Znajdą się tacy, co nigdy ci nie uwierzą.

Władca jest niedostępny i wyniosły,
Jakby jego prace miały własną cenę
Poza ludzkim targowiskiem,
Lecz kiedy ich treść zostanie ogłoszona
Ludzie zazwyczaj powiadają:
„Sami żeśmy tego dokonali”.

Kiedy urywa się ślad Drogi,
Pojawia się uprzejmość i moralność,
Kiedy znika mądrość i inteligencja,
Pojawia się wielka hipokryzja.

Nie starczyło sześciu prawd dla utrzymania pokoju,
Dlatego przepisy panują w naszych domach,
Ojczyznę okrył mrok ściągnięty nieustanną walką,
Oficjalna lojalność stała się stylem.

Uwolnij się od mądrych i pojętnych,
Oddal uczonych profesorów,
A ludzie odniosą wielką korzyść.

Wypędź uprzejmych i wytwornych,
Zlekceważ sprawiedliwych,
Ludzie powrócą do dawnej gościnności.

Wymów pracę rzemieślnikom,
Rozpędź handlarzy,
Znikną również złodzieje.

Jeśli za mało tych trzech sposobów,
By zadowolić serce i ożywić umysł,
Zwróć się ku prostocie życia
Obejmującej niewymuszone czyny,
Przeciętny smak i ubóstwo pożądań.

Sztywne reguły wiedzy
Potęgują ludzką drażliwość,
Różnica pomiędzy „tak” a „zaiste”
Staje się równa otchłani oddzielającej
Dobro od zła.
Czy miałbym również się lękać?
– Jakże jałowa to myśl!

Triumfalne okrzyki ludzkich zbiorowisk,
Procesje i sztandary lub barwny karnawał,
Taneczny korowód schodzący ze wzgórz
Zastają mnie, niestety, samotnie,
Nie rozumiejącego słów,
Jak dziecko, które zapomniało uśmiechu.

Leniwie płyną z prądem
I nie mam gdzie się udać.
Wszyscy inni opływają w dostatek,
Tylko ja tracę.
Mam umysł głupca, zmącony i zakłopotany.
Kiedy twarze wszystkich ludzi jaśnieją
Ja kryję się w mroku,
Widzę wokół zaradnych i świadomych,
Tylko mnie nachodzi smutek.
Jak niespokojne morze miotany
W każdą stronę nie mogę się zatrzymać:
Inni ludzie łatwo znajdują zatrudnienie,
Tylko ja niczego nie osiągam.
Samotny jestem i odmienny,
Szukam pokarmu Matki.

Wszechobecna mądrość może istnieć
Tylko zgodnie z Drogą,
A sama Droga jest jak obraz
Widziany we śnie, nieuchwytny, umykający,
A w nim są nieuchwytne umykające odbicia,
A w nich rzeczy jak cienie o zmierzchu,
W rzeczach treść subtelna choć realna.
To wszystko od zamierzchłej przeszłości
Do teraz
Wiruje oznaczone nazwami bez końca,
Chociaż początek i koniec
Pozostają widoczne.

Skąd znam początek wszystkiego,
Co wypełniło świat?
Właśnie stąd!

Zgięte będzie wyprostowane,
Nierówności zostaną wyrównane,
Strumienie się napełnią,
Pragnienia będą zaspokojone
I zdumieją się bogacze.

Oto Mędrzec niesie wiedzę światu:
Chociaż na siebie nie wskazuje
Wszystkim jest znany,
Chociaż zasług unika,
Zawsze jest wyróżniony,
Nie chwali się siłą,
Lecz jest wydajny
I dumnym nie będąc
Przewodzi.

Taki sztandar niesie światu.
Ponieważ nie walczy
Nikt na świecie go nie zwycięży.

Słowa Starego Mędrca
Nie są próżne:
„Zgięte będzie wyprostowane”.
Być doskonałym
To do nich powrócić.

Oszczędność jest zaiste cechą jego mowy:
Trąba powietrzna nie trwa do rana,
Oberwanie chmury kończy się przed nadejściem świtu.
Któż tak przemawia?
– Ziemia i Niebo!
Daleko bardziej człowiek winien się powściągać.

Jeśli wszedłeś na Drogę
Stajesz się Drogą.
Jeśli pracujesz w imię Dobra
Będzie ci dane Dobro.
Jeśli odtrącisz jedno
Zostaniesz odtrącony przez oba.

Pokłońcie się Drodze, którzy nią stąpacie,
Radośnie cierpcie moc, którzy dobrze dysponujecie.
Swobodnie omijajcie błędy, porzuceni przez zło.

Mało wiary mają ci,
Których wiara jest mała.

Kto stoi na koniuszkach palców
Nie stoi mocno.
Kto jest zbyt pewny siebie
Nie podoła trudom.
Próżny nie może przewodzić.

Człowiek postępujący zgodnie z Drogą
Wystrzega się podobnych cech
Są one bowiem jak najsmakowitszy pokarm
Oddany pasożytom.

Przed powstaniem Ziemi i Nieba
Już istniało nieokreślone,
Ciche, odległe i samotne,
Niezmienne i niezawodne,
Co dotyka każdej rzeczy
I od ich poczęcia
Jest matką wszystkiego.

Nazwy nie posiada,
Bo jej imię to „Droga”,
Gdy chcę ją określić
Nazywam ją wielką,
Wielka znaczy daleka,
Daleka albo dalekosiężna.
Choć wciąż powracająca.

Droga jest wielka,
Niebo jest wielkie
I Ziemia jest wielka,
Cztery są wielkie żywioły,
Lecz ten kto światem włada.
Spoczywa w jednym.

Człowiek przylega do Ziemi
Ziemia przylega do Nieba,
Niebo przylega do Drogi
A Droga do własnej natury.

Ciężar jest stałym fundamentem.
Lekkości i swobody,
Uległa wytrwałość
Jest nauczycielem czynów.

Mędrzec, choć w ciągłej jest podróży,
Nie porzuca swojego skarbu.
Kiedy przypadkiem dosięga go sława
I próżny ceremoniał wielkości
Pozostaje sam u siebie,
Ponad wszystkim.

Czy ten, który prowadzi
Dziesięć tysięcy wozów
Może zaniedbać któryś
Z najsubtelniejszych trybów,
Jakie świat powołał?

Jeśli jest gnuśny
Jego ministrowie są zgubieni.
Jeśli jest rozumny
Nie ma nad niego mistrza.

Dobry biegacz nie zostawia śladów,
Dobre przemówienie nie zawiera błędów,
Dobry rachmistrz nie potrzebuje liczydeł,
Dobre drzwi nie wymagają zakładania rygli,
Dobry węzeł ściągnięty jest lekko i nie luzuje się.

Dobry człowiek nieustannie niesie pomoc,
Nikogo nie odrzuca,
Tak samo postępuje wobec każdej rzeczy,
Żadna się nie marnuje.

Człowiek dobry winien być troskliwym nauczycielem złego.
Jeśli jeden nie szanuje swojego nauczyciela,
A drugi nie kocha własnego zatrudnienia,
Powstaje zamęt.

Czyż tego nie widać?

Bądź świadom siły męskiej natury,
Lecz pierwszeństwo w sobie daj kobiecie,
Ona uczyni cię dzieckiem.

Musisz być dla świata głęboką szczeliną,
Która przyciąga i zatrzymuje niezniszczalną wartość.

Spostrzegaj to, co jasne wokół ciebie,
Lecz pamiętaj, że kryje ono niepoznaną ciemność,
Musisz być dla świata jak badacz,
Którego rzetelność nieomylnie wiedzie
W najdalszą przeszłość.

Strzeż swego honoru i czci,
Lecz nie unikaj skaz,
Musisz być dla świata jak szeroka dolina,
Gdzie różne strumienie biorą początek.

Kiedy dziewiczy pień został rozszczepiony,
Powstały różne instrumenty,
Do końca pozostają one w dyspozycji Mędrca
Jako jego świadkowie,
Ponieważ on sam nigdy nie został rozdzielony.

Wielu jest takich, co chcieliby cały świat
Naprawić zgodnie z własnym wyobrażeniem.
Widzę jednak, że im się to nigdy nie udaje,
Bo świat ten jest świętym naczyniem
Nie po to ukształtowanym, by zmieniać
Go miał człowiek.
Lecz filozofom zdarza się prawdę tę lekceważyć
I wielu jest uzurpatorów.

Ponieważ coś nieustannie biegnie naprzód,
Coś innego pozostaje w tyle.
Jedne rzeczy są cieple, inne zimne;
Jedne mocne, inne słabe;
Jedne się rodzą, inne zamierają.
Człowiek rozumny unika krańcowych skłonności,

Radykalnych sądów,
Nieobliczalnych idei.

Oznaczenia Drogi dla tych,
Którzy będą wspomagać Władcę Narodów
W jego działaniu:

Niech nie próbują orężem
Panować nad światem;
Ta taktyka gorsza jest od klęski,
Bo gdzie armie przejdą,
Tam najwyżej dzika róża wyrośnie,
A na szlaku wielkich marszrut
Pozostaną lata ciemności i głodu.

Kiedy ktoś ma prawdziwie dobre zamiary,
Powstrzymuje się i nie pragnie zwyciężać.
Jeśli czegoś dokonuje, nie wychwala się,
Nie sławi własnych osiągnięć,
Nie pokazuje tego co złupił.

Skoro zwyciężył taka była konieczność,
Lecz nie siłą ani gwałtem.

Świadomość tych zasad z wiekiem słabnie
I może powiesz: „nie miałem z tym nigdy związku”,
Lecz nie mieć związku z Drogą
To przedwczesna śmierć.

Najdoskonalsze systemy broni są chlubą zła,
Lecz człowiek podążający zgodnie z Drogą
Ze wstrętem unika ich widoku.

Dla człowieka dobrych manier
Zaszczytem jest zajmować lewą stronę,
Bo dobra wróżba jest po lewej,
Zła – po prawej.
A żołnierze ciągną na prawo!
Kiedy generał stoi po prawej,
Jego adiutant zajmuje lewą stronę.
W tym choćby zachowanie człowieka o wielkiej władzy
Przypomina żałobny obrzęd.

Oręż jest instrumentem złego losu,
Człowiek subtelny nie wydobędzie go,
Jeśli nie będzie mógł tego uniknąć
Jego interwencja będzie ograniczona;
Nawet w godzinie zwycięstwa
Nie zachwyci go błysk miecza.
Ci tylko napawają się widokiem broni,
Którzy potrafią rozkoszować się zbrodnią,
Ich ambicje nigdy się nie zaspokoją,
Nie wyczerpie się żądza władzy.

Stosy pomordowanych! – ich śmierć
Jest przedmiotem żalu i łez;
Zwycięskie rozwiązanie konfliktu
Staje się tematem żałobnego nabożeństwa.

Wieczna Droga nie posiada imion.
Dziewiczy pień drzewa, chociaż niepokaźny,
Może jednak zadziwić świat.
Jeśli władca i dostojnicy będą mogli
Pozyskać jego właściwości dla dobrych celów,
Wówczas cała ziemia nieprzymuszona
Podda się ich prawu.

Ziemia i Niebo we wspólnym oddziaływaniu
Zrodzą życiodajną rosę,
Plony będą równo dzielone
Bez stosowania przymusu.

Wszystkie stworzenia przyszły na świat
Wedle swego rodzaju i przeznaczenia,
A wraz z nimi – wiedza korzyści i wsparcia
Dająca harmonię i bezpieczeństwo.

Na tym świecie Idący ścieżką
Porównywani są do wartkich strumieni
Płynących ku rzece i morzu.

Mądry jest człowiek znający innych,
Lecz Mistrz znający sam siebie jest oświecony.
Potężny jest ten, kto zwycięża wrogów
I łamie wszelkie przeszkody,
Lecz kto pokonał sam siebie
Potężniejszy jest od niego.

Zdrowie polega na zadowoleniu.
Samowolne jest zakłócanie ludzkich ścieżek.
Wytrwałość polega na utrzymaniu
Swojego miejsca.
Żyć w miejscu właściwym,
To nie lękać się śmierci.

Wypływająca z rozłogów Wielkiej Drogi
Obfitość wszystko przewyższa,
Rozprzestrzenia się wszędzie,
Każda rzecz ma w niej początek
I każde stworzenie jej podlega.
Lecz ona jeśli przywołuje, to nie jak
Swoją własność.
Karmi i przyodziewa, ale nie rozporządza
I nie dyktuje.

Nie mając życzeń, nie tworząc różnic,
Wydaje się znikomą jakością,
Jednakże taka jest prawdziwa wielkość:
Kiedy do niej powrócą
Nie będą mieli nad sobą pana.

Dlatego Mędrzec za życia
Nie ujawnia swojej mocy:
Tak moc się wypełnia.

Gdy raz uchwycisz bezcielesną formę
Będziesz mógł wędrować gdzie zapragniesz
– Cicho, spokojnie, bez trudu
I bez uporczywego lęku.

Muzyka i posiłek wstrzymują wędrowca,
Choć przeznaczona ścieżka
Jest wąska i bezgłośna.
Nie zobaczysz jej, ani nie usłyszysz,
Lecz idąc
Nigdy jej nie wyczerpiesz.

Co teraz słabnie, kiedyś rosło w siłę;
Co się skurczyło, kiedyś było rozpostarte;
Co zostało odrzucone, było wyniesione.

Światło jest nienaganne,
Ciemność nieubłagana.
Delikatne kroki przemogą
Każdy opór.

Jak ryba nie może wypłynąć
Poza krawędź wody,
Ostre narzędzia myśli
Nie będą pokazane nikomu.

Wielka Droga chociaż wszystko porusza
Cicha jest i nieporuszona.
Jeśli władca i jego ministrowie
Zdobędą jej twórczy dar
Wszystkie istoty zmienią charakter.

Lecz mimo zmian zawsze jeszcze próbują
Wymykać się na własne ścieżki.
Będę się starał je powstrzymać
Z myślą o naturalnej prostocie,
Kształtującej prawo istnienia,
Rosnącej w Święty Pień.

Wielka doskonałość nie ma posiadacza.
Mała cnota uniemożliwia posiadanie zasług,
Dlatego jest niczym.
Prawdziwa doskonałość to wielka niewzruszoność,
Sama z siebie nie ma potrzeby działać.
Małe zalety to nieprzerwany interes,
Potrzeba spełnień i zysku.

Największe miłosierdzie świadczone jest
Rzetelnością czynów.
Najlepsza moralność jest przysparzaniem korzyści.
Najlepsza etykieta to niezważanie na wzajemność,
Zakasanie rękawów i pełnienie swojej służby.

Gdy znajomość Drogi znika
Wtedy pozostaje szlachetność i prawość,
Gdy one znikną, pozostaje moralność,
Gdy ona się wykruszy wówczas panuje uprzejmość –
Pozór wiary, pusty ceremoniał
Będący powodem każdej anarchii.

Przeczucie, mówią, wypełnia się
I rozkwita w Doktrynie,
Lecz znacznie lepszym punktem wyjścia
Jest niewiedza:
Kiedy człowiek dojrzały sięga po owoce, nie kwiaty,
Wydobywa miąższ a odrzuca łupinę.
Odrzucając jedno bierze drugie.

To wszystko niegdyś stanowiło Jedno:
Niebo rozjaśnione,
Ziemia mocno utwierdzona,
Duch przenikający,
Rzeki pełne wód,
Niezliczone istoty zaludniające świat,
Władza królów i mądrość praw.

Bez światła jedności
Niebo by ściemniało,
Ziemia by się zatrzęsła
Wszystkie rzeczy rozpadłyby się w proch
I zbłądziłby człowiek.

Pokorny lud wspiera władców,
Jest bierną podstawą na której wywyższeni
Lekko spoczywają,
Oni jednak zwykli mówić o sobie,
Jak o istotach opuszczonych i stroskanych.
Czyż nie oczekują wsparcia kornych ludzi?

Zaiste, pojazd to coś więcej
Niż suma części.

Lepiej grzmieć jak skala
Niż brzęczeć jak jaspis.

Powrót jest zaczynem Drogi,
Gdzie wiedzie słabość.
Z tego co jest
Świat rzeczy się zrodził,
A to, co jest, rośnie
Odwracając się ku temu,
Czego nie ma.

Słysząc przekaz Drogi
Najdoskonalszy z ludzi
Gorliwie będzie badał
Jej niewyczerpany bieg.
Człowiek przeciętny łatwo uchwyci sens,
Poderwie się i zaraz przysiadzie.
Człowiek prymitywny gdy usłyszy Nowinę,
Będzie się śmiał albo nienawidził.
Dlatego powiadają: „na prostej drodze potknie się ten,
Kto idąc co chwilę się ogląda”.

Teraz każda prosta droga pełna jest wyboi,
Wzniosłe męstwo jest jak otchłań,
Najczystsza niewinność okrywa się cieniem,
Największa potęga wydaje się znikoma,
Najwyższy autorytet jest nikczemny,
Każda wartość jest niestała,
Jak przypływ i odpływ wód.

Wielka przestrzeń nie ma kątów,
Wielka moc przychodzi późno,
Potężna muzyka dźwięczy łagodnie,
Droga jest wąska i zupełnie niejasna:
W zręcznym początku mądrość rozwiązania.

Wielka Droga rodzi Jedno.
A Jedno – Dwa.
Z nich powstaje Trzecie
I cala reszta.

Wszystko co jest, dźwiga cień
Na swoich barkach,
A słońce trzyma w ramionach.
Pulsujący oddech między światłem a cieniem
Daje chwiejną równowagę – życie światu.

Człowiek samotny i porzucony
Cierpi i lęka się.
Gdyż Jest przywiązany do osób i rzeczy.
Bogactwo bywa zgubne,
Kiedy indziej zguba jest bogactwem.

Czego inni uczyli Ja też będę uczył:
Jeśli gwałtownik nie zginie nagłą śmiercią,
Od niego będę się uczył.

Najbardziej miękkie tworzywo świata
Łatwo przenika najtwardsze,
Gdzie nie ma już miejsca
Tam wkracza bezkształtne.

Dzięki temu poznaję dobrodziejstwo
Czegoś, co się zrodziło w spokojnym trwaniu.
Na całym świecie niewielu może pojąć
Spełnienie bez ciężkiej pracy,
Instrukcję podaną bez jednego słowa.

Co jest droższe sława czy świadomość?
Człowiek czy pieniądze?
A co ran! bardziej zysk czy strata?

Ubogi płaci cenę najwyższą,
Bogacz największą zgarnia ruinę,
Szczęśliwego nikt nie zawstydzi,
Opanowany niebezpieczeństwa ominie,
Będzie żył wiecznie.

Największa zręczność traktowana jest często
Jak leniwa nieudolność.
Prawdziwa doskonałość, choć jej działanie nigdy
Nie słabnie, wydaje się wątła i pełna wad.
Proste wydaje się zbaczać,
Pełne ma wiele dziur, choć trwa nienaruszone.
Najdoskonalsza wymowa brzmi jak bełkot.

Nieustanny wysiłek przezwycięży
Zimno, bezruch, upał.
Mędrzec, będąc cichym i otwartym
Wybawi świat.

Dopóki Droga rządzi światem
Konne zaprzęgi użyźniają pola,
Gdy tylko zaniknie jej ślad
Konie wojny zarżą w parkach.

Nie ma większego grzechu
Nad uczucie nienawiści.
Trudno wpaść w większą niedolę,
Niż własne niezadowolenie.

Nie ma straszniejszego fatum
Od nieposkromionej żądzy.
Gdy jesteś zadowolony
Niczego ci nie będzie brakować.

Nie wychodząc z domu
Możesz poznać świat.
Wyglądając przez okno
Możesz ujrzeć swoją Drogę
Im dalej pójdziesz
Tym mniej będziesz rozumiał.

Zgodnie z tym Mędrzec
Wie wszystko, chociaż nie docieka,
Widzi nie patrząc,
Działa nie czyniąc.

Student ucząc się osiąga codzienny postęp,
Lecz Drogę można poznać jedynie
Poprzez codzienne straty:
Stracić tu, nie zdążyć tam...
Aż przychodzi spokój.

Wszystkiemu, co istnieje, potrzebna jest swoboda.
Świat cały podlega tym, którzy
Pozwalają mu płynąć lekko.
Lecz jeśli ktoś się nieustannie wysila,
Świat zdaje się niezwyciężony.

Umysłu Mędrca nie krępują żadne reguły,
Lecz akceptuje on to, co ludziom służy.
Dlatego wybiera Dobro będące światłem
Zarówno dla sprawiedliwych jak i złoczyńców.
Podobnie skłania się ku Wierze,
Skoro Dobro wypełnia się Wiarą.

Mędrzec, będąc na ziemi
Bezstronnym świadkiem,
Nie dzieli i nie sądzi,
Mało jest więc widoczny.
Lecz ludzie zewsząd wytężają oczy i uszy.
By słyszeć go i wypatrywać,
Jak to czynią małe dzieci.

Trzydzieści członków formuje tyjące ciało,
Zwłoki – tyleż samo!
Trzydzieści punktów przez które człowiek
Przedostać się może z życia w śmierć.
Dlaczego umiera?
Bo droga jego życia zbyt jest rozrzutna.

Podobno człowiek umiejący zachować całkowity spokój
Zawsze ominie tygrysa lub bawoła.
Podczas bitwy żadna broń go nie zadraśnie.
W jego ciele nie ma miejsca dla tygrysich pazurów,
Ani krzywych rogów bawoła, nie ma wejścia dla miecza.
Przez żaden z członków jego organizmu
Śmierć nie przeniknie.

Wielka Droga rodzi wszystkie istoty,
Jej opatrzność dogląda każdej,
Gdy przyoblekają się w materialne formy
We własnym otoczeniu tropiąc doskonałość.

Oto dlaczego wszystkie stworzenia
Oddają cześć Drodze
I szanują jej potęgę.

Wywyższenie Drogi, sława jej siły
Nie jest sprawą przeznaczeń,
Ani ludzkich postanowień,
Lecz wyłącznie – jej własnej natury.

Droga rodzi wszystkie istoty,
Pielęgnuje, karmi je i obłaskawia,
Aż osiągną swój cel.

Ożywiaj je i zasilaj,
Ożywiaj i nie zagarniaj,
Działaj, lecz bądź daleki,
Rządź, lecz nie bądź władcą.
Oto rejestr wiecznych zasług.

Początkiem jest łono,
Bo świat ma matkę, której synowie
Zawsze będą przez nią pamiętani.
Trzymaj się jej blisko, a póki żyjesz
Nie odczujesz krzywdy.

Zamknij szczelnie drzwi,
Odetnij zmysły,
Bądź pełny w sobie i niewyczerpany,
Bo jeśli zmysłów nie pohamujesz
Będziesz opętany całe życie.

Stajesz się oświecony, gdy dostrzegasz
Życie w drobiazgach.
Mnożenie małych działań uczyni cię wielkim.
Gromadząc wiele iskierek
Oczy twoje rozświetlą mroki zła.

Oto praktyczna stałość.

Kiedy przechadzam się po Wielkiej Drodze,
Czegóż mogę się obawiać?
Jest ona szeroka i wygodna dla stóp,
Lecz ludzie wciąż brną krętymi ścieżkami.

Spójrz: oto dwór królewski cichy i czcigodny,
Podczas gdy pola zarastają chwasty,
Spichlerze pustoszeją
Oni odziani w jedwabne suknie
Mają ostre miecze przy boku
W pełni zdrowia pochłaniają jadło i trunki.

To raczej chełpliwość zbójecka objęła rządy.

Uchwyć się Drogi, nikt cię nie oderwie,
Nikt cię nie poniży.
Najgłębsza przeszłość stanie się
Domem, z którego wychodzisz.

Praktykuj w sobie, a będziesz doskonały,
Praktykuj w domu – stanie się jasny,

Praktykuj w wiosce – będzie pogodna,
Praktykuj państwie – szybko rozkwitnie,
Praktykuj w świecie – stanie się wolny.

Ten, który nadchodzi będzie sądził ludzi;
Ci, co przychodzą z daleka, nawiedzą wasze domy,
Tamta wioska jest wzorem każdej wioski;
Tamten kraj jest życiem każdego kraju;
Tamten świat tego świata jest królestwem.

Człowiek doskonały jest jak dziecko,
Insekty nie dotykają jego skóry,
Drapieżne ptaki i dzikie bestie
Nie odważą się zaatakować jego ciała.

Jego kości są miękkie, ścięgna słabe,
Jednakowoż uścisk dłoni mocny,
Członki w pełni ukształtowane,
A siły witalne są u szczytu.

Może krzyczeć dzień cały bez ochrypnięcia,
Może przemierzać wielkie odległości
Bez objawów zmęczenia.
Jego uczucia są pełne a umysł spokojny.

Poznanie harmonii powoduje stałość,
Utrzymywanie stałości jest oświeceniem.
Wszelki nadmiar energii jest złowieszczy,
A jej wyładowania powodują agresję.

Świadomość tych zasad z wiekiem słabnie
I może powiesz: „nie miałem z tym nigdy związku”.
Lecz nie mieć związku z Drogą
To przedwczesna śmierć.

Ci, którzy wiedzą, milczą,
A ci, którzy mówią, nie wiedzą.

Powściągnij zmysły,
Zatrzaśnij wszystkie wejścia.
Pozwól by rzeczy ostre się stępiły,
A zagmatwane rozwiązały,
By wygasi niepokój
I światło złagodniało.

Taka jest Jedność,
W którą Mędrzec wchodzi
Nie kierując się przywiązaniem
Ani nie tworząc dystansu.

Nie dla splendoru ani pohańbienia,
Nie dla zysku i nie dla wyrzeczeń,
Lecz w zgodzie z całym światem,
Prowadzony jest w miejsce najwyższe.

Rządź krajem sprawiedliwie w czas pokoju.
Bo gdy pokój się rozwieje
Tylko podstęp i zdrada pozostaną.

Ograniczenie jest wędzidłem, które wyznacza
Kierunek światu.
Gdy zakazy rosną, ludzie biednieją;
Kiedy armie się zbroją, w państwie powstaje chaos;
Gdy regulamin rządzi, pełno oszustów i złodziei.

Ale Mędrzec powiada:
Kiedy się ograniczam, ludzie też się zmieniają.
Skoro umiłowałem spokój, oni również ład tworzą.
Stałem się cierpliwy, więc będą się bogacić.
Ja nie pragnę niczego, to i oni stają się uczciwi.

Kiedy twoje rządy są łagodne, ludzie czują się wolni.
Kiedy rządzisz twardą ręką, pełni są niepokoju.
Często pragnienie zła rodzi dobro,
A pożądanie dobra przynosi same klęski.
Człowiek błądzi wśród sprzecznych kierunków,
Skoro sprawiedliwości przypisać można fałszywy rodowód,
A dobro poszukiwane jest pośród magicznych praktyk.

Mędrzec jest prostolinijny ale nie prostacki,
Rozumny, ale nigdy nie złośliwy;
Bywa surowy, ale nie bezwzględny;
I chociaż otacza go promienna jasność
Nigdy nie oślepia.

Sprawowanie rządów wśród ludzi i służba Niebu
Podobne są dozorowaniu wielkich magazynów
Skupiających niewyczerpane zasoby wiary i męstwa.
Taka pojemność określa władzę króla
I zasięg jego królestwa,
Wyznacza fundament sławy i nieśmiertelności.

Rządź wielkim krajem,
Jakbyś smażył małą rybkę.

Złe duchy świata tracą pozory czcigodności,
Gdy rząd postępuje zgodnie z Drogą,
Lecz jeśli nawet nie zmienią swojego oblicza
Ludzie za ich sprawą szkody nie odniosą.
A jeśli złe duchy nie kaleczą ludu,
Tym bardziej Mędrzec nie może być zraniony.

Gdy lud i Mędrzec nie szkodzą nawzajem
Ich cechy mogą się wspomagać.

Wielki kraj jest rozległą doliną,
Gdzie zewsząd strumienie spływają –
To mrowie i żeńskość świata.
Pokora i bierne wyczekiwanie
Przezwyciężą męską aktywność.

Spokojem i cierpliwością
Wielki kraj opanowuje małe narody,
Lecz również małe państwo może podbić
Wielkie swoim poddaniem.

Zdarza się, że ktoś nisko zgięty
Realizuje własne cele,
Podczas gdy inny w naturalny sposób
Panuje nad wszystkim.

Duch wielkiego kraju
Wymaga wielkiej liczby ludzi.
Mały kraj ponad wszystko
Potrzebuje miejsc do pracy.
Oba mogą osiągnąć swój cel
Stosując politykę pokory.

Jak bogowie we wnętrzu domowego sanktuarium,
Tak Droga i jej tajniki skryte są
Pośród materialnych rzeczy –
Skarb ludzi prawych i schronienie nikczemnych.

Dobry towar jest zawsze do zbycia;
Dobre sposoby są jak luźny płaszcz,
Odpowiedni dla każdego.
Na dzień koronacji, kiedy szlachetni są honorowani,
Stokroć lepiej, niż wóz paciorków z jadeitu,
Okazać skarb Drogi jako wyraz czci.

Czyż starożytni nie powiadali, że szukający znajdą,
A tym którzy znaleźli winy będą darowane?
Dlatego wynieśli oni Drogę i jej zasługi
Ponad wszelkie bogactwa w świecie.

Niech twój czyn trwa w bezczynie,
Praca w bezruchu.

Smakuj to, co pozbawione smaku;
Wielkie przyjmuj jak małe,
Częste – jak rzadkie,
Złość nagradzaj dobrem.

Weź ciężki trud na swoje barki,
By uczynić go łatwym.
Podejmij sprawy wielkiej wagi,
Niech stracą ważność.
Kłopoty tego świata są niemożliwe do rozwiązania,
Póki nie przekroczą zwykłych ludzkich możliwości.

Mędrzec w ciągu swego życia
Nie czyni nic wielkiego,
Przez to wielkość pozostaje
W nim samym.
Wybierając trud największy
Nigdy się już nie trudzi.

Łatwo jest zatrzymać to, co się nie porusza,
Łatwo przewidzieć przyszłość, gdy los sprzyja,
Łatwo rozgnieść rzecz kruchą i rozproszyć
Drobne cząstki.

Myśleć o środkach ostrożności
Trzeba zanim coś się zdarzy,
Wszak wielkie drzewa kiedyś były kiełkami,
Wspaniale ogrody pierwszą skibą ziemi,
A tysiącmilowa podróż, pierwszym krokiem.

Działając zepsujesz, zabierając stracisz.
Ponieważ Mędrzec wstrzymuje się od działania
Nie psuje niczego.
Nie podnosi, więc i nie gubi.

Ludzie zawsze niszczą swoje zamierzenia,
Gdy do ich realizacji pozostaje tylko krok.
Dlatego bądź równie uważny pod koniec,
Jak byłeś na początku.

Mędrzec chce tego, co niechciane,
A na to, co przez wszystkich poszukiwane
Nie ustala wysokich cen.
Studiuje on te myśli, które inni lekceważą
I wydobywa na światło to, co dla tysięcy
Pozostawało niezauważone.
Jego zadaniem jest przywrócić wszystko
Do naturalnego stanu,
Lecz nie uczynił jeszcze kroku.

Starożytni, którzy poznali treść Drogi,
Nie oświecali ludzi pouczeniami,
Nie wyjawiali subtelnych racji,
Raczej starali się utrzymać ich w niewiedzy.
Im bardziej lud wie o co chodzi,
Tym trudniej nim rządzić.

Oświecenie ludu jest dla rządu jak złodziej
Pragnący okraść królestwo.
Lecz gdy nadejdą pomyślniejsze czasy
Kraj będzie mógł być rządzony bez propagandy.
Któż rozumie odmienność tych sytuacji?
To tak jak dostrzegać różnicę
Pomiędzy „poszukiwać” i „znajdować”.

Miarą zawsze i wszędzie
Jest nieziszczalne Dobro.
Ono prowadzi głęboko i rozciąga się
W nieograniczoną przestrzeń.
Za jego sprawą rzeczy odmienne
Powracają ku pierwotnym związkom.

Jakim sposobem rzeki i strumienie
Królują w dolinach?
To proste: własna uległość sprowadza je w dół.

Podobnie przewodzić ludziom,
To stać się ich uniżonym sługą.
Jeśli więc chcesz stanąć na czele,
Pozostań daleko w tyle.

Mędrzec, mimo ze znajduje się wysoko,
Nie jest dla ludu ciężarem.
Jego posterunek jest przed wszystkimi,
By w porę dostrzec każde zagrożenie.

Świat wspomaga Mędrca
Bez żadnej zawiści.
Kto nie spiera się o swoje
Łatwo uzyskuje, co jest jego.

Mówią zewsząd: Droga, o której powiadacie,
To szkodliwa niedorzeczność.
Lecz to właśnie wielkość i siła sprawia
Że trudna jest do pojęcia.
Jeśli ma się okazać kodeksem, systemem przykazań,
Lepiej niech będzie błahostką!

Posiadam trzy dobrze strzeżone skarby:
Pierwszy – współczucie; drugi – umiarkowanie;
A trzeci polegający na tym, że nie zamierzam
Zostać władcą tego świata.

Ofiarowując współczucie zyskuję odwagę,
Przejawiając umiarkowanie mam obfitość,
Ponieważ jestem wobec świata pokorny
On czyni mnie najlepszym swoim instrumentem.

Dziś męstwo nie uznaje litości,
Obfitość jest rozpasana,
A dostojeństwo dalekie od pokory.
To, zaiste, pogrzebanie wszelkich naszych nadziei.

W śmiertelne; bitwie litość zwycięża czas,
Nadchodzi doskonałość i moc,
Bronią miłosierdzia Bóg wybawia ludzi.

Zręczny żołnierz nie jest gwałtowny,
Zdolny wojownik nie unosi się gniewem,
Potężny zdobywca nie wydaje bitwy,
Pełen jest pokory.

Takie jest męstwo.
Boska i ludzka doskonałość,
Starożytna godność.

Stratedzy powiadają:
Skoro nie stać mnie bym był gospodarzem,
Muszę być gościem;
Gdy nie posunę się naprzód nawet o cal,
Będę musiał się cofnąć o całą milę.

Oto złote zasady, które nazywają:
Polowaniem bez zwierza,
Kampanią bez przemarszów,
Uzbrojeniem bez broni.

Nie ma nic bardziej zdradzieckiego,
Niż bezradność wrogów,
Przez nich tracę co mam najlepszego.
Gdy nieprzyjaciel zaciekle stawia opór,
Człowiek miłosierny święci triumf.

Słowa moje łatwo jest zrozumieć,
Żyć według nich jest bardzo prosto,
Ale kto to zechce przyjąć?

Moje słowa posiadają wspaniałą przeszłość,
Moje prace mają królewski rodowód,
Lecz kto to poznał?
Gdy słowa moje nie mają gdzie dotrzeć
Ja również pozostanę w cieniu.

Oto zaszczyt największy:
„Mędrzec z klejnotem w piersi
Nadchodzi obleczony w łachmany”.

Wiedzieć że się nie wie
Jest najlepiej.
I chociaż to wielkie cierpienie
Znać, czego się nie może,
Poznać dolegliwość umysłu
Jest największym zdrowiem.

Człowiek mądry dostrzega każde skrzywienie
Dlatego choroba go omija.

Jeśli jesteś władcą, a ludzie nie obawiają się twojej
Potęgi, znacznie większy strach na siebie ściągną.
Bacz, by nie ograniczać ich swobód,
Nie prześladować dzieci, nie niszczyć inwentarza,
Ani nie budzić w nich gniewu własną złością.

Mędrzec zna siebie, lecz myśli nie ujawnia.
Kocha siebie, lecz się nie upiera,
Trudno więc przewidzieć jak postąpi.

Człowiek silny i nie bojący się swego czynu może zabić.
Kiedy jednak się zlęknie, może zachować czyjeś życie.
Tak jedno, jak i drugie pociąga za sobą
Złe i dobre skutki.
Któż zgłębi wszystkie przyczyny cierpień?
Mędrzec również ma chwile zwątpienia.
Droga Niebios wiedzie ku całkowitym zwycięstwom,
Lecz nie mieczem osiąga się tu sukcesy.

Niebiosa odpowiadają bez użycia słów.
Nikt nie woła, a wszystkie istoty przychodzą.
Mistrzowskie plany realizują się wolno,
Jak szeroka sieć obejmują wszystko.
Choć oka są duże, nikt się nie wymknie.

Ludzie nie obawiają się śmierci.
Grożąc im niewiele więc wskórasz,
A jeśli nawet zdołasz ich nastraszyć
I konsekwentnie będziesz działał,
To kto ich pozabija?

Egzekutor jest wyznaczony raz na zawsze,
A Jego zastępcy?
Próbują rąbać, jak czyni to doświadczony rzemieślnik,
A prawie zawsze kaleczą własne dłonie!

Ludzie głodują z powodu tych, którzy ściągając
Z nich podatki bardziej są gorliwi od praw.
Nie jest łatwo rządzić ludźmi zakłócając ich życie
I powodując nieszczęścia.
Wówczas władza jest istotnie niewdzięcznym zadaniem.

W taki czas ludzie przestają się bać śmierci.
Pragnienie wolnego życia przerasta lęk.
Nie mając środków do życia, lekceważą sobie życie.
Lecz przez to bardziej są życia godni
Niż ci, co własne istnienie kochają ponad wszystkie wartości.

Człowiek żywy miękki jest i uległy.
Umarły – surowy, nieugięty.
Zwierzęta, trawy i drzewa żyjąc
Plastyczne są i ustępliwe,
Gdy giną wysychają, stają się sztywne i kruche.

Nieugięty rygor jest towarzyszem śmierci,
A swoboda i spontaniczność przyjacielem życia.

Najtwardsze drzewo doskonale jest do obróbki,
Mocne i potężne łatwo zostanie powalone.
Niepozorne i uległe przerośnie wszystkie inne.

Wielka Droga przypomina dobrze naciągnięty łuk:
Górna część została poruszona i ściągnięta w dół,
Część dolna mknie ku górze.
Wiotkie zostaje wywyższone, a sprężyste ściągnięte.
Ta sama siła odsuwa tych, którzy wiele nagromadzili,
By napełnić miski potrzebujących.
Ludzkie ścieżki jednak zdają się temu zaprzeczać:
Ci, którzy mają mało, stają się jeszcze
Obiektem rabunku płacąc haracz władcom.

Któż będzie oswobodzicielem i dobroczyńcą świata
Czerpiąc z obfitych przecież zasobów?
Jedynie Mędrzec znający Drogę będzie mógł to uczynić.
Stojącemu na uboczu obojętne są ludzkie kaprysy,
I nie sława, ani godność są przyczyną jego sukcesów.

Od wody cóż może być bardziej pokorne?
Lecz kiedy podmywa skaliste brzegi
I gwałtownie napiera, nic się jej nie oprze,
Żadna przeszkoda nie zmieni jej biegu.

Każdy może zobaczyć jej słabość
Przezwycięża moc, a delikatność podbija
Nie wzruszone w człowieku przeszkody.

Dlatego Mędrzec powiada,
Że ten tylko, kto się stał pośmiewiskiem narodów,
Jest wyznaczony na ich Świętego Pana
I tylko ten, kto bierze na siebie
Cale zło tego świata, może być jego Królem.
Oto największy paradoks.

Zdarzają się nieszczęścia zbyt wielkie,
By można je było zignorować,
Choć sama próba roztrząsania może wywołać
Tylko jeszcze większe zadrażnienie.

Mędrzec pominie wątpliwą część kontraktu,
Nie obarczy nikogo długiem.
Człowiek uczciwy dąży do pojednania,
Przewrotny szuka winnych.

Droga Niebios jest bezstronna
Nie wyróżnia osób,
Niemniej dobrych zawsze wspomaga.

Idealny kraj jest mały,
Lud jego nieliczny,
Narzędzi jest tam
Pod dostatkiem,
Stokroć ponad potrzebę.

Ludzie umierają
I umierają,
Lecz nigdy nie emigrują;
Mają wozy i łodzie,
Których nikt nie używa,
Mają broń i zbroje,
Których nigdy nie pokazują.
Ludzie ci rozwiązują cierpliwie,
By użyć po raz drugi,
Tego samego postronka.
Ich posiłki są smaczne,
Ubrania strojne,
Ich domy są ciche,
A zwyczaje ujmujące.

A kraje sąsiednie
Tak są położone,
Że można stamtąd słyszeć
Szczekanie psów
I pianie kogutów.
W tym kraju
Ludzie się starzeją
I będą umierali
Lecz nigdy nikt
Nie zmieni jego nazwy.

Słowa uczciwe nie muszą być przyjemne,
Słowa przyjemne nie muszą być uczciwe.
Człowiek rzetelny nie spiera się,
A ten kto obstaje przy swoim
Niekoniecznie jest rzetelny.
Ci, którzy wiedzą nie są oczytani,
A oczytani często nie posiadają wiedzy.

Mędrzec nie ciuła przedmiotów
Ciężko przyciskany służbą dla dobra innych,
Ma tylko to, co niezbędne,
Lecz potrafi oddać wszystko co posiada,
Zatem naprawdę jest bogaty.

Wielka Droga wymaga, by zysk
Nie stawał się krzywdą.
Drogą Mędrca jest czynić swoją powinność
Bez zabiegania o zaszczyty.

Od Tłumacza

Dokonując przekładu Lao Tsy poprzez język angielski powinienem mieć odczucie, że oddalam się od oryginału na niebezpieczną odległość. I tak jest w istocie. To co przedstawiłem może stanowić jedynie moją własną interpretację myśli Mędrca w oparciu głównie o Blakney’a i parę innych znanych mi przekładów. Przedsięwzięcie to nie wydawało mi się jednak absurdalne przy tego rodzaju tekstach, mówiących że zgodność z Drogą, z jej Pierwotnym Sensem nie może być niczym zagwarantowana. Jest to bowiem sens żywy, ponadhistoryczny i w pewien sposób ponadjęzykowy. Dlatego pewnie tak wiele jest przekładów Tao Te King na języki świata, tak bardzo różne przybierają formy i tak odbiegają od siebie. Nie znaczy to, że każda improwizacja na temat Tao Te King ma być jednakowo uprawniona, jednak podstawa przekładu musi znajdować się poza jakimkolwiek językowym ukształtowaniem w pustce czystego umysłu, w dyspozycyjności wielkich przestrzeni natury. Nie wiem czy tam zdołałem dotrzeć, choćby częściowo, uświadamiałem sobie tylko, że należy szu kać poprzez osiemdziesiąt jeden wierszy.

Michał Fostowicz

Tao, które można wyrazić słowami, nie jest prawdziwym Tao.

Imię, które może być nadane, nie jest stałym imieniem.

Bezimienne jest początkiem nieba i ziemi, imię posiadające – matką wszystkich rzeczy.

Dlatego ten, kto wolny jest od namiętności, widzi jego chwałę, a kto namiętnościami jest ogarnięty, widzi je tylko w formie skończonej.

Pierwsze i wtóre są tego samego pochodzenia, lecz z różnymi nazwami. Razem nazywają się najgłębszym. Od jednego najgłębszego do wtórego – drzwi do wszelkiej cudowności.

Kiedy ludzie dowiadują się, że piękne jest pięknym, pojawia się i wstrętne.

Kiedy dowiadują się, że dobro jest dobrem, pojawia się i zło.

Dlatego byt i niebyt rodzą siebie nawzajem, trudne i łatwe rodzą siebie nawzajem, długie i krótkie wzajemnie się oblekają w kształt, wysokie i niskie wzajemnie się przyciągają, dźwięki łącząc się zestrajają w harmonię, poprzedzające i następujące dokonują się jedno za drugim.

Dlatego mądry człowiek wybiera nieczynienie i realizuje naukę bezgłośnie. Wtedy wszystkie rzeczy rozpoczynają ruch i nie zaprzestają. On stwarza i nie posiada, czyni i nie korzysta, dokonuje i nie pyszni się. Ponieważ nie pyszni się, nie porzucają go.

Jeśli nie wyróżniać mędrców, to w narodzie nie będzie waśni. Jeśli nie cenić drogocennych przedmiotów, to w narodzie nie będzie złodziei. Jeśli nie widać upragnionego przedmiotu, to serca narodu nie będą podniecone.

Dlatego rządy mądrego człowieka czynią serca pustymi, a żołądki pełnymi. Osłabiają one wolę i wzmacniają kości. Będą stale dążyć do tego, aby naród nie posiadał wiedzy i namiętności, a posiadający wiedzę nie ośmielili się działać.

Urzeczywistnienie nieczynienia zawsze przynosi spokój.

Tao jest puste, lecz działając wydaje się niewyczerpane.

O, najgłębsze! Ono wydaję się być praojcem wszelkiej rzeczy.

Jeśli przytępić jego przenikliwość, uwolnić je od chaosu, umiarkować jego blask, upodobnić je do pyłku, to będzie ono wydawać się jasno istniejącym.

Nie wiem czyim ono jest tworem.

Poprzedza ono przodka zjawisk.

Niebo i ziemia nie są humanitarne i odnoszą się one do wszystkich istot, jak do trawy i zwierząt.

Mądry człowiek nie jest humanitarny i nie narusza naturalnego życia narodu.

Przestrzeń między niebem i ziemią podobna jest do miecha kowalskiego i fletu: wewnątrz pusta i prosta. Im silniejszy ruch, tym większy skutek.

Ten, kto wiele mówi, często przeżywa niepowodzenie. Dlatego najlepiej jest przestrzegać środka.

Pustka jest nieśmiertelna i nazywam ją najgłębszym początkiem. Wejście w najgłębszy początek nazywam korzeniem nieba i ziemi. Nieskończone jest jako istnienie i działa bez wysiłku.

Niebo i ziemia są długowieczne. Niebo i ziemia są długowieczne dlatego, że istnieją one nie dla siebie. Oto dlaczego mogą być długowieczne.

Dlatego mądry człowiek stawia siebie za innymi, dzięki czemu okazuje się on przed ludźmi. Lekceważy on swoje życie i tym samym życie jego jest zachowane. Pochodzi to stąd, że mędrzec lekce sobie waży osobiste i tym samym jego osobiste jest spełniane.

Wyższa cnota podobna jest do wody. Woda przynosi pożytek wszystkim ludziom i nie walczy. Ona znajduje się tam, gdzie ludzie nie chcieliby być. Dlatego podobna jest do Tao.

Życie powinno wzorować się na ziemi; serce powinno przestrzegać wewnętrznych pobudek; dobroczynność powinna być zgodna z człowieczeństwem; słowo powinno być zgodne z prawdą; kierowanie powinno być zgodne ze spokojem; czyn powinien być współmierny do możliwości; działanie powinno być zgodne z czasem.

I jeśli nie walczyć – nie będzie narzekania.

Kto napełnia nad miarę i ostrzy zbyt ostro, ten nie może długo zachować.

Jeśli komnata napełniona jest złotem i jaspisem, to nikt nie jest w stanie jej ochraniać. Jeśli bogaci i wielmoże są dumni, to sami ściągają na siebie nieszczęście.

Jeśli sprawa jest zakończona, człowiek powinien odejść. W tym jest prawo naturalnego Tao.

Dla zachowania spokoju duszy należy przestrzegać jedności. Wtedy nie będą budzić się pragnienia. Jeśli uczynić duch miękkim, człowiek stanie się podobny do nowonarodzonego. Jeśli jego postrzeganie staje się czyste, wtedy nie będzie błędów.

Miłowanie ludu i kierowanie krajem odbywa się bez mędrkowania. Wrota świata otwierają się i zamykają przy zachowaniu spokoju. Znajomość tej prawdy czyni możliwym nieczynienie.

Rodzić i wychowywać, stwarzać i nie posiadać, tworzyć i nie korzystać, będąc starszym pośród innych nie uważać siebie za władającego – to wszystko nazywa się najgłębszym Te.

Trzydzieści szprych łączy się w jednej piaście formując koło, a używanie koła zależy od pustki między nimi. Z gliny robi się naczynia, a używanie naczyń zależy od pustki w nich. Przebijają drzwi i okna, aby zrobić dom, a korzystanie z domu zależy od pustki w nim. Oto co znaczy użyteczność bytu i pożytek z niebytu.

Pięć kolorów przytępia wzrok. Pięć dźwięków przytępia słuch. Pięć doznań smakowych przytępia smak. Szybka jazda i polowanie podniecają serce. Drogocenne rzeczy zmuszają człowieka, by dokonał przestępstwa. Dlatego wysiłki mądrego człowieka skierowane są na to, aby życie nasycić, a nie na to, aby posiadać ładne rzeczy. On rezygnuje z tych ostatnich i zadowala się pierwszymi.

Sława i hańba podobne są do strachu. Wielmożność podobna jest do wielkiego nieszczęścia w życiu. Co znaczy, że sława i hańba podobne są do strachu? To znaczy, że pośledni ludzie zyskują sobie sławę ze strachem i tracą ją także ze strachem. Co znaczy, że wielmożność podobna jest do wielkiego nieszczęścia w życiu? To znaczy, że ja mam wielkie nieszczęście, ponieważ cenię samego siebie. Gdy nie będę cenić samego siebie, wtedy nie będę mieć nieszczęścia. Dlatego wielmożny, służąc z samozaparciem ludziom, może żyć pośród nich. Humanitarny, służąc z samozaparciem ludziom, może przebywać pośród nich.

Patrzę na nie i nie widzę, dlatego nazywam je niewidocznym. Słucham go i nie słyszę, dlatego nazywam je niesłyszalnym. Staram się je pochwycić i nie mogę, dlatego nazywam je najdrobniejszym. Te trzy są niewytłumaczalne. Dlatego łączą się one w jedno. Jego wierzch nie jest oświetlony, jego spód nie jest zaciemniony. Ono jest nieskończone i nie może być nazwane. Ono ponownie wraca do niebytu. I oto nazywają je kształtem bez kształtu, kształtem bez istoty. Dlatego nazywają je niejasnym i mglistym. Spotykam się z nim i nie widzę jego twarzy, śledzę je i nie widzę jego pleców.

Trzymając się odwiecznego Tao i opanowując teraźniejszy byt, można poznać odwieczny początek. Nazywa się to nicią Tao.

W dawnych czasach ten, kto był zdolny do oświecenia, znał najdrobniejsze i głębokie. Ukryte, dlatego nie można było ich poznać. Ponieważ nie można było ich poznać, dowolnie nadawano im kształt: one były nieśmiałe, jak gdyby przechodziły zimą przez potok; one były niezdecydowane, jak gdyby bały się swoich sąsiadów; one były ważne jak goście; one były ostrożne, jak gdyby przechodziły po topniejącym lodzie; one były proste jak nieobrobione drzewo; one były nieobjęte jak dolina; one były nieprzeniknione jak mętna woda. To były te, które zachowując spokój, umiały brudne uczynić czystym. To były te, które zdolne czynić długowieczny ruch spokojnym, współdziałały z życiem. One postrzegały Tao i nie pragnęły wiele. Nie pragnąc wiele, zadowalały się tym, co istnieje i nie tworzyły nowego.

Doprowadzę pustkę do kresu – zachowam pełny spokój, i wtedy wszystkie rzeczy będą wzrastać, a ja czekać będę ich powrotu. Wszystkie rzeczy rozkwitają i wracają do swego początku. Powrót do początku nazywa się spokojem, a spokój nazywa się powrotem do życia. Powrót do życia nazywa się stałością. Znajomość stałości nazywa się oświeceniem, a nieznajomość stałości czyni zło. Znający stałość staje się mądrym, mądry staje się sprawiedliwym, a kto jest sprawiedliwy – staje się panującym. Panujący podąża za niebem, niebo podąża za Tao, a Tao jest wieczne. Do końca życia nie zazna niebezpieczeństwa.

Prości ludzie wiedzieli, że mają ludzi wielkich. Oni kochali ich i wywyższali. Potem bali się ich i pogardzali. Dlatego, kto nie zasługuje na zaufanie, ten nie cieszy się zaufaniem. Kto jest wnikliwy i wstrzemięźliwy w słowach, ten zyskuje zasługi i dokonuje czynów, i naród mówi, że on przestrzega naturalności.

Gdy usunięto wielkie Tao, pojawił się „humanizm” i pojawiła się „sprawiedliwość”. Gdy pojawiło się mędrkowanie, powstała i wielka obłuda. Gdy sześciu krewnych wiedzie spór, wtedy pojawia się „synowski szacunek” i „ojcowska miłość”. Gdy w państwie panuje nieporządek, wtedy pojawiają się „wierni poddani”.

Kiedy będą zaniechane mędrkowanie i uczoność, wtedy naród będzie stokroć szczęśliwszy; kiedy będą zaniechane „humanizm” i „sprawiedliwość”, wtedy naród powróci do synowskiego szacunku i ojcowskiej miłości; kiedy będą zniszczone chytrość i wyzysk, wtedy znikną złodzieje i rozbójnicy. Wszystkie te trzy rzeczy pochodzą z braku wiedzy. Dlatego należy wskazywać ludziom, że powinni być oni prości i skromni, zmniejszać osobiste i uwolnić siebie od namiętności.

Kiedy będzie zniszczona „uczoność”, wtedy nie będzie i troski. Jakże niewielka jest różnica pomiędzy obietnicą i pochlebstwem, i jak wielka jest różnica między dobrem i złem. Należy unikać tego, czego ludzie się boją.

O! Jakiż zamęt tam, gdzie wciąż jeszcze nie ustalono porządku. Wszyscy ludzie są radośni, jak gdyby obecni byli na uroczystym przyjęciu lub świętowali nadejście wiosny. Tylko ja jeden jestem spokojny i nie wystawiam siebie na światło. Podobny jestem do dziecka, które nie pojawiło się na świecie. O! Spieszę! Wydaje się, że nie ma miejsca, gdzie mógłbym się zatrzymać. Wszyscy ludzie pełni są pragnień, tylko ja jeden podobny jestem do tego, który ze wszystkiego zrezygnował. Jestem sercem głupiego człowieka. O, jakże ono jest puste! Wszyscy ludzie pełni są światła. Tylko ja jeden pogrążony jestem w mroku. Wszyscy ludzie są zaciekawieni, tylko ja jeden jestem obojętny. Jestem jak ten, kto unosi się w przestworzach mórz i nie wie, gdzie by się zatrzymać. Wszyscy ludzie ujawniają swe zdolności i tylko ja jeden podobny jestem do głupiego i nikczemnego. Tylko ja jeden różnię się od innych tym, że dostrzegam źródło życiodajne.

Kształty wielkiego Te podporządkowują się tylko Tao. Tao – rzecz niejasna i mglista.

O, mgliste! O, niejasne! W nim zawarte są kształty. O, niejasne! O, mgliste! W nim zawarte są rzeczy. O, bezdenne! O, mgliste! W nim zawarte są nasiona. Jego nasiona są całkowicie godne wiary, i w nim zawarta jest prawda. Z dawien dawna do naszych dni jego imię nie zanika. Ono istnieje dla oznaczenia początku wszystkich rzeczy. Dlaczego ja znam początek wszystkich rzeczy? Tylko dzięki niemu.

Niepełne staje się pełnym; krzywe staje się prostym; puste staje się napełnionym; zmurszałe staje się nowym; nieliczne staje się mnogie. Mnogość wywołuje błądzenie. Dlatego mądry człowiek chroni jedność i staje się przykładem dla wszystkich. On nie wystawia siebie na światło – dlatego jaśnieje; on nie mówi o sobie – dlatego jest sławny; on nie wysławia siebie – dlatego jest zasłużony; on nie wywyższa się – dlatego jest starszym pośród innych. On nie walczy – dlatego jest niepokonany w świecie.

W zamierzchłych czasach mówili, że niedoskonałe staje się doskonałym. Czyżby to były puste słowa?

Prawdziwe, doskonałe podporządkowuje sobie wszystko.

Należy mniej mówić, przestrzegać naturalności. Silny wiatr nie trwa przez cały poranek, silny deszcz nie pada cały dzień. Kto czyni to wszystko? Niebo i ziemia. Nawet niebo i ziemia nie mogą uczynić czegokolwiek długowiecznym, tym bardziej człowiek. Dlatego służy on Tao.

Człowiek z Tao – jest tożsamy Tao. Człowiek z Te – jest tożsamy Te. Ten, kto utracił, tożsamy jest stracie. Ten, kto jest tożsamy Tao, otrzymuje Tao. Ten, kto jest tożsamy Te, otrzymuje Te. Ten, kto jest tożsamy utracie, otrzymuje stratę. Tylko wątpliwości rodzą niewiarę.

Kto wspiął się na palce, nie może stać. Kto robi wielkie kroki, nie może chodzić. Kto sam siebie wystawia na światło, nie błyszczy. Kto sam siebie wychwala, ten nie zdobędzie sławy. Kto napada, nie osiąga sukcesu. Kto sam siebie wywyższa, nie może być starszym pośród innych. Wobec Tao, wszystko to nazywa się zbędnym pragnieniem i bezużytecznym postępowaniem. Takich nienawidzą wszystkie istoty. Dlatego człowiek posiadający Tao, nie czyni tego.

Oto rzecz w chaosie powstająca, przed niebem i ziemią zrodzona. O, spokojna! O, pusta! Jednako stoi ona i nie zmienia się. Wszędzie działa i nie wystawiona jest na niebezpieczeństwo. Można ją uważać za matkę sfery podniebnej. Nie znam jej imienia. Oznaczając znakiem, nazwę ją Tao. Dowolne dając imię, nazwę ją wielką. Wielka – nazwę ją przemijającą. Przemijająca – nazwę ją odległą. Odległa – nazwę ją powracającą. Oto dlaczego wielkie jest Tao, wielkie niebo, wielka ziemia, wielki też jest władca. We wszechświecie jest czterech wielkich, a jednym z nich jest władca.

Człowiek posłuszny jest ziemi. Ziemia posłuszna jest niebu. Niebo posłuszne jest Tao, a Tao przestrzega tego, co naturalne.

Ciężkie jest podłożem lekkiego. Spokój jest najważniejszy w ruchu. Dlatego mądry człowiek działa cały dzień, nie porzucając ciężkiej sprawy. Chociaż żywi wspaniałą nadzieję, przebywa w całkowitym spokoju. Na próżno władca dziesięciu tysięcy wozów bojowych, sobą zajęty, tak lekkomyślnie patrzy na świat. Lekkomyślność rujnuje jego podłoże, a jego pośpiech prowadzi do utraty punktu oparcia.

Kto potrafi kroczyć, nie zostawia śladów. Kto potrafi mówić, nie popełnia błędów. Kto umie liczyć, nie korzysta z rachunku. Kto potrafi zamykać drzwi, nie korzysta z zamka i zamyka je tak mocno, że otworzyć nie sposób. Kto potrafi zawiązywać węzły, nie korzysta ze sznura i zawiązuje tak mocno, że rozwiązać nie sposób. Dlatego mądry człowiek stale umiejętnie ratuje ludzi i nie porzuca ich. On zawsze potrafi ratować istoty, dlatego ich nie porzuca. To nazywa się głębokim oświeceniem. W taki sposób cnota jest nauczycielem niedobrych, a niedobrzy są dla niej podporą. Jeśli nie cenią swego nauczyciela i cnota nie lubi swej podpory, to chociaż uważają się za rozumnych, pogrążeni są w ślepocie. Oto co jest najważniejsze i głębokie.

Kto, znając swą odwagę, zachowuje skromność, ten staje się w kraju jak górski strumień. Kto stał się głównym w kraju, ten nie porzuca Te i powraca do stanu niemowlęcia. Kto, znając świąteczne, zachowuje dla siebie powszednie, ten staje się przykładem dla wszystkich. Kto stał się przykładem dla wszystkich, ten nie różni się od Te i powraca do bezpoczątkowego. Kto, znając swoją sławę, pozostaje nieznany, ten staje się głównym w kraju. Kto stał się głównym w kraju, ten osiąga doskonałość w Te i powraca do naturalnego. Kiedy naturalne rozpada się, przekształca się ono w środek, przy którego pomocy człowiek mądry staje się wodzem i jego wielki porządek nie ulega zagładzie.

Jeśli ktokolwiek próbuje siłą opanować kraj, to widzę, że nie osiąga celu. Kraj podobny jest do tajemniczego naczynia, którego nie można dotknąć. Jeśli ktokolwiek dotknie, poniesie klęskę. Jeśli ktokolwiek chwyci, ten utraci.

Dlatego jedne istoty idą, inne podążają za nimi; jedne rozkwitają, inne usychają; jedni wzmacniają się, inni słabną; jedni stwarzają się, inni giną. Dlatego mądry człowiek rezygnuje z nadmiaru, odsuwa rozkosz i marnotrawstwo.

Kto służy przywódcy narodu za pośrednictwem Tao, nie zniewala innych krajów za pomocą wojska, gdyż może to obrócić się przeciwko niemu. Gdzie przebywały wojska, tam rośnie tarnina i oset. Po wielkich wojnach następują lata głodu.

Wytrawny wódz zwycięża i na tym poprzestaje, i nie ośmiela się on dokonywać gwałtu. On zwycięża i nie napada. On zwycięża i nie chełpi się. On zwycięża dlatego, że zmuszają go do tego. On zwycięża, ale nie jest wojowniczy.

Kiedy istota pełna sił starzeje się – nazywa się to brakiem Tao. Kto nie przestrzega Tao, zginie przed czasem.

Dobre wojsko – narzędzie nieszczęścia; nienawidzą go wszystkie istoty. Dlatego człowiek przestrzegający Tao nie używa tego narzędzia.

Szlachetny w czasie pokoju wybiera szacunek, a na wojnie stosuje przemoc. Wojsko – narzędzie nieszczęścia; nie jest ono narzędziem szlachetnego. On tylko wtedy używa wojska, kiedy zmuszają go do tego. Zasada polega na tym, aby zachować spokój, a w wypadku zwycięstwa – nie wysławiać siebie. Wysławiać swoje zwycięstwo, to znaczy cieszyć się z zabicia ludzi. Kto raduje się z zabicia ludzi, nie może znaleźć współczucia w kraju. Dobrobyt stwarzany jest przez szacunek, a nieszczęście pochodzi z gwałtu.

Z lewa stoją dowódcy skrzydeł, z prawej stoi wódz. Mówią, że należy ich powitać ceremonią pogrzebową. Jeśli zabija się wielu ludzi, to należy z tego powodu gorzko płakać. Zwycięstwo należy uczcić ceremonią pogrzebową.

Tao jest wieczne i nie posiada imienia. Chociaż jest ono istotą maleńką, nikt w świecie nie może go sobie podporządkować. Jeśli wielmoże i władcy są w stanie je przestrzegać, to wszystkie istoty stają się spokojne. Wtedy niebo i ziemia łączą się w harmonii, następuje szczęście i dobrobyt, a naród bez nakazów uspokaja się.

Przy ustalaniu hierarchii pojawiają się imiona. Ponieważ pojawiły się imiona, należy znać granicę. Znajomość granicy stwarza możliwość uchronienia siebie przed niebezpieczeństwem.

Tao, znajdując się w świecie, podobne jest do górskich potoków, które płyną do rzek i mórz.

Ten, kto zna ludzi, jest rozsądny. Znając siebie – jest oświecony. Zwyciężający ludzi – jest silny. Zwyciężający siebie – jest mocarny. Kto zna dostatek – jest bogaty.

Kto działa z uporem – posiada wolę. Kto nie traci swej natury – jest długowieczny. Kto umarł, lecz nie jest zapomniany, ten jest nieśmiertelny.

Wielkie Tao przenika wszędzie. Ono może być na prawo i na lewo. Dzięki niemu rodzą się wszystkie istoty, i one nie zatrzymują się. Ono dokonuje czynów bohaterskich, lecz nie pragnie dla siebie sławy. Z miłością wychowując wszystkie istoty, nie staje się ono ich panem. Ono nie ma nigdy własnego pragnienia, dlatego można je nazwać skromnym. Wszystkie istoty powracają do niego, i ono nie uważa siebie za władającego. Można je nazwać wielkim. Ono staje się wielkie dzięki temu, że nigdy za takowe się nie uważa.

Kto jawi sobą wielkie Tao, do tego przychodzi cały naród. Ludzie przychodzą i on im nie wyrządza szkody. On przynosi im spokój, pokój, muzykę i pożywienie. Nawet wędrowiec u niego się zatrzymuje.

Kiedy Tao wychodzi z ust, jest ono przaśne, bez smaku. Jest niewidoczne i nie można go usłyszeć. W działaniu jest niewyczerpane.

To, co ściśnięte – rozszerza się. To, co jest osłabione – wzmacnia się. To, co jest niszczone – rozkwita. Kto pragnie odebrać cokolwiek drugiemu – niewątpliwie traci własne. Wszystko to nazywa się trudno zrozumiałym. Miękkie pokonuje twarde, słabi zwyciężają silnych. Ryba nie może opuścić głębiny. Ostrego oręża w państwie nie należy pokazywać ludziom.

Tao stale realizuje nieczynienie, tym samym nie istnieje nic, czego by ono nie czyniło. Jeśli wielmoże i władcy będą się na nim wzorować, to wszystkie istoty będą się zmieniać same przez się. Jeśli te, które się zmieniają, zechcą działać, to ja uspokoję je za pomocą prostego bytu nie posiadającego imienia. Nie posiadający imienia – prosty byt – niczego dla siebie nie pragnie. Brak pragnienia przynosi spokój, i wtedy porządek w kraju ustala się sam.

Człowiek z wyższym Te nie realizuje dobrych uczynków, dlatego jest on pełen cnoty. Człowiek z niższym Te nie zaniedbuje dobrych uczynków, dlatego nie jest cnotliwy. Człowiek z wyższym Te jest bezczynny i działa przez nieczynienie. Człowiek z niższym Te jest czynny i działa z napięciem. Człowiek „wyższego humanitaryzmu” działa i jego działanie dokonuje się poprzez nieczynienie. Człowiek „wyższej sprawiedliwości” jest czynny i działa z napięciem. Człowiek „wyższej uległości” działa i nikt mu nie odpowiada. Wówczas on zmusza ludzi do szacunku. Oto dlaczego „cnota” pojawia się tylko po utracie Tao, „humanizm” – po utracie „cnoty”, „sprawiedliwość” – po utracie „humanizmu”, „szacunek” – po utracie „sprawiedliwości”. „Uległość”, to oznaka braku zaufania i braku oddania. Jest ona początkiem buntu.

Wygląd zewnętrzny, to kwiat Tao – początek ciemnoty. Dlatego wielki człowiek bierze istotne i pozostawia znikome. Bierze owoc i odrzuca jego kwiat. On wybiera pierwsze i rezygnuje z drugiego.

Oto ci, którzy z dawien dawna przebywają w jedności. Dzięki jedności niebo stało się czyste, ziemia – opoką, duch – wrażliwym, dolina – kwitnącą i zaczęły rodzić się wszystkie istoty. Dzięki jedności wielmoże i władcy stają się w świecie wzorem. Oto co stwarza jedność.

Jeśli niebo jest nieczyste, rozpada się ono; jeśli ziemia jest ruchoma – pęka ona; jeśli duch nie jest czujny, znika on; jeśli doliny nie kwitną, przekształcają się one w pustynię; jeśli rzeczy się nie rodzą – znikają one; jeśli wielmoże i władcy nie są wzorem szlachetności, będą oni obaleni.

Maluczcy są podstawą dla wielkich, a niskie – podstawą wysokiego. Dlatego wielmoże i władcy, którzy sami siebie wywyższają, nie mają trwałego miejsca. Dzieje się tak dlatego, że nie traktują oni maluczkich jako swej podstawy. To błędna droga. Jeśli rozebrać wóz, nic z niego nie zostanie. Nie można być drogocennym jak jaspis, ale należy być prostym jak kamień.

Przeciwstawność jest działaniem Tao, słabość jest właściwością Tao. W świecie wszystkie rzeczy rodzą się w bycie, a byt rodzi się w niebycie.

Mądry człowiek, dowiadując się o Tao, dąży do jego urzeczywistnienia. Wykształcony człowiek, dowiadując się o Tao, to wzoruje się na nim, to je traci. Nieuk, dowiadując się o Tao, wyśmiewa je. Jeśli nie byłoby wyśmiane, nie byłoby Tao. Dlatego istnieje porzekadło: kto dowiaduje się o Tao, podobny jest do ślepca; kto wnika w Tao, podobny jest do wycofującego się; kto jest na poziomie Tao, podobny jest do błądzącego; człowiek najwyższej cnoty podobny jest do prostaka; wielki oświecony podobny jest do wzgardzonego; bezgraniczna cnota podobna jest do jej braku; rozprzestrzenianie cnoty podobne jest do jej grabieży; istotna prawda podobna jest do jej nieobecności.

Wielki kwadrat nie ma kątów; ogromne naczynie długo jest wyrabiane; silnego dźwięku nie można usłyszeć; wielki kształt nie ma kształtu.

Tao ukryte jest i nie posiada imienia. Lecz okazuje ono pomoc i prowadzi do doskonałości.

Tao rodzi jedno, jedno rodzi dwa, dwa rodzą trzy, a trzy – wszystkie istoty. Wszystkie istoty niosą w sobie jin i jang, napełnione są tsi i tworzą harmonię.

Ludzie pogardzają tymi, którzy sami siebie wywyższają i nazywają siebie władcami oraz wielmożami. Wszystkie istoty wzmacniają się po osłabieniu i słabną po wzmocnieniu.

Ludzie rozpowszechniają swoją wiedzę, i ja tym się zajmuję. Okrutni i tyrani nie umierają własną śmiercią. Przytaczam to jako przykład w swoim pouczeniu.

W świecie najsłabsi zwyciężają najsilniejszych. Niebyt przenika wszędzie i gdziekolwiek. Oto dlaczego znam korzyść z nieczynienie. W świecie nie ma niczego, co można by porównać z nauką ciszy i korzyścią nieczynienia.

Co jest bardziej istotne – sława czy życie? Co jest droższe – życie czy bogactwo? Co jest trudniej przeżyć – zysk czy utratę? Kto wiele oszczędza, ten poniesie duże straty. Kto wiele gromadzi, ten poniesie duże straty. Kto zna miarę, ten nie dozna niepowodzenia. Kto zna granicę, ten nie będzie w niebezpieczeństwie. On staje się długowieczny.

Wielka doskonałość podobna jest do niedoskonałości; jej działanie jest nieskończone. Wielka pełnia podobna jest do pustki; jej działanie jest niewyczerpane. Wielka prostota podobna jest do skrzywienia. Wielkie poczucie humoru podobne jest do głupoty. Wielki mówca podobny jest do jąkały.

Ruch przezwycięża chłód, spokój przezwycięża żar. Spokój tworzy ład w świecie.

Kiedy kraj zachowuje Tao, konie pracują na roli; kiedy w kraju brak jest Tao, konie bojowe pasą się na polach. Nie ma większego nieszczęścia, niż nieznajomość granicy swojej namiętności, i nie ma większego niebezpieczeństwa, niż dążenie do korzyści. Dlatego ten, kto potrafi zadowalać się, jest zawsze zadowolony.

Mędrzec, nie wychodząc z domu, poznaje świat. Nie wyglądając przez okno, widzi on naturalne Tao. Im bardziej się oddala, tym mniej poznaje. Dlatego mądry człowiek nie chodzi, lecz poznaje. Nie widząc, nadaje nazwy. Nie czyniąc, tworzy.

Kto się uczy, codziennie powiększa. Kto służy Tao, z dnia na dzień pomniejsza. W nieprzerwanym pomniejszaniu dochodzi do nieczynienia. Nie ma niczego, co by nie dokonywało nieczynienia. Dlatego podbicie kraju zawsze urzeczywistnia się poprzez nieczynienie. Kto działa, nie jest w stanie opanować kraju.

Mądry człowiek nie ma własnego serca. Jego serce składa się z serc narodu. Dobrym czynię dobro i niedobrym życzę dobra. To właśnie jest cnota zrodzona przez Te. Szczerym wierzę i nieszczerym takoż wierzę. To właśnie jest szczerość wypływająca z Te. Mądry człowiek żyje w świecie spokojnie i w swoim sercu zbiera myśli narodu. On patrzy na naród jak na swoje dzieci.

Rodzą się i umierają. Spośród dziesięciu ludzi trzech ku życiu i spośród dziesięciu – trzech ku śmierci. Spośród każdych dziesięciu jest jeszcze trzech ludzi, którzy umierają na skutek swoich czynów. Dlaczego tak jest? Dzieje się tak dlatego, że zbyt silne jest w nich lgnięcie do życia. Słyszałem, że ten, kto umie opanować życie, chodząc po ziemi nie boi się nosorożca i tygrysa; wstępując w bitwę nie boi się uzbrojonych żołnierzy. Nie ma on miejsca, w które nosorożec mógłby wetknąć swój róg, nie ma w nim miejsca, w które tygrys mógłby wrazić swoje pazury, i nie ma miejsca, w które mógłby uderzyć miecz żołnierza. Dlaczego tak jest? Jest tak dlatego, że dla niego nie istnieje śmierć.

Tao rodzi, Tao wykarmia. Rzeczy przybierają kształty, kształty dokonują się. Dlatego nie ma rzeczy, która nie uświęcałaby Tao i nie ceniłaby Te. Tao jest uświęcone, Te jest godne szacunku dlatego, że nie wydają one rozkazów, a zgodne są z naturalnością.

Tao rodzi, Te wykarmia, pielęgnuje, wychowuje, doskonali, czyni zrodzone dojrzałym, obsługuje, podtrzymuje. Stwarzać i nie zagarniać, tworzyć i nie chwalić się, będąc starszym nie rozkazywać. Oto co nazywa się najgłębszym Te.

W sferze podniebnej przebywa początek, który jest matką podniebnej sfery. Gdy poznaje się matkę, to można poznać i jej dzieci. Kiedy już znane są jej dzieci, to nadal należy pamiętać o matce. Wtedy do końca życia nie zaistnieje niebezpieczeństwo. Kto wolny od pragnień i namiętności, do końca życia nie odczuje zmęczenia. Folgujący namiętnościom i pochłonięty swoimi sprawami nie uchroni się przed nieszczęściem.

Widzenie najdrobniejszego nazywa się jasnością. Zachowanie słabości nazywa się potęgą. Korzystając z jego blasku, znowu uczynić je jasnym. Wtedy do końca życie nie napotka się niebezpieczeństwa. To się nazywa przestrzeganiem stałości.

Gdybym opanował wiedzę, to szedłbym po wielkiej drodze. Jedyna rzecz, której się obawiam, to działanie. Wielka droga jest doskonale równa, lecz naród lubi ścieżki.

Jeśli pałac jest przepiękny, to pola zarastają chwastami, a spichlerze są zupełnie puste. Odziewający się w bogate szaty, noszący ostre miecze, nie zadowalają się jedzeniem i gromadzą nadmierne bogactwa. Wszystko to nazywa się rozbojem i chełpliwością. Jest to naruszenie Tao.

Kto umie stać mocno, tego nie można przewrócić. Kto potrafi się oprzeć, tego nie można powalić. Synowie i wnuki po wieczne czasy będą o nim pamiętać.

Kto doskonali swoje wnętrze, tego cnota staje się szczera. Kto doskonali życie rodzinne, tego cnota staje się pełna. Kto doskonali gminę, tego cnota staje się rozległa. Kto doskonali cesarstwo, tego cnota staje się bogata. Kto doskonali sferę podniebną, tego cnota staje się powszechna.

Po sobie można poznać innych; po jednej rodzinie można poznać inne; po jednej gminie można poznać pozostałe; po jednym cesarstwie można poznać cały świat. Skąd ja znam świat jako taki? Dzięki temu.

Kto pełen jest doskonałego Te, ten podobny jest do nowonarodzonego. Jadowite owady i żmije nie ukąszą go, dzikie zwierzęta na niego nie napadają, drapieżne ptaki nie atakują go. Kości jego są miękkie, mięśnie słabe, lecz on trzyma silnie. Nie znając więzi dwu płci, posiada on zdolność tworzenia życia. Jest on bardzo wrażliwy. On woła przez cały dzień i jego głos się nie zmienia. Jest on w pełni harmonijny.

Znajomość harmonii nazywa się stałością. Znajomość stałości nazywa się oświeceniem. Wzbogacenie życia nazywa się szczęściem. Napięcie ducha w sercu nazywa się uporem. Gdy istota pełna sił starzeje się, nazywa się to naruszeniem Tao. Kto jest bez Tao, ginie przed czasem.

Ci, co wiedzą – nie mówią; ci, co mówią – nie wiedzą. Kto pozostawia pragnienie, rezygnuje z namiętności, wyzwala siebie z zamętu, miarkuje swój blask, łączy się w jedną całość – ten jednoczy się z najgłębszym. Nie można go przybliżyć, aby się z nim pokumać; nie można go przybliżyć, aby nim wzgardzić; nie można go przybliżyć, aby mu zaszkodzić; nie można go przybliżyć, aby go wywyższyć; nie można go przybliżyć, aby go poniżyć. Oto dlaczego jest on w kraju szanowany.

Krajem rządzi się sprawiedliwie, wojnę prowadzi się chytrością. Zawładnięcia krajem dokonuje się poprzez nieczynienie. Skąd ja to wszystko wiem? Oto skąd: kiedy w kraju jest wiele niepotrzebnych rzeczy, naród staje się biedny. Kiedy naród posiada wiele ostrego oręża, w kraju rośnie zamęt. Kiedy wielu jest mistrzów rzemiosła, mnożą się rzadkie przedmioty. Kiedy rozmnażają się ustawy i nakazy, zwiększa się ilość złodziei i bandytów.

Dlatego mądry człowiek mówi: jeśli ja nie działam, naród sam się będzie zmieniał; jeśli jestem spokojny, naród sam się poprawi. Jeśli jestem bierny, naród sam stanie się bogaty; jeśli ja nie mam namiętności, naród staje się prostoduszny.

Kiedy rząd jest spokojny, naród staje się prostoduszny. Kiedy rząd jest czynny, naród staje się nieszczęśliwy. O, nieszczęście! Ono jest podstawą, na której opiera się szczęście. Kto zna ich granice? One nie są stałe. Sprawiedliwość zazwyczaj przeradza się w chytrość, dobro – w zło. Człowiek już dawno zbłądził. Dlatego mądry człowiek jest sprawiedliwy i nie odbiera niczego drugiemu. Jest on bezinteresowny i nie czyni zła. Jest on światły, lecz nie pragnie błyszczeć.

Dla rządzenia krajem i służenia ludziom najlepiej jest zachować wstrzemięźliwość. Wstrzemięźliwość powinna stać się główną troską. Ona nazywa się doskonaleniem Te. Doskonałe Te jest siłą wszechzwycięską. Siła wszechzwycięska jest niewyczerpana. Siła niewyczerpana daje możliwość opanowania kraju.

Początek, z którego pomocą rządzi się krajem, jest długowieczny i nazywa się głębokim i trwałym korzeniem. On – wiecznie istniejące Tao.

Rządzenie wielkim cesarstwem podobne jest do przyrządzania potrawy z drobnych rybek. Jeśli w podniebną sferę ludzie wchodzą drogą Tao, to duchy zmarłych nie czynią cudów. Nie tylko nie będą one czynić cudów, lecz przestaną także szkodzić ludziom. Nie tylko duchy nie będą szkodzić ludziom, lecz i mądry człowiek nie będzie szkodzić ludziom. Ponieważ ani duch ani mędrzec nie przynoszą szkody, to ich Te łączy się w jedno.

Wielkie cesarstwo to dolny bieg rzeki, węzeł podniebnej sfery, samica sfery podniebnej. Samica zawsze niewzruszonością zniewala samca, a w samej istocie niewzruszoności stoi poniżej. Dlatego wielkie cesarstwo zaskarbia sobie względy małego, stawiając się poniżej tego ostatniego, a maleńkie cesarstwo zyskuje sympatię wielkiego tym, że stoi poniżej tego ostatniego. Zyskuje się względy tym, że stawia się siebie poniżej, lub tym, że samemu się jest poniżej. Niech wielkie cesarstwo nie pragnie więcej ponadto, aby wszyscy byli jednako nakarmieni, a małe cesarstwo niech nie pragnie więcej, niż służyć ludziom. Wówczas oba otrzymują to, czego pragną. Wielkiemu przystoi być niżej.

Tao – głębia wszystkich rzeczy. Ono jest skarbem dobrych i obroną niedobrych ludzi. Piękne słowa można głosić publicznie, dobre postępowanie można krzewić wśród ludzi. Lecz dlaczego porzucają niedobrych ludzi? W takim razie po cóż wywyższają władcę i wyznaczają mu trzech doradców?

Władca i doradcy, chociaż posiadają drogocenne kamienie i mogą jeździć w kolasach, najlepiej uczynią przestrzegając Tao.

Dlaczego w dawnych czasch ceniono Tao? W tamtych czasach ludzie nie dążyli do bogactw i wbaczali przestępstwa. Dlatego w sferze podniebnej wysoko ceniono Tao.

Należy realizować nieczynienie, zachowywać spokój i smakować to, co smaku jest pozbawione. Wielkie składa się z drobnostek, a mnogość z drobiazgów. Na nienawiść należy odpowiadać dobrem.

Pokonanie trudnego zaczyna się od łatwego, realizacja wielkiego zaczyna się od małego, gdyż w świece trudna sprawa powstaje z łatwych, a wielkie z maleńkich. Dlatego mędrzec zawsze rozpoczyna sprawę nie od wielkiego, dokonując tym samym wielkiego dzieła. Kto wiele obiecuje, nie zasługuje na zaufanie. Gdzie wiele łatwych spraw, tam wiele jest i trudnych. Dlatego mądry człowiek wnika w trudności, w rezultacie zaś nie doznaje ich.

Spokojne łatwo zachować. To, co jeszcze nie ujawniło cech, łatwo naprawić. Słabe łatwo rozdzielić. Drobne łatwo rozproszyć. Działanie należy rozpoczynać od tego, czego jeszcze nie ma. Zaprowadzać ład należy wtedy, kiedy jeszcze nie ma zamętu. Gdyż wielkie drzewo wyrasta z małego, dziewięciopiętrową wieżę rozpoczyna się od garstki ziemi, najdłuższa droga rozpoczyna się od pierwszego kroku.

Kto działa – dozna niepowodzenia. Kto czymkolwiek włada – utraci. Oto dlaczego mądry człowiek jest bezczynny, i on nie doznaje niepowodzenia. On nic nie ma i dlatego niczego nie traci. Ci, którzy dokonując czynów spieszą się, by osiągnąć powodzenie, doznają zawodu. Kto ostrożnie kończy swoje dzieło, podobnie jak je rozpoczął, ten zawsze osiągnie powodzenie. Dlatego mądry człowiek nie ma namiętności, nie ceni przedmiotów zdobywanych z trudem, uczy się u tych, którzy nie posiadają wiedzy, i podąża drogą, po której przeszli inni. Przestrzega on naturalnego porządku rzeczy i nie ośmiela się działać.

W dawnych czasach ten, kto umiał służyć Tao, nie oświecał narodu, a czynił go głupim. Trudno jest rządzić narodem, gdy ten posiada dużą wiedzę. Dlatego kierowanie krajem za pomocą wiedzy jest wrogiem kraju, a bez użycia wiedzy jest szczęściem dla kraju. Kto zna te dwie rzeczy, ten staje się przykładem dla innych. Znajomość tego przykładu jest znajomością najgłębszego Te. Najgłębsze Te – ono jest i głębokie i odległe. Ono jest zwrócone ku wszystkim istotom. Przestrzegając Te, osiągniesz wszelką pomyślność.

Rzeki i morza dlatego władają równiną, że mogą spływać niżej. Dlatego władają równinami.

Kto pragnie wznieść się nad narodem, powinien postawić siebie niżej. Kto pragnie być na czele ludzi, powinien zająć miejsce na końcu. Dlatego, chociaż stoi on przed narodem, to nie jest dla narodu ciężarem; chociaż znajduje się na czele, naród nie wyrządza mu krzywdy. Dlatego ludzie z radością go wywyższają i nie odwracają się od niego. On nie walczy, dzięki czemu jest w świecie niezwyciężony.

Wszyscy mówią, że moje Tao jest wielkie i nie maleje. Jeśliby się zmniejszało, to po długim czasie stałoby się maleńkie. Nie maleje dlatego, że jest wielkie.

Posiadam trzy skarby, które cenię: pierwszy to miłość do człowieka, drugi to oszczędność, trzeci polega na tym, że nie śmiem stanąć przed innymi. Jestem pełen miłości do człowieka, dlatego mogę być odważny. Jestem oszczędny, dlatego mogę być hojny. Nie śmiem stanąć przed innymi, dlatego mogę zostać mądrym wodzem.

Kto jest odważny bez humanizmu, szczodry bez oszczędności, kto będąc na czele odpycha tych, co znajdują się z tyłu, ten ginie. Kto prowadzi wojnę z miłości do człowieka, ten zwycięża, i zbudowana przez niego obrona jest nieprzystępna. Naturalność go ratuje, miłość do człowieka go ochrania.

Mądry wódz nie jest wojowniczy. Prawdziwy wojownik nie bywa gniewny. Umiejący zwyciężać wroga nie napada. Umiejący kierować ludźmi nie stawia siebie w nikczemnej sytuacji. Ja nazywam Te – stroniącym od walki. Oto siła w kierowaniu ludźmi. Znaczy to – przestrzegać praw przyrody i wiekowego porządku.

Sztuka wojenna głosi: nie śmiem zaczynać, powinienem czekać. Nie śmiem posunąć się naprzód chociażby o piędź, lecz odstępuję pół mili. To się nazywa działaniem przez nieczynienie, uderzaniem bez wysiłku. W tym przypadku nie będzie wroga i mogę obejść się bez żołnierzy. Nie ma większego nieszczęścia, niż niedocenianie przeciwnika. Niedocenienie przeciwnika zaszkodzi mojemu tajemnemu orężu. W bitwach, ci co się smucą, zwyciężają.

Moje słowa łatwo zrozumieć i łatwo zrealizować. Lecz ludzie nie mogą zrozumieć i nie mogą zrealizować. W słowach istnieje początek, w sprawach zawarte jest najważniejsze. Ponieważ ludzie ich nie znają, więc nie znają i mnie samego. Ponieważ mało mnie znają, więc jestem drogi. Dlatego mądry człowiek podobny jest do tego, kto ubiera się w prostą tkaninę, a jaspis chowa przy sobie.

Kto posiada wiedzę i udaje prostaka, ten stanął na wysokości. Kto nie ma wiedzy i udaje światłego, ten jest chory. Kto potrafi się wyleczyć – nie choruje. Mądry człowiek nie choruje dlatego, że zdołał się wyleczyć. Dlatego on nie jest chory.

Kiedy naród nie boi się potężnych, wówczas przychodzi potęga. Nie ścieśniajcie jego domu, nie pogardzajcie jego życiem. Kto nie gardzi, ten nie będzie wzgardzony. Dlatego mądry człowiek, znając siebie, nie chełpi się. On lubi siebie i nie wywyższa się. On rezygnuje z samolubstwa i nie pyszni się.

Kto jest odważny i wojowniczy – ginie; kto jest odważny ale nie jest wojowniczy – pozostanie żyw. Te dwie rzeczy oznaczają: jedna – pożytek, druga – szkodę. Kto zna przyczyny nienawiści do wojowniczych? Wyjaśnienie tego jest trudne i dla mędrca.

Naturalne Tao nie walczy, lecz umie zwyciężać. Ono nie mówi, lecz umie odpowiadać. Ono samo przychodzi. Ono jest spokojne i potrafi zarządzać. Sieci przyrody są rzadkie, lecz niczego nie przepuszczają.

Jeśli naród nie boi się śmierci, to po cóż grozić mu śmiercią? Kto zmusza ludzi, by bali się śmierci i lubuje się w tym, tego pochwycę i zniszczę. Kto ośmiela się tak działać?

Zawsze istnieje nosiciel śmierci, który zabija. A jeśli ktoś go zastąpi, to znaczy, że zastąpił wielkiego mistrza. Kto zastępując wielkiego mistrza, siecze – uszkodzi sobie rękę.

Naród głoduje, gdy zbyt duże są podatki i daniny. Oto dlaczego głoduje. Trudno kierować narodem, gdy rząd jest zbyt czynny. Oto dlaczego trudno kierować. Naród łatwo umiera, gdy zbyt lgnie ku życiu. Oto dlaczego łatwo umiera. Ten, kto lekceważy swoje życie, tym samym ceni swoje życie.

Człowiek po narodzeniu jest słaby i wrażliwy, a po śmierci twardy i zakrzepły. Wszystkie istoty po urodzeniu są słabe i wrażliwe, a po śmierci twarde i zakrzepłe. Twarde i zakrzepłe jest to, co ginie, a słabe i wrażliwe jest to, co zaczyna żyć. Dlatego potężne wojsko nie zwycięża, i podobne jest ono do okrzepłego drzewa. Silne i potężne nie posiadają tej przewagi, jaką mają słabe i wrażliwe.

Niebo podobne jest do napinania łuku. Kiedy obniża się jego górna część, podnosi się dolna. Odbiera ono zbędne i oddaje temu, kto jest w potrzebie. Niebo odbiera bogatym i oddaje biednym to, co zostało odebrane. Natomiast ludzkie Tao – odwrotnie. Ono odbiera biednym i oddaje bogatym to, co zostało odebrane. Kto może oddać biednym wszystko, co zbędne? Mogę to zrobić tylko ci, którzy wzorują się na Tao. Dlatego mądry człowiek czyni i nie korzysta z tego, dokonuje zwycięstw i nie chełpi się. On jest szlachetny dlatego, że nie posiada namiętności.

Woda, to najbardziej miękka i słaba istota na świecie, lecz w pokonywaniu twardego i zakrzepłego jest niezwyciężona i nie ma sobie równego na świecie.

Słabi zwyciężają silnych, miękkie pokonuje twarde. O tym wiedzą wszyscy, lecz ludzie nie mogą tak działać. Dlatego mądry człowiek mówi: kto wziął na siebie poniżenie kraju, ten staje się panującym, i kto wziął na siebie nieszczęście kraju – staje się władcą.

Po wielkim gniewie pozostają następstwa. Spokój można nazwać dobrem. Dlatego mądry człowiek składa przysięgę, że nie będzie nikomu czynić wyrzutów. Dobrzy ludzie są wierni przysiędze, a niedobrzy ją naruszają. Niebo nie ma krewnych, ono jest zawsze po stronie dobrych.

Państwo należy uczynić maleńkim, a naród – wyjątkowym. Jeśli nawet jest wiele oręża, nie należy go używać. Należy sprawić, by naród do końca swych dziejów nie wędrował daleko. Jeśli nawet są łodzie i wozy bojowe, nie należy ich używać. Jeśli nawet istnieją wojska zbrojne, nie należy ich wystawiać. Należy sprawić, by naród znów zaczął pleść węzły i używał ich zamiast pisma. Należy uczynić smacznym jego pożywienie, piękną jego odzież, urządzić mu spokojny dom, uczynić wesołym jego życie. Sąsiednie państwa patrzałyby na siebie z daleka, słuchałyby jak u sąsiada pieją koguty i szczekają psy, a ludzie do starości i śmierci nie byliby zmuszeni koczować z miejsca na miejsce.

Celne słowa nie są subtelne. Piękne słowa nie zasługują na zaufanie. Dobry człowiek nie jest krasomówcą. Krasomówca nie może być dobry. Wiedzący nie udowodnia, udowodniający nie wie.

Mądry człowiek niczego nie gromadzi. On wszystko czyni dla ludzi i wszystko oddaje innym. Niebo wszystkim istotom przynosi pożytek i nie wyrządza szkód. Tao mądrego człowieka – wolne od walki nieczynienie.

Przedmowa

Tłumaczenie na język polski na podstawie rosyjskiego tłumaczenia Jan Chinszuna z 1950 r. (Yan-Chin-Shun

Drewnekitajskij fiłosof Lao-Tsy i jego uczenije

), wydanego przez Wydawnictwo Akademii Nauk ZSRR.

Laocy urodził się 14 dnia siódmego miesiąca trzeciego roku panowania cesarza Tingwanga, z dynastii Tszeu, czyli w 54 roku 34. cyklu (604 r. przed narodzeniem Chrystusa) we wsi Khio-dżin, gminie Lai, okręgu Khukien, prowincji Tszu. Nazwisko rodowe brzmi Li, przydomek El, zaszczytne imię Pejang, pośmiertne Tan. Laocy to imię nadane mu przez uczniów (znaczy: stary uczony, stary mistrz). Był bibliotekarzem państwowym. Starał się żyć w odosobnieniu i pozostawać nieznany. Służył długo dynastii Tszeu; świadek jej upadku. Porzucił urząd i udał się ku granicy państwa, na wzgórza Hangufluanu, gdzie władał niejaki Jnhi. Tam, dla jego oświecenia, napisał księgę TAO-TE-KING (Drogi i Cnoty Księga) o sześciu tysiącach znaków. Następnie oddalił się. Nikt nie wie, gdzie i jak zakończył życie. Laocy był mędrcem, który ukochał ubóstwo.

[Z „Kroniki państwowej Sseki”, zapis 104 r. przed nar. Chr.]

To, co nieistność w byt ten przemienia,
A czego zmienny czas się nie imie;
To, z czego wszelkie pochodzi imię:
Samo żadnego nie ma imienia.

To wszechpotęgi dobro olbrzymie,
Samo wyzbyte z wszelkiego mienia;
Oto jest prawda, godna umienia,
A która w sercu twem niech się przyjmie:

TAO – to droga pośród ciemności,
Opromieniona tchem świetlaności;
TAO – to ducha najgłębsze bezdno;
TAO – to łącznik z przestrzenią gwiezdną;
W TAO się wszelka istność poczyna,
Zeń czyn, a ono jest – Bezprzyczyna.

Jedność bezzjawnem źródłem jest wszechtreści.
Objaw z niej płynie, jak ze zdroju rzeka,
A ona – przyczyn przyczyna daleka –
Nigdy się w słowach, ni w czynach nie streści.

Naokół niebo ziemię przyobleka,
Empirejskiemi dalami ją pieści,
Stwarzając z ziemskiej gliny jej niewieściej
Lennego pana wszechbytu – człowieka.

Emanujący z tych prarodzicieli,
Mąż człowieczeństwo ze swą żoną dzieli.
A tak, poczęcie mając to dwoiste,
Niebem i ziemią człowiek jest zaiste.
Umrze – w proch jego ciało się obróci;
Sam duch, że z nieba – do niebios powróci.

Jestestwo, istność niestworzona cała –
Oto co dla nas prawdą jest jedyną,
A reszta – złuda, choć dziś zachwycała,
Niknie z chwilami, które w bezkres płyną.

Naoczny zjaw ma postać coraz inną;
Esencja życia – ta jedynie trwała;
Stworzone rzeczy i ludzie przeminą,
Lecz TO po wszystek jest czas. Temu chwała!

Egzystujące i rzeczy i ludzie
Mijają prędko, jak w sennej ułudzie.
A choć tak dzisiaj żywe, jutro zbledną.

Nie wstrzymasz życia, choćbyś chciał rozpacznie.
Umrze, co żyło, skończy się, co zacznie.
Samo TO wieczne, tylko ono jedno.

Jest droga TAO, ale to droga
Od ziemskich nizin do niebios proga,
A dalej idzie w bezmiar przestworzy,
Nieprzeniknionych, jak sekret boży.

Napróżno człowiek, w ludzkiej swej dumie,
Enigmat ten się rozwiązać sili.
Setki prawd ludzie już nagłosili,
Lecz żadna TEGO pojąć nie umie.

Element pierwszy, życia poczęcie,
Może‑ż mieć w słowach ludzkich ujęcie?
A to, co słowem człek ograniczy,
Nie jest‑że kłamem prawd bezgraniczy?
Ucisz zgiełk żądz swych, a prawda święcie
Sama ci skarb da swój tajemniczy.

Inaczej widzisz, patrząc z wyżyny;
Inne są życia ziemskie ścieżyny.
Gdy z wyżyn patrzysz, widno twym oczom:
Gdyś zszedł na poziom, dale się mroczą.

Droga w niebiesiech, jak strzelił – prosta,
Ale na ziemi człek tem nie sprosta.
Na ziemi, pragnąc żyć tak strzeliście,
Jakżeż się często z dróg zmyliliście!

Jest prawda, ale tej prawdy łono –
Jej najtajniejsze rodzime wnętrze,
W którem się żary tlą najgorętsze –
Nieprzeniknioną skryte zasłoną.
Wiesz tylko jedno, że wśród przestworzy,
W błyskawic dnie, jest moc, która tworzy.

Choćby najżywiej, choć najbarwiściej,
Jeśli się prawda cieleśnie ziści:
Gdy cielesności tych więcej będzie,
Czyż przeto prawdy samej przybędzie?

Można‑ż prawdami żyć dwiema? trzema?…
Prawda jest jedna, lub prawdy niema.
Jeśli jej niema, nikt jej nie złowi;
Jeśli jest jedna, nikt nie wysłowi,

Jest prawda TAO, jak dal bez brzega,
Której nie pojmiesz ciała oczami;
Choć w niej się myśl, jak słońce, zażega,
I chociaż łudzi cię przezroczami,
Lecz ten, kto po nią cielesne dłonie
Wyciąga, żądny jej wcieleń – spłonie.

Być, czem się jest, właściwe niższemu stworzeniu:
Człowiek się uistotnia nie w bycie – w dążeniu.
Treść twoja – to twa dusza, ciało – to twa postać:
Nie tem jesteś, czem jesteś, ale czem chcesz zostać.

Dąż najwyżej, najmocniej, najświęciej, najczyściej,
A to wszystko się tobie, ani wiesz jak, ziści.
Jak ziarno, które siewca zasiał w ziemi łonie,
Miej w duszy cel, aż kwiatem zbożnym ci zapłonie.

Człowiek jest utworzony zasadami dwiema:
Stworzeniem jest znikomem i ciału lenniczem,
Dla którego „nad życie” – umiłowań niema,

I jest duszą, jest wiecznie gorejącym zniczem;
Jest wolą, która pragnie „po nad życie”, niema,
Niewymownie swobodna, nie ujęta niczem.

Istnienia ziemi i niebios Przyczyna
Ani się kończy, ani się zaczyna.
Jedynie tylko tej Przedwiecznej Woli
Mędrzec pożąda, aż się z nią zespoli.

Lecz zanim przyjdzie chwila upragniona,
Weź obowiązków swój trud na ramiona,
Kochaj swych bliźnich serca bezgraniczem,
Oddaj im wszystko, sam się nie wiąż niczem.

Mędrzec niczego nie pragnie od ludzi,
Kłamnemi słowy nikogo nie łudzi,
Powściąga żądze znikomego ciała,
Milczący, w sobie zamknięty i niemy,
Obudza duszę, ażeby widziała.

Czas przyjdzie: wszyscy tacy się staniemy.

Na rzeczy ziemskie spłynie śmierci era,
I samo niebo przeminie i zniknie,
Ale istota duszy nie umiera.
TAO głębokie: nikt go nie przeniknie.

Wola przedwieczna życia jest korzeniem
I nieba z ziemią ślubnem skojarzeniem.
Niebo wraz z ziemią – rzecz codzienna, zwykła,
Ale w istocie czem jest? Któż rozwikła?

Myśl o tem zawsze, o każdym momencie,
Rozwijaj w sobie prawdziwe pojęcie.
Myśl. Z wyraźnością żywych barw naoczną,
Te zjawiać ci się tajemnice poczną:
Jak nie jest życie bez śmierci niczyje,
Tak to, co zmarło, – przyjdzie czas – ożyje.

Takie człowieczych władz są zadania:
W rzeczach materji czyn rodzi mienie,
Z czynności uczuć są pożądania,
A czynem ducha jest – zrozumienie.

O mienie bogactw ludzie krew leją,
Niewolnik uczuć kocha, przeklina…
Uczniu, podążaj myśli koleją:
Oto spokoju wieczna kraina.

Kto w życiu bogactw żył atmosferą,
Po tym, po latach, zostanie zero;
Ten, kto żył sercem, tego miłośnie
Po śmierci wspomni wnuk niedaleki,
I wnet zapomni, skoro podrośnie.
Sam tylko mędrzec – ten przetrwa wieki.

Umieć… Umienie jest lepsze od mienia;
To jest niezmienne, co wiecznie się zmienia.
Od prawdy człowiek oddali się, jeśli
Uczonem słowem zwęży ją – określi.

W której‑ż uznanej mieści się maksymie
To, czego żadne nie da poznać imię?
Niebo i ziemia tę nam prawdę wieści:
Niebo – twór męski, ziemia – twór niewieści.

Gdy ich coś cieszy, gdy coś dręczy srodze,
Ci nie są jeszcze na prawdziwej drodze;
Którzy się z złudą zmysłów nie rozstali,
Będą od prawdy coraz dalej stali:
Poznają tylko życia barwy zwierzchnie,
Lecz tajemnica, gdy się zbliżą – pierzchnie.

Ten, który patrzy, nie zawsze dostrzega;
Jeden pracuje, a plon zbiera inny;
Nie jest bezbrzeżny, kto zbiera bez brzega;
Ten, kto strofuje, często sam jest winny.

Niezawsze widzi ten, który spoziera;
Ten, kto nie zbiera, posiada na wieki;
Źle chodzi ten, kto na palcach się wspiera;
Ten widzi jasno, kto zamknął powieki.

Sędziowie błędów sami też się mylą;
Kto wiecznie żyć chce, niech nie żyje chwilą;
Kto każdą chwilą jest wiecznie przytomny,
Przed tym się schyli do nóg czas potomny.
W kim jest potęga i dobroć łagodna,
Ta osobistość być najpierwszą godna.

Każdej rzeczy, która jest w materjalnym bycie,
Widzisz – zda się – początek jej i jej pozbycie;
Ale to tylko pozór, a w istocie rzeczy
Bez początku i końca ten jest byt człowieczy.

Stwarzać – znaczy dostrzegać, co już dawniej było,
A co się teraz, niby na nowo, dobyło,
I stwarzać znaczy również obecne zniszczenie
Rzeczy jednych, by drugim zapewnić ziszczenie.

Tak jak w trójcy się jedność ukrycie zawiera:
Tak wczorajsza z dzisiejszą i z przyszłą jest era.
To, co było, jest dziś, co dziś jest – jutro będzie.
Dawniej, dzisiaj i kiedyś – to trzy ery w pędzie:
Kto je wszystkie ogarnął jednym myśli rzutem,
Ten, mędrzec, życiem żyje, z czasu pęt wyzutem.

Jeśli chcesz dociec istnienia przyczyny,
Wprzód odpokutuj złe i dobre czyny.
Jedna rzecz z drugą nieodmiennie skuta:
Za zło i dobro musi być pokuta.

Kto świat ogarnął sercem miłosiernie,
Temu świat głowę musi owić w ciernie,
Bo żąda poznać, do jakiej ty głębi
Potrafisz cierpieć, człowiecze gołębi.

Ci tylko życia tajnikiem zawładną,
Którzy nie idą za chęcią żyć żadną.
Jeślim jest atom rzeki i z nią lecę,
Jakże mam wiedzieć cośkolwiek o rzece?
Wiedzą‑ż, jak mają żyć, ludzkie plemiona,
Jeśli ich istność żądzą żyć splamiona?

Trzymaj gotową strzałę na cięciwie,
Ale zabijać nie pragnij zbyt chciwie.
Wszędzie przed tobą nieskończone sedno:
Nie trafisz w drugie, gdyś utrafił w jedno.

Często za dobry czyn odbierasz pletnie;
Niecnieś postąpił, stało się szlachetnie;
Trudna z pozoru rzecz, w istocie łatwa;
Prosta rzecz, spojrzysz bliżej, już się gmatwa.

Z największą rzeczą krewny drobiazg mały;
Dąb mniej od trzciny na wiatr wytrzymały;
Góra upada, nic nie przetrwa stale;
Zburzy czas to, co dziś na piedestale;
Traci, kto zysk miał, zyskuje, kto traci;
Bratem ci obcy, wrogiem – ideał braci.

Oto mądrości nieomylna ścieżka:
Mędrzec buduje świat, lecz w nim nie mieszka.
On jest jak drzewo z owocem w ogrodzie:
Tworzy i służy chciwej żeru trzodzie:

Mędrca zadaniem twór jest – myśl przeczysta:
Z duszy ją wysnuł, a świat z niej korzysta.
Mędrzec to słońce – szafarz tego żaru,
Którym się karmi wieczny chłód obszaru.

Stworzyciel się nad wynalazkiem głowi,
Aż znalazł… Inny zyskiem się obłowi.
Ale w tym innym nie upatruj wroga.
Myśli twej cenność – oto twoja droga.

Bądź morza głębią, z której ludzkie plemię
Wyławia perły i dźwiga w djademie.

Jak drzewo z słońca, tak ty czerp z mądrości.
Żyj najspokojniej, najciszej, najprościej.
Choć miałbyś z czego, lecz się nie kwap chwalić:
Im kto pyszniejszy, tem go łatwiej zwalić.

Do fortunnego nędzarz prawo rości:
Milcz, gdyś szczęśliwy, i nie budź zazdrości.
Patrz, złotodajna góra czy ci o tem
Głosi, że pokład zawiera ze złotem?

Górnik uderza tam i sam ją w gniewie,
A często minie skarb, i o tem nie wie.

Milcz, i niech twojej złotej tajemnicy
Szukają w tobie łupiezcy‑górnicy.
Niech się wokoło rozszaleją żądze.
Ty milcz, zamknięte duszy miej wrzeciądze.

Ci, którzy w własne karby są ujęci,
Tylko ci żyją wedle swojej chęci:
Słuchają innych, sami mówią mało,
Więc to, co zrobią, będzie się trzymało.

Kto z wierzchu zimny, chociaż wewnątrz płonie,
Ten najbogatszym jest w mądrości plonie.
Kto w furji uciech drga, kto łka dziecięco,
Tym wichry, jako piachem Gobi, kręcą.

Kto swoją ufność odmierza na cale,
Ten jakby nie miał zaufania wcale:
To drży, jak w wietrze słaby listek drzewa,
To zbyt rozpacza, to zbyt się spodziewa.
Mądry, kto całkiem wierzy w swe bożyszcze:
Co miał, gdy straci, czego nie miał – zyszcze.

Kto chce po drodze prawdy iść, ten niech się uczy:
Krew i ciało to szaty, które duch obłóczy.
Podobieństwo cielesne bierze po nas młodzież,
Jak znoszoną, lecz świeżo odnowioną odzież.

Czy chwalebne uczynki, czy podległe karze,
Twarz, jak wierny dokument, potomkom przekaże.
Napróżno zapisywać dziejami tablice;
Syn po rodzicach dostał ślad ich dzieł: swe lice.

To, czem być człowiek pragnie, w to się przeistoczy.
Nie to grunt, czem jest, lecz to, dokąd zwraca oczy.
Być, czem się jest – właściwe niższemu stworzeniu.
Człowiek się uistotnia nie w bycie: w dążeniu.
Przekazywać gatunek – posłannictwo zwierza:
Człowiek ducha bogactwo dzieciom niech powierza.

Z kornych los zetrze poniżenia znamię:
Pysznych i hardych przeciwnością złamie.
Nad uczonego, co z ksiąg jest uczony,
Lepszy ktoś, z nieba światłem oświecony.

Ten woli życiem brzydkiem żyć, ten ładnem:
Mędrzec zupełny nie żyć woli żadnem:
Cichy, pokorny, samotny, milczący.
Niebo i ziemię w sobie jednoczący.

Nic hałaśliwie w życiu nie poczyna;
Jest, jak ukryta, niewidna sprężyna,
W sobie skręcona, jak motor w zegarze,
Któremu wnętrznem napięciem iść każe,
A chociaż na nie nie krzyczy, nie woła,
Jednak wskazówki zakreślają koła.

Kto myślą mądrą powszechność ogarnie,
Do tego każdy szczegół sam się garnie;
Nad ziemią, niebem, nad sferami dwiema
Mędrzec ma prawo: innych praw dlań niema.

W czem? – gdzie jest prawda? w słowach nie wyjawię.
Dość chcieć jest prawdy, by ją mieć w objawie.
Gdy nie udręczasz troską się rozpaczną,
Zaraz się tobie lepsze dni wić zaczną.

W bliźnim ci sprzecznym nie będziesz miał wroga;
Ustępuj z drogi innym: oto droga.
Choćby cię chwytał gniewny szał za gardło,
Tłum w sobie wrzenie, ażeby umarło.
Gdyś uległ, giniesz w ziemskich spraw zasobie;
Gdy przezwyciężysz gniew, masz niebo w sobie.

Trzydzieści szprych wbij w piastę: toczyć się sposobna;
Trzydzieści szprych ci na nic, gdy brane z osobna.
Masz wóz, gdy zwiążesz koła, oś i wasąg społem;
Nic ci po tych jest rzeczach, gdy koło nie z kołem.

Ten tylko, kto jednoczyć umie, umie użyć:
Na nic ci rzecz, gdy nie wiesz, do czego ma służyć.
Związuj, związuj i jednaj, co jest w rozprzężeniu.
Służ tej myśli, że wszystko jest nam ku służeniu.

Posiadać rzecz, by chciwie do siebie ją tulić;
By ją na cztery spusty zamknąć, oszkatulić,
Aby świata boże go nie ujrzała wprędce:

Zaiste, nie tak sobie poczynają mędrce.
Oni sobie najlepiej tem rzecz upodwładnią,
Że umieli ją stworzyć i wznieść się po nad nią.

Brać na zapas, mieć więcej, niż każe potrzeba:
Oto stan, do którego nakłaniać nie trzeba.
Dla wzrostu majętności popaść w upodlenie:
Oto co się nazywa postąpić szalenie.

Bogacze, klejnotami zdobni, pozłociści
Depczą tłum i wzbudzają pomruk nienawiści.
A kto rozpala niecne, złe uczucia w tłumie,
Ten, choć się stroi, życia ustroju nie umie.

Bogactwo masz, lecz nie żyj sam jego urokiem.
Dobrobyt niech się toczy łożyskiem szerokiem.
Bogactwo rzecz niepewna, gdy wokoło biedni.
Szczęście jest w obcowaniu i w społecznej jedni.
Bogaczu, który stożysz mienie, stóg do stoga:
Oto przed tobą prosta i zbawienna droga.

Jest ramię prawe i lewe ramię.
Oba choć sprzeczne dwa drogowskazy,
Ale ich łączność w jedno nie kłamie.
Nie w nich: w jedności ich – rdzeń bez skazy.

Nieraz się mówi o cnotach: znam je,
Etyki wzniosłej umiem nakazy.
Sprobujesz iść tak, wnet się grunt łamie.
Ledwieś się ruszył – kamień obrazy.

Enigmat dróg ten jak odcyfrować?
Miłuj!… To droga. Po niej byt prowadź.
A jeśli znajdziesz w kimś niecnót brzeżek,
Nie chciej zbyt nagle prostować ścieżek.
Upadającą wznoś duszę biedną
Sercem pamiętnem, żeś jest z nią – jedno!

Prawdziwy skarb jest przestać na mierze.
Na nic gromadne skupianie mienia.
Twój nadmiar niechaj się rozpromienia.
Moc niech rozdaje: słabość – niech bierze.

Życiodawczego pełen umienia,
Mędrzec powiada; w to jedno mierzę,
Ażeby zawrzeć ścisłe przymierze
Z dobrem najwyższem – z ciszą sumienia.

Pocóż mu walczyć o kęs zażarcie?
Jemu nie grozi żadna zagłada,
Żadne majątku jego pożarcie
Od apetytów wilczych sąsiada.
On psów nie trzyma u drzwi na warcie,
Bo on, nie mając nic, wszystkiem włada.

Nie tkwiąc, jak robak w ziemi odłamie;
Nie drżąc, bogatych wzorem nędzarzy,
Przed wrogim losem, który się zdarzy,
Powiada: wszystko dobre jest dla mnie.

Z pokojem w duszy, z ciszą na twarzy,
Przed możnym we czci karku nie łamie,
Dla biednych miłosierdzia nie kłamie,
Ni wielbi kogo, ni lekceważy.

Takim człowiekiem jest już bezdomnym;
Tak o majątku nie dba zdobycie;
Tak, nie bytując, jest we wszechbycie;
Tak się sam zmniejszył w świecie ogromnym,
I tak się umiał duchem rozszerzyć,
Że już mu jedno: żyć, albo nie żyć.

Idąc po życia wertepnej drodze,
Nim krok uczynisz, uważaj wpierw,
Czy gdzie nie pełza gad przy twej nodze,
Czy się nie tai zdradziecki czerw.

Bo chociaż jesteś mądry, człowiecze,
Chociażeś wszystkie rozumy zgadł:
Niepostrzeżenie skądś się przywlecze
Zdradziecki czerw lub nikczemny gad.

Że bez uwagi na niego żyłeś;
Żeś go nie zdeptał, lecz uraziłeś;
Żeś dla mizernej jego małości
Okazał zbyt wyrozumiałości,
I nie zdeptałeś go na śmierć, gada,
Ten gad (lub czerw) cię weźmie – obgada.

Jeżeli z złej przygody żmiję wybawicie,
Żmija, przez wdzięczność, żądłem żgnie was jadowicie.
Nie przeto, iż dobrego nie oceni dzieła:
Owszem, właśnie przez wdzięczność żądłem was ucięła.

Tylko tem, co ma, każdy, tem się z drugim dzieli.
O tem, jeśli nie wiecie, chcę, byście wiedzieli:
Wyście się podzielili z żmiją sercem radem,
A ona też się dzieli tem, co ma: swym jadem.

Gdy, lasem idącemu, trafi ci się żmija,
Którą chłody zwarzyły, niech ją krok twój mija.
Bo skoro odżywiłeś gada za pazuchą,
Nieroztropność ci twoja nie ujdzie na sucho:
Żmija, by dać ci dowód, że wyszła z omdlenia.
Daje go za pomocą czego? – użądlenia.

Po ukochanych najogromniej,
Ojcu i matce, żonie, bracie,
Choćby łkał człowiek po ich stracie,
Dusza przecierpi i zapomni.

Najdroższe w życiu wam postacie,
Którym, w porywie serc, niepomni,
Rzekliście: „Kocham najniezłomniej,
Na wieki”: – dziś czy pamiętacie?

Ulata życie w dal niewiedną:
Rzeczy, które dziś szczęściem mienię,
I które – bólem, jutro zbledną;
Zgasną najżywszych czuć płomienie,
I pozostanie tylko jedno:
Najwyższa rozkosz – zapomnienie.

Chełpić się dobrem nie bądźcie skorzy.
Niech wam się nazbyt nie przypomina,
Że spełniliście jaki czyn boży:
Nie chciejcie za to rangi bramina.

Kto zły był, też się zbyt niech nie korzy,
Ani urodzin swych nie przeklina:
Że grzech popełnił, to wielka wina,
Lecz… lecz mógł zrobić daleko gorzej.

Osoba, z którąś postąpił ładnie,
Gdy już litością twoją owładnie,
Będzie nad tobą się wynosiła.
A tak na odwrót bywa czasami,
Że ta, która cię ze złości łzami
Wspomni, rzec musi: o, to jest siła!

Jedno, dwa życia z urodzeń dziesięciu;
Ośm, dziewięć rychło pożegna się z światem,
Ale niewiasta aż wzdycha za swatem:
Nietrwały żywot przekaże dziecięciu.

Narodzin tyle, tyle epigonów;
Egzekwii tyle później (tyle zgonów)!
„Szczęściem” swe dzieci mieni człek, więc potem
Leżą tam, w ziemi cmentarnej, pokotem.

Efemerydy, przepełnione lęku.
Mieczami grożą w bratobójczem ręku,
A w oczach strach im wielkooki skrzy się.

Nie miej żadnego przy sobie oręża,
Ujrzysz dziw: jad cię nie uśmierci węża,
Srogie cię nie tkną pazury tygrysie.

Z rzeczy drobnych powstały jak największe dzieła.
Z garści ziemi najwyższa wieża się zaczęła.
Łatwo zapobiedz złemu, gdyś się spostrzegł w porę.
Lwiątko przyswoić – fraszka: trudniej, gdy już spore.

Pożar największy wznieci iskierka maleńka;
Drzewo dzierżą korzeni najcieńsze włókienka;
Mila się od jednego rozpoczyna kroku;
Mgnienie niedostrzegalne jest początkiem roku.

Jeśli nie chcesz utonąć w życia kołowrocie,
Niech cię nie usidlają ziemskich skarbów krocie;
Jeśli nie chcesz utracić, pamiętaj nie zbierać;

Nie pragnij żyć, nie będziesz zmuszony umierać.
Gdy cokolwiek zaczynasz, pamiętaj o końcu:
Oto przed tobą prawda, jako droga w słońcu.

Każdy nad ludźmi chce pozyskać władzę,
Lecz wyznać musi: wszystkim nie poradzę.
Najsilniejszego zawsze ktoś zwycięży:
Panuj nad sobą, gdyż to jest najciężej.

W odmęcie życia, na ziemskim padole,
Zawsze ktoś w górze i zawsze ktoś w dole:
Gdy jedni syci, za to drudzy poszczą;
Gdy ci w dostatkach, tamci im zazdroszczą.

Mędrzec od zgiełku życia się oddala.
Wszystko jest piękne – mówi – ale zdala:
Wszystkie wielkości, wyżyny i szczyty;

Wszystkie honory, godności, zaszczyty;
Wszystko. co tylko ludzkiem szczęściem zwiecie,
Porzuca wszystko a wszystko na świecie.

Matka zła, nie chciej, aby była inna:
Ta, którąś dostał, taką być powinna.
Ojciec, brat, siostra, sercu ci nie mili,
Nie chciej, ażeby ci się odmienili.

Nie mów, żeś biedny, bo zła twoja żona:
Taka snadź dola twoja zasłużona.
W najszlachetniejszym, jak powiadasz, celu
Wad nie odkrywaj w swoim przyjacielu.

Przeciwko sobie zwróć wymówki ostre.
Do swego zajrzyj wprzód własnego serca:
Może to ono twej matki oszczerca,
Może to ono potępiło siostrę?
Brat twój, przyjaciel, może będą inni,
Gdy twoje serce samo się obwini.

Skarb ci ukradli – twą pamiątkę drogą,
Twoją ostatnią, jedyną nadzieję –
Twe szczęście całe skradli ci złodzieje:
Milcz, nie przeklinaj i nie skarż nikogo,

Nie mów: skrzywdzili mię ludzie wyrodni,
Podli, złoczyńcy bez czci i sumienia.
Tyś sam jest winien, żeś miał tyle mienia,
Tyś sam jest winien – tyś winien tej zbrodni.

Ta myśl w pamięci twej ma być wyryta:
Masz przyjaciela swego, faworyta,
Duszę byś oddał za niego najradziej;

Ale jeżeli ten człowiek cię zdradzi,
Nie płacz: faworyt zdradzić cię powinien;
Grzechem jest fawor: tyś winien, tyś winien!

Jednemu uczuć nie dawajcie wrzątku.
Owszem, kochajcie wszystkich bez wyjątku.
A jeśli w bliźnim dojrzycie różnicy:
Nie bądźcie wy źli, gdy oni grzesznicy.

Nie patrz, że z tobą żyje kto nie szczerze.
Eh! – myśl – nań za to zębów nie wyszczerzę.
Sam będę szczerym, choć kłamie mój bliźni,
Leczę zło dobrem w nim, aż się zabliźni.

Eliksir życia ten jest: nieskończenie
Miłować sercem swoje otoczenie,
Ani zważając, z jaką kto jest cnotą.

Natężaj światło, by walczyć z ciemnotą,
Umiej być prawym, gdy wkoło nieprawi,
Stworzysz cud: zło się na dobro poprawi.

Bogacz swój zdradza lęk przez warg drżenie,
Ażeby tego, czem się zbogacił,
Przez jaki losu kaprys nie stracił,
W dzień go i w nocy ssie przerażenie.

Sławna osoba na szczycie chwały
Myślisz, że sobie żyje szczęśliwie?
Spójrz na nią: oto drży bojaźliwie,
Aby jej fale w dół nie porwały.

Bogacz i człowiek ambitny – jedno:
Jedynem szczęściem dla nich jest pycha;
Gromadzić mienie lęk ich popycha;
Z trwogi, że mogą wpaść w dolę biedną,
Gromadzą stosy na zapas mienia,
Zgięci od sławy i dóbr brzemienia.

Mędrzec, choć nie wychodzi za próg swego domu,
Wie, jakie zło i dobro los przynosi komu,
I chociaż swoich bliźnich wcale nie odwiedza,
Jest mu dana dokładna o ich życiu wiedza.

Mędrzec, choć nie przygląda się każdej osobie,
Wszystkie zna, bo ich dusze ma dokładnie w sobie,
Mędrzec, sądząc z pozoru, zdaje się, że nie żył,
A on wszystkie żywoty w swojej duszy przeżył.

Mędrzec jest jako bóstwo w myśli swej oprzędzie:
On wie, co było przedtem, co jest, i co będzie.
On, którego myśl fruwa, jak ten ptak skrzydlaty
Nad ziemią, wie, że dziś jest, co było przed laty;
Wie, że z przeszłą złączona jest przyszłości era;
Wie, że to, co się rodzi, tem jest, co umiera.

Człowieka z pychą złamiesz w danej chwili:
Nie ugniesz tego, który się nachyli.
Dębowe, grube, ociężałe drewno
Huragan skręci i zwali na pewno.

A słaba, wiotka i uległa trzcina
Wytrwa, choć gnie ją wicher i podcina.
Twardy głaz, który wygląda najtrwalej,
Przecie mu grozi śmierć od morskiej fali.

Rzeczy z pozoru najwiotsze, najletsze:
Woda tak płynna, tak lotne powietrze,
I tak subtelne, jako duch człowieczy –

Te najsilniejsze, najtrwalsze są rzeczy.
A czas – nad wszystkiem. Czas był od prawieczy –
I jest: jest niczem, lecz wszystko w proch zetrze.

Kto wie, nie mówi: kto mówi, ten nie wie.
Wygra, w kim spokój: przegra kto jest w gniewie.
A ten, kto, silnym będąc, jest łagodny,
Mąż ten najpierwszym człowiekiem być godny.

Kto w sobie mocny, choć słaby z pozoru,
W takim upatruj sobie ludzi wzoru.
Kto się nie chełpi mądrości sztandarem,
(A mądry), z tym żyć fortuny jest darem.

Gdziekolwiek mędrzec znajdzie się wśród ludzi,
Tam, choć nie woła na nich, życie budzi.
Spokojny, cichy i uczynny stale,

Jest jako światło zamknione w krysztale:
Swoją świetlaną przyświeca im wiedzą,
Że ludzie sami, co im czynić, wiedzą.

Kto przyjął byt, wziąć musi i niebyt do pary;
Kto buduje kołyskę, niech staluje mary,
Tworzy prawdę, kto umiał w złudach życie prześnić,
Tworzy złudę, kto zdołał pomysł ucieleśnić.

Kto śni, marzy, rozmyśla, roztrząsa, rozważa,
Ten, ani sam wie kiedy, rzeczywistość stwarza,
A ten, kto w ucieleśnień zanurzony trudzie,
Ten, czy istniał, nie będą mogli orzec ludzie.

Tych prawd niechaj świetlaność wam rozbłyśnie w pełni:
Kto zbytnio pragnie dobra, często zło popełni;
Kto zbyt wierzy w swój rozum, omyli się snadnie;

Nawet w złem coś dobrego nieraz bywa na dnie;
Nawet w męce najwyższej słodki dreszcz się mieści;
Nawet w rozkosz największą wpełza czerw boleści.

W sprawiedliwą, niezłomną wierz nad nami władzę,
Która rządzi i trzyma światy w równowadze.
Lecz tej władzy cząsteczka (nieskończenie drobna)
Zamieszkuje i w każdej z naszych dusz z osobna.

Z naszych dusz świat się składa calutki, a zatem
Nie on, świat, nami rządzi, ale my nim – światem.
Albowiem w czyjej duszy ujarzmiona żądza,
Temu wszystko się dzieje, jak on rozporządza.

Jeżeliście zdobyli tę sztukę poskromień,
W słońcu wiedzy jest każdy z was, jak jeden promień.
Wszystkich was na tle mroku jedna moc rozścieła,
Wszyscyśmy powołani do jednego dzieła;
Każdemu w tej całości dało przeznaczenie
Być cząsteczką świetlaną (drobną nieskończenie).

Jeśli cię szczęście znikome nie łudzi,
Ni rozkosz żadna, toś najpierwszy z ludzi;
Jeśli dla ciebie wszystkiem byt dostatni –
Jadło, strój, pieniądz, toś z ludzi ostatni.

Stokroć żyć lepiej w łachmanach nędzarza,
Jeśli twą duszę czysta myśl rozżarza,
Niźli posiadłość mieć, choćby wszechziemną,
Jeśli w twej duszy pustynnie i ciemno.

Bogacz niech ziemski ma eden człowieczy,
Grodzony płotem prawnych paragrafów,
Nikły, zależny od fortuny trafów.

Twoją niech będzie tylko myśl o rzeczy.
Rzecz sama rychło zmieni się w proch szary,
A myśli wieczne będą trwać obszary.

Wiernego druha mieć gdy twoim celem,
Ty bądź dla innych wiernym przyjacielem:
Czyń, o cokolwiek kto cię prosić będzie,
Znajdziesz (na moment) przyjaciela wszędzie.

Skarb nie jest w rzeczach wziętych, lecz w rozdanych.
Nie proś: rozdawaj, ile tylko siły,
Będą się ręce do ciebie wznosiły,
I będziesz władcą i królem poddanych.

Zaprawdę, trudno wyjść z błędnego koła,
Którem jest rzeczy zwodnicza zawiłość.
Miej w sobie dobroć, przyjazność i miłość,
Szukać nie będziesz tych cnót dookoła.
Nie każ się ludziom poświęceniem zdobić:
Dość, jeśli ty sam potrafisz je zrobić.

Rzeczy kosztownej wartość w nas rośnie,
Gdy na nią inni patrzą zazdrośnie.
Rzecz najprzyjemniej tę posiadamy,
Której chcą od nas, a my nie damy.

Złota, szafirów, pereł, pieniądza
Wartością co jest? jest ku nim żądza.
Ten, przez nas pysznie noszony, djadem
Jest chciwych bliźnich kosztowny jadem.

Tych djamentów zdobiących szyję
Niech nie pożąda oko niczyje,
A to, co skarbem takim się mieni,
Będzie igraszką zwykłą promieni, –
Będzie ten klejnot jak kropla wodna,
Którą gra w słońcu rozświetli zwodna.

Wśród skarbów żywot twój rozpoczęty:
Najwyszukańsze masz wokół sprzęty,
Najprzepyszniejsze zdobią cię stroje,
Najpobrzękliwsze masz na nich zbroje…

Rój sług: młodzieńców, chłopiąt i dziewek
Dba o ten ziemski twój przyodziewek,
Który zebrali twoi przodkowie,
W twój dom wtłoczyli – w twych sal pustkowie.

Lecz wśród precjozów twoich mnogości,
A które wszystkiem w życiu być mniemasz,
Jednego skarbu ważnego nie masz,
A oto: mądrość tu nie zagości, –
Mądrość, co skarbów na stos nie zwala, –
Mądrość ta, która od złud wyzwala.

Bogacza celem jest – żyć intratnie:
Zabiega, ciuła, zdziera, łupieży;
Każdego radby oskubać z pierzy,
Każdego wciągnąć dla zysku w matnię.

Mędrzec ma za nic pełność śpichlerzy;
Na nic mu złoto, co w skarbcu leży;
On nie dba o to, by zwiększać szatnię:
Mędrzec by oddał giezło ostatnie.

Bogacz do grosza grosz skupia, zbiera,
Zgromadza, wpycha w wór, i umiera;
Wiatr po nim pamięć, jak kurz, rozwionie.

Mędrzec o ziemskiej nie dba mamonie;
Skarb się w mądrości jego zawiera:
Czci jego pamięć potomna era.

Ta cudna woda morza w skał kolebce,
Chociaż tak szumem melodyjnym szepce,
Choć tak ponętna u skalnych podnóży,
Nikt w niej spragnionych pić ust nie zanurzy.

Słowa, któremi szafują pochlebce –
To słodka woda, którą człek rad chłepce.
Deszcz, który polom chlebodajnym służy,
Gdy nie wsiąkł, postać przybiera kałuży.

Podobni morzu, prawd świadomi mędrce,
Jak ono gorzcy i jak ono – słoni.
Brud kłamstw by oni z dusz spłókali wprędce,
Ale któż, pragnąc, ku nim usta skłoni?
Kto prawdy ujrzeć dno tak uległ chętce,
By dla niej zginął w gorzko–słonej toni?

Gdy mówisz „zacność”, patrząc na bliźniego,
Ten myśli: pewno tu chodzi o niego.
Gdyś rzekł: „nikczemność”, i spojrzał mu w oczy,
On się, za innym kimś zerkając, boczy.

Choć, by mu dowieść, że on zły jest, konasz,
Bliźniego swego o tem nie przekonasz.
Jeśli pochlebstwem się mile go łechce –
Wierzy, lecz sprobój, zgań go – wierzyć nie chce.

Tak się po świecie zło, jak tułacz, warta;
Każdy je precz gna: idź – droga otwarta!
Nikt go do siebie brać nie chce, choć ubij,
Nikt go nie uzna, nikt nie przyhołubi…
Wszyscy, że dobrzy są, mniemają błogo,
A usynowić zła – niema nikogo!

Świętości jakże karkołomna ścieżka!
Dobrych sto czynów spełniłeś – stan zwykły:
Zły jeden spełniasz, i już – tamte znikły,
Już cię potępić ogół nie omieszka.

Człowiek cnotliwy – linoskok na linie,
Balansowego dzierżący się drąga:
Kroków dał sto – tłum klaszcze, lecz – urąga,
Jeżeli raz mu noga się powinie.

Czyż może kipieć cały wodny wrzątek,
Gdy jedna kropla – zimny w nim wyjątek?
Temu kto spełnił jeden czyn zły, szary,
Są niedostępne świętości obszary.
Nim wejdziesz w niebo, musisz zła spowicie
Odrzucić z swoich czynów – całkowicie.

Można szczęśliwym być tu na ziemi,
Wszechsamowładnym jakim pół‑bogiem. –
Żyć w upojeniu swych zachceń błogiem
Tak, aby nigdy nie wyrzec: źle mi.

Można, nie walcząc z żadnym nałogiem
Restrykcjami hamującemi,
Nie pragnąc świętej władzy nad niemi,
Żyć tak, by trosk się nie ukłóć głogiem.

Lecz stokroć lepiej myślą ulatać
Z tych nizin, złud omglonych tumanem;
Lepiej się z szczęścia rozstać łachmanem,
Który tak często trzeba tu łatać;
Lepiej do nieba wrót zakołatać:
Lepiej żyć życiem tam nie kłamanem.

Spokojnie umiej wytrwać, choć się w tobie kłębi.
Umiej chęcią zawładnąć i trzymać ją w głębi.
Nie chciej, ażeby sen twój się uroczy prześnił:
Nie pragnij, by ideał twój się ucieleśnił.

Jak prąd bystry, do czynu rwie cię żądz podnieta
Lecz pomnij, że ziszczona raz rzecz jest już nie ta,
Którąś sobie utworzył w idealnym planie,
I z którą w duszy żyłeś sam niepokalanie.

Niechaj lata mijają, niech się sobie piętrzą:
Ty bądź ze swoją wizją w duszy, coraz świętszą.
Niechaj jej wyglądają całe długie wieki…

Ty milcz, a gdy nakoniec odemkniesz powieki,
I usta gdy otworzysz, aż dotąd milczące:
Jak piorun będzie twoje: „Niech się stanie słońce!”

Kto chce drogą iść prawdy, niech tego się uczy:
Krew i ciało to szaty, które duch obłóczy.
A gdy spełniły swoje zadanie człowiecze,
Z wyzwolonego ducha twego śmierć je zwlecze.

Duch twój wciela się w każdy rys twojego lica.
Twarz – to czynami twemi skreślona tablica.
Czy chwalebne uczynki, czy podległe karze,
Ten dokument twój ludziom najwierniej pokaże.

Coś duchem czynił, będziesz ciałem pieczętować.
A przeto swoje życie z tem wskazaniem prowadź:
Cokolwiek przedsięwziąłeś w swoim ziemskim bycie,
Tego wierne odnajdziesz w licu twem odbicie,
A dalej je po tobie odbiorą potomni,
I przeklną cię, lub będą błogosławić. Pomnij!

Miota się, w uczuć dygocząc zalewie;
Faluje, fruwa, i gna, jak obłoki,
Bez przytomności, w ślepym wichur wiewie;
Cieszą go wzlotów i spadań uroki;

Dziś drga weselem, jutro – łzawooki,
Strachem przejęty, lub rzuca się w gniewie;
Kipi nagłością, kostnieje ze zwłoki:
Żyje, używa, przeżywa i… nie wie.

Kto wie, ten nie da przeważać się szali;
Nie bucha gniewem, ani się nie żali;
W spokojnym zawsze i równym humorze,
Radość i boleść jednako przemoże;
Z nadzieją zerwać potrafi jedyną:
Ten będzie trwały, gdy inni przeminą.

Mędrzec nie dba o poklask, nie dba o tłum chwalczy,
O zdobycz niczyjego uznania nie walczy;
Nie zabiega o tytuł, o urząd, o miano;
Nie chce, aby za cnotę go chodzącą miano.

Rad, jeśli los mu czasem dozwoli nie zboczyć,
Nie będzie się na ciebie, żeś ty zbłądził, boczyć;
W radości go nie chwyta zaraz obłąkanie,
W najdotkliwszem nieszczęściu tłumi krzyk i łkanie;

Mędrzec ani nędzarza pychą nie poniży,
Ani się przed monarchą nie kłania najniżej;
Ani ma kogo w wzgardzie, ani ma w estymie:
Jednem mu szermierz krzepki, jednem mu kaleka;
Jednem mu górne, niskie, małe i olbrzymie;
Jednem mu jest rzecz bliska i jednem daleka.

Zło, które w bliźnim swoim widzę,
W mojej się własnej duszy kłębi.
Przeto złoczyńcy nienawidzę,
Że sam złość chowam w serca głębi.

Dobroć, którą być własną mniemam,
Z bliźniego mego jest skarbnicy.
Przeto ku dobru mrę z tęsknicy,
Że sam dobroci w sobie nie mam.

Choć świat ten dla mnie jest zła knieja,
Cnót mam od niego wymaganie;
Za własne winy innych ganię,
Sam w sobie widząc dobrodzieja.
Wszyscy są dla mnie źli poganie,
Wszyscy są podli, tylko – nie ja.

Według takiego się doskonal wzoru:
Bądź w sobie mocny, choć słaby z pozoru.
Żyj pośród ludzi życiem samotniczem.
Łącz wszystko z sobą, sam nie zwarty z niczem.

Niechaj się pysznią ci oklasków chciwi,
Ambitni, dumni, że świat im się dziwi.
A ciebie tłum niech nawet nie wymienia,
Sąd masz swój na dnie własnego sumienia.

Jeżeli ono ci do ucha szepcze,
Żeś grzeszny, słaby, obłudny, nikczemny:
Cóż znaczą tłumów kadzidła pochlebcze?
Czem‑że motłochu o tobie sąd ciemny,
Który cię z boku ugodzi kamieniem?
Nic to, jeżeliś w porządku z sumieniem.

Gdybym był królem, mojaby władza
Byłaby taką, moi poddani,
Która nie ściska powrozem krtani,
Która nie więzi, która nie zgładza.

Ceł by nie było w mojej przystani:
Niech sobie, kto chce, wjeżdża, niech wchadza,
Niech się wprowadza, niech wyprowadza,
Niech żyje, jak mu najpożądaniej.

Byłoby szczęście w mem państwie błogiem,
W którem więzienie stoi odłogiem,
Gdzie zardzewiały miecz leży w kaźni,
Gdzie szafot zmurszał najniepokaźniej;
Gdzieby nie znano obywatela,
Któryby płakał, chyba – z wesela.

Zdaje się nam, iż, w gromadę zwarci,
Będzie nas siła, jako pszczół w barci:
Lecz zer, by miljon – zero przy zerze –
Gdy bez jedności, sił nie nabierze.

Kiedyśmy wszyscy czarni, jak czarci,
I wszyscy grzeszni w jednakiej mierze,
To niech się miljard nas takich zbierze,
Będziemy wszyscy też licha warci.

Dobry jest dobrym, chociaż sam jeden;
Zły – złym zostanie, choćby wśród kroci:
Jeden łotr cały zepsuje eden.

Lecz gdy choć jeden taki jest w tłumie,
Który być lepszym, niż inni, umie,
Ten może podnieść tłum ku dobroci.

Bogacz do szkatuł pcha swoje zbiory, –
Krętacz, w zyskownych czynów rumorze,
Pochłania więcej, niż strawić może:
Ciało – sad‑kwietnik, dusza – bajory.

Lecz myśl o śmierci, straszliwej zmorze,
Powoli zgasza mu lic kolory,
I mimo pomoc aptecznej flory,
Śmierć go – bogacza biednego – zmoże.

Gdy sukcesorzy, jego habendą
Pobogaceni, grzebać go będą,
To, choć pokrewnym był im człowiekiem,
Nikt mu nad trumny nie załka wiekiem,
A gdy już grób się nad nim zesklepi,
Rzekną: żył dobrze, umarł – tem lepiej.

Posiąść bogactwo niepoliczone;
Mieć pośród wygód ciało pieszczone:
Ten niewiednego ideał człowieka –
Tej szczęśliwości mędrzec się zrzeka.

Z spokojem w duszy, z ciszą na twarzy,
Nikogo nie czci, ni lekceważy;
Przed nikim możnym karku nie łamie;
Wobec nędzarza bólu nie kłamie.

Tak, bezdomnemu, świat cały domem;
Tak, nie bytując, jest we wszechbycie;
Tak pełnią wiedzy drga w niewiadomem;
Tak wszelkich pragnień posiadł wyzbycie,
Że, czy mu radość, czy mu żałoba:
Już mu jednakie są krańce oba.

Kwituję z szczęścia, z faworów podziału,
Któremi dola człowieczeństwo raczy,
Wszystko mi jedno, czy mojemu ciału
Jedwab, czy łachman przypadnie żebraczy.

Pocóż ta troska codzienna o mienie?
Pocóż ten mozół, aby mieć do syta?
Pocóż na zapas to ciał przekarmienie?
Pocóż ta suknia złotogłowiem szyta?

Mojem bogactwem te chmurki przelotne…
Pod niebem gwiezdnem czuję się, jak doma.
Bogactwem mojem te myśli samotne.
Mój skarb – wzniesienia duchowe, zawrotne.

Nie do ujęcia to szczęście rękoma –
Ta rozkosz trwała, chociaż tak znikoma.

Mędrzec nie walczy o nic, o nic nie zabiega;
Nikogo nie przymusza, nie gnie, nie niewoli:
A jednak świat stosuje się do jego woli
I ku niemu tak płynie, jak tłum fal do brzega.

Cokolwiek przed się mędrzec wziął, to wziął powoli,
Bo mędrzec do gwałtownych czynów nie podżega,
Nie wciąga w swoją partję, nie klnie z onej zbiega,
Dając każdemu wybór: woli, czy niewoli.

Mędrzec ten jest zaiste i nad światem włada,
W kim żądz pychy i gniewu nastąpi zagłada;
Ten, kto swoich natrętnie ukazów nie głosi;
Czyj śmiech i czyje skargi zbyt nam się nie stręczą.
Niech będzie kołowatą, kto chce być, obręczą:
On w kole stanowisko zajął – mędrzec – osi.

Swych wielkich ucztujących nienawidzą mali.
Naprzód tłum, blaskiem możnych oślepiony, klaszcze.
Potem, widząc te ciągłe zachłysty hulaszcze,
Mruczy, wre i pomstuje, że go okłamali.

Szemrze lud i otwiera, jak lew, głodną paszczę
Na królów, gdy, po uczcie, już się zadrzemali.
Wpadł, i władców obrzękłych, sytych, łapą wali,
I już go król pijaną ręką nie ugłaszcze.

Tak jest. Na widok hucznych, orgiastycznych biesiad,
Przeklina lud te stoły, do których sam nie siadł.
Ten monarcha pobłądził, kto, w weselu płochem,
Okazuje swój szczęścia zbytek przed motłochem,
Żałuje mu, nędznemu, z bankietów ogryzka,
Aż nędzarz ów, jak wulkan, drgnął i – lawą tryska.

Jak z ziemią niebo, z złą dobra sfera,
Oddal z blizkością, wierzch z dnem się zwiera;
Anioł z szatanem, skarb z dolą biedną –
Nierozerwalnie łączą się w jedno.

Nie na nich, ale ponad te rzeczy
Edenu gmach twórz, synu człowieczy;
Swobody szukaj, nie ujarzmienia
Lubością, która w gorycz się zmienia.

Energji pełen bądź, lecz nie wrzawy.
Milcz, nie głoś, nim ją wykonasz, sprawy.
Afektom nie daj zbyt się rozszaleć.
Niepożądanie swym chęciom zaleć,
Usługi bliźniej pełnij czyn błogo:
Sam o nic, o nic nie proś nikogo.

Gdy ukształciło się w nim już siemię,
Kwiatek uwiędły spada na ziemię.
Gdyś poznał ziarno wiedzy bez granic,
Tak samo byt ci ten, jak kwiat, na nic.

Byt z ciebie, gdyś się wiedzy stał ziarnem,
Odpada ciałem swojem ciężarnem;
Dusza, zwolniona z opresji życia,
Odrzuci swoje ziemskie spowicia.

Tak jak ten motyl z owicia przędzy,
W którą się, będąc liszką, omota:
Tak też i człowiek: z nici żywota –
Z jedwabnych złudzeń – ma wyjść najprędzej –
Z tych osnuć, zwartych nad jego duszą:
Trzeba je przegryźć, nim ją zaduszą.

Napaść, gwałt, przemoc nieujarzmiona;
Strach i nieufność, rygiel zawarty;
Twierdze, fortece, czaty i warty:
Oto masz starcze śmierci znamiona.

Lecz jeśli bliźnim swoim wierzycie;
Jeżeliście im tak zaufali,
Jak dziecko uczuć matczynych fali:
To się przed wami otwiera życie.

Spójrz: oto góry się powznosiły
Nad morską głębią urwiskiem stromem.
Porównaj morze z tych skał ogromem
I powiedz: gdzie tu jest więcej siły?
Czy trwalsza głazem skała grożąca?
Czy fala, która ją poroztrąca?

W sposób gniewliwy, zły, napastniczy,
Wojując pięścią, czyniąc rum krzykiem,
Lub zdradą chytrą, lub żmii sykiem
Kto żyje – w śmierci ten uczestniczy.

Mędrzec przewagi nie chce nad nikim;
Szczęśliwszy los go czyjś nie goryczy;
Nie wzbudza skarb w nim zawiści niczyj;
Nie jest niczyich władz zazdrośnikiem.

Ma posłuszeństwo u ludzi prędsze
Ten, kto przenika w ich duszy wnętrze;
Kto cnót nie głosi swoich imienia;
Kto, tak jak słońce, świat opromienia,
Choć, tak jak słońce, jest na uboczu:
Jest źródłem światła dla wszystkich oczu.

Choć cnotę znają wielcy i niscy,
Lecz się jej wskazań trzymają‑ż wszyscy?
Nie zawsze kłamstwo gnieździ się nisko,
Nie zawsze w górze prawdy ognisko.

O prawdzie jedni mówią uczenie,
U drugich znajdziesz zbożne jej czczenie:
I ci i tamci tak tem przejęci.
Że sił im pełnić ją brak i chęci.

Zdarza się też, że w prostaczym tłumie
Ktoś zasad prawdy nie umie orzec,
Ani określić jej najzupełniej;
Choć jej rodzajów i nazw nie umie;
Choć nie przysięga na jej proporzec,
Ale nią żyje, ale ją pełni.

Rzecz, gdy wcielona w dzieło człowiecze,
Jej kontrast za nią, jak cień, się wlecze.
Zawsze się w czynie „tak” z „nie” zespala,
Zawsze jest rzutna i zwrotna fala.

Cenimy dobro, lecz gdy się ziści,
W nas jest przyczyna i złej korzyści;
Najsprawiedliwszych nieraz wag szale
Sprawują ścisłość miar opieszale.

Z występkiem cnota, wielkość z małością;
Z spokojem szał, nienawiść z miłością;
Łatwa rzecz z trudną, z światłami ciemnie;
Śmierć z życiem, góry wysokość z dołem:
Te rzeczy w byt się łączą wzajemnie.
Prawda nie w nich jest: jest ich zespołem.

Jak woda morska, która lądom sprzyja,
Omywa wszystkie, ale jest niczyja;
A choć ogłosi kto, że nad nią władnie,
Nikomu ona nie służy podwładnie:

Na ten żyj przykład. Bądź, jak morska woda –
Element, który swojego ogromu,
Swych fal nie broni nigdy i nikomu,
Lecz się nikomu w niewolę nie poda.

Egoizm niczyj niech nie będzie zdolny
Mieć zaprzedanym sobie twój pęd wolny.
Albowiem tem jest mórz głąb doskonała,
Niczyja że jej moc nieokiełznała.
Ulegnie wrzkomo, uzna twoją wolę:
Strzeż się niebaczny – zginiesz w jej żywiole.

Mędrzec, by z drogi swojej nie zboczyć,
Zamiast się mnożyć, woli jednoczyć.
Nad ilość, wielką niepoliczenie,
W jedności większe widzi znaczenie.

Uważ największe liczebnie dzieła:
Z jedności ich się budowa wszczęła.
Nic, że jesteśmy drobną gromadką,
Jeżeli jedność jest naszą matką.

Tak jak zło dobru, tak wielość rzeczy
Jednej istocie rdzennej ich przeczy.
Chociażby była najbardziej przednią,
Rzecz uiszczona nie jest tą Jednią,
W której się mieści najmniejszy listek
W pierwozamiarze, – w której świat wszystek.

Radością żyć, lub żyć troską rzeszy;
Płynąć na oślep życia potokiem:
Mędrzec, spokojnem patrzący okiem
Na dwa kontrasty bytu – nie śpieszy.

Czegóż bo znęcić ma się urokiem?
Czy go stan jezdny, czy go stan pieszy
Bardziej ten zmartwi, tamten ucieszy?
Ten poniżeniem? ów czemś wysokiem?

Spokojny, cichy, sam, pustelniczy,
Mędrzec od czynu sam się odsądza.
Bo czyn najlepszy ze złem graniczy,
Bo złem jest najszlachetniejsza „żądza”,
Bo tylko ten ktoś zła nie wyrządza,
Kto w dobrodziejstwie nie uczestniczy.

Słodycz ma w sobie człowiek żyjący
I serdecznego pełen jest ciepła:
Ten zaś, w kim moc już życiowa skrzepła,
Zimny jest, sztywny, odstręczający.

Tego, w kim żywa pulsuje siła,
Porównaj z tym, w kim śmierć ją zgasiła.
Tamten miłością będzie zwyciężał;
W tym nie drga serce: zmartwiał, ociężał.

Patrz, jak słabością dziecko jest silne!
Jak jego uśmiech za moc wystarczy!
A patrz, jak słaby jest człowiek starczy,
Jakie stężenie już w nim mogilne!
Starzec wielmożny żyje, by skonać,
A słabe dziecko – by świat pokonać.

Jeżeliście bezgrzeszni, jak maleńkie dziecię,
Od wszelkiej złej przygody bezpieczni będziecie:
Ani doznacie lęku w jaskini ze lwami,
Ni gad żaden nie będzie panował nad wami.

Nie zgrubiały w dziecięciu jeszcze ścięgna, kości;
Energja wielka w niem jest, mimo maleńkości.
Spojrzyj: jakby największą życia znał rękojmię,
Lęk go nie zdejmie żaden, troska go nie dojmie.

Elastyczni, jak dziecię, bądźcie, żywi, zwinni,
Miłujący i ufni, obcy złu, niewinni,
A niewypowiedzianą cudowność ujrzycie:
Nie będzie miało dla was tajemnicy życie,
Ugodzić w was nie będzie mogła boleść żadna…
Sama śmierć się przed wami ukorzy wszechwładna.

Jest owoc słodki z nasieniem cierpkiem,
I bywa korzyść łączna z uszczerbkiem.
Cnotę masz w grzechu, grzech znajdziesz w cnocie:
Tak wszystko żyje w jednej wspólnocie.

Ocean w splotach swoich ma lądy,
A nim powietrzne kołyszą prądy;
Powietrze niebios tchem swoim sięga:
Tak się w jedności z rzeczą rzecz sprzęga.

Najwyższa góra, najgłębszy z dołów –
To jedność, z dwóch się wiążąca połów.
Czy się zaczyna co, czy się kończy –
Wszystko się zwiera, wszystko się łączy.
Kres wiedzy gdzież jest? Jest w czemś bezwiednem,
A razem są – nieskończenie jednem.

Bezkres ten, który ziemię przyobłóczy,
Aura, którą ust poruszasz tchnieniem –
Jakiej‑ż nas wiedzy przeogromnej uczy,
Jakiem‑ż napełnia duszę zolbrzymieniem!

Ten ogrom, który poujarzmiał słońca;
Który początku niema, ani końca;
Który w bezkresach rodzi się i ginie:
Człowiek nim rządzi, gdy tchnie, kiedy skinie.

Powietrze, w które gdy spadł liść najlichszy,
Lekkości jego powiewnej nie wstrzyma,
Gdy ciche; ale jeśli się rozwichrzy,
Wyrwie z korzeniem pień dębu – olbrzyma.
Ten sam wiew, w którym lekko drżą komysze,
Ten sam dziś morzem aż do dna kołysze.

Nie być, nie istnieć, nie mieć ani domu,
Ani własnego nic; zejść do atomu,
W proch się obrócić, którego śmierć blada
Znaleźć nie może: to mi los nie lada!

Nie być! Nie istnieć! Nie mieć domu, żony,
Dzieci, ni krewnych, ni przyjaciół nie mieć!
W grobie nieznanym na wieki oniemieć:
Oto do szczęścia ideał zbliżony!

Lecz jest zjawiskiem to, ufam, wiadomem,
Jak trudno ideał w życiu ucieleśnić.
Więc zanim szczęsnym zostanę atomem,
Muszę ten ziemski przeżyć byt, nie prześnić,
Jakiebykolwiek zsyłał mi los chwile,
Radbym je przeżyć, zanim w grób się schylę.

Nie chciej być panem nad wolą czyją!
Nie chciej zabijać, lub szarpać w gniewie!
Lew, tygrys, szakal – ci niech krew piją,
Niech wydzierają z swych ofiar trzewie.

Kto wie, nie błądzi: kto zbłądził, nie wie.
Czyż prawdy szukać we krwi przelewie?
Jak uczyć tych, co przeciętą szyją
Bluzgając krew dziś, już nie ożyją?

Gdybym był królem, zamknąłbym lochy,
Zniósł paragrafów karnych tysiące –
Ani bym zważał na sędziów szlochy,
Ni na przestępców rzesze płaczące:
Zbrodniarz, wyjęty z pod skrzydeł prawa,
Sechłby i zmarniał, jak bez dżdżu trawa.

Jest król, dokoła niego – dworzanie;
Jest tron i tronu jest podważanie;
Jest cnota: niecność przeciw niej kroczy;
Jest życia urok: zgon – mniej uroczy.

Jest pełnia trudu, i czczość leniwa;
Jest czysty plon, i z kąkolem niwa;
Żyć można prosto, lub żyć zawile;
Czas trwa: w nim giną znikome chwile.

Kto nie zna drogi, idzie zboczeniem –
Puszczą nadziei, knieją rozpaczy, –
Jak w labiryncie błąka się, tuła:

Lecz kto świadomy, kto widzi, baczy;
Kto umie rządzić światłem i cieniem:
Przed tym się prosta droga rozsnuła.

Już mi los przeciwności zsyła nadaremnie.
Otom już jest na ciosy wydarzeń otwarty.
Ani mury mnie bronią, ani zbrojne warty.
Niech, cokolwiek się zdarzy już, uderza we mnie.

Nie pożądam wesela, z cierpień stroję żarty;
Edenu mi jasności i piekielne ciemnie
Siedliskiem byćby mogły zarówno przyjemnie:
Luby mi druh jednako i mój wróg zażarty.

Enigma już mi swoje ból wyjawił do cna.
Miłość znam; wiem, że ona, jako śmierć, jest mocna.
Ach, znam i nienawiści śmiertelne spowicie –
Nienawiści dręczącej, jak śmierć, jadowicie!
Umiem żyć i umierać już… Me usta chwalą
Spokojnie śmierć i życie już. Uderzaj, falo!

Wszystko powraca: prawo niezłomne.
Bo nic nie ginie, co się zdarzyło.
I czemuż płakać mam nad mogiłą?
Szczęście me żyje dziś, bo je pomnę.

Nie wrócę przeszłych dni żadną siłą,
Lecz wstaje z martwych rzecz, którą wspomnę.
To, com raz przeżył, już mi przytomne
Będzie, jak gwiazda w niebie, świeciło.

Znam słodycz w bólu i jad w balsamie;
Żaden przeszłości mnie żal nie złamie.
Nie łkam, że szczęścia minęła era,
Że mi zwodniczym rajem nie kłamie.
Jedynem szczęściem ta prawda szczera:
Wszystko powraca, wszystko umiera.

Ogród z kwitnącą na wiosnę jabłonią;
Gazonów szmaragd i bzu krzew młodzieńczy;
I rój pszczół, który nad lotosem brzęczy;
I słońce, w którem się motyle płonią;

I hałaśliwość gier trzody dziecięcej –
Śmiechy te, które, jak szkło puste, dzwonią…
Świat z jego wrzaskiem, z jego życia wonią
Rzucam, i wracać doń nie pragnę więcej.

Bo ukochałem wśród‑gwiezdne przestrzenie.
Tam wyobraźnią żyłbym nieskończenie
I marzył… O czem? Trwożę się, że o tem,
By żyć na szarej tej ziemi z powrotem,
Gdzie w słońcu pachnie kwiat, gdzie pszczół brzęczenie,
Gdzie motyl skrzydłem połyskuje złotem.

Kto nie znał w życiu, co boleść wraża,
Ten się, gdy umrzeć mu czas, przeraża.
Lecz kto się, żyjąc, krwawił o głogi,
Śmierć dla takiego balsam jest błogi.

Ten, który w życiu miał same święta:
Że śmierć je zgasi mu – niech pamięta.
W kogo cierpienie za życia godzi,
Ten niech wie, że mu śmierć je złagodzi.

A kto żył szczęściem nie tylko samem,
Lecz i trucizny los mu dosączył
Do słodkiej czary, temu jest jedno:
Dobra fortunnych zdarzeń mu kwota;
Dobrze, gdy szczęsnych dni zorze zbledną;
Żyć mu jest dobrze i zbyć żywota.

Miałbym tę boleść w najwyższej cenie,
Która by mogła trwać nieskończenie,
Ażebym płakać mógł całe wieki,
By powstał ocean z łez moich rzeki.

Lecz wiem: najsrożej męka dręcząca
Dziś, jutro swego dobiegnie końca;
Ból, dojmujący dziś najogromniej, –
Jutro już o nim człowiek zapomni.

A rozkosz? Rozkosz miałbym w estymie,
Gdyby nie było: „chwila” jej imię,
Gdyby składała się ze stuleci.
Cóż mi po szczęściu, które uleci?
Czem rozkosz, która dziś zamigoce,
Aby mi jutro zginąć w pomroce?

Z mgieł oceanu tworzy się rzeka;
Początek z nikłych ziaren las bierze;
Małą rzecz z wielką łączy przymierze;
Zwiera się z bliską rzeczą – daleka.

Od bezorężnych giną szermierze;
Prędki, kto śpieszy, prędszy, kto czeka.
Świat jest bezmiarem, lecz dla człowieka
Najlepszą z miar jest: przestać na mierze.

Upokorzeni bywają hardzi;
Z mąk poniżenia ginie, kto gardzi;
Zło się i dobro ze sobą splata;
Ból się z rozkoszą plącze ogniwem,
Rozpacz – z nadzieją, umarłe – z żywem,
Z ciał bezlotnością – dusza skrzydlata.

Cnota zbyt wielka prawdzie kłamała.
Czasem prawdziwszą jest cnota mała.
Nieraz ktoś był na świętości szczycie:
W dół go strąciło cnót nadużycie.

Ludzkość jest słaba, niewytrzymała:
To zbytnio wielbi, to zbyt klnie życie;
Dziś w radosnego szału zenicie:
Jutro by we łzach ręce łamała.

W nieszczęściu wspomódz, w ucisku bronić;
Przecierpieć – trudno – śmiech i wesele;
W tłum się nie cisnąć, lecz i nie stronić;
Mniej radzić, więcej słuchać przestrogi;
Swych nie wynosić zasług na czele:
Nie masz po nad to słuszniejszej drogi.

Kto dziś rozpoczął działać szalenie,
Ten już nazajutrz popadł w omdlenie.
A to, co zwolna dziś się zaczęło,
Olbrzymio wzrośnie i przetrwa dzieło.

Ten, kto szermuje ostrzem oręża,
Zginął, bezsilny po wartkim czynie.
A ów bezbronny – mędrzec – zwycięża,
Okryty chwałą, po wieki słynie.

Tam furja, która w nicość ulata –
Garb fali wodnej, którą wiatr łamie
I uznikomia z ludzkiej pamięci:

Tu – myśl, niezłomnej potęgi znamię,
Tu jasność, której burza nie zmęci,
Ani jej zaćmią potomne lata.

Przedmowa

Laotse urodził się w Chinach, w 604 r. przed Chrystusem. Kiedy umarł, nie wiadomo. Czas jakiś był wychowawcą Inhi, naczelnika prowincji Lingpao, następnie oddalił się w góry Tybetu i wieść o nim zaginęła. Właściwe jego nazwisko – Li‑El‑Pejang‑Tan, zaś Laotse to przydomek i znaczy „sędziwy doktór”. Legenda mówi o nim, że przyszedł na świat, już mając lat 72, a przeżył lat 300. Podług innej wersji, Laotse nie umarł i nie umrze, bo wiedzą swoją zdobył nieśmiertelność. Filozoficzno‑religijna osnowa tej wiedzy zawarta w trzech niedużych rozprawach: 1) Tao – Księga drogi, 2) Te – Księga cnoty albo prawości i 3) Kan‑ing, czyli Księga sankcji. Dwie pierwsze są napisane, trzecia stanowi tradycję ustną i polega na kategoryzacji czynów ludzkich na dodatnie i ujemne, oraz na określeniu ich wzajemnego na siebie oddziaływania. Tao, wyraz pokrewny greckiemu teos lub łacińskiemu deus, charakteryzuje sam Laotse w taki sposób: „Istnieje – powiada on – jakieś najwyższe JEST, które zapłodniło niebyt i które z otchłani możliwości pierwotnej wyłoniło pierwiastki bytu, a później stworzyło z nich wszystkie istoty i ciała. Nie mam dla tego najwyższego JEST nazwy. Dam Mu imię, którem wyrażam Jego najistotniejszą własność (twórczą) – TAO (czyli Droga).

W strofach niniejszych starałem się nie o dosłowność przekładową, ile raczej o oddanie myśli przewodniej tego mędrca wielkiego Wschodu. Czytelników, chcących zapoznać się tekstualniej z treścią Tao, odsyłam do „La voie rationelle” Matgioi, lub do „The saiings of Leo‑Tzeu” przez Lionela Giles’a.

Jan Lemański